<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1927/16/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1927/16"/>
          <FRBRalias value="Indian Forest Act, 1927"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1927/16/eng@1927-09-27/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1927/16/eng@1927-09-27"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1927-09-27" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1927/16/eng@1927-09-27/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1927/16/eng@1927-09-27"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-10-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Indian Forest Act, 1927</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>(16 of 1927)</p>
        <p>An Act to consolidate the law relating to forests, the transit of forest-produce and the duty leviable on timber and other forest-produce.</p>
        <p>Whereas it is expedient to consolidate the law relating to forests, the transit of forest produce and the duty leviable on timber and other forest-produce; It is hereby enacted a follows:</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <heading>Preliminary</heading>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title and extent.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the Indian Forest Act, 1921</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It extends to the whole of India except the territories which, immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised in Part B States.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It applies to the territories which, immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised in the States of Bihar, Bombay, Coorg, Delhi, Madhya Pradesh, Orissa, Punj Uttar Pradesh and West Bengal; but the Government of any State may by notification in Official Gazette bring this Act into force2 in the whole or any specified part of that State which this Act extends and where it is not in force.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Interpretation clause.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-2.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>"cattle" includes elephants, camels, buffaloes, horses, mares, geldings, ponies colts, fillies, mules, asses, pigs, rams, ewes, sheep, lambs, goats and kids;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>"Forest-officer" means, any person whom the State Government or any office empowered by the State Government in this behalf, may appoint to carry out all any of the purposes of this Act or to do anything required by this Act or any rule m thereunder to be done by a Forest-officer;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>"forest-offence" means an offence punishable under this Actor under any rule made thereunder;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.4.list1">
                <listIntroduction>"forest-produce" includes−</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.4.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the following whether found in, or brought from, a forest or not, that is to say timber, charcoal, caoutchouc, catechu, wood-oil, resin, natural varnish, bark, lac, mahua flowers, mahua seeds, kuth and myrabolams, and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.4.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-2.4.list1.b.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>the following when found in, or brought from a forest, that is to say</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-2.4.list1.b.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>trees and leaves, flowers and fruits, and all other parts or produce not herein before mentioned, of trees,</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.4.list1.b.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>plants not being trees (including grass, creepers, reeds and moss), and all parts or produce of such plants,</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.4.list1.b.list0.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>wild animals and skins, tusks, horns, bones, silk, cocoons, honey and wax, and all other parts or produce of animals, and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.4.list1.b.list0.iv">
                      <num>(iv)</num>
                      <p>peat, surface soil, rock and minerals (including lime-stone, laterite, mineral oils, and all products of mines or quaries);</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.4A">
            <num>(4A)</num>
            <content>
              <p>"ownee" includes a Court of Wards in respect of property under the superintendence or charge of such Court;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>"river" includes any stream, canal, creek or other channels, natural or artificial;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>"timber" includes trees, when they have fallen or have been felled, and all wood whether cut up or fashioned or hollowed out for any purpose or not; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>"tree" includes palms, bamboos, skumps, brush-wood and canes.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <heading>Of reserved forests</heading>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Power to reserve forests.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may constitute any forest-land or waste-land which is the property of Government, or over which the Government has proprietary rights, or to the whole or any part of the forest-produce of which the Government is entitled, a reserved forest in the manner hereinafter provided.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Notification by State Government.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-4.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Whenever it has been decided to constitute any land a reserved forest, the State Government shall issue a notification in the Official Gazette</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>declaring that it has been decided to constitute such land a reserved forest;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>specifying, as nearly as possible, the situation and limits of such land; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>appointing an officer (hereinafter called "the Forest Settlement-officer") to inquire into and determine the existence, nature and extent of any rights alleged to exist in favour of any person in or over any land comprised within such limits or in or over any forest-produce, and to deal with the same as provided in this Chapter.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Explanation.−For the purpose of clause (b), it shall be sufficient to describe the limits of the forest by roads, rivers, ridges or other well-known or readily intelligible boundaries.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The officer appointed under clause (c) of sub-section (1) shall ordinarily be a person not holding any forest-office except that of Forest Settlement-officer.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in this section shall prevent the State Government from appointing any number of officers not exceeding three, not more than one of whom shall be a person holding any forest-office except as aforesaid, to perform the duties of a Forest Settlement-officer under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Bar of accrual of forest-rights.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>After the issue of a notification under section 4, no right shall be acquired in or over the land comprised in such notification, except by succession or under a grant or contract in writing made or entered into by or on behalf of the Government or some person in whom such right was vested when the notification was issued; and no fresh clearings for cultivation or for any other purpose shall be made in such land except in accordance with such rules as may be made by the State Government in this behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Proclamation by Forest Settlement-officer.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>When a notification has been issued under section 4, the Forest Settlement-officer shall publish in the local vernacular in every town and village in the neighbourhood of the land comprised therein, a proclamation</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>specifying, as nearly as possible, the situation and limits of the proposed forest;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>explaining the consequences which, as hereinafter provided, will ensue on the reservation of such forest; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>fixing a period of not less than three months from the date of such proclamation, and requiring every person claiming any right mentioned in section 4 or section, 5 within such period either to present to the Forest Settlement-officer a written notice specifying or to appear before him and state, the nature of such right and the amount and particulars of the compensation (if any) claimed in respect thereof.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Inquiry by Forest Settlement-officer.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Forest Settlement-officer shall take down in writing all statements made under section 6, and shall at some convenient place inquire into all claims duly preferred under that section, and the existence of any rights mentioned in section 4 or section 5 and not claimed under section 6 so far as the same may be ascertainable from the records of Government and the evidence of any persons likely to be acquainted with the same.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Powers of Forest Settlement-officers.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>For the purpose of such inquiry, the Forest Settlement-officer may exercise the following powers, that is to say:</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>power to enter, by himself or any officer authorised by him for the purpose, upon any land, and to survey, demarcate and make a map of the same; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the powers of a Civil Court in the trial of suits.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Extinction of rights.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Rights in respect of which no claim has been preferred under section 6, and of the existence of which no knowledge has been acquired by inquiry under section 7, shall be extinguished, unless before the notification under section 20 is published, the person claiming them satisfies the Forest Settlement-officer that he had sufficient cause for not prefer-ring such claim within the period fixed under section 6.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Treatment of claims relating to practice of shifting cultivation.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the case of a claim relating to the practice of shifting cultivation, the Forest Settlement-officer shall record a statement setting forth the particulars of the claim and of any local rule or order under which the practice is allowed or regulated, and submit the statement to the State Government, together with his opinion as to whether the practice should be permitted or prohibited wholly or in part.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On receipt of the statement and opinion, the State Government may make an order permitting or prohibiting the practice wholly or in part.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-10.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>If such practice is permitted wholly or in part, the Forest Settlement-officer may arrange for its exercise</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>by altering the limits of the land under settlement so as to exclude land of sufficient extent, of a suitable kind, and in a locality reasonably convenient for the purposes of the claimants, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.3.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>by causing certain portions of the land under settlement to be separately demarcated, and giving permission to the claimants to practise shifting cultivation therein under such conditions as he may prescribe.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All arrangements made under sub-section (3) shall be subject to the previous sanction of the State Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The practice of shifting cultivation shall in all cases be deemed a privilege subject to control, restriction and abolition by the State Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Power to acquire land over which right is claimed.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the case of a claim to a right in or over any land, other than a right of way or right of pasture, or a right to forest produce or a water-course, the Forest Settlement-officer shall pass an order admitting or rejecting the same in whole or in part.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-11.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>If such claim is admitted in whole or in part, the Forest Settlement-officer shall either</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>exclude such land- from the limits of the proposed forest; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>come to an agreement with the owner thereof for the surrender of his rights; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>proceed to acquire such land in the manner provided by the Land Acquisition Act, 1894 (1 of 1894).</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-11.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>For the purpose of so acquiring such land</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the Forest Settlement-officer shall be deemed to be a Collector proceeding under the Land Acquisition Act, 1894 (1 of 1894);</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.3.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the claimant shall be deemed to be a person interested and appearing before him in pursuance of a notice given under section 9 of that Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.3.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the provisions of the preceding sections of that Act shall be deemed to have been complied with; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.3.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the Collector, with the consent of the claimant, or the Court, with the consent of both parties, may award compensation in land, or partly in land and partly in money.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Order on claims to rights of pasture or to forest-produce.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>In the case of a claim to rights of pasture or to forest-produce, the Forest Settlement-officer shall pass an order admitting or rejecting the same in whole or in part.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Record to be made by Forest Settlement-officer.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Forest Settlement officer, when passing any order under section 12, shall record, so far as may be practicable,</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the name, father’s name, caste, residence and occupation of the person claiming the right; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the designation, position and area of all fields or groups fields (if any), and the designation and position of all buildings (if any) in respect of which the exercise of such rights is claimed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Record where he admits claim. –</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>If the Forest Settlement-officer admits in whole or in part any claim under section 12, he shall also record the extent to which the claim is so admitted, specifying the number and description of the cattle which the claimant is from time to time entitled to graze in the forest, the season during which such pasture is permitted, the quantity of timber and other forest produce which he is from time to time authorised to take or receive, and such other particulars as the case may require. He shall also record whether the timber or other forest-produce obtained by the exercise of the rights claimed may be sold or bartered.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Exercise of rights admitted.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-15.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>After making such record the Forest Settlement officer shall, to the best of his ability, having due regard to the maintenance of the reserved forest in respect of which the claim is made, pass such orders as will ensure the continued exercise of the rights so admitted.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-15.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>For this purpose the Forest Settlement-officer may</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-15.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>set out some other forest-tract of sufficient extent, and in a locality reasonably convenient, for the purposes of such claimants, and record an order conferring upon them a right of pasture or to forest-produce (as the case may be) to the extent so admitted; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-15.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>so alter the limits of the proposed forest as to exclude forest-land of sufficient extent, and in a locality reasonably convenient, for the purposes of the claimants; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-15.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>record an order, continuing to such claimants a right of pasture or to forest-overpage produce, as the case may be, to the e tent so admitted, at such seasons, within such portions of the proposed forest, and under such rules, as may be made in this behalf by the State Government.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Commutation of rights.–</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>In case the Forest Settlement-officer finds it impossible having due regard to the maintenance of the reserved forest, to make such settlement under section 15 as shall ensure the continued exercise of the said rights to the extent so admitted, he shall, subject to such rules as the State Government may make in this behalf, commute such rights, by the payment to such persons of a sum of money in lieu thereof, or by the grant of land, or in such other manner as he thinks fit.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Appeal from order passed under section 11, section 12, section 15 or section 16. –</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Any person who has made a claim under this Act, or any Forest-officer or other person generally or specially empowered by the State Government in this behalf, may, within three months from the date of the order passed on such claim by the Forest Settlement-officer under section 11, section 12, section 15 or section 16, present an appeal from such order to such officer of the Revenue Department of rank not lower than that of a Collector, as the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint to hear appeals from such orders:</p>
              <p>Provided that the State Government may establish a Court (hereinafter called the Forest Court) composed of three persons to be appointed by the State Government, and when the Forest Court has been so established, all such appeals shall be presented to it.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Appeal under section 17. –</heading>
          <subsection id="section-18.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every appeal under section 17 shall be made by petition in writing, and may be delivered to the Forest Settlement-officer, who shall forward it without delay to the authority competent to hear the same.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the appeal be to an officer appointed under section 17, it shall be heard in the manner prescribed for the time being for the hearing of appeals in matters relating to land-revenue.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the appeal be to the Forest Court, the Court shall fix a day and a convenient place in the neighbourhood of the proposed forest for hearing the appeal, and shall give notice thereof to the parties, and shall hear such appeal accordingly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The order passed on the appeal by such officer or Court, or by the majority of the members of such Court, as the case may be, shall, subject only to revision by the State Government, be final.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Pleaders. –</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Government, or any person who has made a claim under this Act, may appoint any person to appear, plead and act on its or his behalf before the Forest Settlement-officer, or the appellate officer or Court, in the course of any inquiry or appeal under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Notification declaring forest reserved.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-20.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-20.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>When the following events have occurred, namely: −</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-20.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the period fixed under section 6 for preferring claims have elapsed and all claims (if any) made under that section or section 9 have been disposed of by the Forest Settlement-officer;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-20.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>if any such claims have been made, the period limited by section 17 for appealing from the orders passed on such claims has elapsed, and all appeals (if any) presented within such period have been disposed of by the appellate officer or Court; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-20.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>all lands (if any) to be included in the proposed forest, which the Forest Settlement-officer has, under section 11, elected to acquire under the Land Acquisition Act, 1894 (1 of 1894), have become vested in the Government under section 16 of that Act,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>the State Government shall publish a notification in the Official Gazette, specifying definitely, according to boundary-marks erected or otherwise, the limits of the forest which is to be reserved, and declaring the same to be reserved from a date fixed by the notification.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>From the date so fixed such forest shall be deemed to be a reserved forest.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Publication of translation of such notification in neighbourhood of forest. –</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Forest-officer shall, before the date fixed by such notification, cause a translation thereof into the local vernacular to be published in every town and village in the neighbourhood of the forest.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Power to revise arrangement made under section 15 or section 18−</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, within five years from the publication of any notification under section 20, revise any arrangement made under section 15 or section 18, and may for this purpose rescind or modify any order made under section 15 or section 18, and direct that any one of the proceedings specified in section 15 be taken in lieu of any other of such proceedings, or that the rights admitted under section 12 be commuted under section 16.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>No right acquired over reserved forest, except as here provided. –</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No right of any description shall be acquired in or over a reserved forest except by succession or under a grant or contract in writing made by or on behalf of the Government or some person in whom such right was vested when the notification under section 20 was issued.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Rights not to be alienated without sanction. –</heading>
          <subsection id="section-24.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in section 23, no right continued under clause (c) of sub-section (2) of section 15 shall be alienated by way of grant, sale, lease mortgage or otherwise, without the sanction of the State Government:</p>
              <p>Provided that, when any such right is appendant to any land or house, it may be sold or otherwise alienated with such land or house.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-24.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No timber or other forest-produce obtained in exercise of any such right shall be sold or bartered except to such extent as may have been admitted in the order recorded under section 14.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Power to stop ways and water-courses in reserved forests. –</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Forest-officer may, with the previous sanction of the State Government or of any officer duly authorised by it in this behalf, stop any public or private way or water-course in a reserved forest, provided that a substitute for the way or water-course so stopped, which the State Government deems to be reasonably convenient, already exists, or has been provided or constructed by the Forest-officer in lieu thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Acts prohibited in such forests. –</heading>
          <subsection id="section-26.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-26.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Any person who−</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-26.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>makes any fresh clearing prohibited by section 5, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>sets fire to a reserved forest, or, in contravention of any rules made by the State Government in this behalf, kindles any fire, or leaves any fire burning, in such manner as to endanger such a forest;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-26.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>or who, in a reserved forest−</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-26.1.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>kindles, keeps or carries any fire except at such seasons as the Forest-officer may notify in this behalf,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.1.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>trespasses or pastures cattle, or permits cattle to trespass;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.1.list3.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>causes any damage by negligence in felling any tree or cutting or dragging any timber;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.1.list3.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>fells, girdles, lops, or bums any tree or strips off the bark or leaves from, or otherwise damages, the same;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.1.list3.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>quarries stone, bums lime or charcoal, or collects, subjects to any manufacturing process, or removes, any forest-produce;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.1.list3.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>clears or breaks up any land for cultivation or any other purpose;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.1.list3.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>in contravention of any rules made in this behalf by the State Government hunts, shoots, fishes, poisons water or sets traps or snares; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.1.list3.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>in any area in which the Elephants’ Preservation Act, 1879 (6 of 1879), is not in force, kills or catches elephants in contravention of any rules so made,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, or with both, in addition to such compensation for damage done to the forest as the convicting Court may direct to be paid.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-26.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-26.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Nothing in this section shall be deemed to prohibit</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-26.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>any act done by permission in writing of the Forest-officer, or under any rule made by the state Government; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the exercise of any right continued under clause (c) of sub-section (2) of section 15, or created by grant or contract in writing made by or on behalf of the Government under section 23.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-26.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Whenever fire is caused wilfully or by gross negligence in a reserved forest, the State Government may (notwithstanding that any penalty has been inflicted under this section) direct that in such forest or any portion there of the exercise of all rights of pasture or to forest produce shall be suspended for such period as it thinks fit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Power to declare forest no longer reserved. –</heading>
          <subsection id="section-27.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that, from a date fixed by such notification, any forest or any portion thereof reserved under the Act shall cease to be a reserved forest.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>From the date so fixed, such forest or portion shall cease to be reserved; but the rights (if any) which have been extinguished therein shall not revive in consequence of such cessation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <heading>Of village-forests</heading>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Formation of village-forests.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-28.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may assign to any village-community the rights of Government to or over any land which has been constituted a reserved forest, and may cancel such assignment. All forests so assigned shall be called village-forests.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-28.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may make rules for regulating the management of village forests, prescribing the conditions under which the community to which any such assignment is made may be provided with timber or other forest-produce or pasture, and their duties for the protection and improvement of such forest.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-28.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All the provisions of this Act relating to reserved forests shall (so far as they are not inconsistent with the rules so made) apply to village-forests.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <heading>Of protected forests</heading>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Protected forests. –</heading>
          <subsection id="section-29.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare the provisions of this Chapter applicable to any forest-land or waste-land which,, is not included in a reserved forest but which is the property of Government, or over which the Government has proprietary rights, or to the whole or any part of the forest produce of which the Government is entitled.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The forest-land and waste-lands comprised in any such notification shall be called a "protected forest".</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No such notification shall be made unless the nature and extent of the rights of Government and of private persons in or over the forest-land or waste-land comprised therein have been inquired into and recorded at a survey or settlement, or in such other manner as the State Government thinks sufficient. Every such record shall be presumed to be correct until the contrary is proved:</p>
              <p>Provided that, if, in the case of any forest-land or waste land, the State Government thinks that such inquiry and record are necessary, but that they will occupy such length of time as in the meantime to endanger the rights of Government, the State Government may, pending such inquiry and record, declare such land to be a protected forest, but so as not to abridge or affect any existing rights of individuals or communities.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading>Power to issue notification reserving trees, etc. –</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-30.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-30.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette,</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-30.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>declare any trees or class of trees in a protected forest to be reserved from a date fixed by, the notification;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>declare that any portion of such forest specified in the notification shall be closed for such term, rot exceeding thirty years, as the State Government thinks fit, and that the rights of private persons, if any, over such portion shall be suspended during such terms, provided that the remainder of such forest be sufficient, and in a locality reasonably convenient, for the due exercise of the right suspended in the portion so closed; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>prohibit, from a date fixed as aforesaid, the quarrying of stone, or the burning of lime or charcoal, or the collection or subjection to any manufacturing process, or removal of, any forest-produce in any such forest, and the breaking up or clearing for cultivation, for building, for herding cattle or for any other purpose, of any land in any such forest.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading>Publication of translation of such notification in neighbourhood. –</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-31.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Collector shall cause a translation into the local vernacular of every notification issued under section 30 to be affixed in a conspicuous place in every town and village in the neighbourhood of the forest comprised in the notification.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules for protected forests. –</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-32.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-32.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The State Government may make rules to regulate the following matters, namely:</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the cutting, sawing, conversion and removal of trees and timber, and the collection, manufacture and removal of forest-produce, from protected forests;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the granting of licences to the inhabitants of towns and villages in the vicinity of protected forests to take trees, timber or other forest-produce for their own use, and the production and return of such licences by such persons;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the granting of licences to persons felling or removing trees or timber or other forest-produce from such forests for the purposes of trade, and the production</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-32.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>d) the payments, if any, to be made by the persons mentioned in clauses (b) and (c) for permission to cut such trees, or to collect and remove such timber or other forest-produce;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.paragraph-0.list3.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the other payments, if any, to be made by them in respect of such trees, timber and produce, and the places where such payment shall be made;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.paragraph-0.list3.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the examination of forest-produce passing out of such forests;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.paragraph-0.list3.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the clearing and breaking up of land for cultivation or other purposes in such forests;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.paragraph-0.list3.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>the protection from fire of timber lying in such forests and of trees reserved under section 30;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.paragraph-0.list3.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the cutting of grass and pasturing of cattle in such forests;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.paragraph-0.list3.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>hunting, shooting, fishing, poisoning water and setting traps or snares in such forests and the killing or catching of elephants in such forests in areas in which the Elephants’ Preservation Act, 1879 (6 of 1879), is not in force;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.paragraph-0.list3.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>the protection and management of any portion of a forest closed under section 30; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.paragraph-0.list3.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>the exercise of rights referred to in section 29.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading>Penalties for acts in contravention of notification under section 30 or of rules under section 32.--(1) Any person who commits any of the following offences, namely: −</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-33.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-33.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-33.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>fells, girdles, lops, taps or bums any tree reserved under section 30, or strips off the bark or leaves from, or otherwise damages, any such tree;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-33.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>contrary to any prohibition under section 30, quarries any stone, or bums any lime or charcoal or collects, subjects to any manufacturing process, or removes any forest-produce;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-33.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>contrary to any prohibition under section 30, breaks up or clears for cultivation or any other purpose any land in any protected forest;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-33.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>sets fire to such forest, or kindles a fire without taking all reasonable precautions to prevent its spreading to any tree reserved under section 30, whether standing fallen or felled, or to say closed portion of such forest;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-33.paragraph-0.list0.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>leaves burning any fire kindled by him in the vicinity of any such tree or closed portion;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-33.paragraph-0.list0.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>fells any tree or drags any timber so as to damage any tree reserved as aforesaid;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-33.paragraph-0.list0.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>permits cattle to damage any such tree;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-33.paragraph-0.list0.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>infringes any rule made under section 32,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, or with both.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-33.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Whenever fire is caused wilfully or by gross negligence in a protected forest, the State Government may, notwithstanding that any penalty has been inflicted under this section, direct that in such forest or any portion thereof the exercise of any right of pasture or to forest-produce shall be suspended for such period as it thinks fit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-34">
          <num>34.</num>
          <heading>Nothing in this Chapter to prohibit acts done in certain cases. –</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-34.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in this Chapter shall be deemed to prohibit any act done with the permission in writing of the Forest-officer, or in accordance with rules made under section 32, or, except as regards any portion of a forest closed under section 30, or as regards any rights the exercise of which has been suspended under section 33, in the exercise of any right recorded under section 29.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <heading>Of the control over forests and lands not being the property of government</heading>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading>Protection of forests for special purposes.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-35.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-35.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, regulate or prohibit in any forest or waste-land</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-35.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the breaking up or clearing of land for cultivation;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-35.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the pasturing of cattle; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-35.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the firing or clearing of the vegetation;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-35.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>when such regulation or prohibition appears necessary for any of the following purposes: −</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-35.1.list3.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>for protection against storms, winds, rolling stones, floods and avalanches;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-35.1.list3.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>for the preservation of the soil on the ridges and slopes and in the valleys of hilly tracts, the prevention of land slips or of the formation of ravines, and torrents, or the protection of land against erosion, or the deposit thereon of sand, stones or gravel;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-35.1.list3.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>for the maintenance of a water-supply in springs, rivers and tanks;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-35.1.list3.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>for the protection of roads, bridges, railways and other lines of communication;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-35.1.list3.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>for the preservation of the public health.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-35.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, for any such purpose, construct at its own expense, in or upon any forest or waste-land, such work as it thinks fit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-35.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No notification shall be made under sub-section (1) nor shall any work be begun under sub-section (2), until after the issue of a notice to the owner of such forest or land calling on him to show cause, within a reasonable period to be specified in such notice, why such notification should not be made or work constructed, as the case may be, and until his objections, if any, and any evidence he may produce in support of the same, have been heard by an officer duly appointed in that behalf and have been considered by the State Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-36">
          <num>36.</num>
          <heading>Power to assume management of forests. –</heading>
          <subsection id="section-36.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In case of neglect of, or wilful disobedience to, any regulation or prohibition under section 35, or if the purposes of any work to be-constructed under that section so require, the State Government may, after notice in writing to the owner of such forest or land and after considering his objections, if any, place the same under the control of a Forest-officer, and may declare that all or any of the provisions of this Act relating to reserved forests shall apply to such forest or land.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The net profits, if any, arising from the management of such forest or land shall be paid to the said owner.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-37">
          <num>37.</num>
          <heading>Expropriation of forests in certain cases. –</heading>
          <subsection id="section-37.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In any case under this Chapter in which the State Government considers that, in lieu of placing the forest or land under the control of a Forest-Officer, the same should be acquired for public purposes, the State 3overnment may proceed to acquire it in the manner provided by the Land Acquisition Act, 1894 (1 of 1894).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-37.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The owner of any forest or land comprised in any notification under section 35 may, t any time not less than three or more than twelve years from the date thereof, require that such forest or land shall be acquired for public purposes, and the State Government shall require such forest or land accordingly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-38">
          <num>38.</num>
          <heading>Protection of forests at request of owners. –</heading>
          <subsection id="section-38.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-38.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The owner of any land or, if there more than one owner thereof, the owners of shares therein amounting in the aggregate at least two-thirds thereof may, with a view to the formation or conservation of forests thereon, represent in writing to the Collector their desire</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-38.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>that such land be managed on their behalf by the Forest-officer as a reserved or a protected forest on such terms as may be mutually agreed upon; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-38.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>that all or any of the provisions of this Act be applied to such land.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-38.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In either case,-the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, apply to such land such provisions of this Act as it thinks suitable to the circumstances thereof and as may be desired by the applicants.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VI">
        <num>VI</num>
        <heading>Of the duty on timber and other forest-produce</heading>
        <section id="section-39">
          <num>39.</num>
          <heading>Power to impose duty on timber and other forest-produce. –</heading>
          <subsection id="section-39.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-39.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Central Government may levy a duty in such manner, at such places and at such rates as it may declare by notification in the Official Gazette on all timber or other forest-produce</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-39.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>which is produced in the territories to which this Act extends, and in respect of which the Government has any right;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-39.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>which is brought from any place outside 8 the territories to which this Act extends.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-39.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In every case in which such duty is directed to be levied ad valorem the Central Government may fix by like notification the value on which such duty shall be assessed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-39.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All duties on timber or other forest-produce which, at the time when this Act comes into force in any territory, are levied therein under the authority of the State Government, shall be deemed to be and to have been duty levied under the provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-39.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything in this section, the State Government may, until provision to the contrary is made by Parliament, continue to levy any duty which it was lawfully levying before the commencement of the Constitution, under this section as then in force:</p>
              <p>Provided that nothing in this sub-section authorises the levy of any duty which as between timber or other forest-produce of the State and similar produce of the locality outside the State, discriminates in favour of the former, or which, in the case of timber or other forest-produce of localities outside the State, discriminates between timber or other forest-produce of one locality and similar timber or other forest-produce of another locality.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-40">
          <num>40.</num>
          <heading>Limit not to apply to purchase-money or royalty.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-40.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in this Chapter shall be deemed to limit the amount, if any, chargeable as purchase-money or royalty on any timber or other forest-produce, although the same is levied on such timber or produce while in transit, in the same manner as duty is levied.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VII">
        <num>VII</num>
        <heading>Of the control of timber and other forest-produce in transit</heading>
        <section id="section-41">
          <num>41.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules to regulate transit of forest produce.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-41.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The control of all rivers and their banks as regards the floating of timber, as well as the control of all timber and other forest-produce in transit by land or water, is vested in the State Government, and it may make rules to regulate the transit of all timber and other forest-produce.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-41.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-41.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power such rules may</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-41.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>prescribe the routes by which alone timber or other forest-produce may be imported, exported or moved into, from or within 14 the State;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>prohibit the import or export or moving of such timber or other produce without a pass from an officer duly authorised to issue the same, or otherwise than in accordance with the conditions of such pass;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>provide for the issue, production and return of such passes and for the payment of fees therefor;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>provide for the stoppage, reporting, examination and marking of timber or other forest-produce in transit, in respect of which there is reason to believe that any money is payable to the Government on account of the price thereof, or on account of any duty, fee, royalty or charge due thereon, or, to which it is desirable for the purposes of this Act to affix a mark;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>provide for the establishment and regulation of depots to which such timber or other produce shall be taken by those in charge of it for examination, or for the payment of such money, or in order that such marks may be affixed to it, and the conditions under which such timber or other produce shall be brought to, stored at and removed from such depots;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.2.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>prohibit the closing up or obstructing of the channel or banks of any river used for the transit of timber or other forest-produce, and the throwing of grass, brushwood, branches or leaves into any such river or any act which may cause such river to be closed or obstructed;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.2.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>provide for the prevention or removal of any obstruction of the channel or banks of any such river, and for recovering the cost of such prevention or removal from the person whose acts or negligence necessitated the same;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.2.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>prohibit absolutely or subject to conditions, within specified local limits, the establishment of sawpits, the converting, cutting, burning, concealing or making of timber, the altering or effacing of any marks on the same, or the possession or carrying of marking hammers or other implements used for marking timber;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.2.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>regulate the use of property marks for timber, and the registration of such marks; prescribe the time for which such registration shall hold good; limit the number of such marks that may be registered by any one person, and provide for the levy of fees for such registration.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-41.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may direct that any rule made under this section shall not apply to any specified class of timber or other forest-produce or to any specified local area.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-41A">
          <num>41A.</num>
          <heading>Powers of Central Government as to movements of timber across customs frontiers.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-41A.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything in section 41, the Central Government may make rules to prescribe the route by which alone timber or other forest-produce may be imported, exported or moved into or from the territories to which this Act extends) across any customs frontier as defined by the Central Government, and any rules made under section 41 shall have effect subject to the rules made under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-42">
          <num>42.</num>
          <heading>Penalty for breach of rules made under section 41.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-42.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may by such rules prescribe as penalties for the contravention thereof imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, or both.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-42.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Such rules may provide that penalties which are double of those mentioned in subsection (1) may be inflicted in cases where the offence is committed after sunset and before sunrise, or after preparation for resistance to lawful authority, or where the offender has been previously convicted of a like offence.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-43">
          <num>43.</num>
          <heading>Government and Forest-officers not liable for damage to forest-produce at depot.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-43.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Government shall not be responsible for any loss or damage which may occur in respect of any timber or other forest-produce while at a depot established under a rule made under section 41, or while detained elsewhere, for the purposes of this Act; and no Forest-officer shall be responsible for any such loss or damage, unless he causes such loss or damage negligently, maliciously or fraudulently.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-44">
          <num>44.</num>
          <heading>All persons bound to aid in case of accidents at depot. –</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-44.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>In case of any accident or emergency involving danger to any property at any such depot, every person employed at such depot, whether by the Government or by any private person, shall render assistance to any Forest-officer or Police-officer demanding his aid in averting such danger or securing such property from damage or loss.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VIII">
        <num>VIII</num>
        <heading>Of the collection of drift and stranded timber</heading>
        <section id="section-45">
          <num>45.</num>
          <heading>Certain kinds of timber to be deemed property of Government until title thereto proved, and may be collected accordingly.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-45.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All timber found adrift, beached, stranded or sunk;</p>
              <p>all wood or timber bearing marks which have not been registered in accordance with the rules made under section 41, or on which the marks have been obliterated, altered or defaced by fire or otherwise; and in such areas as the State Government directs, all unmarked wood and timber, shall be deemed to be the property of Government, unless and until any person establishes his right and title thereto, as provided in this Chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Such timber may be collected by any Forest-officer or other person entitled to collect the same by virtue of any rule made under section 51 and may be brought to any depot which the Forest-officer may notify as a depot for the reception of drift timber.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 6xempt any class of timber from the provisions of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-46">
          <num>46.</num>
          <heading>Notice to claimants of drift timber.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-46.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Public notice shall from time to time be given by the Forest-officer, of timber collected under section 45. Such notice shall contain a description of the timber, and shall require any person claiming the same to present to such officer, within a period not less than two months from the date of such notice, a written statement of such claim.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-47">
          <num>47.</num>
          <heading>Procedure on claim preferred to such timber.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-47.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When any such-statement is presented as aforesaid, the Forest-officer may, after making such inquiry as he thinks fit, either reject the claim after according his reasons for so doing, or deliver the timber to the claimant.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-47.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If such timber is claimed by more than one person, the Forest-officer may either deliver the same to any of such persons who he deems entitled thereto, or may refer the claimants to the Civil Courts, and retain the timber pending the receipt of an order from any such Court for its disposal.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-47.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person whose claim has been rejected under this section may, within three months from the date of such rejection, institute a suit to recover possession of the timber claimed by him; but no person shall recover any compensation or costs against the Government, or against any Forest-officer on account of such rejection, or the detention or removal of any timber, or the delivery thereof to any other person under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-47.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No such timber shall be subject to process of any Civil, Criminal or Revenue Court until it has been delivered, or a suit has been brought, as provided in this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-48">
          <num>48.</num>
          <heading>Disposal of unclaimed timber.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-48.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>If no such statement is presented as aforesaid, if the claimant omits to prefer his claim in the manner and within the period fixed by the notice issued under section 46, or on such claim having been so preferred by him and having been rejected, omits to institute a suit to recover possession of such timber within the further period fixed by section 47, the ownership of such timber shall vest in the Government, or, when such timber has been delivered to another person under section 47, in such other person free from all encumbrances not created by him.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-49">
          <num>49.</num>
          <heading>Government and its officers not liable for damage to such timber.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-49.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>TN Government shall not be responsible for any loss or damage which may occur in respect any timber collected under section 45, and no Forest-officer shall be responsible for any such loss or damage, unless he causes such loss or damage negligently, maliciously fraudulently,</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-50">
          <num>50.</num>
          <heading>Payments to be made by claimant before timber is delivered to him.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-50.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No person shall be entitled to recover possession of any timber collected or delivered as aforesaid until he has paid to the Forest-officer or other person entitled to receive it such sum on account thereof as may be due under any rule made under section 51.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-51">
          <num>51.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules and prescribe penalties.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-51.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-51.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The State Government in make rules to regulate the following matters, namely:</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-51.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the salving, collection and disposal of all timber mentioned in section 45;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-51.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the use and registration of boats used in salving and collecting timber;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-51.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the amounts to be paid for salving, collecting, moving, storing or disposing such timber; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-51.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the use and registration of hammers and other instruments to be used marking such timber.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-51.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may prescribe, as penalties for the contravention of any rule made under this section, imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, or both.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IX">
        <num>IX</num>
        <heading>Penalties and procedure</heading>
        <section id="section-52">
          <num>52.</num>
          <heading>Seizure of property liable to confiscation.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-52.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When there is reason to believe that a forest-offence has been committed in respect of any forest-produce, such produce together with all tools, boats, carts or cattle used in committing any such offence, may be seized by any Forest-officer or Police-officer.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-52.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every officer seizing any property under this section shall place on such property a mark indicating that the same has been so seized, and shall, as soon as may be, make a - report of such seizure to the Magistrate having jurisdiction to try the offence on account which the seizure has been made:</p>
              <p>Provided that, when the forest-produce with respect to which such offence is belie to have been committed is the property of Government, and the offender is unknown, it shall be sufficient if the officer makes, as soon as may be, a report of the circumstances to his official superior.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-53">
          <num>53.</num>
          <heading>Power to release property seized under section 52.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-53.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Any Forest-officer of a rank not inferior to that of a Ranger who, or whose subordinate, has seized any tools, boats, carts or cattle under section 52, may release the same on the execution by the owner thereof a bond for the production of the property so released, if and when so required, before the Magistrate having jurisdiction to try the offence on account of which the seizure has been made.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-54">
          <num>54.</num>
          <heading>Procedure thereupon.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-54.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Upon the receipt of any such report, the Magistrate shall, with all convenient despatch, take such measures as may be necessary for the arrest and trial of the offender and the disposal of the property according to law.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-55">
          <num>55.</num>
          <heading>Forest-produce, tools, etc., when liable to confiscation.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-55.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All timber or forest produce which is not the property of Government and in respect of which a forest-offence has been committed, and all tools, boats, carts and cattle used in committing any forest offence, shall be liable to confiscation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-55.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Such confiscation may be in addition to any other punishment prescribed for such offence.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-56">
          <num>56.</num>
          <heading>Disposal on conclusion of trial for forest-offence, of produce in respect of which it was committed.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-56.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>When the trial of any forest-offence is concluded, any forest-produce in respect of which such offence has been committed shall, if it is the property of Government or has been confiscated, be taken charge of by a Forest-officer, and, in any other case, may be disposed of in such manner as the Court may direct.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-57">
          <num>57.</num>
          <heading>Procedure when offender not known or cannot be found.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-57.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>When the offender is not known or cannot be found, the Magistrate may, if he finds that an offence has been committed, order the property in respect of which the offence has been committed to be confiscated and taken charge of by the Forest-officer, or to be made over to the person whom the Magistrate deems to be entitled to the same:</p>
              <p>Provided that no such order shall be made until the expiration of one month from d date of seizing such property, or without hearing the person, if any, claiming any rig thereto, and the evidence, if any, which he may produce in support of his claim.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-58">
          <num>58.</num>
          <heading>Procedure as to perishable property siezed under section 52.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-58.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Magistrate may, notwithstanding anything hereinbefore contained, direct the sale of any property seized under section 52 and subject to speedy and natural decay, and may deal with the proceeds as he would have dealt with such property if it had not been sold.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-59">
          <num>59.</num>
          <heading>Appeal from orders under section 55, section 56 or section 57.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-59.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The officer made the seizure under section 52, or any of his official superiors, or any person claim to be interested in the property so seized, may, within one month from the date of any order passed under section 55, section 56 or section 57, appeal therefrom to the Court to will orders made by such Magistrate are ordinarily appealable, and the order passed on A appeal shall be final.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-60">
          <num>60.</num>
          <heading>Property when to vest in Government.-When an order for the confiscation any property has been passed under section 55 or section 57, as the case may be, and the period limited by section 59 for an appeal from such order has elapsed, and no such an appeal has been preferred, or when, on such an appeal being preferred, the Appellate C4 confirms such order in respect of the whole or a portion of such property, such property or such portion thereof, as the case may be, shall vest in the Government free from all incumbrances.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-61">
          <num>61.</num>
          <heading>Saving of power to release property seized.-Nothing hereinbefore contained shall be deemed to prevent any officer empowered in this behalf by the State Government, from directing at any time the immediate release of any property seized under section 52.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-62">
          <num>62.</num>
          <heading>Punishment for wrongful seizure.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-62.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Any Forest-officer or Police-officer who vexatiously and unnecessarily seizes any property on pretence of seizing property liable confiscation under this Act shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, or with both.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-63">
          <num>63.</num>
          <heading>Penalty for counterfeiting or defacing marks on trees and timber and for altering boundary marks.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-63.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-63.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Whoever, with intent to cause damage or injury to the public or to any person, or to cause wrongful gain as defined in the Indian Penal Code−</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-63.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>knowingly counterfeits upon any timber or standing tree a mark used by Forest-officers to indicate that such timber or tree is the property o Government or of some person, or that it may lawfully be cut or removed some person; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-63.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>alters, defaces or obliterates any such mark placed on a tree or on timber by under the authority of a Forest-officer; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-63.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>alters, moves, destroys or defaces any boundary-mark of any forest or waste land to which the provisions of this Act are applied,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years, or fine, or with both.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-64">
          <num>64.</num>
          <heading>Power to arrest without warrant.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-64.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any Forest-officer or Police-officer without orders from a Magistrate and without a warrant, arrest any person against whom a reasonable suspicion exists of his having been concerned in any forest-offence punishable with imprisonment for one month or upwards.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-64.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every officer making an arrest under this section shall, without unnecessary delay and subject to the provisions of this Act as to release on bond, take or send the person arrested before the Magistrate having jurisdiction in the case, or to the officer in charge of the nearest police station.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-64.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in this section shall be deemed to authorise such arrest for any act which is an offence under Chapter IV unless such act has been prohibited under clause (c) of section 30.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-65">
          <num>65.</num>
          <heading>Power to release on a bond a person arrested.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-65.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Any Forest-officer of a rank not inferior to that of a Ranger, who, or whose subordinate, has arrested any person under the provisions of section 64, may release such person on his executing a bond to appear, if and when so required, before the Magistrate having jurisdiction in the case, or before the officer in charge of the nearest police station.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-66">
          <num>66.</num>
          <heading>Power to prevent commission of offence.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-66.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every Forest-officer and Police officer shall prevent, and may interfere for the purpose of preventing, the commission of any forest-offence.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-67">
          <num>67.</num>
          <heading>Power to try offences summarily.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-67.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The District Magistrate or any Magistrate of the first class specially empowered in this behalf by the State Government may try summarily, under the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898, any forest-offence punishable with imprisonment for a term not exceeding six months, or fine not exceeding five hundred rupees, or both.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-68">
          <num>68.</num>
          <heading>Power to compound offences.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-68.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-68.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, empower a Forest officer−</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-68.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to accept from any person against whom a reasonable suspicion exists that he has committed any forest-offence, other than an offence specified in section 62 or section 63, a sum of money by way of compensation for the offence which such person is suspected to have committed, and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-68.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>when any property has been seized as liable to confiscation, to release the same on payment of the value thereof as estimated by such officer.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-68.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On the payment of such sum of money, or such value, or both, as the case may be, to such officer, the suspected person, if in custody, shall be discharged, the property, if any seized shall be released, and no further proceedings shall be taken against such person or property.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-68.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A Forest-officer shall not be empowered under this section unless he is a Forest officer of a rank not inferior to that of a Ranger and is in receipt of a monthly salary amounting to at least one hundred rupees, and the sum of money accepted as compensation under clause (a) of sub-section (1) shall in no case exceed the sum of fifty rupees.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-69">
          <num>69.</num>
          <heading>Presumption that forest-produce belongs to Government.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-69.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>When in any proceedings taken under this Act, or in consequence of anything done under this Act, a question arises as to whether any forest-produce is the property of the Government, such produce shall be presumed to be the property of the Government until the contrary is proved.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-X">
        <num>X</num>
        <heading>Cattle-trespass</heading>
        <section id="section-70">
          <num>70.</num>
          <heading>Cattle-trespass Act, 1871, to apply.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-70.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Cattle trespassing in a reserved forest any portion of a protected forest which has been lawfully closed to grazing shall be deem to be cattle doing damages to a public plantation within the meaning of section II of Cattle-trespass Act, 1871 (1 of 1871), and may be seized and impounded as such by Forest-officer or Police-officer.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-71">
          <num>71.</num>
          <heading>Power to alter fines fixed under that Act.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-71.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, notification in the Official Gazette, direct that, in lieu of the fines fixed under section I the Cattle-trespass Act, 1871 (1 of 1871), there shall be levied for each head of cattle impounded under section 70 of this Act such fines as it thinks fit, but not exceeding following, that is to say:-</p>
              <p>For each elephant ten rupees</p>
              <p>For each buffalo or camel two rupees</p>
              <p>For each horse, mare, gelding, pony, colt, filly, mule, bull,</p>
              <p>bullock, cow, or heifer one rupee</p>
              <p>For each calf, ass, pig, ram, ewe, sheep, lamb, goat or kid eight annas</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-XI">
        <num>XI</num>
        <heading>Of forest-officers</heading>
        <section id="section-72">
          <num>72.</num>
          <heading>State Government may invest Forest-officers with certain powers.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-72.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-72.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The State Government may invest any Forest-officer with all or of the following powers, that is to say:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-72.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>power to enter upon any land and to survey, demarcate and make a map of the same;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-72.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the powers of a Civil Court to compel the attendance of witnesses and production of documents and material objects;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-72.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>power to issue a search-warrant under the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898); and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-72.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>power to hold an inquiry into forest-offences, and, in the course of such inquiry, to receive and record evidence.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-72.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any evidence recorded under clause (d) of sub-section (1) shall be admissible in subsequent trial before a Magistrate, provided that it has been taken in the presence of accused person.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-73">
          <num>73.</num>
          <heading>Forest officers deemed public servants.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-73.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>All Forest-officers shall be deemed be public servants within the meaning of the Indian Penal Code, 1860 (45 of 1860).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-74">
          <num>74.</num>
          <heading>Indemnity for acts done in good faith.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-74.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No suit shall lie against any public servant for anything done by him in good faith under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-75">
          <num>75.</num>
          <heading>Forest-officers not to trade.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-75.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Except with the permission in writing of the State Government, no Forest-officer shall, as principal or agent, trade in timber or other forest produce, or be or become interested in any lease of any forest or in any contract for working any forest, whether in or outside 17 the territories to which this Act extends.</p>
              <p>CHAP TER XII-SUBSIDIARY RULES</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-76">
          <num>76.</num>
          <heading>Additional powers to make rules.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-76.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-76.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The State Government may make rules</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-76.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to prescribe and limit the powers and duties of any Forest-officer under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-76.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>to regulate the rewards to be paid to officers and informers out of the proceeds of fines and confiscation under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-76.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>for the preservation, reproduction and disposal of trees and timber belonging to Government, but grown on lands belonging to or in the occupation of private persons; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-76.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>generally, to carry out the provisions of this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-77">
          <num>77.</num>
          <heading>Penalties for breach of rules.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-77.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Any person contravening any rule under this Act, for the contravention of which no special penalty is provided, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one month, or fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, or both.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-78">
          <num>78.</num>
          <heading>Rules when to have force of law.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-78.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>All rules made by the State Government under this Act shall be published in the Official Gazette, and shall thereupon, so far as they are consistent with this Act, have effect as if enacted therein.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-XIII">
        <num>XIII</num>
        <heading>Miscellaneous</heading>
        <section id="section-79">
          <num>79.</num>
          <heading>Persons bound to assist Forest-officers and Police-officers.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-79.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-79.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Every person who exercises any right in a reserved or protected forest, or who is permitted to take any forest-produce from, or to cut and remove timber or to pasture cattle in, such forest, and every person who is employed by any such person in such forest, and every person in any village contiguous to such forest who is employed by the Government or who receives emoluments from the Government for services to be performed to the community, shall be bound to furnish without unnecessary delay to the nearest Forest-officer or Police officer any information he may possess respecting the commission of, or intention to commit, any forest-offence, and shall forthwith take steps, whether so required by any Forest-officer or Police officer or not,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-79.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to extinguish any forest fire in such forest of which he has knowledge or information;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-79.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>to prevent by any lawful means in his power any fire in the vicinity of such forest of which he has knowledge or information from spreading to such forest, and shall assist any Forest-officer or Police-officer demanding his aid−</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-79.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>in preventing the commission in such forest of any forest-offence; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-79.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>when there is reason to believe that any such offence has been committed such forest in discovering and arresting the offender.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-79.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-79.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Any person who, being bound so to do, without lawful excuse (the burden ofprovin which shall lie upon such person) fails−</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-79.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to furnish without unnecessary delay to the nearest Forest-officer or Polic( officer any information required by sub-section (1);</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-79.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>to take steps, as required by sub-section (1), to extinguish any forest fire in reserved or protected forest;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-79.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>to prevent, as required by sub-section (1), any fire in the vicinity of such fore.4 from spreading to such forest or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-79.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>to assist any Forest-officer or Police officer demanding his aid in preventing th commission in such forest of any forest-offence, or, when there is reason believe that any such offence has been committed in such forest, in discover and arresting the offender,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which extend to one month, or with fine which may extend to two hundred rupees, or with both.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-80">
          <num>80.</num>
          <heading>Management of forests the joint property of Government and other persons. –</heading>
          <subsection id="section-80.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-80.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>If the Government and any person be jointly interested in any forest or waste-land, a in the whole or any part of the produce thereof, the State Government may either−</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-80.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>undertake the management of such forest, waste-land or produce, accounting to such person for his interest in the same; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-80.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>issue such regulations for the management of the forest, waste-land or produce by the person so jointly interested as it deems necessary for the management thereof and the interests of all parties therein.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-80.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When the State Government undertakes under clause (a) of sub-section (1) the management of any forest, waste-land or produce, it may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare that any of the provisions contained in Chapters 11 and IV shall apply to such forest, waste-land or produce, and thereupon such provisions shall apply accordingly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-81">
          <num>81.</num>
          <heading>Failure to perform service for which a share in produce of Government forest is employed.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-81.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>If any person be entitled to a share in the produce of any forest which is the property of Government or over which the Government has proprietary rights or to any part of the forest-produce of which the Government is entitled upon the condition of duly performing any service connected with such forest, such share shall be liable to confiscation in the event of the fact being established to the satisfaction of the State Government that such service is no longer so performed:</p>
              <p>Provided that no such share be confiscated until the person entitled thereto, and the evidence, if any, which he may produce in proof of the due performance of such service, have been heard by an officer duly appointed in that behalf by the State Government.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-82">
          <num>82.</num>
          <heading>Recovery of money due to Government.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-82.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>All money payable to the Government under this Act, or under any rule made under this Act, or on account of the price of any forest produce, or of expenses incurred in the execution of this Act in respect of such produce, may, if not paid when due, be recovered under the law for the time being in force as if it were an arrear of land-revenue.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-83">
          <num>83.</num>
          <heading>Lien on forest-produce for such money.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-83.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When any such money is payable for or in respect of any forest-produce, the amount thereof shall deemed to be a first charge on such produce, and such produce may be taken possession of by a Forest-officer until such amount has been paid.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-83.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If such amount is not paid when due, the Forest-officer may sell such produce by public auction, and the proceeds of the sale shall be applied first in discharging such amount.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-83.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The surplus, if any, if not claimed within two months from the date of the sale by the person entitled thereto, shall be forfeited to Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-84">
          <num>84.</num>
          <heading>Land required under this Act to be deemed to be needed for a public purpose under the Land Acquisition Act, 1894.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-84.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Whenever it appears to the State Government that any land is required for any of the purposes of this Act, such land shall be deemed to be needed for a public purpose within the meaning of section 4 of the Land Acquisition Act, 1894 (1 of 1894).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-85">
          <num>85.</num>
          <heading>Recovery of penalties due under bond.−</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-85.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>When any person, in accordance with any provision of this Act, or in compliance with any rule made thereunder, binds himself by any an bond or instrument to perform any duty or act or covenants by any bond or instrument that he, or that he and his servants and agents will abstain from any act, the whole sum mentioned in such bond or instrument as the amount to be paid in case of a breach of the conditions thereof may, notwithstanding anything in section 74 of the Indian Contract Act, 1872 (9 of 1872), be recovered from him in case of such breach as if it were an arrear of land revenue.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-85A">
          <num>85A.</num>
          <heading>Saving for rights of Central Government.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-85A.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in this Act shall authorise a Government of any State to make any order or do anything in relation to any property not vested in that State or otherwise prejudice any rights of the Central Government or the Government of any other State without the consent of the Government concerned.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-86">
          <num>86.</num>
          <heading>Repeals.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-86.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Rep. by Repealing and Amending Act, 1947 (2 of 1948), sec.2 and Sch.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
