<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1985/2/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1985/2"/>
          <FRBRalias value="Karnataka Advocates' Welfare Fund Act, 1983"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1985/2/eng@1985-12-28/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1985/2/eng@1985-12-28"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1985-12-28" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1985/2/eng@1985-12-28/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1985/2/eng@1985-12-28"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-07-20" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>Karnataka Advocates' Welfare Fund Act, 1983</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>(Act No. 2 of 1985)</p>
      </longTitle>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[28th December, 1985]</docDate>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>An Act, to provide for the constitution of a welfare fund for the payment of retirement benefits to advocates in the State of Karnataka and for matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.</p>
      <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the constitution of a welfare fund for the payment of retirement benefits to advocates in the State of Karnataka and for matters connected therewith or incidental thereto;</p>
      <p>BE it enacted by the Karnataka State Legislature in the Thirty-fourth year of the Republic of India as follows:-</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Karnataka Advocates' Welfare Fund Act, 1983.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the State Government may, by notification in the official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act unless the context otherwiserequires,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"advocate" means a personwhose name has been entered in the State roll of Advocates prepared andmaintained by the Bar Council of Karnataka under section 17 of the Advocates'Act, 1961 (Central Act 25 of 1961) and includes a legal practitioner whoserights are saved under section 55 of the said Act and who ordinarily practicesin the State of Karnataka;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"bar association" means anassociation of advocates recognised by the Bar Council under section 13;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>"Bar Council", means the BarCouncil of Karnataka constituted under section 3 of the Advocates' Act, 1961(Central Act 25 of 1961);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>"cessation of practice" meansremoval of the name of an advocate from the roll maintained by the Bar Councilor non-renewal of Pleadership Certificate on the ground of,-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>death; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>permanent disability; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>voluntary retirement on attaining an age of seventy five years or on completion of fifty years of practice whichever is earlier;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>"dependents" means wife,husband, father, mother and unmarried minor children or suchof them as are alive;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>"Fund" means the AdvocatesWelfare Fund constituted under section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.ff">
                <num>(ff)</num>
                <p>interlocutory application includes all applications filed before any Court, Tribunal or Authority in respect of any pending or disposed of case or proceeding;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>"member" means member of the fund;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.ga">
                <num>(ga)</num>
                <p>"permanent disability” means disability incurred by an advocate after becoming a member which renders him totally incapable from practicing as an advocate and certified as such by the District Surgeon of the District where the advocate is practicing;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>"prescribed" means prescribed by the Bar Council by rules made underthis Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>"retirement" means stoppage ofpractice as an advocate communicated to and recorded by the Bar Council andthe trustee committee;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>"registered clerk"means a person who is registered as a recognised clerk or gumasta of anadvocate or a pleader in connection with any rules passed by the High Court ofKarnataka under Article 225 of the Constitution of India and section 54 of theState Re-organisation Act, 1956 or under section 122 of the Code of CivilProcedure or any other law.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.jj">
                <num>(jj)</num>
                <p>“schedule” means the schedule appended to this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>"stamp" means the stampprinted and distributed under section 22;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>"State" means the State ofKarnataka;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>"suspension of practice" meansvoluntary suspension of practice as an advocate or suspension by the BarCouncil for misconduct; Certain words have been inserted by Act 18 of2002 but yet to be brought into force. The text of the amendment is producedbelow.-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>in clause (m) the words figures andbrackets "and includes deemed voluntary suspension of practice referred toin sub-section (4) of section 16 " shall be inserted at the end</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>"trustee committee" means thecommittee established under section 4;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>"vakalath" means vakalathnama and includes memorandum of appearanceor any other document by which an advocate is empowered to appear or pleadbefore any court, tribunal or other authority.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Advocates Welfare Fund</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government shall constitute afund called the Karnataka Advocates' Welfare Fund for the payment of retirement and otherbenefits to the advocates and their dependents, in the State.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>There shall be credited to the Fund,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>Deleted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any contribution made by the Bar Council;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any voluntary donation or contribution made to the Fund by the Bar Council of India, any bar association, any other association or institution, any advocateor any other person;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>any grant made by the State Governmentto the Fund;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the amounts set apart from the LegalBenefit Fund constituted under section 76A of the Karnataka Court Fees andSuits Valuation Act, 1958 (Karnataka Act 16 of 1958), for providing socialsecurity measures for the legal profession;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>any sum borrowed under section 10;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>all sums received from the LifeInsurance Corporation of India on the death of an advocate under the groupinsurance policy;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>any profit or dividend received from theLife Insurance Corporation of India in respect of policies of Group Insuranceof the members of the Fund;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>any interest or dividend or other returnon any investment made of any part of the Fund;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>all sums collected by way of sale ofwelfare fund stamps under section 22;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>amounts collected under section 15 by way ofadmission fee.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The sums specified in sub-section (2),shall be paid to, or collected by, such agencies, at such intervals and in suchmanner, and the accounts of the Fund shall be maintained and operated in suchmanner, as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Establishment of trustee committee.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification, establish with effect from such date as may be specified therein a committee to be called the Karnataka Advocates' Welfare Fund Trustee Committee.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The trustee committee shall be a body corporate having perpetual succession and a common seal with power to acquire and hold property and shall, by the said name, sue and be sued.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The trustee committee shall consists of,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>The Chairman of the Bar Council who shall be the chairman of the Trustee Committee, ex-officio;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.aa">
                <num>(aa)</num>
                <p>The Advocate General of Karnataka who shall be a member- Ex-officio.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>The Secretary, Department of Law, Government of Karnataka who shall be a Member Ex-officio.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>two members nominated by the State Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>three members of the Bar Council nominated by it;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the Chairman of the Bar Council, who shall be the Treasurer of the trustee committee, ex-officio; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the Secretary of the Bar Council, who shall be the Secretary of the trustee committee, ex-officio;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A member nominated by the State Government under clause (c) of sub-section (3), shall hold office for a term of three years.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A member nominated by the Bar Council under clause (d) of sub-section (3), shall hold office for a term of three years or for the duration of his membership in the Bar Council, whichever is less.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Disqualification and removal of nominated members of trustee committee</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A member nominated under clause (c) or clause (d) of sub-section (3) of section 4, shall be disqualified to be a member of the trustee committee, if he,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>becomes of unsound mind; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>is adjudged an insolvent; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>is absent without leave of the trustee committee, for more than three consecutive meetings thereof; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>has committed breach of trust; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>is convicted by a criminal court for an offence involving moral turpitude, unless such conviction has been set aside by a competent court.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may remove any member who is or has become disqualified under sub-section (1) from membership of the trustee committee:</p>
            <p>Provided that no order removing any member shall be passed unless that member and the Bar Council, in the case of a member nominated by it, have been given an opportunity of being heard.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Resignation by nominated members of trustee committee and filling up of casual vacancies.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any member nominated under clause (c) or clause (d) of sub-section (3) of section 4, may resign his office by giving one months' notice in writing to the State Government or the Bar Council, as the case may be, and on such resignation being accepted by the State Government or the Bar Council, shall be deemed to have vacated his office:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Bar Council shall consult the State Government before accepting the resignation.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A casual vacancy in the office of a member referred to in sub-section (1), may be filled as soon as may be, by the State Government or the Bar Council, as the case may be, and a member so nominated to fill such vacancy shall hold office for the unexpired portion of the term of office of the member whose place he fills.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Act of trustee committee not to be invalidated by vacancy, defect, etc</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>No act done or proceeding taken under this Act or the rules made thereunder by the trustee committee shall be invalidated merely by reason of,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any vacancy or defect in the constitution of the committee; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any defect or irregularity in the nomination of any person as a member thereof; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any defect or irregularity in such act or proceeding not affecting the merits of the case.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Vesting and application of Fund</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Fund shall vest in , and be held and applied by, trustee committee subject to the provisions and for the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Function of trustee committee</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The trustee committee shall administer the Fund.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In the administration of the Fund, the trustee committee shall, subject to the provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>hold the amounts and assets belonging to the Fund in trust;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>Deleted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>receive applications from the members of the Fund, their nominees or legal representatives, as the case may be, for payments out of the Fund, conduct such enquiry as it deems necessary for the disposal of such applications and dispose of the applications within three months from the date of receipt thereof;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>record in the minutes book of the trustee committee, its decisions on the applications;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>pay to the members amounts in accordance with the Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>send such periodical and annual reports as may be prescribed, to the State Government and the Bar Council;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>communicate to the applicants by registered post with acknowledgment due, the decisions of the trustee committee in respect of claims to the benefits of the fund;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>do such other acts as are, or may be, required to be done under this Act and the rules made thereunder.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Borrowing and investment</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The trustee committee may, with theprior approval of the State Government and the Bar Council, borrow from time totime any sum required for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The trustee committee shall deposit allmoneys and receipts forming part of the Fund in any scheduled bank or investthe same in loans to any corporation owned or controlled by the CentralGovernment or the State Government or in loans floated by the CentralGovernment or the State Government or in any other manner as the Bar Councilmay, from time to time direct with the prior approval of the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All amounts due and payable under thisAct and all expenditure relating to the management and administration of theFund and allexpenditure relating to supply of Welfare Fund stamps shall be paid outof the Fund.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The accounts of the trustee committeeshall be audited annually by a chartered accountant appointed by the Bar Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The accounts of the trustee committee,as certified by the auditor, together with the audit reports thereon, shall beforwarded to the Bar Council by the trustee committee and the Bar Council mayissue such directions as it deems fit to the trustee committee in respectthereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The trustee committee shall comply withthe directions issued by the Bar Council under sub-section (5).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Powers and duties of Secretary</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Secretary of the trustee committee shall,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>be the chief executive authority of the trustee committee and be responsible for carrying out its decisions;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>represent the trustee committee in all suits and proceedings for and against it;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>authenticate by his signature all decisions and instructions of the trustee committee;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>operate the bank accounts of the trustee committee jointly with the Chairman;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>convene meetings of the trustee committee and prepare its minutes;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>attend the meetings of the trustee committee with all the necessary records and information;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>maintain such forms, registers and other records as may be prescribed from time to time and do all correspondence relating to the trustee committee;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>inspect and verify periodically the accounts and registers of the Bar Associations regarding stamps;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>prepare an annual statement of business transacted by the trustee committee during each financial year; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>do such other acts as may be directed by the trustee committee.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Deleted;</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Recognition and registration of bar associations</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All associations of advocates known by any name functioning in any court centre may, before a date to be notified by the Bar Council in this behalf, apply to the Bar Council in such form as may be prescribed for recognition and registration.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every application for recognition and registration shall be accompanied by the rules or bye-laws of the association made by adopting model by-laws circulated by the Bar Council, and registered under the Karnataka Societies Registration Act, 1960 (Karnataka Act 17 of 1960), names and addresses of the office bearers of the association and with an uptodate list of the members of the association showing the name, address, age, date of enrolment and the ordinary place of practice of each member.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Bar Council may, after such enquiry as it deems necessary, recognise the bar association and issue a certificate of registration in such form as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The decision of the Bar Council regarding the recognition and registration of the bar association shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to such rules and conditions as may be prescribed by the Government every registered bar association may be paid grants by the Government every year.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Duties of bar associations</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every bar association shall, on or before the 30th April of every year, intimate to the Bar Council a list of its members as on the 31st March of that year.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Every bar association shall intimate to the Bar Council,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any change of the office bearers of the association within fifteen days from such change;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any change in the membership including admission or re-admission within thirty days of such change;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the death, retirement or voluntary suspension of practice of any of its members within thirty days from the date of occurrence thereof; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>such other matter as may be required by the Bar Council or the Government from time to time.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Membershipof the Fund.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Advocate on the roll of the Karnataka State Bar Council and every person holding pleadership certificate practicing in the State of Karnataka shall be a member of the Fund and shall file a declaration in such form along with such admission fee as may be prescribed. -</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every member shall furnish the particularsof place of practice with such other details as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every member who voluntarily suspendspractice or retires shall within fifteen days of such suspension or retirementintimate that fact to the trustee committee and if any member fails to do sowithout sufficient reason the trustee committee may reduce the amount due tothat member in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every member who has completed fifteen years of practice shall pay a fee of rupees one thousand to the fund and who has not completed fifteen years of practice shall pay a fee of rupees five hundred to the fund on or before the thirty first day of December of every year, next after the year of becoming member, failing which, he shall be deemed to have voluntarily suspended practice for the purpose of this Act:</p>
            <p>Provided that a member may pay such fee within six months from the expiry of the due date along with a penalty of rupees fifty per month, in which case it shall not be construed as deemed voluntary suspension of practice:</p>
            <p>Provided further that a member who has completed fifteen years of practice may, in lieu of payment of fee every year, pay in a lumpsum rupees fifteen thousand.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (4), a member who is enrolled as an advocate before attaining an age of forty years, fails to pay fees under subsection (4) after attaining an age of seventy years shall be eligible to claim benefit under sub-section (1) of sub-section 16, so however, arrears of fee due under subsection (4) shall be deducted in the amount payable under sub-section (1) of subsection 16.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For every year of deemed suspension under sub-section (4) an amount of rupees five thousand per annum shall be deducted from out of the amount payable under sub-section (1) of section 16.</p>
            <p>Provided that where a deemed suspension under sub-section (4) is consecutively for a period of five years and more, amount payable under sub-section (1) of section 16 shall not exceed one lakh rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Payment from the Fund on cessation of practice</heading>
        <subsection id="section-16.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-16.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where the cessation of practice,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-16.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>is due to death of a member, his nominee and if there is no nominee, to his dependents or heirs as the case may be; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.1.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>is due to reasons other than death, the member, shall be entitled to receive an amount specified in the schedule, from out of the fund:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-16.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that the following categories of members shall be entitled to receive an amount at the rate of five thousand rupees for every completed year of practice subject to a maximum of rupees one lakh fifty thousand namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-16.1.list3.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>an advocate who becomes member after attaining an age of forty years except those who have become members prior to the commencement of the Karnataka Advocates’ Welfare Fund (Amendment ) Act, 2010;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.1.list3.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>an advocate enrolled after attaining an age of forty years;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.1.list3.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>an advocate who has voluntarily suspended practice for a period exceeding two years for the purposes of any employment, avocation or business;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.1.list3.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>an advocate enrolled after retirement, dismissal or removal from service or employment;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.1.list3.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>an advocate who has become member on or after the first day of August 2000 and has attained an age of sixty years on the date of becoming member;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.1.list3.vi">
                <num>(vi)</num>
                <p>an advocate who becomes member on transfer from other states, after attaining an age of forty years:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided further that an advocate who had become member prior to the second day of April, 1997 and has failed to pay balance fee due and has not been re-admitted to the fund after the second day of April, 1997, shall be entitled only to an amount at the rate of three thousand rupees for every completed year of practice but not exceeding an amount of rupees fifty thousand and this amount shall be paid to him or to his nominees, and where there are no nominees to his dependants or heirs as the case may be on cessation of practice.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the event of the death of a member , the amount shall be paid to his nominee or, where there is no nominee, to his legal dependents or heirs in accordance with the law of inheritance applicable to such member.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Deleted;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-16.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>While calculating period of completed years of practice for the purpose of payment under this Act,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-16.4.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>fraction of three months and more shall be treated as one full year; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.4.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>the period of suspension practice as a result of misconduct under section 35 of the Advocates Act, 1961 (Central Act 25 of 1961) shall be excluded.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.4A">
          <num>(4A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In case of an advocate enrolled prior to the second day of April 1997 and admitted to the fund after the Second day of April 2002, every four years of practice before admission as a member to the fund shall be computed as one year of completed year of practice and added on to the number of completed years of practice after such admission for the purpose of payment under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Deleted;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An application for payment from the Fund shall be preferred to the trustee committee in such form as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An application received under sub-section (6), shall be disposed of by the trustee committee after such enquiry as it deems necessary.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If a claim made by any applicant under sub-section (6) is found to be false or incorrect by the trustee committee after making payment to him based on such claim, the trustee committee may, after holding such enquiry as it deems fit and after giving an opportunity of being heard to the applicant, direct him to refund the amount paid in excess of the amount due to him, and in case of default it shall be recoverable as an arrear of land revenue.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16A">
        <num>16A.</num>
        <heading>Medical relief.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-16A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any member suffering from such serious ailment as may be prescribed undergoes treatment for the prescribed ailment, he may apply to the Trustee committee in such form along with such documents as may be prescribed for payment from the fund towards the amount actually incurred for the treatment:</p>
            <p>Provided that, the amount payable under this section shall not exceed rupees one lakh or fifty percent of the amount payable under section 16, whichever is less.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The member should have completed five years of practice as a member of the fund on the date of treatment.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The application should be made within three months from the date of initial hospitalization and this may be extended by the trustee committee for a further period of three months on the member showing sufficient cause for delay in making the application.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16A.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The benefit under this section shall be available only once in the life time of the member.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16A.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Total number of applications which may be considered for payment under this section during a financial year shall be fixed by the trustee committee having regard to its financial position, feasibility of future operation of the fund, need of the applicant and other relevant factors.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16A.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The trustee committee may after making such enquiry as it deems fit, either grant or reject the application. The application shall be considered strictly according to the date of their filing.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16A.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The amount paid under this section shall be deducted at the time of making final payment under section 16.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16A.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an applicant has received amount in respect of his ailment under the Bar Council of India Advocate’s Welfare Fund Scheme, the trustee committee shall while granting amount under this section deduct the amount so received under that scheme.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16A.9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any statements or particulars given by the applicant or documents produced in support of his claim are found to be false by the trustee committee, it shall make a report to the Bar council and the Bar council may after holding such enquiry as it deems fit and after giving an opportunity of being heard to the applicant call upon him to refund the entire amount received under this section along with an interest at the rate of twelve percent per annum. If the applicant fails to comply with the direction of the Bar council, the entire amount received under this section along with an interest at the rate of twelve percent per annum shall be deducted while making final payment under section 16.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16B">
        <num>16B.</num>
        <heading>Part payment from the fund during financial hardship.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-16B.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A member who has attained the age of seventy years and has completed twenty years of practice as an advocate and twelve years as a member of the fund is facing a financial hardship may apply in a prescribed form to the trustee committee seeking part payment from the fund. The Situation leading to such financial hardship shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16B.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the trustee committee is satisfied with the claim of the applicant it may, with the prior approval of the Bar Council, sanction an amount equivalent to fifty percent of entitlement of the applicant under section 16 or one lakh rupees whichever is less.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16B.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The applications shall be considered strictly according to their dates of filing.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16B.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The amount paid under this section shall be deducted at the time of making final payment under section 16.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16B.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Total number of applications which may be considered for payment under this section during a financial year shall be fixed by the trustee committee having regard to its financial position, feasibility of future operation of the fund and need of the applicant and other relevant factors as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Restriction on alienation, attachment, etc., of interest in the Fund</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The interest of any member in the Fund, or the right of a member or his nominee or legal heirs to receive any amount from the Fund, shall not be assigned, alienated or charged and shall not be liable to attachment under any decree or order of any court, tribunal or other authority.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No creditor shall be entitled to proceed against the Fund or the interest therein of any member or his nominee or heirs.</p>
            <p>Explanation.- For the purposes of this section, 'creditor' includes the State or an official assignee or receiver appointed under the Provincial Insolvency Act, 1920 or any other law for the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Group Life Insurance for members and other benefits</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-18.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Bar Council may, for the welfare of the members of the Fund,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>obtain from the Life Insurance Corporation of India policies of group insurance for the members of the Fund ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>Deleted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>provide for such other benefits as may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Meetings of trustee committee</heading>
        <subsection id="section-19.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The trustee committee shall meet at least once in three months or more often if found necessary to transact business under this Act or the rules made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Three members of the trustee committee shall form the quorum for a meeting of the committee.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chairman or in his absence, a member elected by the members present shall preside over a meeting of the trustee committee.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any matter coming before a meeting of the trustee committee shall be decided by a majority of the members present and voting at the meeting and, in the case of an equality of votes, the Chairman or the member presiding over the meeting shall have a casting vote.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Travelling and daily allowance to members of trustee committee</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The non-official members of the trustee committee shall be eligible to get such travelling allowance and daily allowance as are admissible to the members of the Bar Council.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Appeal against decisions of trustee committee</heading>
        <subsection id="section-21.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An appeal against any decision of the trustee committee shall lie to the Bar Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-21.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-21.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The appeal shall be in the prescribed form and shall be accompanied by,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-21.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>a copy of the order appealed against; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-21.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>a receipt evidencing payment of one hundred rupees to the credit of the Bar Council, in any of the branches in Karnataka of any Scheduled Bank.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-21.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The appeal shall be filed within thirty days from the date of receipt of the order appealed against.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-21.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The decision of the Bar Council on the appeal shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Printing and distribution of stamps by Bar Council</heading>
        <subsection id="section-22.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Bar Council shall cause to be printed Welfare Fund stamps of the value of five rupees or ten rupees with the Bar Council Emblem and its value inscribed thereon.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-22.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The welfare Fund stamps shall be of the size 1"x2" and be sold only to members of the Fund.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-22.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The custody of the welfare Fund stamps shall be with the Bar Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-22.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Bar Council shall control the distribution and sale of the welfare Fund stamps through bar associations.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-22.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Bar Council and the bar association shall keep proper accounts of the welfare Fund stamps in such form and in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-22.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The bar associations shall purchase the welfare Fund stamps from the Bar Council after paying the value thereof less ten per cent of such value towards incidental expenses.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Vakalath to bear stamps</heading>
        <subsection id="section-23.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Advocate shall affix one welfare Fund stamp on every vakalath filed by him and no vakalath shall be filed before or received by any court, tribunal or other authority unless it is so stamped.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.1A">
          <num>(1A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Advocate shall affix Welfare Fund stamp of the value of rupees five on every interlocutory application.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every welfare Fund stamp affixed on vakalaths filed before any court, tribunal or other authority shall be cancelled in the manner provided in the Karnataka Court Fees and Suits Valuation Act, 1958 (Karnataka Act 16 of 1958).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The value of the welfare Fund stamp shall neither be costs in the case nor be collected in any event from the client.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any contravention of the provisions of sub- section (3) by the member shall disentitle him to the benefits of the Fund and the trustee committee shall report such instances to the Bar Council for appropriate action.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23A">
        <num>23A.</num>
        <heading>Contribution by Senior Advocate</heading>
        <subsection id="section-23A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every designated Senior Advocate shall contribute rupees five thousand in every financial year to the Fund before thirty first March.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any designated Senior Advocate fails to pay the contribution under sub-section (1) on or before thirty-first March of every year, such contribution may be paid within six months from that date together with a late fee of rupees one hundred per month or part of a month subject to a maximum of rupees five hundred.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the event of non-payment of contribution within the period specified in sub-section (2) such default shall be construed as deemed suspension of practice for the purpose of this Act and the provisions of sub-sections (5) and (6) of section 15 shall mutatis mutandis apply.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith</heading>
        <subsection id="section-24.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against any person for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any rule made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No suit or other legal proceedings shall lie against the trustee committee or the Bar Council for any damage caused or likely to be caused by anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any rule made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Bar of jurisdiction of civil courts</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No civil court shall have jurisdiction to settle, decide or deal with any question or to determine any matter which is by or under this Act required to be settled, decided or dealt with or to be determined by the trustee committee or the Bar Council.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Power to summon witnesses and take evidence</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-26.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The trustee committee and the Bar Council shall, for the purposes of any enquiry under this Act, have the same powers as are vested in a civil court while trying a suit under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908, in respect of the following matters, namely:--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>enforcing the attendance of any person or examining him on oath;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>requiring the discovery and production of documents;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>receiving evidence on affidavit;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Registered Clerks Welfare Fund</heading>
        <subsection id="section-27.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to such rules as may be prescribed by it, the State Government shall constitute a fund called the Karnataka Registered Clerks' Welfare Fund for payment of retirement benefits to the registered clerks in the State.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-27.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>There shall be credited to the Fund,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-27.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any grant that may be made by the State Government; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-27.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any donation or contribution made to the Fund by the Bar Council of India, Bar Council, any Bar Association, any association or authority, institution, any advocate or any other person.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government shall constitute a committee for the administration of the Fund.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may make rules to provide for all matters relating to the Fund including its membership and administration and the conditions subject to which payment from the Fund shall be made.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28">
        <num>28.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Bar Council may, with the previous approval of the State Government, by notification in the official Gazette, make rules for the purposes of carrying into effect the provisions of this Act other than for provisions of section 27.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29">
        <num>29.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of Act 16 of 1958</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-29.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In the Karnataka Court Fees and Suits Valuation Act, 1958 (Karnataka Act 16 of 1958), after section 76 , the following section shall be inserted, namely:-</p>
            <p>"76A. Legal Benefit Fund.-</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-29.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act or any other law for the time being in force, it shall be competent for the State Government to levy an additional court-fee, by notification, in respect of appeals or revisions to tribunals or appellate authorities, other than Civil and Criminal courts, at a rate not exceeding one hundred rupees for each appeal or revision.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be constituted a legal benefit fund to which shall be credited the proceeds of the additional court-fee levied and collected under sub-section (1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The fund constituted under sub-section (2), shall be applied and utilised for the purpose of providing an efficient legal service for the people of the State and to provide social security measures for the legal profession.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The mode and manner in which legal service to the people may be made more efficient and social security measures for the legal profession may be provided, shall be as prescribed by rules made by Government".</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-schedule">
      <doc name="schedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1985/2/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1985/2"/>
              <FRBRalias value="Schedule"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1985/2/eng@1985-12-28/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1985/2/eng@1985-12-28"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1985/2/eng@1985-12-28/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1985/2/eng@1985-12-28"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-05-30" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="schedule">
            <paragraph id="schedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>(see sub-section (1) of section 16)</p>
                <table id="schedule.paragraph-0.table1">
                  <tr>
                    <th>
                      <p>Completed years of practice</p>
                    </th>
                    <td>
                      <p>Entitlement</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>(1) Not exceeding ten years</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rupees one lakh fifty thousand</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>(2) Exceeding ten years but not exceeding twenty years</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rupees two lakhs</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>(3) Exceeding twenty years but not exceeding thirty years</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rupees two lakhs fifty thousand</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>(4) Exceeding thirty years but not exceeding forty years</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rupees three lakhs fifty thousand</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>(5) Exceeding forty years</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rupees four lakhs</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </table>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
