<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1976/11/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1976/11"/>
          <FRBRalias value="Karnataka Improvement Boards Act, 1976"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1976/11/eng@1976-03-02/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1976/11/eng@1976-03-02"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1976-03-02" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1976/11/eng@1976-03-02/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1976/11/eng@1976-03-02"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-06-18" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>Karnataka Improvement Boards Act, 1976</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>(Act, No. 11 of 1976)</p>
      </longTitle>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[2nd March, 1976]</docDate>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>An Act to provide for the establishment of Improvement Boards for the development of urban areas in the State of Karnataka and for matters connected therewith.</p>
      <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the establishment of Improvement Boards for the development of urban areas in the State of Karnataka;</p>
      <p>BE it enacted by the Karnataka State Legislature in the Twenty-seventh Year of the Republic of India as follows:-</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <heading>Preliminary</heading>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title, extent and commencement</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the Karnataka Improvement Boards Act, 1976.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Karnataka.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the twentieth day of November, 1975 in the urban areas comprising the Hubli-Dharwar Municipal Corporation and the cities of Belgaum, Bellary, Bijapur, Bhadravathi, Davangere, Gulbarga and Shimoga, and on such date and in such other urban areas as the State Government may, by notification, specify and different dates may be specified for different urban areas.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions</heading>
          <subsection id="section-2.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>'Bagalkot Town Area' means the area comprising the Bagalkot City Municipality constituted or continued under the Karnataka Municipalities Act, 1964 and such other area adjacent thereto, as the Government may, from time to time, by notification specify;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.aa">
                  <num>(aa)</num>
                  <p>'Board' means an Improvement Board established under section 3 for any urban area 1 [and includes the Bagakot Town Development Authority constituted under section 12-A;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>'Chairman' means the Chairman of the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>'development', with its grammatical variations means the carrying out of building, engineering or other operations in, on, over or under the land or the making of any material change in any building or land and includes re-development but does not include regulation and development of drinking water and drainage facilities and slum clearance or slum improvement;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>'development scheme' means a scheme prepared and sanctioned under this Act for purposes of the development of an urban area;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>'engineering operations' includes the formation or laying out of means of access to a road or the laying out of means of water supply;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>'Government' means the State Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>'improvement' with its grammatical variations means re-development of any built up area, whether partly built or fully built for the purpose of improving the environmental conditions of the locality by undertaking work such as widening of roads extending or augmenting civic amenities, community facilities, utilities and services but does not include regulation and development of drinking water and drainage facilities and slum clearance or slum improvement;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>'improvement scheme' means a scheme prepared and sanctioned under this Act for purposes of the improvement of an urban area;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>'land' includes benefits to arise out of land and things attached to the earth or permanently fastened to anything attached to the earth;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>'local authority' means a Municipal Corporation, Municipal Council, Sanitary Board or a Notified Area Committee constituted or continued under any law for the time being in force;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>'member' means a member of the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>'planning authority' means a Planning Authority as defined in clause (7) of section 2 of the Karnataka Town and Country Planning Act, 1961;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.m">
                  <num>(m)</num>
                  <p>'section' means a section of this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.n">
                  <num>(n)</num>
                  <p>'street' has the same meaning as in the Karnataka Municipalities Act, 1964;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.o">
                  <num>(o)</num>
                  <p>'urban area' means any local area which is within the jurisdiction of a local authority and includes such other area adjacent to the limits of the local authority, as the Government may, from time to time, by notification, specify.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All other words and expressions used herein but not defined shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the respective Municipal laws in force in the area.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <heading>Improvement boards</heading>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>- Establishment and Incorporation of Improvement Boards</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As soon as may be, after the commencement of this Act the Government, may by notification, establish for the purposes of this Act a Board for any urban area to be called the "The Improvement Board of...................".</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall be a body corporate by the name aforesaid having perpetual succession and a common seal, with power to acquire, hold and dispose of property and to contract and shall by the said name sue and be sued.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The jurisdiction of the Board constituted in respect of any urban area shall stand extended to such other areas as may be notified under clause (o) of sub-section (1) of section 2 in respect of such urban area, with effect from the date of such notification.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Constitution of the Board</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Board shall consist of the following members, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>a Chairman who shall be appointed by the Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>an officer of the Town and Country Planning Department not below the rank of an Assistant Director of Town and Country Planning appointed by the Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the Executive Engineer of the division;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.cc">
                  <num>(cc)</num>
                  <p>two persons, of whom one shall be a woman and one shall be a person belonging to the Scheduled Castes or the Scheduled Tribes, who shall be appointed by the Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>two persons who are ordinarily resident in the urban area for which the Board is constituted, appointed by the Government; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>two elected representatives of the local authority concerned.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Term of office</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the pleasure of the Government, the Chairman and other members appointed by the Government shall hold office for a period of three years:</p>
              <p>Provided that the term of office of the representative of the local authority shall come to an end when he ceases to be a councillor or member or when the local authority is superseded.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chairman or a member, other than an ex-officio member, may resign his office by writing under his hand addressed to the Government but shall continue in office until his resignation is accepted.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No act or proceeding of the Board shall be invalid by reason only of the existence of any vacancy or defect in the constitution of the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Casual vacancy</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Any casual vacancy in the office of a member other than the Chairman occasioned by death, resignation or disqualification of such member or occasioned by virtue of the proviso to sub-section (1) of section 5 shall be filled within one month of the occurrence of the vacancy in the same manner and subject so far as may be, to the same conditions specified in section 41 or section 12-A:</p>
              <p>Provided that the representatives of a superseded local authority shall be nominated by the Government:</p>
              <p>Provided further that the member so chosen or nominated shall continue in office for the remainder of the term of the member in whose place he is appointed.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Disqualification for office of membership</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-7.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>A person shall be disqualified for being appointed as and for being a member if he,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>has been convicted and sentenced to imprisonment for an offence which in the opinion of the Government involves moral turpitude; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>is of unsound mind and stands so declared by a competent court; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>is an undischarged insolvent; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>has been removed or dismissed from the service of the Central Government or a State Government or a corporation owned or controlled by the Central Government or a State Government; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.1.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>has directly or indirectly by himself or his partner any share or interest in any work done by the order of the Board or in any contract or employment with or under or by or on behalf of the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.1.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>being an elected member ceases to be a councillor or a member of the local authority concerned;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.1.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>is employed as paid legal practitioner on behalf of the Board or accepts employment as legal practitioner against the Board.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A person shall not be disqualified under clause (e) of sub-section (1) or be deemed to have any share or interest in any contract or employment within the meaning of the said clause by reason only of his having a share or interest in any newspaper in which any advertisement relating to the affairs of the Board is inserted.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Removal of member</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Government shall remove a member if,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>he becomes subject to any of the disqualifications mentioned in section 7:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that no member shall be removed on the ground that he has become subject to the disqualification mentioned in clause (e) of that section, unless he has been given an opportunity of making his representation aganist the proposal ; or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>he refuses to act or becomes incapable of acting; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>he, without obtaining leave of absence from the Board, absents from three consecutive meetings of the Board; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>in the opinion of the Government he has so abused his position as to render his continuance in office detrimental to the public interest:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that no member shall be removed under this clause unless he has been given an opportunity of making his representation against the proposal.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Meetings of the Board</heading>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The meetings of the Board shall be convened by the Chairman and shall be held at any place within the jurisdiction of the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall meet at such times and shall observe such rules of procedure in regard to the transaction of business at its meetings (including quorum) as may be provided by the bye-laws.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If, for any reason the Chairman is unable to attend any meeting, any other member chosen by the members present at the meeting shall preside at the meeting.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All questions which come up before any meeting of the Board shall be decided by a majority of the votes of the members present and voting and in the event of an equality of votes, the Chairman or in his absence, the person presiding shall have and exercise a second or casting vote.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A member shall not, at any meeting of the Board take part in the discussion of or vote on any matter in which he has directly or indirectly by himself or his partner, any share or interest.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Proceedings presumed to be good and valid</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No disqualification of or defect in the appointment of any person acting as Chairman or member shall be deemed to vitiate any act or proceeding of the Board if such act or proceeding is otherwise in accordance with the provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Execution of contracts</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every contract shall be made on behalf of the Board by the Chairman:</p>
              <blockList id="section-11.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.1.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>no contract involving an expenditure exceeding two lakhs rupees shall be made except with the previous sanction of the Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.1.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>( i) no contract involving an expenditure exceeding fifty thousand rupees but not exceeding two lakhs rupees shall, subject to clause (a), be made without the previous sanction of the Board;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>(ii ) no estimate or tender involving an expenditure of two lakhs rupees or more, shall, subject to clause (a), be sanctioned or accepted without the previous sanction of the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Sub-section (1) shall apply to every variation or abandonment of a contract or estimate.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every contract made by the Chairman shall, subject to the approval of the Board, be entered into in such manner and form as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any contract not made and executed as provided in this section and the rules made thereunder shall not be binding on the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Duties of Chairman</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Chairman shall-</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-12.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>attend every meeting of the Board, unless prevented by sickness or other reasonable cause;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>carry into effect the resolutions of the Board;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>keep and conduct the Board's correspondence;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>carry out and execute such schemes and works as the Government may require under sub-section (3) of section 13 and incur, subject to the other provisions of this Act, necessary expenditure therefor;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>exercise supervision and control over the acts and proceedings of all officers and servants of the Board in matters of executive administration and in matters concerning the accounts and records of the Board; and to the extent specified in section 54 dispose of all questions relating to the service conditions of officers and servants, and their pay, privileges and allowances;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>furnish to the Government a copy of the minutes of the Boards's proceedings and also furnish any returns or other information which the Government may, from time to time, call for; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>perform such other duties as are imposed on him by or under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IIA">
        <num>IIA</num>
        <heading>Bagalkot town development authority</heading>
        <section id="section-12A">
          <num>12A.</num>
          <heading>Constitution and incorporation of Bagalkot Town Development Authority</heading>
          <subsection id="section-12A.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Government shall by notification, constitute for the Bagalkot Town Area an authority to be called the Bagalkot Town Development Authority (hereinafter in this Chapter referred to as the Authority).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12A.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Authority shall be a body corporate by the name aforesaid having perpetual succession and common seal, with power to acquire, hold and dispose of property and to contract and shall by the said name sue and be sued.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12A.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-12A.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Authority shall consist of the following members, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12A.3.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>a Chairman who shall be appointed by the Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12A.3.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>the Member of the Parliament representing a part or whole of Bagalkot Town Area;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12A.3.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>the Members of the Karnataka Legislative Assembly representing a part or whole of Bagalkot Town Area;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12A.3.list1.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>the President of the City Municipal Council Bagalkot;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12A.3.list1.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>the Secretary to Government, Finance Department, Government of Karnataka, or his nominee ;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12A.3.list1.vi">
                  <num>(vi)</num>
                  <p>the Secretary to Government, Housing and Urban Development Department, Government of Karnataka, or his nominee;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12A.3.list1.vii">
                  <num>(vii)</num>
                  <p>the Secretary to Government, Public Works, Command Area Development and Electricity Department, Government of Karnataka, or his nominee ;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12A.3.list1.viii">
                  <num>(viii)</num>
                  <p>the Chief Engineer, Upper Krishna Project, Dam Zone, Almatti;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12A.3.list1.ix">
                  <num>(ix)</num>
                  <p>the Deputy Director of Town Planning, Belgaum;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12A.3.list1.x">
                  <num>(x)</num>
                  <p>the Deputy Commissioner, Bijapur District;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12A.3.list1.xi">
                  <num>(xi)</num>
                  <p>three non-official members being residents of Bagalkot Town Area appointed by the Government; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12A.3.list1.xii">
                  <num>(xii)</num>
                  <p>the Chief Engineer of the Authority who shall be the member-secretary.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12A.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Authority shall execute the works approved by the Action Plan Committee constituted under section 12-B.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12A.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of sections 12-A, 12-B, 12-C, 12-D, 12-E, 12-F and 12-G, the provisions of this Act shall mutatis mutandis apply to the Authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12B">
          <num>12B.</num>
          <heading>Action Plan Committee</heading>
          <subsection id="section-12B.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-12B.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In addition to the other powers and duties of the Authority under this Act, the Authority shall take expeditious steps to shift that portion of the Bagalkot Town Area which is to be submerged by the Almatti Dam and for this purpose, there shall be constituted an Action Plan Committee consisting of the following members, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12B.1.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the Additional Chief Secretary to Government of Karnataka who shall be the Chairman;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12B.1.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>the Commissioner and Secretary to Government, Revenue Department, Government of Karnataka;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12B.1.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>the Secretary to Government, Housing and Urban Development Department, Government of Karnataka;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12B.1.list1.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>the Secretaries to Government, Public Works Command Area Development and Electricity Department Government of Karnataka;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12B.1.list1.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>the Secretary to Government, Finance Department, Government of Karnataka.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12B.1.list1.vi">
                  <num>(vi)</num>
                  <p>the Director, Karnataka Engineering Research Station, Krishnaraja Sagar;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12B.1.list1.vii">
                  <num>(vii)</num>
                  <p>the Chief Architect to Government of Karnataka;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12B.1.list1.viii">
                  <num>(viii)</num>
                  <p>the Director of Town Planning, Government of Karnataka;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12B.1.list1.ix">
                  <num>(ix)</num>
                  <p>the Chief Engineer, Upper Krishna Project, Dam Zone, Almatti;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12B.1.list1.x">
                  <num>(x)</num>
                  <p>the Divisional Commissioner, Belgaum Division, Belgaum;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12B.1.list1.xi">
                  <num>(xi)</num>
                  <p>the Divisional Joint Director, Health and Family Welfare Services, Belgaum Division, Belgaum; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12B.1.list1.xii">
                  <num>(xii)</num>
                  <p>the Chief Engineer of the Authority who shall be the member-secretary.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12B.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Authority shall be bound by the directions, orders and instructions issued from time to time by the Action Plan Committee or the High Level Review Committee constituted under section 12C.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12C">
          <num>12C.</num>
          <heading>High Level Review Committee</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12C.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-12C.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>To review the progress of works done by the Authority there shall be a High Level Review Committee consisting of the following members, namely :-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12C.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the Chief Minister, Karnataka, who shall be the Chairman;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12C.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>the Minister in-charge of Public Works, Karnataka;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12C.paragraph-0.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>the Minister in-charge of Irrigation, Karnataka;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12C.paragraph-0.list1.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>the Minister in-charge of Bijapur District;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12C.paragraph-0.list1.iva">
                  <num>(iva)</num>
                  <p>the Minister incharge of Urban Development, Karnataka;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12C.paragraph-0.list1.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>the Additional Chief Secretary to Government of Karnataka;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12C.paragraph-0.list1.vi">
                  <num>(vi)</num>
                  <p>the Development Commissioner, Government of Karnataka;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12C.paragraph-0.list1.vii">
                  <num>(vii)</num>
                  <p>the Secretary to Government, Finance Department, Government of Karnataka;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12C.paragraph-0.list1.viii">
                  <num>(viii)</num>
                  <p>the Secretary to Government, Housing and Urban Development Department, Government of Karnataka; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12C.paragraph-0.list1.ix">
                  <num>(ix)</num>
                  <p>the Secretary to Government, Public Works, Command Area Development and Electricity Department, Government of Karnataka, or his nominee who shall be the member-convener.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12D">
          <num>12D.</num>
          <heading>Powers of different authorities</heading>
          <subsection id="section-12D.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chief Engineer of the Authority (hereinafter referred to in this Chapter as the Chief Engineer) may, on behalf of the Authority, sanction any estimates, call for tenders or enter into any contract or agreement the value or amount whereof shall not exceed ten lakhs of rupees in such manner and form as according to the law for the time being in force would bind him, if such contract or agreement were on his own behalf; and every such contract or agreement shall be reported to the Authority at its next meeting.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12D.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Authority may sanction any estimate, call for tenders or enter into any contract or agreement the value or amount whereof exceeds ten lakhs of rupees but does not exceed fifty lakhs of rupees; and where the value or amount of any estimate, contract or agreement exceeds fifty lakhs of rupees the same shall not be entered into except with the previous sanction of the Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12D.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every contract or agreement on behalf of the Authority other than a contract or agreement referred to in sub-section (1) shall be in writing and shall be signed by the Chief Engineer and sealed with the common seal of the Authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12D.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The common seal of the authority shall be in the custody of the Chief Engineer who shall personally affix the seal to any contract or instrument.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12D.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The acceptance of any tender shall be subject to such rules as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12D.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A contract not made or executed as provided in this section and the rules made thereunder shall be null and void and shall not be binding on the Authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12E">
          <num>12E.</num>
          <heading>Appointment of Chief Engineer</heading>
          <subsection id="section-12E.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Government shall appoint an officer not below the rank of a Chief Engineer to be the Chief Engineer of the Authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12E.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chief Engineer shall receive such monthly salary and other allowances as the Government may from time to time, determine.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12E.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Government may, from time to time, grant leave of absence for such period as it thinks fit to the Chief Engineer. A copy of every order granting such leave shall be communicated to the Chairman.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12F">
          <num>12F.</num>
          <heading>Powers and duties of Chief Engineer</heading>
          <subsection id="section-12F.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chief Engineer shall be the Chief Executive and Administrative Officer of the Authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12F.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-12F.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Chief Engineer shall, in addition to performing such functions as are conferred on him by or under this Act or under any law for the time being in force,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12F.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>carry into effect the resolutions of the Authority;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12F.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>keep and conduct the Authority's correspondence;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12F.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>carry out and execute such schemes and works as the Government may direct and incur necessary expenditure therefore;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12F.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>be responsible for implementing the schemes of the Authority;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12F.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>operate the accounts of the Authority and be responsible for the maintenance of the accounts of the Authority;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12F.2.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>exercise supervision and control over the accounts and proceedings of all officers and servants of the Authority in matters of executive administration and in the matters concerning the accounts and records of the authority and exercise the powers of the Chairman under sub-section (1) of section 54 relating to the officers and servants of the Authority;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12F.2.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>furnish to the Government a copy of the minutes of the Authority's proceedings and any return or other information which the Government may, from time to time, call for;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12F.2.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>authenticate by his signature all permissions, orders, decisions, notices and other documents of the Authority and the orders of the Chairman; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12F.2.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>have all the powers of a major Head of the Department of the State Government under the Karnataka State Civil Services Rules for the time being in force as respects the officers and servants of the Authority.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12G">
          <num>12G.</num>
          <heading>Powers to remove difficulties</heading>
          <subsection id="section-12G.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, if any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act in its application to the Authority, the Government may, by order, make such modifications to the Act or to any rule or bye-law made thereunder as it may consider necessary to remove such difficulty.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12G.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every order made under sub-section (1) shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of the State Legislature while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one or more successive sessions and if before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions, both Houses agree in making any modification to the order or the annulment of the order, the order, shall, with effect from the date on which the modification or annulment is notified by the Government in the official Gazette, have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect as the case may be ; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything done under such order.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <heading>Duties and powers</heading>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Power of Board to undertake works and incur expenditure for development, improvements, etc.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-13.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-13.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Board may, subject to the control of the Government,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-13.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>draw up detailed schemes (hereinafter referred to as development schemes or Improvement Schemes) for the development or improvement or both of the areas within its limits; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>undertake and execute any such Development Schemes or Improvement Schemes as may be necessary from time to time and incur expenditure therefor.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-13.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Board may also from time to time make any new or additional development schemes or Improvement Schemes,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-13.2.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>on its own initiative from its resources; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.2.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>at the request of the local authority concerned, if such local authority places at the disposal of the Board the necessary funds for framing and carrying out any such schemes:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that the schemes of the Board referred to in clause (a) of sub-section (1) and in this sub-section shall be prepared in conformity with the Outline Development Plan or Comprehensive Development Plan, if any, of the Planning Authority of the area concerned.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-sections (1) and (2) but subject to conformity with the Outline Development or Comprehensive Development Plans referred to in sub-section (2), the Government may, when it deems necessary, require the Board to take up any Development Scheme or Improvement Scheme or work and execute it in accordance with such terms and conditions as may be specified by the Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Particulars to be provided for in a Development Scheme or Improvement Scheme</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every development scheme or improvement scheme under section 13,-</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-14.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>shall, within the limits of the area comprised in the scheme, provide for,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-14.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>acquisition of any land which, in the opinion of the Board, is necessary for the execution of the scheme; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>laying or re-laying out of all or any land including the construction and reconstruction of buildings and the formation and alteration of streets;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-14.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>may, within the limits aforesaid, provide for,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-14.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>raising any land which the Board may deem expedient to raise for the better drainage of the locality;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>forming open spaces for the better ventilation of the area comprised in the scheme or any adjoining area;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the whole or any part of the sanitary arrangements required;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>sites for parks, playgrounds, stadium, recreation grounds, school buildings, markets, motor vehicles stands, theatres, police stations, post offices, co-operative societies, public urinals and latrines, petrol service stations, hospitals, dispensaries, banks, burial and cremation grounds and sites for public purposes of other kinds;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>may, within the limits aforesaid, provide for the construction of houses for the accommodation of the persons to be displaced in the execution of the scheme and such accommodation shall be deemed to include shops.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Procedure after preparation of the scheme</heading>
          <subsection id="section-15.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-15.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>When any development scheme or improvement scheme has been prepared, the Board shall prepare a draft of a notification stating the fact of a scheme having been made and naming a place where the particulars of the scheme, a map of the area comprised therein and a statement specifying the land which it is proposed to acquire and of the land in regard to which it is proposed to recover a betterment tax may be seen at all reasonable hours and shall,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-15.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>communicate a copy of such notification to the local authority concerned which shall, within sixty days from the date of receipt thereof, forward to the Board, for transmission to the Government as hereinafter provided, any representations which the local authority may think fit to make with regard to the scheme; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-15.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>cause a copy of the said notification to be published in the official Gazette and affixed in some conspicuous part of the Boards office, the Deputy Commissioners office, the office of the local authority concerned and in such other places as the Board may consider necessary.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If no representations is received from the local authority within the time specified in the communication under clause (a) of sub-section (1), the concurrence of the local authority to the proposal shall be deemed to have been given.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>During the thirty days next following the day on which such notification is published in the official Gazette, the Board shall serve a notice on every person whose name appears in the assessment list of the local authority within the local limits of whose jurisdiction the area comprised in the scheme is situated or in the land revenue register as being primarily liable to pay the property tax or land revenue assessment on any building or land which it is proposed to acquire in executing the scheme requiring such person to show cause within thirty days why such acquisition of the building or the land and the recovery of the betterment tax as specified in the notice should not be made.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Forwardal of scheme</heading>
          <subsection id="section-16.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Upon compliance with the foregoing provisions with respect to the publication and service of notices of the Scheme, the Board shall, after consideration of any representation received under section 15 and after making such modifications in the scheme as it may deem fit, apply to the Government for sanction to the scheme.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-16.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The application for sanction shall, save in the case provided for by sub-section (3), be accompanied, by,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-16.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>a description with full particulars of the scheme including the reasons for any modifications made therein;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>complete plans and estimates of the cost of executing the scheme;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>a statement specifying the land proposed to be acquired;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>any representation received under sub-section (1) of section 15;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>a schedule showing the rateable value, entered in the assessment list of the local authority at the date of the publication of a notification relating to the land under section 15, or the land revenue assessment of all land specified in the statement under clause (c); and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.2.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>such further particulars, if any, as may be prescribed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When under any development scheme or improvement scheme provision is made for the construction of houses the Board may, after complying with the provisions of section 15, submit to the Government for sanction plans and estimates for the construction of such houses and on receipt of such sanction the provisions of section 17 shall, with all necessary modifications be applicable to the part of the scheme providing for the construction of such houses, as if such part were the scheme.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Sanction to scheme and republication in case of modification</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Government may sanction either with or without modification or may refuse to sanction or may return for reconsideration, a development scheme or improvement scheme submitted to it under section 16.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a scheme returned for reconsideration under sub-section (1) is modified by the Board, the Board shall, if the modification affects the boundaries of the area comprised in the scheme or involves the acquisition of any land not previously proposed to be acquired, publish the modified scheme in the manner specified in section 15.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Upon sanction, declaration to be published giving particulars of land to be acquired</heading>
          <subsection id="section-18.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Upon sanction of the scheme, the Government shall publish in the official Gazette a declaration stating the fact of such sanction and that the land proposed to be acquired by the Board for the purposes of the scheme is required for a public purpose.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The declaration shall state the limits within which the land proposed to be acquired is situated, the purpose for which it is needed, its approximate area and the place where a plan of the land may be inspected.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The said declaration shall be conclusive evidence that the land is needed for a public purpose, and the Board shall, upon the publication of the said declaration proceed to execute the scheme.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If at any time it appears to the Board that an improvement can be made in any part of the scheme, the Board may alter the scheme for the purpose of making such improvement and shall subject to the provisions of sub-sections (5) and (6) forthwith proceed to execute the scheme as altered.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the estimated cost of executing the scheme as altered exceed, by a greater sum than five per cent of the estimated cost of executing the scheme as sanctioned, the Board shall not, without the previous sanction of the Government, proceed to execute the scheme as altered.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the scheme as altered involves the acquisition otherwise than by agreement, of any land other than that specified in the Schedule referred to in clause (e) of sub-section (2) of section 16 the provisions of sections 15 and 16 and of sub-section (1) of this section shall apply to the part of the scheme so altered, in the same manner as if such altered part were the scheme.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Levy of betterment tax</heading>
          <subsection id="section-19.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where as a consequence of execution of any development or improvement scheme, the market value of any land in the area comprised in the scheme which is not required for the execution thereof has, in the opinion of the Board, increased or will increase, the Board shall be entitled to levy on the owner of the land or any person having an interest therein a betterment tax in respect of the increase in value of the land resulting, from the execution of such scheme.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Such increase in value shall be the amount by which the value of the land, on the completion of the execution of the scheme, estimated as if the land were clear of buildings, exceeds the value of the land prior to the execution of the scheme estimated in like manner, and the betterment tax shall be one-third of such increase in value.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Assessment of betterment tax by the Board</heading>
          <subsection id="section-20.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When it appears to the Board that any development or improvement scheme is sufficiently advanced to enable the amount of the betterment tax to be determined, the Board may, by an order made in this behalf, declare that for the purpose of determining the betterment tax the execution of the scheme shall be deemed to have been completed and shall thereupon give notice in writing to the owner of the property or any person having an interest therein that the Board proposes to assess the amount of the betterment tax in respect of the property under section 19.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall then assess the amount of betterment tax payable by the person concerned after giving such person an opportunity of being heard and such person shall, within sixty days from the date of receipt of the notice in writing of such assessment from the Board, inform the Board in writing whether or not he accepts the assessment.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When the assessment proposed by the Board is accepted by the person concerned within the period specified in sub-section (2) such assessment shall be final.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the person concerned does not accept the assessment or fails to give the Board the information required by sub-section (2) within the period specified therein the Board shall make a reference to the District Court for determining the betterment tax payable by such person.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Manner of payment of betterment tax</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The betterment tax determined under section 20 shall be paid within such time and in such number of instalments not exceeding ten as may be specified by the Board together with interest at such rates as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Recovery of betterment tax</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Where any person liable to pay betterment tax fails to pay the same within the time specified by the Board or makes default in payment of two consecutive instalments or any three instalments, the Board shall be entitled to recover the whole of the amount due together with interest from the said person or his successor-in-interest in such land in the manner provided in Chapter VII of the Karnataka Municipalities Act, 1964, for the recovery of taxes and if the said money is not so recovered, the Chairman may, after giving public notice of his intention to do so, and not less than one month after the publication of such notice sell the land or the interest of the said person or his successor-in-interest in such land by public auction and may deduct the said money and the expenses of the sale from the proceeds of the sale and shall pay the balance (if any) to the defaulter.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Payment no bar for acquisition under a fresh declaration</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>If any land, in respect of which the payment of a betterment tax has been accepted or determined under section 20 be subsequently required for any of the purposes of this Act, the acceptance or payment shall not be deemed to prevent the acquisition of the land in pursuance of a fresh declaration published under section 6 of the Land Acquisition Act, 1894.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Power of Board to take up works for further Development</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, the Board may, with the previous sanction of the Government, take up such works in regard to any area as the Board considers necessary or desirable for the further development of that area.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Crediting betterment tax collected to the funds of the local authority in certain cases</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Where the increase in value of any land is as a result of the execution of a development or improvement scheme made at the request of a local authority and for which the local authority has placed at the disposal of the Board necessary funds, the betterment tax collected by the Board from the person concerned shall, after deducting ten percent thereof as collection charges, be credited by the Board to the local authority.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Board to execute schemes within three years</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall execute a development scheme or an improvement scheme within a period of three years from the date of sanction of the Scheme :</p>
              <p>Provided that the Government may, by order, extend the time for execution.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <heading>General</heading>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Land vested in a local authority and required by the Board for formation or alteration of street to be vested temporarily in the Board</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Whenever under any development or improvement scheme, the whole or any part of any existing public street or other land vested in a local authority is included in the site of any part of a street to be formed, altered widened, diverted, raised, re-arranged or reconstructed by the Board, the Board shall give notice to the local authority concerned that the whole or a part, as the case may be, of such existing street or other land (hereinafter called the "part required") is required by it as part of a street to be dealt with as aforesaid, and the part required shall, thereupon subject to the provisions of sub-section (1) of section 29, be vested in the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Board to exercise powers and functions of local authorities</heading>
          <subsection id="section-28.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In any urban area or part thereof to which this Act applies, the Government may, by notification, declare that from such date and for such period and subject to such restrictions and modifications, if any, as may be specified in the notification, the powers and functions of the local authority or a standing committee thereof shall be exercised and discharged by the Board:</p>
              <p>Provided that the local authority shall be consulted before making such declaration, if such area or part thereof lies within the limits of the local authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-28.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On the making of a declaration under sub-section (1), notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being in force, the local authority or any standing committee or officer thereof shall not be competent to exercise or discharge the powers or functions conferred or imposed on the Board by such declaration.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-28.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board may delegate any of the functions exercisable by it under sub-section (1) to any officer or servant of the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-28.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The exercise or discharge of any of the powers or functions delegated under sub-section (3), shall be subject to such limitations, conditions and control as may be laid down by the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Streets on completion and open spaces to vest in and be maintained by the local authority</heading>
          <subsection id="section-29.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Government, after consulting the local authority and on being satisfied that any street formed by the Board has been duly levelled, paved, metalled, flagged, channelled, drained and sewered in the manner provided for in the plans of any Scheme sanctioned by the Government and that such lamps, lamp-posts and other apparatus as are, in its opinion, necessary for the lighting thereof and should be provided by the Board have been so provided shall declare such street to be a public street, and such street shall thereupon vest or revest, as the case may be, in the local authority and the local authority shall thenceforward maintain, keep in repair, light and cleanse such street. If the local authority concerned does not reply within sixty days when it is consulted by the Government, its concurrence shall be deemed to have been given.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any open space reserved for ventilation and the areas reserved for motor parks, playgrounds, public urinals and latrines, burial and cremation grounds in any part of the area within the jurisdiction of the local authority and provided by the Board as part of any development scheme or improvement scheme sanctioned by the Government shall be transferred on completion to the local authority and shall there upon vest in the local authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any dispute which arises between the Board and the local authority in regard to interpreting or implementing the provisions of this section shall be determined by the Government, whose decision shall be final.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading>Board not to sell or otherwise dispose of sites in certain cases</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-30.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall not sell or otherwise dispose of any sites for the purpose of constructing buildings thereon for the accommodation of persons until all the improvements specified to section 29 have been substantially provided for.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading>Forming of new extensions or layouts or making new private streets</heading>
          <subsection id="section-31.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything to the contrary in any law for the time being in force, no person shall form or attempt to form any extension or layout for the purpose of constructing buildings thereon without the express sanction in writing of the Board and except in accordance with such conditions as the Board may specify :</p>
              <p>Provided that where any such extension or layout lies within the limits of a local authority, the Board shall not sanction the formation of such extension or layout without the concurrence of the local authority. The concurrence of the local authority shall be deemed to have been given if it fails to convey its opinion within sixty days after it is consulted :</p>
              <p>Provided further that where the local authority and the Board do not agree on the formation of, or the conditions relating to the execution or layout, the matter shall be referred to the Government whose decision thereon shall be final.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person intending to form an extension or layout or to make a new private street shall send to the Chairman, a written application with plans and estimates showing such particulars, as may be prescribed by bye-laws made by the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of this Act and of any rules or bye-laws made under it as to the level and width of streets and the height of buildings abutting thereon, shall apply also in the case of streets referred to in that sub-section shall be subject to the approval of the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Within six months after the receipt of any application under sub-section (2), the Board shall sanction the forming of the extension or layout or the making of streets on such conditions as it may think fit or disallow it or ask for further information with regard to it.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board may require the applicant to deposit, before sanctioning the application, the amount necessary for meeting the expenditure for making roads, side-drains, culverts, under-ground drainage and water supply and lighting and the charges for such other purposes as the applicant may be called upon by the Board to deposit, provided he agrees to transfer the ownership of the roads, drains, water supply mains and open spaces laid out by him to the Board permanently without claiming any compensation therefor.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-31.6.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Such sanction may be refused,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-31.6.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>if the proposed street would conflict with any arrangements which have been made or which are, in the opinion of the Board likely to be made, for carrying out any general scheme of street improvement or other schemes of improvement or development by the Board ;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-31.6.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>if the proposed street does not conform to the provisions of this Act, and the rules and bye-laws made under it ;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-31.6.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>if the proposed street is not designed so as to connect at one end with a street which is already open ; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-31.6.list1.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>if the layout, in the opinion of the Board, cannot be fitted with any existing or proposed development or improvement schemes of the Board.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No person shall form a layout or make any new private street without the sanction of or otherwise than in conformity with the conditions imposed in this behalf by the Board. If the Board requires further information from the applicant, no steps shall be taken by him to form the layout or make the street until orders have been passed by the Board after the receipt of such information:</p>
              <p>Provided that the passing of such orders shall not, in any case, be delayed for more than six months after the Board has received all the information which it considers necessary to enable it to deal finally with the said application.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the Board does not refuse sanction within six months from the date of receipt of the application under sub-section (2) or when information is called for under sub-section (7), within six months from the date such information is furnished, such sanctions shall be deemed to have been granted and the applicant may proceed to form the extension or layout or to make the street but not so as to contravene any of the provisions of this Act and the rules or bye-laws made under it.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every extension or layout for the formation of which sanction is granted or deemed to have been granted under this section shall be in conformity with the Outline Development Plan or the Comprehensive Development Plan, if any, of the Planning Authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.10">
            <num>(10)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person who forms or attempts to form any extension or layout in contravention of the provisions of sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) or makes any street without or otherwise than in conformity with the orders of the Board under sub section (7) shall be liable, on conviction, to fine which may extend to one thousand rupees.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>Alteration or demolition of extension, layout or street</heading>
          <subsection id="section-32.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-32.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>If any person forms an extension or layout or makes any street referred to in section 31 or puts up any building without or otherwise than in conformity with the orders of the Board under the said section, the Board may, whether or not such person be prosecuted under this Act, by notice,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>require him to show sufficient cause by a written statement signed by him and sent to the Board on or before such day as may be specified in the notice, why such extension, layout or street should not be altered to the satisfaction of the Board or if such alteration be deemed impracticable by the Board, why such extension, layout or street should not be demolished, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>require him to appear before the Board either personally or by a duly authorised agent on such day and at such time and place as may be specified in the notice and show cause as aforesaid.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any person on whom such notice is served fails to show sufficient cause to the satisfaction of the Board why such extension, layout or street should not be so altered or demolished, the Board, may for reasons to be recorded in writing direct the alteration or demolition of such extension, lay-out or street.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any person fails to comply with any direction issued under sub-section (2) the Board may carry out the direction and recover the cost incurred therefor from such person as if it were arrears of land revenue.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-32A">
          <num>32A.</num>
          <heading>Prohibition of unauthorised occupation of land</heading>
          <subsection id="section-32A.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person who unauthorisedly enters upon and uses or occupies any land belonging to the Board to the use or occupation of which he is not entitled or has ceased to be entitled, shall, on conviction, be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years and with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32A.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person who having unauthorisedly occupied, whether before or after the commencement of the Karnataka Municipal Corporations and Certain other Laws (Amendment) Act, 1984 any land belonging to the Board to the use or occupation of which he is not entitled or has ceased to be entitled, fails to vacate such land in pursuance of an order under sub-section (1) of section 5 of the Karnataka Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) Act, 1974 (Karnataka Act 32 of 1974), shall, on conviction, be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years and with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees and with a further fine which may extend to fifty rupees per acre of land or part thereof for every day on which the occupation continues after the date of the first conviction for such offence.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32A.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Whoever intentionally aids or abets the commission by any other person of an offence punishable under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) shall, on conviction, be punishable with the same punishment provided for such offence under the saidsub-sections.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading>Power of Board to order work to be carried out or to carry it out itself in default</heading>
          <subsection id="section-33.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-33.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Board may,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-33.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>if any person permitted to carry out the work relating to the forming of the extension or lay-out or the making of a street, does not carry it out ; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-33.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>if any private street or part thereof is not levelled, paved, metalled, flagged, channelled, sewered, conserved or lighted to the satisfaction of the Board,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>by notice, require the person forming the extension or lay-out or the owners of such street or part and the owners of buildings and lands abutting such street or part, including in cases where the owners of the land or the building thereon are different the owners both of the land and of the building, to carry out any work which, in its opinion, may be necessary and within such time as may be specified in such notice.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-33.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any such work is not carried out within the time specified in the notice under sub-section (1), the Board may, if it thinks fit, execute it and the expenses incurred shall be paid by the persons or owners referred to in sub-section (1) in such proportions as may be determined by the Board, such expenses may be recovered from the persons concerned as if they were arrears of land revenue.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <heading>Acquisition of land</heading>
        <section id="section-34">
          <num>34.</num>
          <heading>Board to have power to acquire land by agreement</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-34.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act and with the previous approval of the Government the Board may enter into an agreement with the owner of any land or any interest therein whether situated within or without the urban area for the purchase or lease of such land or interest therein for the purpose of this Act:</p>
              <p>Provided that the Board may enter into an agreement with the previous approval of the Deputy Commissioner of the district where the total area of such land does not exceed five hectares and of the Divisional Commissioner of the division where the total area of such land exceeds five hectares but does not exceed ten hectares.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading>Provisions applicable to the acquisition of land otherwise than by agreement</heading>
          <subsection id="section-35.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The acquisition otherwise than by agreement of land within or without the urban area under this Act shall be regulated by the provisions, so far as they are applicable, of the Land Acquisition Act, 1894.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-35.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purpose of sub-section (2) of section 50 of the Land Acquisition Act, 1894, the Board shall be deemed to be the local authority concerned.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-35.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>After the land vests in the Government under section 16 of the Land Acquisition Act, 1894 the Deputy Commissioner shall, upon payment of the cost of the acquisition, and upon the Board agreeing to pay any further costs which may be incurred on account of the acquisition, transfer the land to the Board, and the land shall thereupon vest in the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VI">
        <num>VI</num>
        <heading>Property and finance</heading>
        <section id="section-36">
          <num>36.</num>
          <heading>Power of Government to transfer to Board lands belonging to it or to a local authority</heading>
          <subsection id="section-36.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Government may, by notification, for the purposes of this Act and subject to such limitations and conditions as it may impose and to the provisions hereinafter contained, transfer to and vest in the Board any land belonging to Government or to a local authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No land belonging to a local authority shall be vested in the Board under sub-section (1) except after consulting such local authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Whenever it appears to the Government that any land vested in the Board under sub-section (1) is not required by the Board for purposes of this Act or any other land vesting in the Board is required by the Government or local authority, the Government may, by notification, direct that the land shall revest in or stand transferred to the Government or the local authority concerned, as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-37">
          <num>37.</num>
          <heading>Power of Board to lease, sell or transfer property</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-37.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Subject to such restrictions, conditions and limitations as may be prescribed, the Board shall have power to lease, sell or otherwise transfer any movable or immovable property which belongs to it, and to appropriate or apply any land vested in or acquired by it for the formation of open spaces or for building purposes or in any other manner for the purpose of any development scheme.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-37A">
          <num>37A.</num>
          <heading>Power of the Bagalkot Town Development Authority to make bulk allotment</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-37A.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-37A.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act or development scheme sanctioned under this Act, the Bagalkot Town Development Authority may, subject to any restriction, condition and limitation as may be prescribed, make bulk allotment by way of sale, lease or otherwise of any land which belongs to it or is vested in, or acquired by it, for the purpose of any development scheme,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-37A.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>to the State Government; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-37A.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>to the Central Government; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-37A.paragraph-0.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>to any Corporation, Body or Organisation owned or controlled by the Central Government or the State Government; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-37A.paragraph-0.list1.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>to any Housing Co-operative Society registered under the Karnataka Co-operative Societies Act, 1959 (Karnataka Act 11 of 1959); or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-37A.paragraph-0.list1.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>to any society registered under the Karnataka Societies Registration Act, 1960 (Karnataka Act 17 of 1960); or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-37A.paragraph-0.list1.vi">
                  <num>(vi)</num>
                  <p>to a trust create wholly for the charitable, educational or religious purpose;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that prior approval of the Government shall be obtained for allotment of land to any category listed above except category(i)</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-38">
          <num>38.</num>
          <heading>Power of Board to borrow</heading>
          <subsection id="section-38.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board may, from time to time with the previous sanction of the Government and subject to such conditions as may be prescribed in this behalf borrow any sum required for the purpose of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-38.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The rules made by the Government for the purpose of this section may empower the Board to borrow by the issue of debentures and to make arrangement with the bankers.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-38.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Debentures issued by the Board shall be in such form as the Board may, with the sanction of the Government, from time to time determine.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-38.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every debenture shall be signed by the Chairman and one other member of the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-38.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Loans borrowed and debentures issued under this section may be guaranteed by the Government as to the repayment of principal and payment of interest at such rate as may be fixed by the Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-39">
          <num>39.</num>
          <heading>Board Fund, the items to be credited to such Fund and its deposit</heading>
          <subsection id="section-39.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-39.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Board shall have and maintain its own Fund to which shall be credited,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-39.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>all moneys received by the Board from the Government by way of grants, loans, advances or otherwise;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-39.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>all fees, fines and charges received by the Board under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-39.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>all moneys received by the Board from the disposal of lands, buildings or other property movable or immovable;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-39.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>all moneys received by the Board by way of rents and profits or in any other manner from any other source.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-39.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Fund shall be applied by the Board in the administration of this Act and for no other purposes.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-39.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall keep such sum of money out of its Fund as may be prescribed in the Government Treasury and any money in excess of it shall be deposited in a Scheduled Bank or invested in such manner as may be approved by the Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-40">
          <num>40.</num>
          <heading>Laying of annual estimate of income and expenditure.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-40.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chairman shall, at a special meeting to be held not later than the first day of February in each year, lay before the Board an estimate of the income and of the expenditure of the Board for the year commencing on the first day of April then next ensuing in such detail and form as the Board shall, from time to time, direct.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-40.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Such estimate shall make provision for the efficient administration of this Act and a copy of the estimate shall be sent by post or otherwise to each member of the Board at least ten clear days prior to the date of the meeting.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-41">
          <num>41.</num>
          <heading>Board to approve or amend such estimates.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-41.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall consider the estimate so submitted to it and shall approve the same either unaltered or subject to such alterations as it thinks fit.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-42">
          <num>42.</num>
          <heading>Estimates to be submitted to Government for sanction.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-42.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The estimate, as approved by the Board shall be submitted to the Government which may either sanction or disallow such estimate or any portion thereof and return the same for amendment. The Board shall forthwith amend the estimate so returned and shall re-submit the amended estimate to the Government. A copy of the estimate as sanctioned by the Government shall be sent to the local authorities concerned.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-43">
          <num>43.</num>
          <heading>Supplementary estimates may be prepared and submitted when necessary.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-43.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Board may, at any time during the year for which any estimate has been sanctioned, cause a supplementary estimate to be prepared and submitted to it. Every such supplementary estimate shall be considered and approved by the Board and submitted to the Government for sanction and a copy of the estimate as sanctioned shall be sent to the local authority concerned, in the same manner as if it were an original annual estimate.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-44">
          <num>44.</num>
          <heading>Provisions regarding expenditure.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-44.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No sum shall be expended by or on behalf of the Board, unless included in the estimate or a supplementary estimate:</p>
              <p>Provided that an expenditure not exceeding twenty-five thousand rupees may be incurred, though not so included, in unforeseen circumstances or to satisfy a decree of a court and in such a case the Chairman shall make a report, as soon as practicable, to the Government indicating the circumstances in which the expenditure was incurred and the source from which it is proposed to be met:</p>
              <p>Provided further that any such expenditure shall be included in a supplementary estimate to be approved and sanctioned in the manner laid down in section 43.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-45">
          <num>45.</num>
          <heading>Power to make reappropriation.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-45.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Subject to such rules as may be made under this Act, the Board may within the sanctioned budget make reappropriations from one sub-head to another or from one minor head to another minor head under the same major head of account.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-46">
          <num>46.</num>
          <heading>Audit of Accounts.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-46.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The accounts of the Board shall be audited annually by an auditor appointed by the Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-46.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The auditor shall, for the purpose of the audit, have access to all the accounts and other records of the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-46.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall pay from its fund such charges for the audit as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-47">
          <num>47.</num>
          <heading>Power of auditor to require production of documents and attendance of persons concerned.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-47.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-47.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Auditor may,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-47.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>require in writing the production of such vouchers, statement, returns, correspondence, notes or other documents in relation to the accounts as he may think fit;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-47.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>require in writing any salaried servant of the Board accountable for or having the custody or control of such vouchers, statements, returns, correspondence, notes or other documents or of any property of the Board or any person having directly or indirectly by himself or his partner, any share or interest in any contract with or under the Board to appear in person before him at the Board office and answer any question ;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-47.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>in the event of a clarification being required on any specific point from the Chairman or any officer or member in writing, require such person to furnish the clarification on such point.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-47.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The auditor may, in any requisition made under sub-section (1) fix a reasonable period not being less than three days within which the said requisition shall be complied with.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-47.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The auditor shall give to the Board not less than two weeks notice in writing of the date on which he proposes to commence the audit :</p>
              <p>Provided that notwithstanding anything contained in the sub-section, the auditor may, for special reasons which shall be recorded in writing, give shorter notice than two weeks or commence a special or detailed audit if so directed by the Government without giving notice.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-48">
          <num>48.</num>
          <heading>Penalty for disobeying requisition under section 47.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-48.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Any person who wilfully neglects or refuses to comply with any requisition lawfully made upon him under clauses (a), (b) or (c) of sub-section (1) of section 47 shall, on conviction, be punished with fine which may extend to two hundred rupees:</p>
              <p>Provided that no proceedings under this section shall be instituted except with the sanction of the Government or such other officer as the Government may authorise in this behalf:</p>
              <p>Provided further that before giving such sanction the Government or the authorised officer shall call upon the person against whom the proceedings are to be instituted to show cause why the sanction should not be given.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-49">
          <num>49.</num>
          <heading>Audit Report.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-49.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-49.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The auditor shall include in his report a statement of,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-49.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>every payment which appears to him to be contrary to law;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-49.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the amount of any deficiency or loss which appears to have been caused by the gross negligence or misconduct of any person;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-49.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the amount of any sum received which ought to have been but is not brought into account by any person, and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-49.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>any material impropriety or irregularity which he may observe in the accounts other than those mentioned in clauses (a), (b) and (c).</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-49.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Within three months after the completion of the audit, the auditor shall send a report on the accounts audited and examined to the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-50">
          <num>50.</num>
          <heading>Board to remedy defects.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-50.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Within two months of the receipt of the report under section 49, the Chairman shall place it before a meeting of the Board together with a statement of the action taken or proposed to be taken to remedy any defect or irregularity that may have been pointed out in such report and an explanation in regard thereto and shall with the approval of the Board, remedy the defects or irregularities. He shall also as soon as may be, after the decision of the Board send to the Controller, State Accounts Department, intimation of having remedied the defects or irregularities pointed out in the report, or shall, within the said period, supply the Controller any further explanation in regard to such defects or irregularities as the Board may decide to give.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-50.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-50.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>On receipt of such intimation or explanation the Controller may,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-50.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>accept the explanation given by the Board and withdraw the objection;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-50.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>direct that the matter be re-investigated at the next audit or at any earlier date; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-50.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>hold that the defects or irregularities have not been removed or remedied.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-50.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Controller, shall send a report to the Government and shall forward a copy of such report to the Chairman. The Controller shall state in the report whether in his opinion the defects or irregularities have or have not been removed or remedied and indicate whether the defects or irregularities can be regularised or whether they can be condoned. He shall also state whether the amounts to which the defects or irregularities relate should, in his opinion, be surcharged or charged. The audited accounts and the report shall be laid before each House of the State Legislature as soon as may be, after it is received by the Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-50.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall include in its next administration report such portions of the report under section 49 as deal with defects and irregularities falling under clause (c) of sub-section (2), the explanation if any, given under sub-section (1) and the final report of the Controller thereon under sub-section (3).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-50.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in this section shall preclude the Controller, at any time from bringing to the notice of the Government any matter which appears to him to involve criminal misappropriation or fraud or deserves special attention or immediate investigation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-51">
          <num>51.</num>
          <heading>Government to surcharge or charge illegal payment or loss caused by negligence or misconduct.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-51.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Government may, after considering the report of the Controller and after taking the explanation of the person concerned or making such further enquiry as it may consider necessary, by order disallow any item which appears to it to be contrary to law and surcharge the same on the person making or authorising the making of the illegal payment; and may charge any person responsible therefor the amount of any deficiency or loss caused by the negligence or misconduct of that person, or any such amount received which ought to have been, but is not brought into account by that person and shall, in every such case, certify the amount due from such person.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-51.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Government shall state in writing the reason for its decision in respect of every surcharge or charge and shall send by registered post a copy thereof to the person against whom it is made.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-51.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a person to whom a copy of the Government decision is sent under sub-section (2) refuses to take delivery thereof he shall be deemed to have duly received it on the day on which it was refused by him.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-52">
          <num>52.</num>
          <heading>Recovery of surcharge and charge how made.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-52.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The amount surcharged or charged shall be paid by the person concerned within one month from the date of communication of the order under section 51, into the treasury or bank holding the funds of the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-52.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The said sum, if not so paid, shall be recovered as arrears of land revenue.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VII">
        <num>VII</num>
        <heading>Officers and servants of the board</heading>
        <section id="section-53">
          <num>53.</num>
          <heading>Schedule of officers and servants to be submitted for sanction of Government.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-53.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall, from time to time, prepare and submit for the sanction of the Government a schedule of the staff of officers and servants whom it may consider necessary and proper to employ for its purposes. Such schedule shall also set forth the amount and nature of the salaries and allowances which the Board proposes for each such officer or servant. No alteration in the sanctioned scheduled shall be made without prior sanction of the Government.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-54">
          <num>54.</num>
          <heading>Appointments by whom to be made.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-54.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of section 365 of the Karnataka Municipalities Act, 1964 (Karnataka Act 22 of 1964), the rules and bye-laws made under this Act and of the schedule for the time being in force sanctioned by the Government under section 53 the powers of appointing, promoting, suspending, dismissing, fining, reducing or granting leave to the officers and servants of the Board (not being officers of the Government lent to or working under the Board) shall be exercised, in the case of officers and servants whose monthly salary does not exceed two hundred and fifty rupees by the Chairman and in every other case by the Board:</p>
              <p>Provided that in the case of officers of the Government lent to the Board, the Chairman may exercise the powers of granting leave and sanctioning increments and after following the prescribed procedure, of withholding increments and shall report the fact to the Head of the Department to which such officer belongs.</p>
              <p>Explanation.- For purposes of section 365 of the Karnataka Municipalities Act, 1964, the Board shall be deemed to be a local authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-54.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The power of dispensing with the services of any officer or servant of the Board, otherwise than by reason of such officers or servants misconduct or of permitting any such officer or servant to retire on a pension, gratuity or compassionate allowance shall,</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-54.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any party aggrieved by an order of the Board under sub-section (2) may appeal to the Government within thirty days of the order.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VIII">
        <num>VIII</num>
        <heading>Control</heading>
        <section id="section-55">
          <num>55.</num>
          <heading>Control by Government.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-55.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall carry out such directions as may be issued to it from time to time by the Government under the provisions of the Act for the efficient administration of the Board and its affairs.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-56">
          <num>56.</num>
          <heading>Action in case of defaults by Board.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-56.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>If the Board fails to carry out any direction issued under section 55 within the period, if any, fixed in such direction, the Government may make arrangements to take such action and recover all expenses connected therewith from out of the Boards Fund.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-57">
          <num>57.</num>
          <heading>Power to cancel or modify order, etc.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-57.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>If in the opinion of the Government the execution of any order or resolution of the Board or the doing of anything which is about to be done or being done by or on behalf of the Board is unjust, unlawful or improper or is causing or is likely to cause loss or damage to or prejudice to the interests of the Board or is causing or likely to cause injury or annoyance to the public or breach of the peace, the Government may, by order, cancel or modify such order or resolution or pass such other order as it deems fit:</p>
              <p>Provided that before passing an order under this section, the Government shall give the Board an opportunity of making representation against the proposed order:</p>
              <p>Provided further that pending action under this section, the Government may direct the stay of the execution of any order or resolution of the Board or the doing of anything by or on behalf of the Board subject to such conditions as it may think fit.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-58">
          <num>58.</num>
          <heading>Supersession of the Board.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-58.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the Government is satisfied that the Board has made default in performing any duties imposed on it by or under this Act or any other law or has abused its power or is acting in a manner prejudicial to the interests of the Board or its finances the Government may by notification, supersede and reconstitute the Board:</p>
              <p>Provided that before issuing the notification under this sub-section the Government shall give an opportunity to the Board to make a representation why it should not be superseded and shall consider the representation, if any, made.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-58.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>After the supersession of the Board and until it is reconstituted, the powers, duties and functions of the Board shall be exercised by such officer or officers as the Government may appoint.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-59">
          <num>59.</num>
          <heading>Dissolution of the Board.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-59.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where the Government is satisfied that the purpose for which the Board was established has been substantially achieved so as to render the existence of the Board unnecessary, it may, by order published in the official Gazette, declare that the Board shall be dissolved with effect form such date as may be specified in the order and thereupon the Board shall be deemed to be dissolved accordingly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-59.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>From the said date,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-59.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>all properties, funds, dues which are vested in or releasible by the Board shall vest in or be releasible by the local authority concerned;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-59.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>all Government lands placed at the disposal of the Board shall revert to the Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-59.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>all liabilities which are enforceable against the Board shall be enforceable against the local authority concerned; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-59.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>for the purpose of carrying out any development which has not been fully carried out by the Board and for the purpose of realising the properties, funds and dues referred to in clause (a), the functions of the Board shall be discharged by the local authority concerned.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When the Board is dissolved under sub-section (1), the Government may pass such orders as it deems necessary in respect of the officers and servants of the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-60">
          <num>60.</num>
          <heading>Penalty for being interested in contracts with the Board.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-60.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>If any member or officer or servant of the Board knowingly acquires, directly or indirectly by himself or by a partner, employer or servant, any share or interest in any contract or employment with, by or on behalf of the Board, he shall be deemed to have committed the offence under section 168 of the Indian Penal Code:</p>
              <p>Provided that a person shall not be deemed to have any share or interest, in such contract or employment by reason only of his having a share or interest if any, in any newspaper in which any advertisement relating to the affairs of the Board is inserted.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-61">
          <num>61.</num>
          <heading>Members and officers to be public servants.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-61.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every member and every officer or other employee of the Board shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-62">
          <num>62.</num>
          <heading>Sanction of prosecutions.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-62.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No court shall take cognizance of an offence under this Act, the rules or bye-laws made thereunder except on the complaint made with the previous sanction of the Board by such officer as the Board may authorise in this behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-63">
          <num>63.</num>
          <heading>Fines to be credited to Board Fund.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-63.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>All fines recovered under this Act by or under the order of a court shall be paid to the credit of the Board Fund.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-64">
          <num>64.</num>
          <heading>Recovery of sums due.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-64.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Save as otherwise provided in section 22 all sums due by any person to the Board on account of sale proceeds of property vested in or acquired by the Board or otherwise howsoever and remaining in arrears after fifteen days from the date of service on such person of a notice of demand may be recovered in any one or more of the following ways, namely:-</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-64.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>by distraint and sale, by or under the orders of the Board, of the movable property of such person; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-64.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>as arrears of land revenue, on the written application of the Board in this behalf to the Deputy Commissioner of the district in which proceedings are required to be taken.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-65">
          <num>65.</num>
          <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-65.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against the Board, the Chairman, member, officer or servant of the Board or any person acting under the orders or directions of the Board for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or any rule or bye-law made thereunder.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-66">
          <num>66.</num>
          <heading>Service of notice.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-66.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Save as otherwise provided any notice or order issued or made under this Act shall be served in the prescribed manner.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-67">
          <num>67.</num>
          <heading>Offences by companies.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-67.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where an offence under this Act is committed by a company, the company as well as every person in charge of and responsible to the company for the conduct of its business at the time of the commission of the offence, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:</p>
              <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to any punishment if he proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or that he exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-67.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of or that the commission of the offence is attributable to any neglect on the part of any director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary or other officer, shall also be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punishedaccordingly.</p>
              <blockList id="section-67.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Explanation.- For the purpose of this section,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-67.2.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>company means a body corporate and includes a firm or other association of individuals; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-67.2.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>director in relation to a firm means a partner in the firm.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-68">
          <num>68.</num>
          <heading>Effect of other laws.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-68.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Save as provided in this Act the provisions of this Act shall be in addition to and not in derogation of any other law.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-68.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where a Board is constituted for and is functioning in any urban area the provisions contained in Chapter VIII of the Karnataka Municipalities Act, 1964 (Karnataka Act 22 of 1964), shall not be applicable to such area.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IX">
        <num>IX</num>
        <heading>Miscellaneous</heading>
        <section id="section-69">
          <num>69.</num>
          <heading>Rules.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-69.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Government may, by notification and after previous publication, make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-69.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-69.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-69.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>allowances payable to the Chairman and non-official members;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-69.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the manner and form in which any contract of the Board may be executed under section 11;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-69.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the further particulars to be furnished in the application for sanction of a scheme under section 16;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-69.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the manner of payment of betterment tax;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-69.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the procedure, conditions and restrictions subject to which and the form in which the Board may let on hire, lease, sell or otherwise convey any movable or immovable property;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-69.2.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the amount of money to be kept by the Board in the Government Treasury;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-69.2.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the form in which, and the time within which, the budget estimates of the Board shall be prepared and submitted to the Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-69.2.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>any other matter for which rules have to be made or necessary under this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-69.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In making a rule under this section, the Government may provide that a person guilty of a breach thereof shall be punishable with fine which may extend to one hundred rupees and in the case of continuing breach, with additional fine which may extend to fifty rupees for every day during which such breach continues after receipt of a notice from the Board requiring such person to discontinue the breach.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-69.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A rule under this Act may be made with retrospective effect and when such a rule is made the reasons for making the rule shall be specified in a statement laid before both Houses of the State Legislature. Subject to any modification made under sub-section (5) every rule made under this Act shall have effect as if enacted in this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-69.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made under this Act shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made before each House of the State Legislature while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions and if before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive session aforesaid both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall, from the date on which the modification or annulment is notified by the Government in the official Gazette, have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect , as the case may be, so however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under such rule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-70">
          <num>70.</num>
          <heading>Power of Board to make bye-laws.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-70.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-70.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Subject to the provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder the Board may from time to time, make, alter or rescind byelaws,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-70.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>for regulating the delegation of the powers and duties of the Board to an officer of the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-70.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>for the guidance of persons employed by it under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-70.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>for regulating the matters relating to the recruitment, discipline and other conditions of service of the officers and servants of the Board, not being officers of the Government lent to or working under the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-70.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>for the management , use and regulation of houses constructed under any scheme;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-70.1.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>for regulating the construction and reconstruction of buildings in regard to the following matters, namely, the notice to be submitted, the line of frontage with neighbouring buildings, the free space to be left about the building, the level and width of foundation, the stability of structure and materials to be used and the provision to be made for drainage, and ventilation;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-70.1.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>for the forming of extensions or lay-outs and the laying out of private streets, the information and plans to be submitted with the application for permission to form extensions or lay-outs and to make private streets, and for regulating the level and width of streets and the height of buildings abutting thereon;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-70.1.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>relating to the construction of footpaths, erection of street lights and planting of trees; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-70.1.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>generally for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-70.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In making a bye-law under sub-section (1), the Board may provide that a breach thereof shall be punishable with fine which may extend to one hundred rupees and in the case of a continuing breach with additional fine which may extend to fifty rupees for every day during which such breach continues after notice is received from the Board requiring such person to discontinue the breach.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-70.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any such bye-law may also provide that a person contravening the same shall be required to remedy the mischief, if any caused by such breach.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-70.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall, before making any bye-law under this section, publish in the official Gazette for the information of persons likely to be affected thereby, a draft of the proposed bye-law together with a notice specifying a date not being earlier than thirty days from the date of publication of the draft of the proposed bye-law on or after which the draft will be taken into consideration, and shall before making the bye-law consider any objection or suggestion received with respect to the said draft before the date so specified.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-70.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No bye-law made by the Board under this section shall have effect until it has been approved by the Government and every such bye-law shall be submitted to the Government along with a statement containing the views of the Board on the objections and suggestions if any, received and a copy of the notice published under the subsection (4) and every objection or suggestion received with respect to the draft bye-law.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-70.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Government while approving a bye-law may make any change therein which appears to it to be necessary.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-70.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every bye-law as approved by the Government shall be published in the official Gazette and shall come into force from such date not being earlier to the date of publication of the bye-laws in the Gazette as may be specified by the Board and when no such date is specified, on the date of such publication.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-71">
          <num>71.</num>
          <heading>Rules and bye-laws to be exhibited.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-71.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The rules and bye-laws made under sections 69 and 70 shall be exhibited at such places as may be prescribed and copies shall be made available for sale by the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-72">
          <num>72.</num>
          <heading>Repeal of the Karnataka Ordinance No. 20 of 1975.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-72.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Karnataka Improvement Board Ordinance, 1975 (Karnataka Ordinance No. 20 of 1975) is hereby repealed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-72.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding such repeal anything done or any action taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
