<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1957/5/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1957/5"/>
          <FRBRalias value="Karnataka Ministers Salaries And Allowances Act, 1956."/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1957/5/eng@2017-07-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1957/5/eng@2017-07-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-07-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1957/5/eng@2017-07-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1957/5/eng@2017-07-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-07-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>Karnataka Ministers Salaries And Allowances Act, 1956.</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT No. 5 OF 1957</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[28th January 1957]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the Salaries and Allowances of the Ministers, Ministers of State and Deputy Ministers of the State of Karnataka and certain other matters.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the Salaries and Allowances of the Ministers, Ministers of State and Deputy Minister of the State of Karnataka and certain other matters;</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>BE it enacted by the Karnataka State Legislature in the Seventh Year of the Republic of India as follows:—</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Karnataka Ministers Salaries and Allowances Act, 1956.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the first day of November, 1956.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>‘highest class’ in relation to journeys by train includes air conditioned accommodation available in the train;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>‘Minister’, ‘Minister of State’ and ‘Deputy Minister’ mean respectively, ‘Minister’, ‘Minister of State’ and ‘Deputy Minister’; and ‘Minister’ includes the Chief Minister.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>‘prescribed’ means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>‘residence’ includes the staff quarters and other buildings appurtenant thereto and the gardens thereof.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Salaries of Chief Minister and Ministers.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>There shall be paid to the Chief Minister a salary of fifty thousand rupees per mensem and to each Minister a salary of forty thousand rupees per mensem. They shall also be paid a sumptuary allowance of three lakhs rupees per annum.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Residences of Ministers.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Each Minister shall be entitled, to the use of a furnished residence in the City of Bangalore throughout his term of office and for a period of sixty days immediately thereafter, or in lieu of such furnished residence to a house rent allowance at the rate of eighty thousand rupees per mensem. The residence provided under this sub-section shall be furnished on such scales, and the plinth area thereof shall not exceed such limits, as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In a residence used by a Minister who is entitled to a house rent allowance in lieu of a furnished residence, three rooms shall be furnished by the State Government on such scales as may be prescribed, to be used for</p>
            <p>official purposes. He shall be entitled for an allowance of twenty thousand rupees per month for maintenance and upkeep of residence and for layout and maintenance of gardens included in such residence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Conveyances for Ministers.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may provide a suitable motor car for the use of each Minister.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be paid to each Minister a conveyance allowance equal to the cost of One thousand litres of petrol per mensem.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Charges payable by the Minister and the Government.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Each Minister shall in respect of the residence and motor car allotted for his use under sub-section (1) of section 4 and section 5, be liable to pay the following charges, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>cost of petrol required for their respective motor cars in excess of the cost of One thousand litres of petrol paid by the Government.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>he first two hundred rupees of the aggregate monthly charges for the consumption of electricity and water in the residence.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All other charges for the maintenance and upkeep of the residence provided under sub-section (1) of section 4 and the motor car provided under section 5, including the cost of repairs thereof, the salaries and allowances of the drivers and cleaners of such motor car, rates and taxes, and all expenditure for the layout and the maintenance of the gardens included in such residence, shall be borne by the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6A">
        <num>6A.</num>
        <heading>Salaries of Ministers of State.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>There shall be paid to each Minister of State a salary of thirty five thousand rupees per mensem and a sumptuary allowance of two lakhs rupees per annum.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6B">
        <num>6B.</num>
        <heading>Residences of Ministers of State.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6B.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Each Minister of State shall be entitled, to the use of a furnished residence in the City of Bangalore throughout his term of office and for a period ofsixty days immediately thereafter, or in lieu of such furnished residence to a house rent allowance at the rate of eighty thousand rupees per mensem. The residence provided under this sub-section shall be furnishedon such scales, and the plinth area thereof shall not exceed such limits, as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6B.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In a residence used by a Minister of State who is entitled to a house rent allowance in lieu of a furnished residence, three rooms shall be furnished by the State Government on such scales as may be prescribed, to be used for official purposes. He shall be entitled for an allowance of twenty thousand rupees per month for maintenance and up keep of residence and for layout and maintenance of gardens included in such residence</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6C">
        <num>6C.</num>
        <heading>Conveyance for Ministers of State.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6C.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may provide a suitable motor car for the use of each Minister of State.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6C.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be paid to each Minister of State a conveyance allowance equal to the cost of One thousand litres of petrol per mensem.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6D">
        <num>6D.</num>
        <heading>Charges payable by the Minister of State and the Government.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6D.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6D.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Each Minister of State shall in respect of the residence and motor car allotted for his use under sub-section (1) of section 6B and section 6C, be liable to pay the following charges, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6D.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>cost of petrol required for their respective motor cars in excess of the cost of One thousand litres of petrol paid by the Government.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6D.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the first two hundred rupees of the aggregate monthly charges for the consumption of electricity and water in the residence.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6D.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All other charges for the maintenance and upkeep of the residence provided under sub-section (1) of section 6B and the motor car provided under section 6C, including the cost of repairs thereof, the salaries andallowances of the drivers and cleaners of such motor car, rates and taxes, and all expenditure for the layout and the maintenance of the gardens included in such residence, shall be borne by the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Salaries of Deputy Ministers.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>There shall be paid to each Deputy Minister a salary of thirty thousand rupees per mensem and a sumptuary allowance of One lakh fifty thousand rupees per annum.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Residences of Deputy Ministers.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Each Deputy Minister shall be entitled to the use of a furnished residence in the City of Bangalore throughout his term of office and for a period of sixty days immediately thereafter or in lieu of such furnished residence to a house rent allowance at the rate of eighty thousand rupees per mensem. The residence provided under this sub-section shall be furnishedon such scales and the plinth area thereof shall not exceed such limits, as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In a residence used by a Deputy Minister who is entitled to a house rent allowance in lieu of a furnished residence three rooms shall be furnished by the State Government on such scales as may be prescribed, to be used for official purposes. He shall be entitled for an allowance of twenty thousand rupees per month for maintenance and up keep of residence and for layout and maintenance of gardens included in such residence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Conveyance for Deputy Ministers.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may provide a suitable motor car for the use of each Deputy Minister.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be paid to each Deputy Minister a conveyance allowance equal to the cost of One thousand litres of petrol per mensem.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9A">
        <num>9A.</num>
        <heading>Use of helicopter and aircraft by Ministers etc.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every Minister, Minister of State or Deputy Minister shall, subject to availability, be entitled to use the helicopter or aircraft owned by the State Government, for official purposes, free of charge.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Charges payable by the Deputy Minister and the Government.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Each Deputy Minister shall in respect of the residence and motor car allotted for his use under sub-section (1) of section 8 and section 9, be liable to pay the following charges, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>cost of petrol required for their respective motor cars in excess of the cost of One thousand litre of petrol paid by the Government.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the first two hundred rupees of the aggregate monthly charges for the consumption of electricity and water in the residence.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All other charges for the maintenance and upkeep of the residence provided under sub-section (1) of section 8 and the motor car provided under section 9, including the cost of repairs thereof, the salaries and allowances of the drivers and cleaners of such motor cars, rate and taxes, and all expenditure for the layout and the maintenance of the gardens included in such residence, shall be borne by the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10A">
        <num>10A.</num>
        <heading>State Government to bear electricity and water charges in certain other cases.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In respect of the residence of a Minister, a Minister of State and a Deputy Minister, who does not avail the facility of furnished residence, monthly charges in excess of first two hundred rupees per month for consumption of electricity and water together in his residence shall be borne by the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10B">
        <num>10B.</num>
        <heading>Deductions in respect of house rent etc.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10B.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10B.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>There shall be deducted every month from the salary payable to a Minister, a Minister of State and a Deputy Minister,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10B.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>a sum equal to ten per cent of his salary as house rent, if he is in occupation of residence provided by the State Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10B.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>a sum equal to two and a half per cent of his salary as rent of the furnishings of his residence, if the same has been furnished by the State Government.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Travelling Allowances of a Minister, a Minister of State or a Deputy Minister on assuming or relinquishing office.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A Minister, Minister of State or Deputy Minister shall:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for the journey in respect of assuming office, to the City of Bangalore, from his usual place of residence in the State if it is outside the City, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>for the journey in respect of relinquishing office, from the City of Bangalore, to his usual place of residence in the State before he assumed office if such place is outside the City,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-11.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>be entitled to travelling allowance for himself and the members of his family and for the transport of his personal effects at the rates hereinafter specified, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.1.list3.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the actual charges incurred by the Minister, the Minister of State or the Deputy Minister for himself and the members of his family, whether the journey is made by train or by road or both;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.1.list3.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>the actual charges incurred for the transport of the personal effects whether by road or by rail; provided that if a railway wagon is reserved for such transport, the charges for such wagon.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Explanation.- For the purpose of this section, member of the family means the husband, wife, son, daughter, father, mother, brother or sister if wholly dependent on and residing with the Minister, the Minister of State or the Deputy Minister as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Travelling and other allowances on tours.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Minister, Minister of State and Deputy Minister shall be entitled, while touring on duty connected with his office, to travelling and daily or other allowances at the rates and upon the conditions specified in this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-12.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>While touring on official business every Minister, Minister of State and Deputy Minister shall be entitled,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for journeys by train to two times the single fare of the highest class available in the train:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that if a Minister, a Minister of State or a Deputy Minister reserves a compartment for the journey, the charges for such compartment shall be borne by the State Government:</p>
            <blockList id="section-12.2.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Provided further that if any person in addition to the Minister, the Minister of State or the Deputy Minister travels in the reserved compartment, the charges in respect of such person shall be recovered and credited to Government;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.2.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>for journeys by road, to road mileage at thirty rupees per kilometre;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.2.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>for journeys by air, to one and one-fifth times the single fare paid for such journeys and to the prescribed insurance premium for insurance against accidents during such journeys;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.2.list4.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>to daily allowance at two thousand rupees per day for the days of journey and for the days of halt at any place:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that in the case of tours outside the State, the daily allowance shall be at two thousand five hundred rupees per day for the days of journey and for the days of halt at any place:</p>
            <p>Provided further that if a Minister, a Minister of State or a Deputy Minister is treated as a State Guest, he shall be entitled only to one-fourth of the daily allowance for the period for which he is treated as a State Guest.</p>
            <p>Provided also that in case of tour outside the state where he has stayed in a hotel or registered establishment providing boarding and loadging at scheduled rates, he shall be entitled for daily allowance of rupees five thousand per day subject to production of bills.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2A">
          <num>(2A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Minister, Minister of State and Deputy Minister touring outside India on duty or travelling outside India for medical treatment shall be entitled to the same terms and conditions in regard to travelling and other expenses as a Minister of the Government of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2B">
          <num>(2B)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When a Minister, Minister of State or Deputy Minister while making a journey by road in a motor car provided by the State Government, has to undertake in the public interest further journey by train or by air, he shall be entitled to the petrol charges incurred by him for the return of the motor car to the city of Bangalore from the place at which he ceases to use the motor car.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2C">
          <num>(2C)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Minister, Minister of State and Deputy Minister shall in addition to the allowances payable under sub-section, be entitled to use without payment of charges, the motor cars maintained by the State Government at the Karnataka Bhavan in New Delhi.</p>
            <p>Provided that if no such motor car is available for use and if a motor car is hired by him for journeys in connection with his official business he shall be entitled to recover the actual hire charges paid by him.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may maintain suitable motor cars for tours by Ministers, Ministers of State and Deputy Ministers in prescribed places within the State which are not easily accessible, and when such motor cars are used by any Minister, Minister of State or Deputy Minister on tour, then, notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (2), he shall not be entitled to any allowance other than the daily allowance.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If a motor car provided to him by the State Government goes out of order while on tour by road and a motor car is hired by him for journeys connected with his official business, the Minister, Minister of State or the Deputy Minister shall be entitled to recover the actual hire charges paid by him.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12A">
        <num>12A.</num>
        <heading>Omitted</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Medical attendance.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Subject to rules made by the State Government, a Minister, a Minister of State and a Deputy Minister and the members of the family of the Minister, the Minister of State or the Deputy Minister who are residing with and are dependent on him shall be entitled free of charge to accommodation in hospitals maintained by the State Government and to medical attendance and treatment. They shall also be entitled, subject to rules made by the State Government, to reimbursement of the expenses incurred by them for medical attendance and treatment obtained at any other place whether within or outside India.</p>
            <p>Explanation.—For the purpose of this section, member of the family means the husband, wife, son, daughter, father, mother, brother or sister.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Ministers, Ministers of State and Deputy Ministers not to practise profession, etc.,-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A Minister, a Minister of State or a Deputy Minister shall not, during the tenure of his office, practise any profession or engage in any trade or undertake for remuneration, any employment other than his duties as Minister, Minister of State or Deputy Minister as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Karnataka Gazette, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.1A">
          <num>(1A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any rule under this Act may be made to have effect retrospectively, and if any such rule is made, a statement specifying the reasons for making such a rule shall be laid before both Houses of the State Legislature along with the rule under sub-section (2).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All rules made under sub-section (1) shall be laid, as soon as may be, after they are made, before each House of the State Legislature while it is in session for a total period of one month which may be comprised in one session or in two or more sessions and if, before the expiry of the said period, either House of the State Legislature makes any modification in the rules or directs that any rule shall not have effect and, if the modification or direction is agreed to by the other House, the rules shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Repeal of Karnataka Ordinance No.2 of 1956 and savings.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Karnataka Ministers’ Salaries and Allowances Ordinance, 1956, is hereby repealed; but any rules made, anything done and any action taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been made, done or taken under this Act as if this Act had come into force on the first day of November, 1956 and all rules made under the said Ordinance shall be laid, as soon as may be, after the passing of this Act, before each House of the State Legislature while it is in session for a total period of one month which may be comprised in one session or in two or more sessions and if, before the expiry of the said period either House of the State Legislature makes any modification in the rules or directs that any rule shall not have effect and, if the modification or direction is agreed to by the other House, the rules shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
