<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1963/15/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1963/15"/>
          <FRBRalias value="Karnataka Parliamentary Secretaries Allowances Act, 1963"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1963/15/eng@2017-07-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1963/15/eng@2017-07-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-07-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1963/15/eng@2017-07-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1963/15/eng@2017-07-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-07-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>Karnataka Parliamentary Secretaries Allowances Act, 1963</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT No. 15 OF 1963</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[20th April 1963]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the Salary, allowances and miscellaneous provisions of Parliamentary Secretaries.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the Salary, Allowances and Miscellaneous Provisions of Parliamentary Secretaries of the State of Karnataka;</p>
      </longTitle>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by the Karnataka State Legislature in the Fourteenth Year of the Republic of India as follows:—</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Karnataka Parliamentary Secretaries Salary, Allowances and Miscellaneous Provisions Act, 1963.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force at once.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—In this Act, unless the context, otherwise requires,—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“Parliamentary Secretary” means a member of the Karnataka Legislative Assembly or the Karnataka Legislative Council appointed as a Parliamentary Secretary by the Chief Minister;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>***</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Salary and allowances of Parliamentary Secretary.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A Parliamentary Secretary shall be entitled to such salaries and allowances as are admissible to a Minister, Minister of State or a Deputy Minister under the Karnataka Minister's Salaries and Allowances Act, 1956, as may be specified by the Government from time to time.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Parliamentary Secretary not to draw salaries and allowances as member.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A Parliamentary Secretary shall not, while he draws salary and allowances for his office, be entitled to any salary and allowances as a me.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Functions and duties of Parliamentary Secretary.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The funtions and duties of a Parliamentary Secretary shall be such as may be specified by the Chief Minister or a Minister to whom he is the Parliamentary Secretary.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Oath of Office and of Secrecy.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Before a Parliamentary Secretary enters upon his office, the Chief Minister shall administer to him the oath of office and of secrecy according to such form as may be specified by the Government in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Parliamentary Secretary not to practise profession, etc.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A Parliamentary Secretary shall not, during the tenure of his office, practise any profession or engage in any trade or undertake for remuneration, any employment other than his duties as Parliamentary Secretary.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Karnataka Gazette, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of the State Legislature while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session in which it is so laid or the session immediately following, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
