<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kl/act/1968/20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kl/act/1968/20"/>
          <FRBRalias value="Kerala Animals and Birds Sacrifices Prohibition Act, 1968"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kl/act/1968/20/eng@1968-09-17/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kl/act/1968/20/eng@1968-09-17"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1968-09-17" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kl/act/1968/20/eng@1968-09-17/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kl/act/1968/20/eng@1968-09-17"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>Kerala Animals And Birds Sacrifices Prohibition Act, 1968</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[Act No. 20 of 1968]</p>
      </longTitle>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[17th September, 1968]</docDate>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>An Act to consolidate and amend the laws relating to prohibition of the sacrifice of animals and birds in or in the precincts of Hindu temples in the State of Kerala.</p>
      <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to consolidate and amend the laws relating to prohibition of the sacrifice of animals and birds in or in the precincts of Hindu temples in the State of Kerala;</p>
      <p>BE it enacted in the Nineteenth Year of the Republic of India as follows:-</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and extent</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Kerala Animals and Birds Sacrifices Prohibition Act, 1968.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Kerala.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"precincts", in relation to a temple, includes all lands and buildings near a temple, whether belonging to the temple or not, which are ordinarily used for purposes connected with the worship conducted inside the temple or outside, and in particular the mandapams prakarams, back-yards front-yards and foot-yards of the temple, by whatever name called, and also the ground on which the temple car ordinarily stands;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"sacrifice" means the killing or maiming of any animal or bird for the purpose, or with the intention, of propitiating any deity ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>"temple" means a place by whatever designation known, used as a place of public religious worship, and dedicated to, or for the benefit of, or used as of right by, the Hindu community or any section thereof, as a place of public religious worship.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Sacrifice of animals and birds in temples or its precincts prohibited</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No person shall sacrifice any animal or bird in any temple or its precincts.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Officiating at sacrifice, etc., prohibited</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>No person shall-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>officiate or offer to officiate at, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>perform or offer to perform, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>serve, assist, or participate, or offer to serve, assist or participate, in any sacrifice in a temple or its precincts.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Temple or its precincts not to be allowed to be used for sacrifice</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>No person shall knowingly allow any sacrifice to be performed at any place which-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>is situated within any temple or its precincts, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>is in his possession or under his control</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Penalties</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever contravenes the provisions of section 3 shall be punishable with fine which may extent to three hundred rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever contravenes the provisions of section 4 shall be punishable with fine which may extend to three hundred rupees:</p>
            <p>Provided that if the offender is an officer, servant, authority trustee or priest of the temple or the holder of any office in receipt of emoluments or prequisites for the performance of any service in the temple, he shall be punishable with simple imprisonment for a terms which may extend to three months, or with fine which may extend to three hundred rupees, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever contravenes the provisions of section 5 shall be punishable with simple imprisonment for a term which may extend to three months, or with fine which may extent to three hundred rupees, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Inquiry and trial</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No offence punishable under this Act shall be inquired into or tried by a court inferior to that of a Magistrate of the first or second class.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Repeal</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Madras Animals and Birds Sacrifice Prohibition Act, 1950 (XXXII of 1950), as in force in the Malabar district referred to in sub-section (2) of section 5 of the States Reorganisation Act, 1956 (Central Act 37 of 1956) and the Travancore-Cochin Animals and Birds Sacrifices Prohibition Act, 1953, (VII of 1953), are hereby repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
