<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-pun/act/1941/7/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-pun/act/1941/7"/>
          <FRBRalias value="Punjab Suppression of Indecent Advertisement Act, 1941"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-pun/act/1941/7/eng@1941-04-30/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-pun/act/1941/7/eng@1941-04-30"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1941-04-30" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-pun/act/1941/7/eng@1941-04-30/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-pun/act/1941/7/eng@1941-04-30"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-12-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>Punjab Suppression Of Indecent Advertisement Act, 1941</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[Act No. 7 of 1941]</p>
        <p>[April 30, 1941]</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short Title.–</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>This act may be called the Punjab Suppression of Indecent Advertisement Act, 1941.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Interpretation.–</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>For the purposes of this Act any advertisement relating to syphilis, gonorrhea, nerves debility or other complaint or infirmity arising from or relating to sexual intercourse shall be deemed to be printed or written matter of an indecent nature.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Proceedings against persons affixing, etc. indecent pictures or printed or written matter.–</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever affixes to inscribes or stencils on any house, building, wall, hoarding, gate, fence, pillar, post, board, tree, or any other thing whatsoever so as to be visible to a person being in or passing along any street, public highway or footpath and whoever affixes to, inscribes or stencils On any public latrine or urinal or exhibits to public view in the window, of any house or shop, any picture or printed or written matter which is of indecent nature, shall, on conviction, be punished with imprisonment of either description for a term which may extend to six months or with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, or with both such imprisonment and fine.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whenever any printed or written matter of an indecent nature has been displayed in the manner prohibited by sub¬section (1), any person being in possession or control of the land, building, structure or premises to which such printed or written matter has been affixed who knowingly allows the same to be continued to be displayed shall, on conviction, be punished with imprisonment which may extend to six months or with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, or with both such imprisonment and fine.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Proceedings against persons sending others to do the acts punishable under section 3.–</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever gives or delivers to any other person any such pictures, or printed or written matter mentioned in Section 3 with the intent that the same, or some one or more thereof, should be affixed, inscribed, stenciled, or exhibited as therein mentioned, shall, on conviction, be punished with imprisonment of either description which may extend to one thousand rupees or with both such imprisonment and fine.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Power to seize, remove, deface or destroy pictures or printed or written matter of an indecent nature.–</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If a District Magistrate, Sub­Divisional Magistrate or Executive Magistrate of the First Class has reason to believe that any picture or printed or written matter of an indecent nature which has been affixed, inscribed or stenciled as mentioned in section 3, continues to be exhibited to public view after the commencement of this Act, he may by order in writing authorize any police officer to enter, with such assistance as may be required, and place any seize, remove, deface or destroy any such picture or printed or written matter.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Police officer may arrest on view of offence.–</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any police officer may arrest without warrant any person whom he shall find committing any offence against this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Saving.–</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Noting in this Act shall apply to any advertisement published by any municipal corporation or by any municipal, small town or notified area committee or published with the sanction of the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
