<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-raj/act/2008/1/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-raj/act/2008/1"/>
          <FRBRalias value="Rajasthan Prevention of Anti-Social Activities Act, 2006"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-raj/act/2008/1/eng@2017-01-20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-raj/act/2008/1/eng@2017-01-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-20" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-raj/act/2008/1/eng@2017-01-20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-raj/act/2008/1/eng@2017-01-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-12-06" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>Rajasthan Prevention Of Anti-Social Activities Act, 2006</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[Act No. 1 of 2008]</p>
      </longTitle>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[25th February 2008]</docDate>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>An Act to provide for preventive detention of boot-leggers, dangerous persons, drug offenders, immoral traffic offenders and property grabbers for preventing their anti-social and dangerous activities</p>
      <p>prejudicial to the maintenance of public order.</p>
      <p>Be it enacted by the Rajasthan State Legislature in the Fifty­seventh Year of the Republic of India, as follows:-­</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This act may be called the Rajasthan Prevention of Anti-social Activities Act, 2006.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the state of Rajasthan.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force at once.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-­</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"authorized officer" means a District Magistrate authorized under sub-section (2) of section 3 to exercise the powers conferred under sub-section (1) of that section;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"boot-legger" means a persons who habitually distills, manufactures, stores, transports, imports, exports, sells or distributes any liquor, intoxicating drug or other intoxicant in contravention of any provision of the Rajasthan Excise Act, 1950 (Act No. 2 of 1950) and the rules and orders made thereunder, or of any other law for the time being in force or who knowingly expends or applies any money or supplies any animal, vehicles, vessel or other conveyance or any receptacle or any other material whatsoever in furtherance or support of the doing of any of the things described above by or through any other person, or who abets in any other manner the doing of any such thing;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>"dangerous person" means a person, who either by himself or as member or leader of a gang, habitually commits, or a attempts to commit or abets the commission of any of the offences punishable under Chapter XVI or Chapter XVII of the Indian Penal Code, 1860 (Central Act No. 45 of 1860) or any of the offences punishable under Chapter V of the Arms Act, 1959 (Central Act No. 54 of 1959) or any of the offences punishable under first proviso to sub-section (1), and sub-section (1 A), of section 51 of the Wild life (Protection) Act, 1972 (Central Act No. 53 of 1972) or any offence punishable under section 67 of the Information Technology Act, 2000 (Central Act No. 21 of 2000);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>"Detention order" means an order made under section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>"detenu" means a person detained under a detention order;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>"drug offender" means a person who habitually­­</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>Imports any drug in contravention of section 10 of the Drugs and Cosmetics Act, 1940 (Central Act No. 23 of 1940) (hereinafter in this definition referred to as "the Drugs Act");</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>manufactures for sale, or sells, or stocks or exhibits for sale, or distributes any drug in contravenion of section 18 of the Drugs Act;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>Manufactures for sale or for distribution, or sels, or stocks or exhibits or offers for sale, or distribues any Ayurvedic, Siddha or Unani drug in contravention of section 33­EEC of the Drugs Act;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f.list0.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>Cultivates any coca plant, opium poppy, or cannabis plant or produces, manufactures, possesses, sells, purchases, transports, warehouses, imports inter-state, exports inter-state, imports into India, exports from India or trans-ships any narcotic drug or psychotropic substances in contravention of section 8 of the Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances Ac, 1985 (Central Act No. 61 of 1985);</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f.list0.v">
                    <num>(v)</num>
                    <p>Knowingly expends or applies any money it furtherance or support of the doing of any of the things mentioned in any of the sub­clauses (i) to (iv) by or through any other person; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f.list0.vi">
                    <num>(vi)</num>
                    <p>Abets in any manner the doing of any of the things mentioned in any of the sub­clauses (i) to (v);</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>"habitual", With all its grammatical variations, includes acts or omissions committed repeatedly, persistently and frequently having a thread of continuity stringing together similar repetitive acts or omission but shall not include isolated, individual and dissimilar acts or omissions;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>"immoral traffic offender" means a person who habitually commits or abets the commission of any offence under the Immoral Traffic (Prevention) Act, 1956 (Central Act no. 104 of 1956);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>"property grabber" means a person who illegally takes possession of any land situated within the urban limits of any district Head Quarters not belonging to himself but belonging to Government, local authority or any other person or who illegally enters into or creates illegal tenancies or leave and licence agreements or any other agreements in respect of such land or who constructs any structure thereon for sale or hire or gives such land to any person on rental or leave and licence basis for construction of any structure thereon or use and occupation or who knowingly gives financial aid to any person for taking illegal possession of such land or for construction of any structure thereon or who collects or attempts to collect from any occupiers of such land rent, compensation or other charges by criminal intimidation or who evicts or attempts to evict any such occupiers by force without resorting to the lawful procedure or who abets in any manner it he doing of any of the above mentioned things;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>"public order" shall have the same meaning as assigned to it under sub-section (4) of section 3.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Power to make orders detaining certain persons</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, if satisfied with respect to any person that with a view to preventing him from acting in any manner prejudicial to the maintenance of public order, it is necessary so to do, make an order directing that such person be detained.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If, having regard to the circumstances prevailing or likely to prevail in any area within the local limits of the jurisdiction of a District Magistrate, the State Government is satisfied that it is necessary so to do, it may, by order in writing, direct that the District Magistrate, may also, if satisfied as provided in sub-section (1), exercise the powers conferred by the said subsection.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When any order is made under this section by an authorized officer he shall forthwith report the fact to the State Government together with the grounds on which the order has been made and such other particulars as, in his opinion, have a bearing on the matter, and no such order shall remain in force for more than twelve days after the making thereof, unless, in the meantime, it has been approved by the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of this section, a person shall be deemed to be "acting in any manner prejudicial to the maintenance of public order" when such person is engaged in or is making preparation for engaging in any activities whether as a boot-legger or dangerous person or drug offender or immoral traffic offender or property grabber, which affect adversely or are likely to affect adversely the maintenance of public order.</p>
            <p>Explanation-­For the purpose of this sub-section public order shall be deemed to have been affected adversely or shall be deemed likely to be affected adversely inter alia if any of the activities of any person referred to in this sub-section directly or indirectly, is causing or is likely to cause any harm, danger or alarm or feeling of insecurity among the public at large or any section thereof or a grave or widespread danger to life, property or public health.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Execution of detention orders</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A detention order may be executed at any place in the State in the manner provided for the execution of warrant of arrest under the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (Central Act No. 2 of 1974).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Power to regulate place and conditions of detention</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Every person in respect of whom a detention order has been made shall be liable-­</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to be detained in such place and under such conditions, including conditions as to maintenance of discipline and punishment for breaches of discipline, as the Government may, be general or special order, specify; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to be removed from one place of detention to another, place of detention, within the State by order of the State Government.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Grounds of detention severable</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where a person has been detained in pursuance of an order of detention under section 3 which has been made on two or more grounds, such order of detention shall be deemed to have been made separately on each of such grounds and accordingly-­</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>Such order shall not be deemed to be invalid or inoperative merely because one or some of the grounds is or are­­</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>Vague,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>non-existent,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>not­relevant,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>not connected or not proximately connected with such person, or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.v">
                    <num>(v)</num>
                    <p>invalid for any other reason whatsoever, and it is not, therefore, possible to hold that the State Government or the authorized officer making such order would have been satisfied as provided in section 3 with reference to the remaining ground or grounds and made the order of detention,</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the State Government or the authorized officer making the order of detention shall be deemed to have made the order or detention under the said section after being satisfied as provided in that section with reference to the remaining ground or grounds.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Detention orders not to be invalid or inoperative on certain grounds</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>No detention order shall be invalid or inoperative merely by reason-­</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>that the person to be detained thereunder, though within the State, is outside the territorial jurisdiction of the authorized officer making the order, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>that the place of detention of such person, though within the State, is outside the said limits.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Powers in relation to absconding persons</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the State Government or the authorized officer has reason to believe that a person, in respect of whom a detention order has been made, has absconded, or is concealing himself so that the order cannot be executed, in that case the State Government or, as the case may be, the authorized officer shall, irrespective of his ordinary jurisdiction, be deemed to be empowered to exercise all the powers of the Competent Court for issuing a proclamation for such person and for attachment and sale of his property situated in any part of the State and for taking any other action, and the provisions contained in sections 82, 83, 84 and 85 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (Central Act No. 2 of 1974) shall mutatis mutandis apply as it the detention order as aforesaid was a warrant of arrest issued by a Competent Court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If such person fails to comply with such proclamation, unless he proves that it was not possible for him to comply therewith, and that he had, within the period specified in the order, informed the officer mentioned in the order of the reasons which rendered compliance therewith impossible and of his whereabouts, or proves that it was not possible for him to so inform the officer mentioned in the order, shall on conviction, be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year or with fine, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An appeal from any order made by the State Government or, as the case may be, by the authorized officer rejecting application for restoration of attached property shall lie to the court of sessions having jurisdiction over the place where the property in question is situated.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (Central Act No. 2 of 1974) every offence under sub-section (2) shall be cognizable.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Grounds of order of detention to be disclosed to detenu</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When a person is detained in pursuance of a detention order the authority making the order shall, as soon as may be, but not later than three days from the date of detention, communicate to him the grounds on which the order has been made and shall afford him the earliest opportunity of making a representation against the order to the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in sub-section (1) shall require the authority to disclose facts which it considers to be against the public interest to disclose.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of Advisory Boards</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government shall constitute one or more Advisory Boards for the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every such Board shall consist of a Chairman and two other members who are, or have been, Judges of any High Court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Reference to Advisory Board</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In every case where a detention order has been made under this Act the State Government shall, within three weeks from the date of detention of a person under the order, place before the Advisory Board constituted by it under section 10 the grounds on which the order has been made and the representation, if any, made by the "detenue" and where the order has been made by an authorized officer, also the report made by such officer under sub-section (3) of section 3.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Procedure of Advisory Board</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Advisory Board, shall after considering the materials placed before it and, after calling for such further information as it may deem necessary from the State Government or from any person called for the purpose through the State Government or from the detenu and if, in any particular case, the Advisory Board considers it essential so to do or if the detenu desires to be heard, after hearing the detenu in person, submit its report to the State Government, within fifty days from he date of detention of the detenu.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The report of the Advisory Board shall specify in a separate part thereof the opinion of the Advisory Board as to whether or not there is sufficient cause for the detention of the detenu.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When there is a difference of opinion among the members forming the Advisory Board the opinion of the majority of such members shall be deemed to be the opinion of the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The proceedings of the Advisory Board and its report excepting that part of the report in which the opinion of the Advisory Board is specified shall be confidential.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in this section shall entitle any person against whom a detention order has been made to appear by any legal practitioner in any matter connected with the reference to the Advisory Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Action upon report of Advisory Board</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In any case where the Advisory Board has reported that there is, in its opinion, sufficient cause for the detention of the detenu, the State government may confirm the detention order and continue the detention of the detenu for a period not exceeding the maximum period prescribed by section 14 as it thinks fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In any case where the Advisory Board has reported that there is, in its opinion, no sufficient cause for the detention of the person concerned, the State Government shall revoke the detention order and cause the detenu to be released forthwith.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Maximum period of detention</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The maximum period for which any person may be detained in pursuance of any detention order made under this Act which has been confirmed under section 13, shall be one year from the date of detention.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Revocation of detention orders</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Without prejudice to the provisions of section 23 of the Rajasthan General Clauses Act, 1955 (Act No. 8 of 1955) a detention order may, at any time for reasons to be recorded in writing, be revoked or modified by the State government, notwithstanding that the order has been made by an authorized officer.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The expiry or revocation of a detention order (hereinafter in this sub-section referred to as "the earlier detention order") shall not bar the making of another detention order (hereinafter in this sub-section referred to as "the subsequent detention order") under -section 3 against the same person:</p>
            <p>Provided that in a case where no fresh facts have arisen after the expiry or revocation o the earlier detention order made against such person, the maximum period for which such person may be detained in pursuance of the subsequent detention order shall in no case, extend beyond the expiry of a period of twelve months from the date of detention under the earlier detention order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Temporary release of person detained</heading>
        <subsection id="section-16.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, at any time, for reasons to be recorded in writing, direct that any person detained in pursuance of a detention order may be released for any specified period, either without conditions or upon such conditions specified in the direction as that person accepts, and may, at any time, cancel his release.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In directing the release of any detenu under sub-section (1), the State Government may require him to enter into a bond, with or without sureties, for the due observance of the conditions specified in the direction.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any detenu released under sub-section (1) shall surrender himself at the time and place, and to the authority, specified in the order directing his release or cancelling his release, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any detenu fails without sufficient cause to surrender himself in the manner specified in sub-section (3), he shall on conviction, be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years, or with fine, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any detenu release under sub-section (1) fails to fulfil any of the conditions specified in the direction, for due observance of which a bond was executed by him, the bond shall be declared to be forfeited and any person bound thereby shall be liable to pay the penalty thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the State government or any officer or person, for anything in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Matters within the purview of this Act to be dealt with under this Act only</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>On and after the commencement of this act, no order of detention under the National Security Act, 1980 (Central Act No. 65 of 1980) shall be made by the State Government or any officer subordinate to it, in respect of any boot-legger, drug offender, dangerous person, immoral traffic offender, or property grabber in the State on the ground of preventing him from acting in any manner prejudicial to the maintenance of public order, in so far as an order under this Act, could be made for detention of such person.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
