<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1965/10/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1965/10"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Karnataka Public Libraries Act, 1965"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1965/10/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1965/10/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1965/10/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1965/10/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-06-16" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Karnataka Public Libraries Act, 1965</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No. 10 of 1965</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the establishment and maintenance of public libraries and the organisation of a comprehensive rural and urban library service in the State of Karnataka1</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the establishment and maintenance of public libraries and the organisation of a comprehensive rural and urban library service in the State of Karnataka and for matters connected therewith;</p>
      <p>BE it enacted by the Karnataka State Legislature in the Sixteenth Year of the Republic of India as follows:-</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <heading>Preliminary</heading>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the Karnataka Public Libraries Act, 1965.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Karnataka.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on such date as the State Government may, by notification, appoint.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-2.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>'academic library' means a library maintained by a university, college, school or research institution;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>'aided library' means a library declared by the Director of Public Libraries to be eligible for aid from the Government in accordance with the rules made under this Act;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>'book' includes,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.3.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>every volume,part or division of a volume, and pamphlet, in any language;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.3.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>every sheet of music, map, chart or plan separately printed or lithographed;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.3.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>newspapers, periodicals and other such materials;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>'Chief Librarian' means the Librarian appointed to be in charge of a City Central Library or a District Central Library and other Libraries and the library service under the control of a City Library Authority or a District Library Authority, as the case may be;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>'City Library Authority' means a Library Authority constituted for a city or other urban area under sections 16 and 17;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>'State-owned Library' means a library maintained by a Department of the State Government, the State Legislature, the High Court or any other court or any authority of the State;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>'district' means a revenue district;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>'District Library Authority' means a Library Authority constituted for a district under sections 16 and 18;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <p>'library cess' means a cess levied under section 30;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.10">
            <num>(10)</num>
            <content>
              <p>'Local Library Authority' means a City Library Authority or a District Library Authority;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.11">
            <num>(11)</num>
            <content>
              <p>'notification' means a notification published in the official Gazette;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.12">
            <num>(12)</num>
            <content>
              <p>'outlier library' means any library other than a public library;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.13">
            <num>(13)</num>
            <content>
              <p>'prescribed' means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.14">
            <num>(14)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.14.list1">
                <listIntroduction>'public library' means,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.14.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>a library established or maintained by a Local Library Authority, including the branches and delivery stations of such library;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.14.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>a library established or maintained by the State Government and declared open to the public;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.14.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>a library established or maintained by any local authority and declared open to the public;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.14.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>a library declared to be eligible for aid and receiving aid from the State Government; and includes, any other library notified by the State Government as a public library for the purposes of this Act;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.15">
            <num>(15)</num>
            <content>
              <p>'State Central Library' means the library declared to be the State Central Library under Chapter VI;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.16">
            <num>(16)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Director of Public Libraries means the Director of Public Libraries appointed under this Act;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.17">
            <num>(17)</num>
            <content>
              <p>'State Library Authority' means the Authority constituted under section 3;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.18">
            <num>(18)</num>
            <content>
              <p>'year' means the financial year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <heading>The Karnataka State Library Authority</heading>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Constitution and composition of the State Library Authority.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As soon as may be after the commencement of this Act, the State Government shall, by notification, constitute for the purposes of this Act, an authority to be called the State Library Authority. Such authority shall be a body corporate having perpetual succession and a common seal with power, subject to the provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of property, and to contract, and may by the same name sue and be sued.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The State Library Authority shall consist of,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the Minister in charge of Public Libraries who shall ex-officio be the President of the Authority;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>four persons elected by the Karnataka Legislative Assembly from among its members;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>two persons elected by the Karnataka Legislative Council from among its members;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>one person elected by the Syndicate of each of the Universities in the State from among the members of the Syndicate;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Explanation.- For purposes of this clause, in respect of the University of Agricultural Sciences, "Syndicate" means the Board of Regents.</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.2.list3.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>one person elected by the Executive Committee of the Karnataka Library Association from among the members of the Association;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.2.list3.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>one person elected by the City Library Authority of the City of Bangalore from among its members;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.2.list3.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>one person elected by the City Library Authority of one of the cities in the State other than the City of Bangalore for which a City Library Authority is established, from among the members of such Authority, subject to the condition that such election shall be made by each City Library Authority for one term in such order or rotation as the State Government may by order determine;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.2.list3.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>one person elected by the District Library Authority of one of the Districts in each Revenue Division of the State from among the members of such Authority, subject to the condition that such election shall be made by each District Library Authority in every Revenue Division for one term in such order of rotation as the State Government may by order determine;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.2.list3.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the Secretary to the Government, Education Department;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.2.list3.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>the Director of Public Instruction in Karnataka;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.2.list3.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>three persons nominated by the State Government who in the opinion of the State Government are experts in library science:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that at the first constitution of the Authority for purposes of clauses (f), (g) and (h), six persons ordinarily resident in the cities and districts of the Revenue Divisions for which the Library Authorities may be established, shall be nominated by the State Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Director of Public Libraries shall ex-officio be the Secretary of the State Library Authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Functions of the State Library Authority.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Library Authority shall advise the State Government on all matters connected with the administration of this Act, shall be the managing authority for the State Central Library, and shall exercise and perform such powers and duties conferred and entrusted to the said Authority by this Act, and such other powers and duties as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Nomination of members in default of election.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>If any of the bodies referred to in sub-section (2) of section 3 does not, by such period as may be prescribed, elect a person to be a member of the State Library Authority, the State Government shall, by notification, nominate to the vacancy a person qualified for election thereto; and the person so nominated shall be deemed to be a member of the Authority as if he had been duly elected by the said body.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Term of office.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Save as otherwise provided in this Act, the term of office of members of the State Library Authority, other than ex-officio members, shall be for a period of three years commencing from the date on which the first meeting of the Authority is held after the election or nomination of the members under section 3.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An outgoing member shall continue in office until the election or nomination of his successor.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An outgoing member shall be eligible for re-election or re-nomination.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Vacancies.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>In the event of a vacancy arising out of death, resignation, disability or otherwise, previous to the expiry of the term of office of any member of the State Library Authority, the vacancy shall be filled by election or nomination, as the case may be, of another person in the manner provided in sub-section (2) of section 3, and any person elected or nominated to fill the vacancy shall hold office only so long as the member in whose place he is elected or nominated would have held office if the vacancy had not occurred.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Disabilities for continuing as member.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>If any member other than an ex-officio member of the State Library Authority, during the period for which he has been nominated or elected,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>absents himself without excuse sufficient in the opinion of the Authority, from three consecutive meetings of the Authority; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>in the case of a member elected by any body referred to in sub-section (2) of section 3, ceases to be a member of the body concerned,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>his office in the Authority shall become vacant.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Disqualifications.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>A person shall be disqualified for being chosen as, and for being, a member of the State Library Authority,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>if he has been sentenced by a criminal court for an offence involving moral turpitude and punishable with imprisonment for a term exceeding three months, such sentence not having been subsequently reversed, quashed or remitted, unless he has, by order, which the State Government is hereby empowered to make in this behalf, been relieved from the disqualification arising on account of such sentence;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>if he is an undischarged insolvent;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>if he is of unsound mind and stands so declared by a competent court.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Meetings of the State Library Authority.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Library Authority shall meet at least twice a year on dates to be fixed by the President. One of such meetings shall be the annual meetings.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The President may also, whenever he thinks fit, convene a special meetings of the Authority for the transaction of urgent business.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to prescribed conditions special meetings shall be convened by the President to discuss matters of urgent importance upon a requisition by the members of the Authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Two-fifths of the total number of members of the Authority, shall be the quorum for a meeting of the State Library Authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The President, if present, shall preside at every meeting of the Authority. In the absence of the President, the members present at the meeting shall choose one from among themselves to preside.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Procedure of State Library Authority.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Library Authority shall transact business in such manner and in accordance with such procedure as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <heading>Department of Public Libraries</heading>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Department of Public Libraries.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>For the purposes of this Act, a Department of Public Libraries shall be constituted with a Director of Public Libraries as its head and such other officers and servants as the Government may by order specify.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Functions of the Department.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-13.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the control of the State Government, the Department of Public Libraries shall be responsible for the administration of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-13.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, the Department shall,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-13.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>superintend and direct all matters relating to all public libraries;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>promote the establishment of public library service so as to achieve the purposes of this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>supervise and direct all matters relating to libraries receiving aid from the State Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>maintain State Registers of Libraries and of Librarians;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>superintend, direct, and deal with the exercise of powers and the performance of duties by Local Library Authorities under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.2.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>ensure the proper utilisation of the Library Funds and library man-power of the State;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.2.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>perform such other functions as may be entrusted to the Department by or under the provisions of this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Director of Public Libraries.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A whole-time officer having the prescribed qualifications to practise the library profession shall be appointed by the State Government as theDirector of Public Libraries.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-14.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Director of Public Libraries shall,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-14.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>function as the Librarian of the State Central Library;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>superintendent, direct, and deal with all matters relating to the Press and Registration of Books Act, 1867 (Central Act 25 of 1867) and to the maintenance and service of the books sent under the said Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>control the appointments, postings, and transfers of officers and servants in the State Library Service;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>generally assist the State Library Authority in performing its functions;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>exercise such other powers and performs such other duties as may be conferred or imposed on him by or under this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>State Library Service.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-15.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law, all posts in the Department of Public Libraries, the State Central Library and every Local Library Authority shall be filled by appointment of persons belonging to the Karnataka State Library Service.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Karnataka State Library Service shall consist of the Director of Public Libraries, Chief Librarians of Cities and Districts, Librarians and such other classes and categories of posts as the State Government may from time to time determine. All members of the said service shall be Government servants, and their recruitment and conditions of service shall, subject to the provisions of Article 309 of the Constitution, be regulated by such rules as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The salary, allowances, gratuity, pension and other benefits of the members of the Karnataka State Library Service shall be met from the Consolidated Fund of the State.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <heading>Local Library Authorities</heading>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Constitution of Local Library Authorities.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-16.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-16.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>For the purpose of organising and administering Public Libraries in the State, there shall be constituted Local Library Authorities,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-16.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>for the Cities of Bangalore, Hubli-Dharwar, Mangalore, Mysore and Belgaum, and for such other urban area having a population of more than one lakh, as the State Government may by notification specify, called the City Library Authority; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>for each revenue district, excluding the area for which a City Library Authority is constituted, called the District Library Authority;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every Local Library Authority shall by the name of the area for which it is constituted, be a body corporate having perpetual succession and a common seal with power, subject to the provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of property, and to contract, and may by the same name sue and be sued.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Composition of City Library Authorities.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-17.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Every City Library Authority shall consist of,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the Mayor of the municipal corporation or the President of the municipal council or other municipal body of the City who shall ex-officio be the Chairman of the Authority;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>a principal of a First Grade College in the city nominated ex-officio by the State Government, who shall be the Vice-Chairman of the Authority;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>two persons elected by the municipal corporation, municipal council or other municipal body of the city from among its members;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>one person nominated by the State Government from among the members of governing bodies of aided libraries in the city;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.1.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>a Headmaster of a High School in the city nominated ex-officio by the State Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.1.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>one person nominated by the council of the city branch, if any, of the Karnataka Library Association;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.1.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>an officer of the Department of Public Instruction having jurisdiction over the city, nominated ex-officio by the State Government.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.1.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>two persons nominated by the State Government from among persons ordinarily resident in the city.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chief Librarian of the city shall ex-officio be the Secretary of the City Library Authority and of the Committees of the said Authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Composition of District Library Authorities.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-18.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-18.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Every District Library Authority shall consist of,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-18.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the Deputy Commissioner of the district who shall ex-officio be the Chairman of the Authority;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the Deputy Director of Public Instructions incharge of the district;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>two persons elected from among its members by the District Development Council;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>one person elected from among its members by each municipal council or other municipal body in the district with jurisdiction over a municipal area other than an area for which a City Library Authority is established having a population of not less than fifty thousand;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.1.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>two persons nominated by the State Government from among the members of municipal councils or other municipal bodies in the district with jurisdiction over a municipal area having a population of less than fifty thousand;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.1.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>one person nominated by the council of the District Branch, if any, of the Karnataka Library Association;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.1.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>one person nominated by the State Government from among the members of the Taluk Development Boards in the district;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.1.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>two persons nominated by the State Government from among the members of the village panchayats and town panchayats in the district;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.1.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>two persons nominated by the State Government from among the members of the governing bodies of aided libraries in the district;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.1.list1.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>a Principal of a First Grade College in the district nominated ex-officio by the State Government ;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.1.list1.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>a Headmaster of a High School in the district nominated ex-officio by the State Government ;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.1.list1.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>an officer of the Department of Public Instruction having jurisdiction over the district or a part thereof nominated ex-officio by the State Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.1.list1.m">
                  <num>(m)</num>
                  <p>three persons nominated by the State Government from among persons ordinarily resident in the district;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Vice-Chairman of the District Library Authority shall be elected by the members from among themselves.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chief Librarian of the district shall ex-officio be the Secretary of the District Library Authority and of the Committees of the said Authority;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Nomination of members in default of election.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>If any of the bodies referred to in section 17 or 18 does not by such period as may be prescribed elect or nominate a person to be a member of the City Library Authority or the District Library Authority, as the case may be, the State Government shall, by notification, nominate to the vacancy, a person qualified for election thereto; and the person so nominated shall be deemed to be a member of the Authority as if he had been duly elected by the said body.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Term of office.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-20.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Save as otherwise provided in this Act, the term of office of members of a Local Library Authority, other than ex-officio members, shall be for a period of three years commencing from the date on which the first meeting of the Authority is held after the election or nomination of the members under sections 17, 18 and 19.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An outgoing member shall continue in office until the election or nomination of his successor.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An outgoing member shall be eligible for re-election or re-nomination.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Vacancies.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>In the event of a vacancy arising out of death, resignation, disability or otherwise, before the expiry of the term of office of any member of a Local Library Authority, the vacancy shall be filled by election or nomination, as the case may be, of another person in the manner provided in section 17 or section 18, as the case may be, and any person elected or nominated to fill the vacancy shall hold office only so long as the member in whose place he is elected or nominated would have held office if the vacancy had not occurred.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Disabilities for continuing as member.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-22.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>If any member other than an ex-officio member of a Local Library Authority, during the period for which he has been nominated or elected,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-22.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>absents himself without excuse sufficient in the opinion of the Authority, from three consecutive meetings of the Authority; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-22.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>in the case of a member elected by any body referred to in section 17 or section 18 ceases to be member of the body concerned, his office in the Authority shall become vacant.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Disqualifications.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-23.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>A person shall be disqualified for being chosen as, and for being, a member of the Local Library Authority,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-23.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>if he has been sentenced by a criminal court for an offence involving moral turpitude and punishable with imprisonment for a term exceeding three months, such sentence not having been subsequently reversed, quashed or remitted, unless he has, by order, which the State Government is hereby empowered to make in this behalf, been relieved from the disqualification arising on account of such sentence;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>if he is an undischarged insolvent;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>if he is of unsound mind and stands so declared by a competent court.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Meetings of Local Library Authorities.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-24.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every Local Library Authority shall meet at least twice a year on dates to be fixed by the Chairman. One of such meetings shall be the annual meeting.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-24.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chairman may also, whenever he thinks fit, convene a special meeting of the Authority for the transaction of urgent business.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-24.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to prescribed conditions, special meetings shall be convened by the Chairman to discuss matters of urgent importance upon a requisition by the members of the Authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-24.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A Local Library Authority shall transact business in such manner and in accordance with such procedure as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Powers and duties of Chairman and Vice-Chairman.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-25.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-25.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Chairman of a Local Library Authority shall,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-25.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>preside at the meetings of the Authority;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-25.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>watch over the financial and executive administration of the Authority and exercise general supervision and control.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-25.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Vice-Chairman of a Local Library Authority shall,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-25.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>in the absence of the Chairman, preside at the meetings of the Authority;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-25.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>exercise such powers and perform such duties of the Chairman as the Chairman may, from time to time, delegate to him.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Powers and functions of Local Library Authorities.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-26.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall be the duty of every City Library Authority and every District Library Authority to provide library service to the persons residing in the area within its jurisdiction. The Library Authority shall in every City establish a City Central Library and Branch Libraries and in every district establish a District Central Library and branch libraries.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-26.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-26.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>For purposes of sub-section (1), a Local Library Authority may,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-26.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>provide suitable lands and buildings for public libraries, and the furniture, fittings, equipment and other conveniences necessary for the purpose;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>provide such libraries with books, periodicals, newspapers, maps, gramophone records, manuscripts, works and specimens of art and science, lantern slides, films, cinema projectors, recorders and the like;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>with the previous sanction of the Government shift or close any public library;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>accept any endowment or gift for any purpose connected with its activities;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-26.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that no gift or endowment of an immovable property shall be accepted without the previous sanction of the State Government;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-26.2.list3.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>provide for lectures and conduct other activities as may be conducive to the carrying out of the purposes of this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.2.list3.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>with the consent of the management and the previous sanction of the State Government acquire any library on such conditions as may be approved by the State Government ;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.2.list3.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>with the sanction of the State Government do any other thing that may be conducive to the furtherance of the purposes of this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.2.list3.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>exercise such other powers and perform such other duties as may be conferred or imposed by or under this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Library Development Plan.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-27.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the general or special orders of the State Government , as soon as possible after a Local Library Authority is constituted and thereafter as often as may be required by the Director of Public Libraries every Local Library Authority shall, and whenever it considers it necessary so to do, a Local Library Authority may, prepare a plan (hereinafter referred to as the 'Local Library Development Plan') for establishing libraries and spreading library service within the jurisdiction of such Authority in such form and manner and containing such particulars as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The salient features of every Local Library Development Plan prepared under sub-section (1) shall be published in such manner as may be prescribed along with a notice inviting objections and suggestions from all persons interested in the Plan within such period as may be specified in the notice. Any objection or suggestion which may be received from any person with respect to the Local Library Development Plan shall be considered by the Local Library Authority and such modifications in the Plan shall be made as the Authority deems fit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Local Library Development Plan shall thereafter be sent to the Director of Public Libraries along with a copy of the objections and suggestions received under sub-section (2). The Director of Public Libraries shall with his comments on the Local Library Development Plan submit it to the State Government for sanction.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may if it deems fit after ascertaining the views of the State Library Authority sanction the Local Library Development Plan with such alterations as it considers necessary. The State Government may on application by the Local Library Authority concerned, modify any Local Library Development Plan sanctioned under this sub-section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-27.5.list0">
                <item id="section-27.5.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>As soon as may be after the State Government sanctions a Local Library Development Plan under sub-section (4), the Director of Public Libraries shall in conformity with the provisions of the said Plan make an order called the Local Library Order for the area, specifying the Central Library and the Branch Libraries including branches, to be located in educational institutions, prisons and hospitals and the service stations, which shall be established and maintained by the Local Library Authority, the measures to be taken by the Local Library Authority for providing adequate library service to the people in the area and the stages in which such measures shall be taken.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.5.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>A Local Library Order made under clause (a) may be amended in consultation with the Local Library Authority, whenever the Director of Public Libraries considers it expedient to do so.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every Local Library Authority shall give effect to the Local Library Development Plan as sanctioned by the State Government and the Local Library Order made under sub-section (5).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Local Library Authority to appoint committees.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-28.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-28.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Every Local Library Authority shall constitute the following committees by election from among its members, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-28.1.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the Executive Committee; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.1.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>the Finance Committee.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-28.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A Local Library Authority may constitute committees for such other purposes as it deems fit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-28.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chairman of the Local Library Authority shall ex-officio be a member and Chairman of the Executive Committee, and the Finance Committee.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-28.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-28.4.list0">
                <item id="section-28.4.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>The Executive Committee shall be responsible for the executive functions of the Local Library Authority.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.4.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>The Finance Committee shall scrutinise proposals for increase of revenue, examine the receipts and expenditure statements, consider all new propositions affecting finance and shall generally supervise the revenue and expenditure of the Local Library Authority.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Advisory Library Committees.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-29.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purpose of advising on local requirements relating to library service of each branch library and each service station in a village served by travelling library service, Advisory Committees shall be constituted in accordance with the provisions of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-29.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Every Branch Library Committee shall consist of,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-29.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the Branch Librarian who shall ex-officio be the Chairman and convener of the Committee;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-29.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>one person representing the area which the Branch Library serves, on the municipal council or other municipal body or the panchayat having jurisdiction over that area, elected by the body concerned;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-29.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>three teachers of educational institutions in the area in which the branch library is located, nominated by the Chief Librarian of the City or the Chief Librarian of the district, as the case may be;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-29.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>three persons from among the registered borrowers of the branch library nominated by the Chief Librarian of the City or the Chief Librarian of the district, as the case may be.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-29.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Every Village Service Library Committee shall consist of,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-29.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the Travelling Librarian visiting the service station in the village who shall ex-officio be the Chairman and convener of the Committee;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-29.3.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>two teachers of educational institutions in the area served by the service station, nominated by the Chief Librarian of the District;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-29.3.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>two persons from among the registered borrowers in the area served by the service station, nominated by the Chief Librarian of the district.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The nominated members of the Branch Library Committee and the Village Service Library Committee shall hold office for a period of three years or until their successors are nominated.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <heading>Finance and Accounts</heading>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading>Library Cess.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-30.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-30.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>With effect from the date of commencement of this Act,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-30.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-30.1.list1.a.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>a library cess in the form of a surcharge on,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-30.1.list1.a.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>tax on lands and buildings;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-30.1.list1.a.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>tax on entry of goods into the local area for consumption, use or sale therein;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-30.1.list1.a.list0.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>tax on vehicles;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-30.1.list1.a.list0.iv">
                      <num>(iv)</num>
                      <p>tax on professions, trades, calling and employments;</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-30.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>shall be levied in the area within the jurisdiction of every City Library Authority under the relevant laws relating to local authorities providing for the levy of such taxes, at the rate of three paise for every rupee of the taxes so levied;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-30.1.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>a library cess in the form of a surcharge on tax on lands and buildings shall be levied in the area within the jurisdiction of every District Library Authority, under the relevant laws relating to local authorities providing for the levy of such tax at the rate of three paise for every rupee of the tax so levied.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-30.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A City Library Authority or District Library Authority may, with the previous sanction of the State Government , by notification, increase the rate of library cess levied on any item of tax specified in clause (a) or (b) of sub-section (1), subject to the condition that the rate shall not exceed six paise for every rupee of the tax levied.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-30.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The cess levied under clause (a) or clause (b) of sub-section (1) or increased under sub-section (2) shall be collected by the municipal corporation, municipal council or other municipal body, or the village panchayat or other local authority having jurisdiction over the area as if the cess were a tax referred to in the said clause payable under the relevant laws for the time being in force in the area, and all the provisions of the said laws relating to the levy and collection of the said tax shall apply subject to such modifications as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-30.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Out of the cess collected by it under sub-section (3) every local authority shall be entitled to retain ten per cent of the amount collected towards the cost of collection and the balance shall be paid to the City Library Authority or the District Library Authority, as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading>Government grant to District Library Authority of a portion of land revenue.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-31.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government shall make annually a grant to every District Library Authority of an amount equal to six per cent of the land revenue collection of the district.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The amount granted to a District Library Authority under sub-section (1) shall be credited to the District Library Fund at such times and in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-31.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Land Revenue collection of a district for the purposes of sub-section (1) shall mean,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-31.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>until the revision settlement of land revenue under Chapter X of the Karnataka Land Revenue Act, 1964, the land revenue determined on the basis of the average land revenue collection of the district for a period of three years preceding the date of such determination;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-31.3.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>after the determination of land revenue on the basis of the aforesaid revision settlement, the land revenue collected during the year preceding the year for which the grant is made.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>City and District Library Fund.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-32.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every City Library Authority and District Library Authority shall maintain a Fund called the City Library Fund and the District Library Fund, as the case may be, from which all its payments under this Act shall be met.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-32.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>There shall be credited to the City Library Fund and the District Library Fund, as the case may be, the following sums, namely :-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the amount of cess paid by the local authority under sub-section (4) of section 30;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the grant under section 31;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>contributions, gifts, and income from endowments, made to the Library Authority for the benefits of public libraries;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>grant which the Central Government or the State Government may make;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>funds and other amounts collected by the Local Library Authority under rules or bye-laws made under this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading>State Library Fund.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-33.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Library Authority shall maintain a Fund called the State Library Fund from which all its payments under this Act shall be met.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-33.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-33.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>There shall be credited to the State Library Fund the following sums, namely :-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-33.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the grants made by the State Government to the State Library Authority to perform the duties entrusted to it;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-33.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>grants which the Central Government may make;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-33.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>contributions and gifts made to the State Library Authority;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-33.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>funds and other amounts collected by the State Library Authority under the rules or bye-laws made under this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-34">
          <num>34.</num>
          <heading>Accounts.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-34.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An account shall be kept of the receipts and expenses of the State Library Authority and of each City Library Authority and District Library Authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-34.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The accounts shall be open to inspection, and shall be subject to audit, disallowance and surcharge and shall be dealt with in all other respects in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VI">
        <num>VI</num>
        <heading>State Central Library</heading>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading>Vesting of Bangalore Public Library in the State Library Authority.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-35.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>With effect from such date as the State Government may, by notification appoint (hereinafter referred to in this Chapter as the appointed day), the entire management and control of the Public Library, Bangalore, now vested in the Committee of Management of the Public Library, Bangalore, shall be vested in the State Library Authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-35.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As from the appointed day, the Committee of Management of the Public Library, Bangalore, a society registered under the Mysore Societies Registration Act, 1904, now deemed to be registered under the Karnataka Societies Registration Act, 1960, shall stand dissolved and all property, movable and immovable, and all rights, powers and privileges of the said society which immediately before the appointed day belonged to or vested in the said society shall vest in the State Library Authority and shall be applied for the purposes specified in this Act and such other purposes as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-35.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As from the appointed day, all debts and liabilities of the said society shall stand transferred to and vest in the State Library Authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-35.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every employee of the said society shall, as from the appointed day, become an employee of the State Government and shall hold his office under the State Government as a member of the Karnataka State Library Service on the same tenure, at the same remuneration, and upon the same terms and conditions, and with the same rights and privileges as to provident fund, gratuity and other matters, as he would have held the same, as an employee of the said society, and shall continue to do so unless and until his remuneration, terms and conditions are duly altered by the State Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-36">
          <num>36.</num>
          <heading>Karnataka State Central Library .-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-36.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As from the appointed day, the Public Library, Bangalore, shall be the Karnataka State Central Library.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-36.2.list0">
                <item id="section-36.2.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>The Karnataka State Central Library shall be maintained as a reservoir of books and other materials for the proper functioning of the State Library system.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-36.2.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-36.2.list0.b.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>In addition to a general library, the State Central Library shall consist of the following sections namely.-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-36.2.list0.b.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>a State Bureau of Copyright Collections;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-36.2.list0.b.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>a State Library for the Blind;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-36.2.list0.b.list0.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>a State Bureau of inter-library loans;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-36.2.list0.b.list0.iv">
                      <num>(iv)</num>
                      <p>a State Bibliographical Bureau;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-36.2.list0.b.list0.v">
                      <num>(v)</num>
                      <p>a State Bureau of Technical Service;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-36.2.list0.b.list0.vi">
                      <num>(vi)</num>
                      <p>such other sections as may be prescribed.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-37">
          <num>37.</num>
          <heading>Sections of State Central Library.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-37.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-37.1.list0">
                <item id="section-37.1.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>One copy of each book received under the Press and Registration of Books Act, 1867 (Central Act 25 of 1867) shall be kept in the State Central Library as a Bureau of Copyright.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-37.1.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>Copies of books in the Bureau of Copyright shall not be issued by way of loan of any kind but may be made available for reference in the library premises.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-37.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-37.2.list0">
                <item id="section-37.2.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>The production and storage of books, sound records of books and kindred materials for the blind and the issue of such books and materials for the use of the blind shall be dealt with in the section relating to the State Library for the Blind.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-37.2.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>The State Central Library may collaborate with other Libraries for the Blind in India and undertake such work as may be necessary for purposes of such collaboration.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-37.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-37.3.list0">
                <item id="section-37.3.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>The State Bureau of inter-library loan shall implement such schemes of inter-library loans among the public libraries, academic libraries, State-owned libraries, aided libraries and the outlier libraries in the State as may be prescribed.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-37.3.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>The State Central Library may with the approval of the State Government, collaborate in any scheme of inter-State library loans.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-37.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-37.4.list0">
                <item id="section-37.4.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>The State Bibliographical Bureau shall undertake such bibliographical work as may be prescribed and may for this purpose collaborate with Departments of Government and educational and other bodies in the State.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-37.4.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>The State Central Library may, with the approval of the State Government, collaborate with Bibliographical Bureaux or agencies in India and undertake such bibliographical work as may be necessary for purposes of such collaboration.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-37.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-37.5.list0">
                <item id="section-37.5.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>The State Bureau of Technical Service shall be maintained for centralised technical services, such as, acquisition, classification and cataloguing of books for public libraries, academic libraries, State owned libraries, aided libraries and outlier libraries, in accordance with such schemes as may be prescribed.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-37.5.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>The State Central Library may, with the approval of the State Government, collaborate with other similar Bureaux of Technical Service in India and undertake such technical work as may be necessary for purposes of such collaboration:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that no scheme under sub-section (3) or sub-section (5) shall be implemented in respect of any library other than a library owned or controlled by the State, except with the concurrence of the authority which owns or controls such library.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VII">
        <num>VII</num>
        <heading>Reports, Returns and Inspection</heading>
        <section id="section-38">
          <num>38.</num>
          <heading>Reports and returns.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-38.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every Local Library Authority and every person in charge of a public library shall submit such reports and returns and furnish such information to the Director of Public Libraries or any person authorised by him in this behalf as the said librarian or authorised person may, from time to time, require.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-39">
          <num>39.</num>
          <heading>Inspection of libraries.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-39.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Director of Public Libraries or any person authorised by him in this behalf may inspect any public library or any institution attached thereto for the purpose of satisfying himself that the provisions of this Act and the rules and bye-laws made thereunder are duly carried out.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-40">
          <num>40.</num>
          <heading>Annual Report.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-40.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Director of Public Libraries shall, in respect of each financial year, prepare an annual report of the progress made by the Local Library Authorities during the year along with such information and particulars as may be prescribed and submit such report to the State Government before such date as the State Government may by order specify.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-40.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Director of Public Libraries shall, in respect of each financial year prepare an annual report of the activities of the State Library Authority during the year along with such information and particulars as may be prescribed and submit such report to the State Government before such date as the State Government may by order specify.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VIII">
        <num>VIII</num>
        <heading>Miscellaneous</heading>
        <section id="section-41">
          <num>41.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-41.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, after previous publication, by notification, make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-41.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-41.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-41.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the method of election or nomination of members to the State Library Authority, the Local Library Authorities, the Branch Library Committees and the Village Service Library Committees;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the maintenance of a State Library Fund and the City and District Library Funds;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the administration, inspection and management of the State Central Library;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the maintenance of accounts by the State Library Authority and the Local Library Authorities and the publication of audited statement of accounts and the reports of auditors;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the grants-in-aid to aided libraries and the standards to be maintained by such libraries;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.2.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the maintenance of State Registers of Libraries, and of Librarians;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.2.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the constitution of committees by the State Library Authority and the Local Library Authorities;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.2.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>the restrictions and conditions subject to which the State Library Authority or a Local Library Authority may enter into contracts, or acquire, hold or dispose of property.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-41.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made under this Act shall, as soon as may be after it is made, be laid before each House of the State Legislature while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions and if before the expiry of the session in which it is so laid or the sessions immediately following, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-42">
          <num>42.</num>
          <heading>Power of State Library Authority and Local Library Authorities to make bye-laws.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-42.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Library Authority and every Local Library Authority may, subject to the provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder and with the previous sanction of the State Government, by notification, make bye-laws generally to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-42.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-42.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such bye-laws may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-42.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the admission of the public to the public libraries under the control of the State Library Authority or the Local Library Authority subject to such conditions as may be specified in such bye-laws:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-42.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that no fees shall be charged for such admission;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-42.2.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the guarantee or security to be furnished by persons desiring to use such libraries, against injury to, or misuse, destruction or loss of the property of such libraries;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-42.2.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which the property of such libraries may be used and the protection of such property from injury, misuse, destruction or loss;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-42.2.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the authority to be exercised by the officers and servants of the State Library Authority or the Local Library Authority for the purpose of exclusion or removal from any such library of any person who contravenes or does not comply with any provisions of this Act or any rule or bye-law made thereunder;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-42.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every bye-law made under this section shall be subject to the condition of previous publication for a period of not less than thirty days, and such publication shall be in the official Gazette and in such other manner as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-42.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may by notification modify or cancel any bye-law made by State Library Authority or a Local Library Authority under this section:</p>
              <p>Provided that before modifying or cancelling any bye-law, the State Government shall give the State Library Authority or the Local Library Authority concerned a reasonable opportunity to make its representations in the matter.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-43">
          <num>43.</num>
          <heading>Offences and penalties.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-43.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-43.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Whoever,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-43.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>in a public library or other institution maintained under this Act acts in any manner likely to cause annoyance or disturbance to any person using such library or institution, or behaves in a disorderly manner or uses violent or abusive language in any such library or institution; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-43.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>after due warning persists in remaining therein beyond the hours fixed for closing, shall be liable to be removed from such library or institution and shall also be punishable with fine which may extend to rupees ten and for a second or subsequent offence with fine which may extend to rupees fifty.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-44">
          <num>44.</num>
          <heading>Control of Local Library Authorities by Government.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-44.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If, at any time, it appears to the State Government that a Local Library Authority has failed to perform its functions or has exceeded or abused any of the powers conferred upon it by or under this Act, the State Government may communicate the particulars thereof to the Local Library Authority, and if the Local Library Authority omits to remedy such failure, excess or abuse or to give an explanation which in the opinion of the State Government is satisfactory within such time as the State Government may fix in this behalf, the State Government may supersede the Local Library Authority for such period as the State Government may direct.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-44.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-44.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>If a Local Library Authority is superseded,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-44.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>all the powers and duties of the Authority shall, during the period of supersession, be exercised and performed by such person or persons as the State Government may from time to time appoint in this behalf;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-44.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>all property vested in the Local Library Authority shall during the period of supersession, vest in the State Government; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-44.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>on the expiry of the period of supersession, the Local Library Authority shall be reconstituted in the manner provided in this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-45">
          <num>45.</num>
          <heading>Liability of members for loss, waste or misapplication.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-45.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every member of a Local Library Authority shall be personally liable for the loss, waste or misapplication of any money or other property of the Authority to which he has been a party, or which has been caused or facilitated by his misconduct or neglect of his duty as a member.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If after giving the member or members concerned a reasonable opportunity for showing cause to the contrary the Director of Public Libraries is satisfied that the loss, waste or misapplication of any money or other property of the Local Library Authority is a direct consequence of misconduct or neglect on his or their part, the Director of Public Libraries shall by order in writing direct such member or members to pay to the Local Library Authority before a specified date, the amount required to reimburse it for such loss, waste or misapplication.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the amount is not so paid, it shall be recoverable as an arrear of land revenue.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An appeal shall lie from the decision of the Director of Public Libraries to the Karnataka Revenue Appellate Tribunal within such period as may be prescribed, and the decision of the Karnataka Revenue Appellate Tribunal on such appeal shall be final.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-46">
          <num>46.</num>
          <heading>Members and employees of Library Authorities to be public servants.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-46.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every member of the State Library Authority or a Local Library Authority and every officer and servant employed under such authority shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-47">
          <num>47.</num>
          <heading>Savings of validity of acts and proceedings.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-47.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-47.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>No act done, or proceedings taken under this Act shall be questioned merely on the ground,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-47.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>of any vacancy or defect in the constitution of any Authority or any committee thereof; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-47.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>of any defect or irregularity in such act or proceedings not affecting the merits of the case.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-48">
          <num>48.</num>
          <heading>Provisions relating to suits, etc.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-48.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No suit or other legal proceeding shall be instituted against the State Library Authority or a Local Library Authority or any of its officers or any person acting under its direction until the expiration of two months next after notice in writing shall have been delivered or left at the office of the Authority or at the place of abode of such officer or person; such notice shall state the cause of action, the relief sought, the amount of compensation, if any, claimed, and the name and place of abode of the intending plaintiff.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-48.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the State Government, the Director of Public Libraries, the State Library Authority or a Local Library Authority, or any member, officer, servant or agent of such Authority acting under its direction, in respect of anything done or intended to have been done lawfully and in good faith under this Act or any rule, bye-law or order made thereunder.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-49">
          <num>49.</num>
          <heading>Power to remove difficulties.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-49.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the State Government may, by order, make such provisions as appear to it to be necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-50">
          <num>50.</num>
          <heading>Transfer of certain libraries.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-50.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-50.1.list0">
                <item id="section-50.1.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>With effect from such date as the State Government may by notification appoint (hereinafter referred to in this sub-section as the appointed day), the entire management and control of the Public Library, Mysore, now vested in the Committee of Management of the Public Library, Mysore, shall be vested in the Mysore City Library Authority.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-50.1.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>As from the appointed day, the Committee of Management of the Public Library, Mysore, a society registered under the Mysore Societies Registration Act, 1904, now deemed to be registered under the Karnataka Societies Registration Act, 1960, shall stand dissolved and all property, movable and immovable, and all rights, powers and privileges of the said society which immediately before the appointed day belonged to or vested in the said society shall vest in the Mysore City Library Authority and shall be applied for purposes specified in this Act and such other purposes as may be prescribed.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-50.1.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>As from the appointed day, all debts and liabilities of the said society shall stand transferred to and vest in the Mysore City Library Authority.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-50.1.list0.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>Every employee of the said society shall, as from the appointed day, become an employee of the State Government and shall hold his office under the State Government as a member of the Karnataka State Library Service on the same tenure, at the same remuneration and upon the same terms and conditions and with the same rights and privileges as to provident fund, gratuity and other matters, as he would have held the same as an employee of the said society, and shall continue to do so unless and until his remuneration, terms and conditions are duly altered by the State Government.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-50.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-50.2.list0">
                <item id="section-50.2.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>The State Government may by notification transfer the Mahatma Gandhi Public Library, Mercara, to the Coorg District Library Authority, with effect from such date as may be specified in such notification.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-50.2.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>With effect from the day on which such transfer takes place, all assets and liabilities appertaining to the said library shall stand transferred to and vest in the Coorg District Library Authority.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-50.2.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>With effect from the day on which such transfer takes place, every person employed by the Government in connection with the said public library shall hold his office under the State Government as a member of the Karnataka State Library Service on the same tenure, at the same remuneration and upon the same terms and conditions and with same rights and privileges as to provident fund, gratuity and other matters, as he would have held the same if the transfer had not taken place and shall continue to do so unless and until his remuneration, terms and conditions are duly altered by the State Government.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-50.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-50.3.list0">
                <item id="section-50.3.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in section 47, with effect from such date as the State Government may by notification appoint (hereinafter referred to in this sub-section as the specified day), the entire management and control of Karnad Sadashiva Rao District Central Library, Mangalore shall stand transferred to the Mangalore City Library Authority.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-50.3.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>As from the specified day, the assets and liabilities of the South Kanara District Library Authority appertaining to the said District Central Library shall vest in the Mangalore City Library Authority, and the South Kanara District Library Authority in such proportion and in such manner as the State Government may direct.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-50.3.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>Every employee of South Kanara District Library Authority who was employed by the said Authority wholly or mainly in connection with the said District Central Library shall, as from the specified day, become an employee of the State Government and shall hold his office under the State Government as a member of the Karnataka State Library Service on the same tenure, at the same remuneration, and upon the same terms and conditions and with the same rights and privileges as to provident fund, gratuity and other matters, as he would have held the same as an employee of the South Kanara District Library Authority, and shall continue to do so unless and until his remuneration, terms and conditions are duly altered by the State Government.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-51">
          <num>51.</num>
          <heading>Amendment of the Press and Registration of Books Act, 1867 in its application to the State of Karnataka.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-51.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-51.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Press and Registration of Books Act, 1867 (Central Act XXV of 1867) shall, in its application to the State of Karnataka1, be amended as follows:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-51.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>in the first paragraph of section 9, for clause (a), the following clause shall be substituted, namely:-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-51.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>"(a) in any case, within one calendar month after the day on which any such book shall first be delivered out of the press, three such copies, and";</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-51.paragraph-0.list3.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>in the last paragraph of section 9, for clause (i), the following clause shall be substituted, namely:-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-51.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>"(i) any second or subsequent edition of a book in which edition no additions or alterations either in the letter-press or in the maps, block prints or other engraving belonging to the book have been made, and three copies of the first or some preceding edition of which book have been delivered under this Act, or "</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-51.paragraph-0.list5.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>in section 11, for the first sentence, the following sentence shall be substituted, namely:-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>"Out of the three copies delivered pursuant to clause (a) of the first paragraph of section 9 of this Act, one copy shall be sent to the State Central Library, Bangalore, referred to in the Karnataka Public Libraries Act, 1965, and the remaining two copies shall be disposed of in such manner as the State Government may, from time to time determine."</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-52">
          <num>52.</num>
          <heading>Repeal and savings.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-52.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Madras Public Libraries Act, 1948 (Madras Act XXIV of 1948) and the Hyderabad Public Libraries Act, 1955 (Hyderabad Act III of 1955) are hereby repealed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-52.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-52.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding such repeal,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-52.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the members of the Local Library Authorities constituted under the Madras Public Libraries Act, 1948, and holding office immediately before the commencement of this Act shall be deemed to be the members of the Local Library Authorities constituted under this Act and shall exercise all powers and perform all duties conferred on such Authorities in the respective areas in which they are functioning at such commencement until their present term expires or until new authorities are constituted under this Act, whichever is later;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-52.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>anything done or any action taken (including any appointment or delegation made, fee or cess imposed, notification, order, instrument or direction issued, rule, regulation, form, or scheme framed) under the said Acts and in force at the commencement of this Act, shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the provisions of this Act and shall continue to be in force accordingly until they are superseded or modified by anything done or any action taken under this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
