<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1949/64/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1949/64"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Police Act, 1949"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1949/64/eng@1949-12-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1949/64/eng@1949-12-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1949-12-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1949/64/eng@1949-12-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1949/64/eng@1949-12-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-28" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Police Act, 1949</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[27th December, 1949]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No. 64 of 1949</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the constitution of a general police district embracing two or more Union Territories and for the establishment of a police force therefor.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the constitution of general police district embracing two or more Union Territories and for the establishment of a police force therefor;</p>
        <p>It is hereby enacted as follows:—</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Police Act, 1949.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to all the Union Territories.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force in a Union Territory on such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint in this behalf for such territory.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definition.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In this Act “general police-district” means the general police-district constituted under section 3.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of general police-district embracing two or more Union Territories.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Police Act, 1861 (V of 1861), the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute a general police-district embracing two or more Union Territories.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of one police-force for general police district.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The entire police establishment in a general police-district shall be one police force and shall consist of such number of officers and men and shall be constituted in such manner as the Central Government may, by order, direct.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Superintendence and administration of police.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The superintendence of the police throughout a general police-district shall vest in, and be exercised by, the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The administration of the said police-force shall vest in an officer, appointed in this behalf by the Central Government, who shall exercise in respect of that police- force such of the powers exercisable by an Inspector-General of Police under the Police Act, 1861 (5 of 1861), as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Application of the Police Act, 1861.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Save as otherwise expressly provided in this Act, the provisions of the Police Act, 1861 (5 of 1861), shall apply to the police-force constituted for the general police-district as if it were one police force constituted for a State, and members of the said police force shall have, in every part of any territory which is included in the general police distict the same powers, duties and privileges, and shall be subject to the same liabilities, as they would have had, or would have been subject to, as police-officers if they had formed a police-establishment under one State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Saving.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in this Act shall be deemed to affect the provisions contained in the Delhi Special Police Establishment Act, 1946 (25 of 1946).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
