<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2010/19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2010/19"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The National Green Tribunal Act, 2010"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2010/19/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2010/19/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2010/19/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2010/19/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-10-17" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The National Green Tribunal Act, 2010</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government may, by notification, in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"accident" means an accident involving a fortuitous or sudden or unintended occurrence while handling any hazardous substance or equipment, or plant, or vehicle resulting in continuous or intermittent or repeated exposure to death, of, or, injury to, any person or damage to any property or environment but does not include an accident by reason only of war or civil disturbance;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"Chairperson" means the Chairperson of the National Green Tribunal;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>"environment" includes water, air and land and the inter-relationship, which exists among and between water, air and land and human beings, other living creatures, plants, micro-organism and property;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>"Expert Member" means a member of the Tribunal who, is appointed as such, and holds qualifications specified in sub-section (2) of section 5, and, is not a Judicial Member;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>"handling", in relation to any hazardous substance, means the manufacture, processing, treatment, package, storage, transportation, use, collection, destruction, conversion, offering for sale, transfer or the like of such hazardous substance;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>"hazardous substance" means any substance or preparation which is defined as hazardous substance in the Environment (Protection) Act, 1986 (29 of 1986), and exceeding such quantity as specified or may be specified by the Central Government under the Public Liability Insurance Act, 1991 (6 of 1991);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>"injury" includes permanent, partial or total disablement or sickness resulting out of an accident;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>"Judicial Member" means a member of the Tribunal who is qualified to be appointed as such under sub-section (1) of section 5 and includes the Chairperson;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>"notification" means a notification published in the Official Gazette;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.1.list1.j.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>"person" includes-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.1.list1.j.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>an individual,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.1.list1.j.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>a Hindu undivided family,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.1.list1.j.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>a company,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.1.list1.j.list0.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>a firm,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.1.list1.j.list0.v">
                    <num>(v)</num>
                    <p>an association of persons or a body of individuals, whether incorporated or not,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.1.list1.j.list0.vi">
                    <num>(vi)</num>
                    <p>trustee of a trust,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.1.list1.j.list0.vii">
                    <num>(vii)</num>
                    <p>a local authority, and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.1.list1.j.list0.viii">
                    <num>(viii)</num>
                    <p>every artificial juridical person, not falling within any of the preceding sub-clauses;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>"prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>"Schedule" means Schedules I, II and III appended to this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.1.list1.m.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>"substantial question relating to environment" shall include an instance where,-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.1.list1.m.list1.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <blockList id="section-2.1.list1.m.list1.i.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>there is a direct violation of a specific statutory environmental obligation by a person by which,-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-2.1.list1.m.list1.i.list2.A">
                        <num>(A)</num>
                        <p>the community at large other than an individual or group of individuals is affected or likely to be affected by the environmental consequences; or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-2.1.list1.m.list1.i.list2.B">
                        <num>(B)</num>
                        <p>the gravity of damage to the environment or property is substantial; or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-2.1.list1.m.list1.i.list2.C">
                        <num>(C)</num>
                        <blockList id="section-2.1.list1.m.list1.i.list2.C.list0">
                          <listIntroduction>the damage to public health is broadly measurable;</listIntroduction>
                          <item id="section-2.1.list1.m.list1.i.list2.C.list0.ii">
                            <num>(ii)</num>
                            <p>the environmental consequences relate to a specific activity or a point source of pollution;</p>
                          </item>
                        </blockList>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>"Tribunal" means the National Green Tribunal established under section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>"workman" has the meaning assigned to it in the Workmen's Compensation Act, 1923 (8 of 1923).</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The words and expressions used in this Act but not defined herein and defined in the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1974 (6 of 1974), the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Cess Act, 1977 (36 of 1977), the Forest (Conservation) Act, 1980 (69 of 1980), the Air (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1981 (14 of 1981), the Environment (Protection) Act, 1986 (29 of 1986), the Public Liability Insurance Act, 1991 (6 of 1991) and the Biological Diversity Act, 2002 (18 of 2003) and other Acts relating to environment shall have the meaning, respectively, assigned to them in those Acts.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Establishment of Tribunal. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government shall, by notification, establish, with effect from such date as may be specified therein, a Tribunal to be known as the National Green Tribunal* to exercise the jurisdiction, powers and authority conferred on such Tribunal by or under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Composition of Tribunal. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Tribunal shall consist of,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>a full-time Chairperson;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>not less than ten but subject not maximum of twenty full-time Judicial Members as the Central Government may, from time to time, notify;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>not less than ten but subject to maximum of twenty full-time Expert Members, as the Central Government may, from time to time notify.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chairperson of the Tribunal may, if considered necessary, invite any one or more person having specialised knowledge and experience in a particular case before the Tribunal to assist the Tribunal in that case.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification, specify the ordinary place or places of sitting of the Tribunal, and the territorial jurisdiction falling under each such place of sitting.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government may, in consultation with the Chairperson of the Tribunal, make rules regulating generally the practices and procedure of the Tribunal including:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the rules as to the persons who shall be entitled to appear before the Tribunal;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.4.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the rules as to the procedure for hearing applications and appeals and other matters including the circuit procedure for hearing at a place other than the ordinary place of its sitting falling within the jurisdiction referred to in sub-section (3), pertaining to the applications and appeals;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.4.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the minimum number of Members who shall hear the applications and appeals in respect of any class or classes of applications and appeals:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-4.4.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that the number of Expert Members shall, in hearing an application or appeal, be equal to the number of judicial Members hearing such application or appeal;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.4.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>rules relating to transfer of cases by the Chairperson from one place of sitting (including the ordinary place of sitting) to other place of sitting.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Comments</p>
            <p>(Based on Notes on Clauses of the Bill)</p>
            <p>This section specifies the composition of the Tribunal. The Tribunal shall consist of a full-time Chairperson, such number of full-time Judicial Members and Expert Members as the Central Government may, from time to time, notify. Sub-section (2) provides that the Chairperson of the Tribunal may, if considered necessary, invite any one or more person having specialised knowledge and experience in a particular case before the Tribunal to assist the Tribunal in that case. Sub-section (3) provides that the Tribunal shall sit at such place or places as the Central Government may, by notification, specify. Sub-section (4) empowers the Central Government to make rules in consultation with the Chairperson of the Tribunal regulating generally the practices and procedure of the Tribunal including rules as to the persons who shall be entitled to appear before the Tribunal, the procedure for hearing applications and appeals and other matters pertaining to the applications and appeals, and the minimum number of members who shall hear the applications and appeals in respect of any class or classes of applications and appeals.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Qualifications for appointment of Chairperson, Judicial Member and Expert Member. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A person shall not be qualified for appointment as the Chairperson or Judicial Member of the Tribunal unless he is, or has been, a Judge of the Supreme Court of India or Chief Justice of a High Court:</p>
            <p>Provided that a person who is or has been a Judge of the High Court shall also be qualified to be appointed as a Judicial Member.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A person shall not be qualified for appointment as an Expert Member, unless he,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>has a degree in Master of Science (in physical sciences or life sciences) with a Doctorate degree or Master of Engineering or Master of Technology and has an experience of fifteen years in the relevant field including five years practical experience in the field of environment and forests (including pollution control, hazardous substance management, environment impact assessment, climate change management; biological diversity management and forest conservation) in a reputed national level institution or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>has administrative experience of fifteen years including experience of five years in dealing with environmental matters in the Central or a State Government or in a reputed National or State level institution.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chairperson, Judicial Member and Expert Member of the Tribunal shall not hold any other office during their tenure as such.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chairperson and other Judicial and Expert Members shall not, for a period of two year from the date on which they cease to hold office, accept any employment in, or connected with the management or administration of, any person who has been a party to a proceeding before the Tribunal under this Act:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing contained in this section shall apply to any employment under the Central Government or a State Government or local authority or in any statutory authority or any corporation established by or under any Central, State or Provincial Act or a Government company as defined in section 617 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Appointment of Chairperson, Judicial Member and Expert Member. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of section 5, the Chairperson, Judicial Members and Expert Members of the Tribunal shall be appointed by the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chairperson shall be appointed by the Central Government in consultation with the Chief Justice of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Judicial Members and Expert Members of the Tribunal shall be appointed on the recommendations of such Selection Committee and in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Term of office and other conditions of service of Chairperson, Judicial Member and Expert Member. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Chairperson, Judicial Member and Expert Member of the Tribunal shall hold office as such for a term of five years from the date on which they enter upon their office, but shall not be eligible for re-appointment:</p>
            <p>Provided that in case a person, who is or has been a Judge of the Supreme Court, has been appointed as Chairperson or Judicial Member of the Tribunal, he shall not hold office after he has attained the age of seventy years:</p>
            <p>Provided further that in case a person, who is or has been the Chief Justice of a High Court, has been appointed as Chairperson or Judicial Member of the Tribunal, he shall not hold office after he has attained the age of sixty-seven years:</p>
            <p>Provided also that in case a person, who is or has been a Judge of a High Court, has been appointed as Judicial Member of the Tribunal, he shall not hold office after he has attained the age of sixty-seven years:</p>
            <p>Provided also that no Expert Member shall hold office after he has attained the age of sixty-five years.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Resignation. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Chairperson, Judicial Member and Expert Member of the Tribunal may, by notice in writing under their hand addressed to the Central Government, resign their office.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Salaries, allowances and other terms and conditions of service. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The salaries and allowances payable to, and the other terms and conditions of service (including pension, gratuity and other retirement benefits) of, the Chairperson, Judicial Member and Expert Member of the Tribunal shall be such as may be prescribed:</p>
            <p>Provided that neither the salary and allowances nor the other terms and conditions of service of the Chairperson, Judicial Member and Expert Member shall be varied to their disadvantage after their appointment.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Removal and suspension of Chairperson, Judicial Member and Expert Member. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government may, in consultation with the Chief Justice of India, remove from office of the Chairperson or Judicial Member of the Tribunal, who,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>has been adjudged an insolvent; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>has been convicted of an offence which, in the opinion of the Central Government, involves moral turpitude; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>has become physically or mentally incapable; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>has acquired such financial or other interest as is likely to affect prejudicially his functions; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>has so abused his position as to render his continuance in office prejudicial to the public interest.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chairperson or Judicial Member shall not be removed from his office except by an order made by the Central Government after an inquiry made by a Judge of the Supreme Court in which such Chairperson or Judicial Member has been informed of the charges against him and given a reasonable opportunity of being heard in respect of those charges.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may suspend from office the Chairperson or Judicial Member in respect of whom a reference of conducting an inquiry has been made to the Judge of the Supreme Court under sub-section (2), until the Central Government passes an order on receipt of the report of inquiry made by the Judge of the Supreme Court on such reference.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by rules, regulate the procedure for inquiry referred to in sub-section (2).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Expert Member may be removed from his office by an order of the Central Government on the grounds specified in sub-section (1) and in accordance with the procedure as may be notified by the Central Government:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Expert Member shall not be removed unless he has been given an opportunity of being heard in the matter.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>To act as Chairperson of Tribunal or to discharge his functions in certain circumstances. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In the event of the occurrence of any vacancy in the office of the Chairperson of the Tribunal, by reason of his death, resignation or otherwise, such Judicial Member of the Tribunal as the Central Government may, by notification, authorised in this behalf, shall act as the Chairperson until the date on which a new Chairperson is appointed in accordance with the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Staff of Tribunal. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government shall determine the nature and categories of the officers and other employees required to assist the Tribunal in the discharge of its functions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The recruitment of the officers and other employees of the Tribunal shall be made by the Chairperson in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The officers and other employees of the Tribunal shall discharge their functions under the general superintendence of the Chairperson.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The salaries and allowances and conditions of service of the officers and other employees of the Tribunal shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Financial and administrative powers of Chairperson. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Chairperson of the Tribunal shall exercise such financial and administrative powers as may be vested in him under the rules made by the Central Government: Provided that the Chairperson may delegate such of his financial and administrative powers, as he may think fit, to any Judicial Member or Expert Member or officer of the Tribunal subject to the condition that the Member or such officer, while exercising such delegated power, continues to act under the direction, control and supervision of the Chairperson.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Tribunal to settle disputes. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Tribunal shall have the jurisdiction over all civil cases where a substantial question relating to environment (including enforcement of any legal right relating to environment), is involved and such question arises out of the implementation of the enactments specified in Schedule I.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Tribunal shall hear the disputes arising from the questions referred to in sub-section (1) and settle such disputes and pass order thereon.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No application for adjudication of dispute under this section shall be entertained by the Tribunal unless it is made within a period of six months from the date on which the cause of action for such dispute first arose: Provided that the Tribunal may, if it is satisfied that the applicant was prevented by sufficient cause from filing the application within the said period, allow it to be filed within a further period not exceeding sixty days.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Relief, compensation and restitution. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-15.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Tribunal may, by an order, provide,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>relief and compensation to the victims of pollution and other environmental damage arising under the enactments specified in the Schedule I (including accident occurring while handling any hazardous substance);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>for restitution of property damaged;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>for restitution of the environment for such area or areas, as the Tribunal may think fit.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The relief and compensation and restitution of property and environment referred to in clauses (a), (b) and (c) of sub-section (1) shall be in addition to the relief paid or payable under the Public Liability Insurance Act, 1991 (6 of 1991).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No application for grant of any compensation or relief or restitution of property or environment under this section shall be entertained by the Tribunal unless it is made within a period of five years from the date on which the cause for such compensation or relief first arose:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Tribunal may, if it is satisfied that the applicant was prevented by sufficient cause from filing the application within the said period, allow it to be filed within a further period not exceeding sixty days.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Tribunal may, having regard to the damage to public health, property and environment, divide the compensation or relief payable under separate heads specified in Schedule II so as to provide compensation or relief to the claimants and for restitution of the damaged property or environment, as it may think fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every claimant of the compensation or relief under this Act shall intimate to the Tribunal about the application filed to, or, as the case may be, compensation or relief received from, any other court or authority.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Tribunal to have appellate jurisdiction. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any person aggrieved by,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>an order or decision, made, on or after the commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, by the appellate authority under section 28 of the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1974 (6 of 1974);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>an order passed, on or after the commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, by the State Government under section 29 of the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1974 (6 of 1974);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>directions issued, on or after the commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, by a Board, under section 33A of the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1974 (6 of 1974);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>an order or decision made, on or after the commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, by the appellate authority under section 13 of the Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Cess Act, 1977 (36 of 1977);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>an order or decision made, on or after the commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, by the State Government or other authority under section 2 of the Forest (Conservation) Act, 1980 (69 of 1980);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>an order or decision, made, on or after the commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, by the Appellate Authority under section 31 of the Air (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1981 (14 of 1981);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>any direction issued, on or after the commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, under section 5 of the Environment (Protection) Act, 1986 (29 of 1986);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>an order made, on or after the commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, granting environmental clearance in the area in which any industries, operations or processes or class of industries, operations and processes shall not be carried out or shall be carried out subject to certain safeguards under the Environment (Protection) Act, 1986 (29 of 1986);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>an order made, on or after the commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, refusing to grant environmental clearance for carrying out any activity or operation or process under the Environment (Protection) Act, 1986 (29 of 1986);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>any determination of benefit sharing or order made, on or after the commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, by the National Biodiversity Authority or a State Biodiversity Board under the provisions of the Biological Diversity Act, 2002 (18 of 2003), may, within a period of thirty days from the date on which the order or decision or direction or determination is communicated to him, prefer an appeal to the Tribunal:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that the Tribunal may, if it is satisfied that the appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from filing the appeal within the said period, allow it to be filed under this section within a further period not exceeding sixty days.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Liability to pay relief or compensation in certain cases. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where death of, or injury to, any person (other than a workman) or damage to any property or environment has resulted from an accident or the adverse impact of an activity or operation or process, under any enactment specified in Schedule I, the person responsible shall be liable to pay such relief or compensation for such death, injury or damage, under all or any of the heads specified in Schedule II, as may be determined by the Tribunal.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the death, injury or damage caused by an accident or the adverse impact of an activity or operation or process under any enactment specified in Schedule I cannot be attributed to any single activity or operation or process but is the combined or resultant effect of several such activities, operations and processes, the Tribunal may, apportion the liability for relief compensation amongst those responsible for such activities, operations and processes on an equitable basis.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Tribunal shall, in case of an accident, apply the principle of no fault.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Application or appeal to Tribunal. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Each application under sections 14 and 15 or an appeal under section 16 shall, be made to the Tribunal in such form, contain such particulars, and, be accompanied by such documents and such fees as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-18.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Without prejudice to the provisions contained in section 16, an application for grant of relief or compensation or settlement of dispute may be made to the Tribunal by-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the person, who has sustained the injury; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the owner of the property to which the damage has been caused; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>where death has resulted from the environmental damage, by all or any of the legal representatives of the deceased; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>any agent duly authorised by such person or owner of such property or all or any of the legal representatives of the deceased, as the case may be; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>any person aggreived, including any representative body or organisation; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the Central Government or a State Government or a Union territory Administration or the Central Pollution Control Board or a State Pollution Control Board or a Pollution Control Committee or a local authority, or any environmental authority constituted or established under the Environment (Protection) Act, 1986 (29 of 1986) or any other law for the time being in force:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that where all the legal representatives of the deceased have not joined in any such application for compensation or relief or settlement of dispute, the application shall be made on behalf of, or, for the benefit of all the legal representatives of the deceased and the legal representatives who have not so joined shall be impleaded as respondents to the application:</p>
            <p>Provided further that the person, the owner, the legal representative, agent, representative body or organisation shall not be entitled to make an application for grant of relief or compensation or settlement of dispute if such person, the owner, the legal representative, agent, representative body or organisation have preferred an appeal under section 16.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The application, or as the case may be, the appeal filed before the Tribunal under this Act shall be dealt with by it as expeditiously as possible and endeavour shall be made by it to dispose of the application, or, as the case may be, the appeal, finally within six months from the date of filing of the application, or as the case may be, the appeal, after providing the parties concerned an opportunity to be heard.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Procedure and powers of Tribunal. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-19.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Tribunal shall not be bound by the procedure laid down by the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) but shall be guided by the principles of natural justice.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Tribunal shall have power to regulate its own procedure.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Tribunal shall also not be bound by the rules of evidence contained in the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-19.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Tribunal shall have, for the purposes of discharging its functions under this Act, the same powers as are vested in a civil court under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), while trying a suit, in respect of the following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-19.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person and examining him on oath;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.4.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>requiring the discovery and production of documents;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.4.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>receiving evidence on affidavits;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.4.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>subject to the provisions of sections 123 and 124 of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872), requisitioning any public record or document or copy of such record or document from any office;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.4.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses or documents;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.4.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>reviewing its decision;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.4.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>dismissing an application for default or deciding its ex parte;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.4.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>setting aside any order of dismissal of any application for default or any order passed by it ex parte;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.4.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>pass an interim order (including granting an injunction or stay) after providing the parties concerned an opportunity to be heard, on any application made or appeal filed under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.4.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>pass an order requiring any person to cease and desist from committing or causing any violation of any enactment specified in Schedule I;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.4.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>any other matter which may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All proceedings before the Tribunal shall be deemed to be the judicial proceedings within the meaning of sections 193, 219 and 228 for the purposes of section 196 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860) and the Tribunal shall be deemed to be a civil court for the purposes of section 195 and Chapter XXVI of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Tribunal to apply certain principles. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Tribunal shall, while passing any order or decision or award, apply the principles of sustainable development, the prescautionary principle and the polluter pays principle.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Decision to be taken by majority. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The decision of the Tribunal by majority of Members shall be binding:</p>
            <p>Provided that if there is a difference of opinion among the Members hearing an application or appeal, and the opinion is equally divided, the Chairperson shall hear (if he has not heard earlier such application or appeal) such application or appeal and decide:</p>
            <p>Provided further that where the Chairperson himself has heard such application or appeal along with other Members of the Tribunal, and if there is a difference of opinion among the Members in such cases and the opinion in equally devided, he shall refer the matter to other Members of the Tribunal who shall hear such application or appeal and decide.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Appeal to Supreme Court. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any person aggrieved by any award, decision or order of the tribunal, may, file an appeal to the Supreme Court, within ninety days from the date of communication of the award, decision or order of Tribunal, to him, on any one or more of the grounds specified in section 100 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908):</p>
            <p>Provided that the Supreme Court may, entertain any appeal after the expiry of ninety days, if it is satisfied that the appellant was prevented by sufficience cause from preferring the appeal.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Cost. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-23.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>While disposing of an application or an appeal under this Act, the Tribunal shall have power to make such order as to costs, as it may consider necessary.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the Tribunal holds that a claim is not maintainable, or is false or vexatious, and such claim is disallowed, in whole or part, the Tribunal may, if it so thinks fit, after recording its reasons for holding such claim to be false or vexatious, make an order to award costs, including lost benefits due to any interim injunction.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Deposit of amount payable for damage to environment. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-24.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any amount by way of compensation or relief is ordered to be paid under any award or order made by the Tribunal on the ground of any damage to environment, that amount shall be remitted to the authority specified under sub-section (3) of section 7A of the Public Liability Insurance Act, 1991 (6 of 1991) for being credited to the Environmental Relief Fund established under that section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The amount of compensation or relief credited to the Environmental Relief Fund under sub-section (1), may, notwithstanding anything contained in the Public Liability Insurance Act, 1991 (6 of 1991), be utilised by such persons or authority, in such manner and for such purposes relating to environment, as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Execution of award or order or decision of Tribunal. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-25.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An award or order or decision of the Tribunal under this Act shall be executable by the Tribunal as a decree of a civil court, and for this purpose, the Tribunal shall have all the powers of a civil court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), the Tribunal may transmit any order or award made by it to a civil court having local jurisdiction and such civil court shall execute the order or award as if it were a decree made by that court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the person responsible, for death of, or injury to any person or damage to any property and environment, against whom the award or order is made by the Tribunal, fails to make the payment or deposit the amount as directed by the Tribunal within the period so specified in the award or order, such amount, without prejudice to the filing of complaint for prosecution for an offence under this Act or any other law for the time being in force, shall be recoverable from the aforesaid person as arrears of land revenue or of public demand.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for failure to comply with orders of Tribunal. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-26.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever, fails to comply with any order or award or decision of the Tribunal under this Act, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years, or with fine which may extend to ten crore rupees, or with both and in case the failure or contravention continues, with additional fine which may extend to twenty-five thousand rupees for every day during which such failure or contravention continues after conviction for the first such failure or contravention:</p>
            <p>Provided that in case a company fails to comply with any order or award or a decision of the Tribunal under this Act, such company shall be punishable with fine which may extend to twenty-five crore rupees, and in case the failure or contravention continues, with additional fine which may extend to one lakh rupees for every day during which such failure or contravention continues after conviction for the first such failure or contravention.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), every offence under this Act shall be deemed to be non-cognizable within the meaning of the said Code.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Offences by companies. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-27.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any offence under this Act has been committed by a company, every person who, at the time the offence was committed, was directly in charge of, and was responsible to the company for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to any punishment provided in this Act, if he proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence under this Act has been committed by the company and it is proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.</p>
            <blockList id="section-27.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation. -For the purposes of this section,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-27.2.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"company" means any body corporate and includes a firm or other association of individuals; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-27.2.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"director" in relation to a firm means a partner in the firm.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28">
        <num>28.</num>
        <heading>Offences by Government Department. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-28.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any Department of the Government fails to comply with any order or award or decision of the Tribunal under this Act, the Head of the Department shall be deemed to be guilty of such failure and shall be liable to be proceeded against for having committed an offence under this Act and punished accordingly:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing contained in this section shall render such Head of the Department liable to any punishment if he proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or that he exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-28.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence under this Act has been committed by a Department of the Government and it is proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of any officer, other than the Head of the Department, such officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29">
        <num>29.</num>
        <heading>Bar of jurisdiction. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-29.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>With effect from the date of establishment of the Tribunal under this Act, no civil court shall have jurisdiction to entertain any appeal in respect of any matter, which the Tribunal is empowered to determine under its appellate jurisdiction.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No civil court shall have jurisdiction to settle dispute or entertain any question relating to any claim for granting any relief or compensation or restitution of property damaged or environment damaged which may be adjudicated upon by the Tribunal, and no injunction in respect of any action taken or to be taken by or before the Tribunal in respect of the settlement of such dispute or any such claim for granting any relief or compensation or restitution of property damaged or environment shall be granted by the civil court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-30">
        <num>30.</num>
        <heading>Cognizance of offences. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-30.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-30.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>No court shall take cognizance of any offence under this Act except on a complaint made by,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-30.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the Central Government or any authority or officer authorised in this behalf by that Government; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-30.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any person who has given notice of not less than sixty days in such manner as may be prescribed, of the alleged offence and of his intention to make a complaint, to the Central Government or the authority or officer authorised as aforesaid.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-30.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No court inferior to that of a Metropolitan Magistrate or, a Judicial Magistrate of the first class shall try any offence punishable under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-31">
        <num>31.</num>
        <heading>Members and staff of Tribunal to be public servants. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-31.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Chairperson, the Judicial and Expert Members, officers and other employees of the Tribunal shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-32">
        <num>32.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-32.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the employees of the Central Government or a State Government or any statutory authority, for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any rule or order made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-32.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Chairperson or, Judicial Member or Expert Member of the Tribunal or any other person authorised by the Chairperson or Judicial Member or the Expert Member for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any rule or order made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-33">
        <num>33.</num>
        <heading>Act to have overriding effect. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-33.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of this Act, shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent contained in any other law for the time being in force or in any instrument having effect by virtue of any law other than this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-34">
        <num>34.</num>
        <heading>Power to amend Schedule I. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-34.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification, amend the Schedule I by including therein any other Act, enacted by Parliament having regard to the objective of environmental protection and conservation of natural resources, or omitting therefrom any Act already specified therein and on the date of publication of such notification, such Act shall be deemed to be included in or, as the case may be, omitted from the Schedule I.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-34.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A copy of every notification proposed to be issued under sub-section (1), shall be laid in draft before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in disapproving the issue of the notification or both Houses agree in making any modification in the notification, the notification shall not be issued or, as the case may be, shall be issued only in such modified form as may be agreed upon by both the Houses.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-35">
        <num>35.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-35.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-35.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-35.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-35.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>rules as to the persons who shall be entitled to appear before the Tribunal under clause (a) of sub-section (4) of section 4;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-35.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the procedure for hearing applications and appeals and other matters pertaining to the applications and appeals under clause (b) of sub-section (4) of section 4;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-35.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the minimum number of members who shall hear the applications and appeals in respect of any class or classes of applications and appeals under clause (c) of sub-section (4) of section 4;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-35.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the transfer of cases by the Chairperson from one place of sitting (including the ordinary place of sitting) to other place of sitting;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-35.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>such selection committee and the manner of appointment of the Judicial Member and Expert Member of the Tribunal under sub-section (3) of section 6;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-35.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the salaries and allowances payable to, and other terms and conditions of service (including pension, gratuity and other retirement benefits) of, the Chairperson, Judicial Member and Expert Member of the Tribunal under section 9;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-35.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the procedure for inquiry of the charges against the Chairperson or Judicial Member of the Tribunal under sub-section (4) of section 10;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-35.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the recruitment of officers and other employees of the Tribunal under sub-section (2) section 12; and the salaries and allowances and other conditions of service of the officers and other employees of the Tribunal under sub-section (4) of that section;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-35.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the financial and administrative powers to be exercised by the Chairperson of the Tribunal under section 13;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-35.2.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>the form of application or appeal, the particulars which it shall contain and the documents to be accompanied by and the fees payable under sub-section (1) of section 18;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-35.2.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>any such matter in respect of which the Tribunal shall have powers of a civil court under clause (k) of sub-section (4) of section 19;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-35.2.list1.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>the manner and the purposes for which the amount of compensation or relief credited to the Environment Relief Fund shall be utilised under sub-section (2) of section 24;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-35.2.list1.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>the manner of giving notice to make a complaint under clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 30;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-35.2.list1.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>any other matter which is required to be, or may be, specified by rules or in respect of which provision is to be made by rules.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-35.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this Act by the Central Government shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-36">
        <num>36.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of certain enactments. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-36.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The enactments specified in the Schedule III to this Act shall be amended in the manner specified therein and such amendments shall take effect on the date of establishment of the Tribunal.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-37">
        <num>37.</num>
        <heading>Power to remove difficulties.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-37.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government, may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act as may appear to it to be necessary for removing the difficulty: Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a period of two years from the commencement of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-37.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every order made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-38">
        <num>38.</num>
        <heading>Repeal and savings. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-38.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The National Environment Tribunal Act, 1995 (27 of 1995) and the National Environment Appellate Authority Act, 1997 (22 of 1997) are hereby repealed (hereinafter referred to as the repealed Act).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-38.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken under the said Acts shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-38.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The National Environment Appellate Authority established under sub-section (1) of section 3 of the National Environment Appellate Authority Act, 1997 (22 of 1997), shall, on the establishment of the National Green Tribunal under the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, stand dissolved.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-38.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On the dissolution of the National Environment Appellate Authority established under sub-section (1) of section 3 of the National Environment Appellate Authority Act, 1997 (22 of 1997), the persons appointed as the Chairperson, Vice-chairperson and every other person appointed as Member of the said National Environment Appellate Authority and holding office as such immediately before the establishment of the National Green Tribunal under the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, shall vacate their respective offices and no such Chairperson, Vice-chairperson and every other person appointed as Member shall be entitled to claim any compensation for the premature termination of the term of his office or of any contract of service.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-38.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All cases pending before the National Environment Appellate Authority established under sub-section (1) of section 3 of the National Environment Appellate Authority Act, 1997 (22 of 1997) on or before the establishment of the National Green Tribunal under the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, shall, on such establishment, stand transferred to the said National Green Tribunal and the National Green Tribunal shall dispose of such cases as if they were cases filed under that Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-38.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The officers or other employees who have been, immediately before the dissolution of the National Environment Appellate Authority appointed on deputation basis to the National Environment Appellate Authority, shall, on such dissolution, stand reverted to their parent cadre, Ministry or Department, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-38.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On the dissolution of the National Environment Appellate Authority, the officers and other employees appointed on contract basis under the National Environment Appellate Authority and holding office as such immediately before such dissolution, shall vacate their respective offices and such officers and other employees shall be entitled to claim compensation for three months' pay and allowances or pay and allowances for the remaining period of service, whichever is less, for the premature termination of term of their office under their contract of service.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-38.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The mention of the particular matters referred to in sub-sections (2) to (7) shall not be held to prejudice or affect the general application of section 6 of the General Clauses Act, 1897 (10 of 1897) with regard to the effect of repeal.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-schedulei">
      <doc name="schedulei">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2010/19/schedulei"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2010/19"/>
              <FRBRalias value="Schedule I"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2010/19/eng@1980-01-01/schedulei"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2010/19/eng@1980-01-01"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2010/19/eng@1980-01-01/schedulei"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2010/19/eng@1980-01-01"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-10-17" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="schedulei">
            <heading>[See sections 14(1), 15(1), 17(1)(a), 17(2), 19(4)(j) and 34(1)]</heading>
            <subsection id="schedulei.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1974;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Water (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Cess Act, 1977;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Forest (Conservation) Act, 1980;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.4">
              <num>(4)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Air (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1981;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.5">
              <num>(5)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Environment (Protection) Act, 1986;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.6">
              <num>(6)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Public Liability Insurance Act, 1991;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.7">
              <num>(7)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Biological Diversity Act, 2002.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-scheduleii">
      <doc name="scheduleii">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2010/19/scheduleii"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2010/19"/>
              <FRBRalias value="Schedule II"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2010/19/eng@1980-01-01/scheduleii"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2010/19/eng@1980-01-01"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2010/19/eng@1980-01-01/scheduleii"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2010/19/eng@1980-01-01"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-10-17" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduleii">
            <heading>[See sections 15(4) and 17(1)]</heading>
            <paragraph id="scheduleii.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <blockList id="scheduleii.paragraph-0.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>HEADS UNDER WHICH COMPENSATION OR RELIEF FOR DAMAGE MAY BE CLAIMED</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="scheduleii.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>Death;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="scheduleii.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>Permanent, temporary, total or partial disability or other injury or sickness;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="scheduleii.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <p>Loss of wages due to total or partial disability or permanent or temporary disability;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="scheduleii.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                    <num>(d)</num>
                    <p>Medical expenses incurred for treatment of injuries or sickness;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="scheduleii.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                    <num>(e)</num>
                    <p>Damages to private property;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="scheduleii.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                    <num>(f)</num>
                    <p>Expenses incurred by the Government or any local authority in providing relief, aid and rehabilitation to the affected persons;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="scheduleii.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                    <num>(g)</num>
                    <p>Expenses incurred by the Government for any administrative or legal action or to cope with any harm or damage, including compensation for environmental degradation and restoration of the quality of environment;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="scheduleii.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                    <num>(h)</num>
                    <p>Loss to the Government or local authority arising out of, or connected with, the activity causing any damage;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="scheduleii.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>Claims on account of any harm, damage or destruction to the fauna including milch and draught animals and aquatic fauna;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="scheduleii.paragraph-0.list1.j">
                    <num>(j)</num>
                    <p>Claims on account of any harm, damage or destruction to flora including aquatic flora, crops, vegetables, trees and orchards;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="scheduleii.paragraph-0.list1.k">
                    <num>(k)</num>
                    <p>Claims including cost of restoration on account of any harm or damage to environment including pollution of soil, air, water, land and eco-systems;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="scheduleii.paragraph-0.list1.l">
                    <num>(l)</num>
                    <p>Loss and destruction of any property other than private property;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="scheduleii.paragraph-0.list1.m">
                    <num>(m)</num>
                    <p>Loss of business or employment or both;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="scheduleii.paragraph-0.list1.n">
                    <num>(n)</num>
                    <p>Any other claim arising out of, or connected with, any activity of handling of hazardous substance.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-scheduleiii">
      <doc name="scheduleiii">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2010/19/scheduleiii"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2010/19"/>
              <FRBRalias value="Schedule III"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2010/19/eng@1980-01-01/scheduleiii"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2010/19/eng@1980-01-01"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2010/19/eng@1980-01-01/scheduleiii"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2010/19/eng@1980-01-01"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-10-17" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduleiii">
            <heading>[See section 36]</heading>
            <paragraph id="scheduleiii.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>AMENDMENT TO CERTAIN ENACTMENTS</p>
                <p>(Part I) - AMENDMENT TO THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL OF POLLUTION) ACT, 1974 (6 of 1974)</p>
                <p>Insertion of new section 33B.- After section 33A, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-</p>
                <blockList id="scheduleiii.paragraph-0.list4">
                  <listIntroduction>"33B. Appeal to National Green Tribunal.- Any person aggrieved by,-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="scheduleiii.paragraph-0.list4.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>an order or decision of the appellate authority under section 28, made on or after the commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="scheduleiii.paragraph-0.list4.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>an order passed by the State Government under section 29, on or after the commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="scheduleiii.paragraph-0.list4.c">
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <p>directions issued under section 33A by a Board, on or after the commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010,</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <p>may file an appeal to the National Green Tribunal established under section 3 of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, in accordance with the provisions of that Act.".</p>
                <p>(Part II) - AMENDMENTS TO THE WATER (PREVENTION AND CONTROL OF POLLUTION) CESS ACT, 1977 (36 of 1977)</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <subsection id="scheduleiii.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Amendment of section 13.- In section 13 in sub-section (4), for the words "shall be final", the words, figures and letters "shall, if no appeal has been filed under section 13A, be final" shall be substituted.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleiii.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Insertion of new section 13A.- After section 13, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-</p>
                <p>" 13A. Appeal to National Green Tribunal.- Any person aggrieved, by an order or decision of the appellate authority made under section 13, on or after the commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, may file an appeal to the National Green Tribunal established under section 3 of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, in accordance with the provisions of that Act.".</p>
                <p>(Part III) - AMENDMENT TO THE FOREST (CONSERVATION) ACT, 1980 (69 of 1980)</p>
                <p>Insertion of new section 2A. -After section 2, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-</p>
                <p>"2A. Appeal to National Green Tribunal .-Any person aggrieved, by an order or decision of the State Government or other authority made under section 2, on or after the commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, may file an appeal to the National Green Tribunal established under section 3 of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, in accordance with the provisions of that Act.".</p>
                <p>(Part IV) - AMENDMENT TO THE AIR (PREVENTION AND CONTROL OF POLLUTION) ACT, 1981 (14 of 1981)</p>
                <p>Insertion of new section 31B.- After section 31A, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-</p>
                <p>"31B. Appeal to National Green Tribunal .-Any person aggrieved by an order or decision of the Appellate Authority under section 31, made on or after the commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, may file an appeal to the National Green Tribunal established under section 3 of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, in accordance with the provisions of that Act.".</p>
                <p>(Part V) - AMENDMENT TO THE ENVIRONMENT (PROTECTION) ACT, 1986 (29 of 1986)</p>
                <p>Insertion of new section 5A. -After section 5, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-</p>
                <p>"5A. Appeal to National Green Tribunal .-Any person aggrieved by any directions issued under section 5, on or after the commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, may file an appeal to the National Green Tribunal established under section 3 of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, in accordance with the provisions of that Act.".</p>
                <p>(PART VI) - AMENDMENTS TO THE BIOLOGICAL DIVERSITY ACT, 2002(18 OF 2003)</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleiii.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Amendment of section 52. -In section 52, after the proviso, the following provisos shall be inserted, namely:-</p>
                <p>"Provided further that nothing contained in this section shall apply on and from the commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010:</p>
                <p>Provided also that any appeal pending before the High Court, before the commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, shall continue to be heard and disposed of by the High Court as if the National Green Tribunal had not been established under section 3 of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010.".</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleiii.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Insertion of new section 52A. -After section 52, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-</p>
                <p>" 52A. Appeal to National Green Tribunal .-Any person aggrieved by any determination of benefit sharing or order of the National Biodiversity Authority or a State Biodiversity Board under this Act, on or after the commencement of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, may file an appeal to the National Green Tribunal established under section 3 of the National Green Tribunal Act, 2010, in accordance with the provisions of that Act.".</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
