<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1986/02/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1986/02"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Karnataka Agricultural Credit Pass Book Act, 1984"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1986/02/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1986/02/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1986/02/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1986/02/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-16" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Karnataka Agricultural Credit Pass Book Act, 1984</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No. 2 of 1986</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the issue of Agricultural Credit Pass Books to enable agriculturists to have credit facilities and for matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the issue of Agricultural Credit Pass Books to enable agriculturist to have credit facilities;</p>
      <p>BE it enacted by the Karnataka State Legislature in the Thirty-fifth Year of the Republic of India, as follows :-</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <heading>Preliminary</heading>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title, commencement, etc., -</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the Karnataka Agricultural Credit Pass Book Act, 1984.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on such date as the State Government may, by notification, appoint and different dates may be appointed for different areas.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Section 129A of the Karnataka Land Revenue Act, 1964 (Karnataka Act 12 of 1964) shall cease to be in force in any area during the period this Act is in force in such area and shall stand revived on the expiry of the said period.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>"agriculture" includes making land fit for cultivation, cultivation of land, improvement of land including development of sources of irrigation, raising and harvesting of crops and such other prescribed activities as are generally carried on by agriculturists;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>"agriculturist" means a person who is engaged in agriculture;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>"bank" means a banking company as defined in clause (c) of section 5 of the Banking Regulation Act, 1949 (Central Act 10 of 1949) and includes,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>***</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>the State Bank of India constituted under the State Bank of India Act, 1955 (Central Act 23 of 1955);</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>a subsidiary bank as defined in the State Bank of India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, 1959 (Central Act 38 of 1959);</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0.iv">
                      <num>(iv)</num>
                      <p>National Bank for Agricultural and Rural Development constituted under the National Bank for Agricultural and Rural Development Act, 1981 (Central Act 61 of 1981);</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0.v">
                      <num>(v)</num>
                      <p>a corresponding new bank constituted under the Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings) Act, 1970 (Central Act 5 of 1970);</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0.vi">
                      <num>(vi)</num>
                      <p>a corresponding new bank constituted under the Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings) Act, 1980 (Central Act 40 of 1980);</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0.vii">
                      <num>(vii)</num>
                      <p>Regional Rural Bank constituted under the Regional Rural Banks Act, 1976 (Central Act 1 of 1976);</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0.viii">
                      <num>(viii)</num>
                      <p>the Karnataka Agro-Industries Corporation, a company incorporated under the Companies Act, 1956 (Central Act 1 of 1956);</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0.ix">
                      <num>(ix)</num>
                      <p>Agricultural Finance Corporation Limited, a company incorporated under Companies Act, 1956 (Central Act 1 of 1956);</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0.x">
                      <num>(x)</num>
                      <p>any other financial institution which may be notified in this behalf by the State Government; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0.xi">
                      <num>(xi)</num>
                      <p>a Co-operative Society;</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>"Co-operative Society" means a Co-opeative society registered or deemed to be registered under the Karnataka Co-operative Societies Act, 1959 (Karnataka Act 11 of 1959), the object of which is to provide financial assistance to its members, and includes a Co-operative Agriculture and Rural Development Bank;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>"financial assistance" means an assistance by way of loans, advances, guarantee or otherwise for the purposes of agriculture;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>"land" means land used for the purposes of agriculture and any purpose subservient thereto and which is assessed by the Government to land revenue but not being land appurtenant to any residential building situate within the local limits of a corporation, municipality or notified area;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>"pass book" means an agricultural credit pass book issued under section 4;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>"revenue officer" means a Tahsildar or any other officer appointed by the State Government for the purposes of this Act; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>"Sub-registrar" shall have the meaning assigned to it in the Registration Act, 1908 (Central Act 16 of 1908).</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Act to override other laws.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of this Act or any rule made thereunder shall have effect notwithstanding anything in the Karnataka Co-operative Societies Act, 1959 (Karnataka Act 11 of 1959) or in any enactment, other than this Act, or in any instrument having effect by virtue of any enactment other than this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <heading>Issue of pass books and matters relating thereto</heading>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Issue of pass books etc.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On the commencement of this Act, it shall be lawful for a revenue officer to provide for facilities for agricultural credit by the issue of pass books, in such form and containing such particulars as may be prescribed, to agriculturists having for the time being, land within the local limits of his jurisdiction.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An agriculturist who desires to have a pass book may make an application to the concerned revenue officer, in such form and on payment of such fee as may be prescribed, for the issue of such pass book to him.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every application referred to in sub-section (2) shall contain full particulars of the land owned by the applicant or in relation to which the applicant holds an interest or in relation to the crops, if any, standing on such land or in relation to which the applicant, holds any interest.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On receipt of the application made under sub-section (2), the revenue officer shall make or cause to be made, in such manner as may be prescribed, an inquiry about the title of the applicant in relation to the lands specified in the application or any interest held by the applicant therein or in respect of any crop standing thereon and where, after such inquiry, the revenue officer is satisfied with regard to the title of the applicant relating to all or any of the properties aforesaid or any part thereof, he may issue a pass book to the applicant indicating therein the properties in relation to which the applicant has title and the extent of encumbrances, if any existing in relation to any of such properties on the date of issue of the pass book.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The revenue officer shall retain a copy of the pass book issued by him under sub-section (4) and send a true copy thereof to the Sub-Registrar within the local limits of whose jurisdiction the properties specified in the pass book are situate, and on receipt thereof, the Sub-Registrar shall place the copy of the pass book on his records.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the revenue officer is satisfied that any pass book issued by him has been lost or destroyed, he may issue a duplicate pass book, on payment of such fee as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every entry made by the revenue officer in a pass book issued by him shall be presumed to be correct.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The entries in the pass book shall be prima facie evidence of the title of the holder thereof in respect of the land or other interest in the land or crops specified therein and shall be accepted as such by a bank for the purpose of granting financial assistance to the holder of the pass book whether or not on the security of the properties specified in the pass book.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The revenue officer may, from time to time require the holder of the pass book to produce it before him in order to make entries regarding mutation or transfer entered or to be entered in the revenue records.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Endorsements on pass books.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A bank granting any financial assistance to the holder of a pass book shall make an endorsement on the pass book indicating the amount of such financial assistance and where such financial assistance has been given on the security of any property the bank shall also make an endorsement against the property on the security of which the financial assistance has been granted by it, and the endorsement so made shall have the effect of creating a charge in favour of the bank on the property against which the endorsement has been so made and the holder of the pass book shall be debarred from alienating the said property until the outstanding amount of the financial assistance granted by the bank has been repaid together with interest due thereon.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-5.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The bank shall forward a copy of every endorsement made by it under the provisions of sub-section (1) to the revenue officer and another copy to the Sub-Registrar within the local limits of whose jurisdiction the whole or any part of the property which has been so charged is situate, and on receipt of the copy of such endorsement,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the revenue officer shall make the necessary entries in the Record of Rights maintained by him under the Karnataka Land Revenue Act, 1964 (Karnataka Act 12 of 1964) ; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-5.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the Sub-Registrar shall place, or cause to be placed, such endorsement on the copy of the pass book forwarded to him under section 4.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The holder of the pass book may also produce the endorsement made by the bank on the pass book before the Sub-Registrar to enable him to satisfy himself as to whether, a copy of the said endorsement has or has not been placed on his records, and in case it has not been so done, to get the said endorsement copies on the pass book which had been forwarded to him under section 4.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5A">
          <num>5A.</num>
          <heading>Registration of charge.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-5A.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Indian Registration Act, 1908 (Central Act 16 of 1908), a charge in favour of the Bank on the property against which the endorsement has been made on the pass book under sub-section (1) of section 5, shall be deemed to have been duly registered in accordance with the provisions of that Act with effect from the date of endorsement on forwarding a copy of every such endorsement to the Sub-Registrar under sub - section (2) of section 5 within the time stipulated by the State Government for the purpose.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Transfer not to be registered except on production of pass book.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No transfer made by the holder of a pass book in respect of any land specified in such pass book or any interest in such land or any crops standing thereon shall be registered by the Sub Registrar, unless the pass book is produced before him ; and on the production of the pass book, he shall make an endorsement thereon indicating the particulars of the transfer registered by him.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any transfer made by the holder of a pass book without complying with the provisions of sub-section (1) shall be void and shall not convey any title.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Removal of disability in creation of charges.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Where any charge on any land or interest therein or crops standing thereon was created in favour of a cooperative society before the commencement of this Act, it shall be lawful for an agriculturist to create, after such commencement a subsequent charge on such land or interest therein or crops standing thereon in favour of a bank, as security, for any financial assistance given to the agriculturist by the bank.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Priority of charges.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No charge or mortgage created on any land or interest or crops standing thereon after the commencement of this Act, in favour of Government or a co-operative society shall have priority over a charge or mortgage on such land or interest created by an agriculturist in favour of a bank as security for financial assistance given to the agriculturist by the Bank after the commencement of this Act and prior to the charge or mortgage in favour of Government or the cooperative society.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <heading>Miscellaneous</heading>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No suit or other legal proceedings shall lie against the Government or any officer or authority for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any rule made thereunder.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, by notification, in the official Gazette and after previous publication, make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-10.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the form in which pass book may be issued under sub-section (1) of section 4;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the form to be used for an application and the fee therefor under subsection (2) of section 4;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which the revenue officer may, make, or cause an inquiry to be made under sub-section (4) of section 4;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the fees required to be paid for a duplicate pass book under sub-section (6) of section 4; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>any other matter which has to be, or may be prescribed under this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made under this section or any other provisions of this Act shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made before each House of the State Legislature while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions and if before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rules should not be made, the rule shall from the date on which the modification or annulment is notified by the Government in the official Gazette have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be ; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
