<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1886/6/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1886/6"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Births, Deaths And Marriages Registration Act, 1886"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1886/6/eng@1886-03-08/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1886/6/eng@1886-03-08"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1886-03-08" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1886/6/eng@1886-03-08/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1886/6/eng@1886-03-08"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-10-24" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Births, Deaths And Marriages Registration Act, 1886</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 6 OF 1886</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 8th March, 1886.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the voluntary registration of certain births and deaths, for the establishment of General Registry Offices for keeping registers of certain births, deaths and marriages, and for certain other purposes.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <heading>Preliminary</heading>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title and commencement.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the Births, Deaths and Marriages Registration Act, 1886; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on such day as the Central Government, by notification in the Official Gazette, directs.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Extent.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>This Act extends to the whole of India except the territories which, immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised in Part B States.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Definitions.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>In this Act, unless there is something repugnant in the subject or context,--</p>
              <p>"sign" includes mark, when the person making the mark is unable to write his name:</p>
              <p>"prescibed" means prescribed by a rule made under this Act; and</p>
              <p>"Registrar of Births and Deaths" means a Registrar of Births and Deaths appointed under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Saving of local laws.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in this Act, or in any rule made under this Act, shall affect any law heretofore or herafter passed providing for the registration of births and deaths within particular local areas.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Powers exercisable from time to time.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>All powers conferred by this Act may be exercised from time to time as occasion required.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <heading>GENERAL REGISTRY OFFICES OF BIRTHS, DEATHS AND MARRIAGES</heading>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Establishment of general registry offices and appointment of Registrars General.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-6.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Each State Government--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>shall establish a general registry office for keeping such certified copies of registers of births and deaths registered under this Act, or marriages registered under Act 3 of 1872 (15 of 1872), (to provide a form of marriage in certain cases) or the Indian Christian Marriage Act, 1872 (15 of 1872), or, beyond the local limits of the ordinary original civil jurisdiction of the High Court of Judicature at Bombay, under the Parsi Marriage and Divorce Act, 1865 (15 of 1865), as may be sent to it under this Act, or under any of the three last mentioned Acts, as amended by this Act;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-6.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.1.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>may appoint to the charge of that office an officer, to be called the Registrar General of Births, Deaths and Marriages, for the territories under its administration:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>***</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Indexes to be kept at general registry office.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Each Registrar General of Births, Deaths and Marriages shall cause indexes of all the certified copies of registers sent to his office under this Act, or under Act 3 of 1872, the Indian Christian Marriage Act, 1872 (15 of 1872), or the Parsi Marriage and Divorce Act, 1865 (5 of 1865), as amended by this Act, to be made and kept in his office in the prescribed form.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Indexes to be open to inspection.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the payment of the prescribed fees, the indexes so made shall be at all reasonable times open to inspection by any person applying to inspect them, and copies of entries in the certified copies of the registers to which the indexes relate shall be given to all persons applying for them.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Copies of entries to be admissible in evidence.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>A copy of an entry given under the last foregoing section shall be certified by the Registrar General of Births, Deaths and Marriages, or by an officer authorized in this behalf by the State Government, and shall be admissible in evidence for the purpose of proving the birth, death or marriage to which the entry relates.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Superintendence of Registrars by Registrar General.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Each Registrar General of Births, Deaths and Marriages shall exercise a general superintendence over the Registrars of Births and Deaths in the territories for which he is appointed.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <heading>Registration of births and deaths</heading>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A.-- Application of this Chapter</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Persons whose births and deaths are registrable.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-11.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The persons whose births and deaths shall, in the first instance, be registrable under this Chapter are the following, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>in the territories to which this Act extends the members of every race, sect or tribe to which the Indian Succession Act, 1865 (10 of 1865.), applies, and in respect of which an order under section 332 of that Act is not for the time being in force, and all persons professing the Christian religion;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>But the State Government, by notification in the Official Gazette, may extend the operation of this Chapter to any other class of persons either generally or in any local area.</p>
              <p>B.-- Registration establishment</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Power for State Government to appoint Registrars for its territories.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may appoint, either by name or by virtue of their office, so many persons as it thinks necessary to be Registrars of Births and Deaths for such local areas within the territories under its administration as it may define and, if it sees fit, for any class of persons within any part of those territories.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Power for Central Government to appoint Registrars for Indian States</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Repealed</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Registrar to be deemed a public servant.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every Registrar of Births and Deaths shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Power to remove Registrars.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Repealed.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Office and attendance of Registrar.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-16.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every Registrar of Births and Deaths shall have an office in the local area, or within the part of the territories or dominions, for which he is appointed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every Registrar of Births and Deaths to whom the State Government may direct this sub- section to apply shall attend at his office for the purpose of registering births and deaths on such days and at such hours as the Registrar General of Births, Deaths and Marriages may direct, and shall cause to be placed in some conspicuous place on or near the outer door of his office his name, with the addition of Registrar of Births and Deaths for the local area or class for which he is appointed, and the days and hours of his attendance.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Absence of Registrar or vacancy in his office.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When any Registrar of Births and Deaths to whom the State Government may direct this section to apply, not being a Registrar of Births and Deaths for a local area in the town of Calcutta, Madras or Bombay, is absent, or when his office is temporarily vacant, any person whom the Registrar General of Births, Deaths and Marriages appoints in this behalf, or, in default of such appointment, the Judge of the District Court within the local limits of whose jurisdiction the Registrar's office is situate, or such other officer as the State Government appoints in this behalf, shall be the Registrar of Births and Deaths during such absence or until the State Government fills the vacancy.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When any such Registrar of Births and Deaths for a local area in the town of Calcutta, Madras or Bombay is absent, or when his office is temporarily vacant, any person whom the Registrar General of Births, Deaths and Marriages appoints in this behalf shall be the Registrar of Births and Deaths during such absence or until the State Government fills the vacancy.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Registrar General of Births, Deaths and Marriages shall report to the State Government all appointments made by him under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Register books to be supplied and preservation of records to be provided for.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Government shall supply every Registrar of Births and Deaths with a sufficient number of register books of births and of register books of deaths, and shall make suitable provision for the preservation of the records connected with the registration of births and deaths.</p>
              <p>C.-- Mode of registration</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Duty of Registrar to register births and deaths of which notice is given.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every Registrar of Births and Deaths, on receipt of notice of a birth or death within the local area or among the class for which he is appointed, shall, if the notice is given within the prescribed time and in the prescribed mode by a person authorized by this Act to give the notice, forthwith make an entry of the birth or death in the proper register book:</p>
              <blockList id="section-19.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>if he has reason to believe the notice to be in any respect false, he may refuse to register the birth or death until he receives an order from the Judge of the District Court directing him to make the entry and prescribing the manner in which the entry is to be made; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>he shall not enter in the register the name of any person as father of an illegitimate child, unless at the request of the mother and of the person acknowledging himself to be the father of the child.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Persons authorized to give notice of birth.- Any of the following persons may give notice of a birth, namely:--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-20.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the father or mother of the child;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>any person present at the birth;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>any person occupying, at the time of the birth, any part of the house wherein the child was born and having knowledge of the child having been born in the house;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>any medical practitioner in attendance after the birth and having personal knowledge of the birth having occurred;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list0.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>any person having charge of the child.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Persons authorized to give notice of death.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Any of the following persons may give notice of a death, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>any relative of the deceased having knowledge of any of the particulars required to be registered concerning the death;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>any person present at the death;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>any person occupying, at the time of the death, any part of the house wherein the death occurred and having knowledge of the deceased having died in the house;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>any person in attendance during the last illness of the deceased;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>any person who has seen the body of the deceased after death.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Entry of birth or death to be signed by person giving notice.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-22.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When an entry of a birth or death has been made by the Registrar of Births and Deaths under section 19, the person giving notice of the birth or death must sign the entry in the register in the presence of the Registrar:</p>
              <p>Provided that it shall not be necessary for the person giving notice to attend before the Registrar or to sign the entry in the register if he has given such notice in writing and has furnished to the satisfaction of the Registrar such evidence of his identity as may be required by any rules made by the State Government in this behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Until the entry has been so signed or the conditions specified in the proviso to sub- section (1) have been complied with, the birth or death shall not be deemed to be registered under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When the birth of an illegitimate child is registered, and the mother and the person acknowledging himself to be the father of the child jointly request that person may be registered as the father, the mother and that person must both sign the entry in the register in the presence of the Registrar.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Grant of certificate of registration of birth or death.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Registrar of Births and Deaths shall, on application made at the time of registering any birth by the person giving notice of the birth or death, and on payment by him of the prescribed fee, give to the applicant a certificate in the prescribed form, signed by the registrar, of having registered the birth or death.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Duty of Registrars as to sending certified copies of entries in register books to Registrar Genearal.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-24.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every Registrar of Births and Deaths in the territories to which this Act extends] shall send to the Registrar General of Births, Deaths and Marriages for the territories within which the local area or class for which he is appointed is situate or resides, at the prescribed intervals, a true copy certified by him, in the prescribed from, of all the entries of births and deaths in the register book kept by him since the last of those intervals:</p>
              <p>Provided that in the case of Registrars of Births and Deaths who are clergyman of the churches of England, Rome and Scotland, the Registrar may, if so directed by his ecclesiastical superior, send the certified copies in the first instance to that superior, who shall send them to the proper Registrar General of Births, Deaths and Marriages.</p>
              <p>In this sub-section" Church of England" and" Church of Scotland" mean the Church of England and the Church of Scotland as by law established respectively; and" Church of Rome" means the Church which regards the Pope of Rome as its spiritual head.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Searches and copies of entries in register books.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-25.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every Registrar of Births and Deaths shall, on payment of the prescribed fees, at all reasonable times, allow searches to be made in the register books kept by him, and give a copy of any entry in the same.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every copy of an entry in a register book given under this section shall be certified by the Registrar of Births and Deaths, and shall be admissible in evidence for the purpose of proving the birth or death to which the entry relates.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Exceptional provision for registration of certain births and deaths.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything in section 19, the State Government may make rules authorizing Registrars of Births and Deaths, on conditions and in circumstances to be specified in the rules, to register births and deaths occuring outside the local areas or classes for which they are appointed.</p>
              <p>D.-- Penalty for false information</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Penalty for wilfully giving false information.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>If any person wilfully makes, or causes to be made, for the purpose of being inserted in any register of births or deaths, any false statement in connection with any notice of a birth or death under this Act, he shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years, or with fine or with both.</p>
              <p>E.-- Correction of errors</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Correction of entry in register of births or deaths.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-28.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If it is proved to the satisfaction of a Registrar of Births and Deaths that any entry of a birth or death in any register kept by him under this Act is erroneous in form or substance, he may, subject to such rules as may be made by the State Government] with respect to the conditions and circumstances on and in which errors may be corrected, correct the error by entry in the margin, without any alteration of the original entry, and shall sign the marginal entry and add thereto the date of the correction.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-28.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a certified copy of the entry has already been sent to the Registrar General of Births, Deaths and Marriages, the Registrar of Births and Deaths shall make and send a separate certified copy of the original erroneous entry and of the marginal correction therein made.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <heading>Amendment of marriage acts.</heading>
        <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Repealed</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <heading>Special provisions as to certain existing registers</heading>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>Permission to persons having custody of certain records to send them within one year to Registrar General.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-32.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>If any person in the territories to which this Act extends] has for the time being the custody of any register or record of birth, baptism, naming, dedication, death or burial of any persons of the classes referred to in section 11, sub- section (1), or of any register or record of marriage of any persons of the classes to which Act 3 of 1872 or the Indian Christian Marriage Act, 1872 (15 of 1872), or the Parsi Marriage and Divorce Act, 1865 (15 of 1865), applies, and if such register or record has been made otherwise than in performance of a duty specially enjoined by the law of the country in which the register or record was kept, he may, at any time before the first day of April, 1891, send the register or record to the office of the Registrar General of Births, Deaths and Marriages for the territories within which he resides,</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading>Appointment of Commissioners to examine registers.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-33.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any State Government in the case of registers or records sent under section 32 to the Registrar General for the territories under its administration, may appoint so many persons as it thinks fit to be Commissioners for examining such registers or records.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-33.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Commissioners so appointed shall hold office for such period as the authority appointing them], by the order of appointment, or any subsequent order, directs.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-34">
          <num>34.</num>
          <heading>Duties of Commissioners.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-34.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The commissioners appointed under the last foregoing section shall enquire into the state, custody and authenticity of every such register or record as may be sent to the Registrar General of Births, Deaths and Marriages under section 32; and shall deliver to the Registrar General a descriptive list or descriptive lists of all such registers or records, or portions of registers or records, as they find to be accurate and faithful.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-34.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The list or lists shall contain the prescribed particulars and refer to the registers or records, or to the portions of the registers or records, in the prescribed manner.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-34.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Commissioners shall also certify in writing, upon some part of every separate book or volume containing any such register or record, or portion of a register or record, as is referred to in any list or lists made by the Commissioners, that it is one of the registers or records, or portions of registers or records, referred to in the said list or lists.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading>Searches of lists prepared by Commissioners and grant of certified copies of entries.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-35.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the payment of the prescribed fees, the descriptive list or lists of registers or records, or portions of registers or records, delivered by the Commissioners to the Registrar General of Births, Deaths and Marriages shall be, at all reasonable times, open to inspection by any person applying to inspect it or them, and copies of entries in those registers or records shall be given to all persons applying for them.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-35.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A copy of an entry given under this section shall be certified by the Registrar General of Births, Deaths and Marriages, or by an officer or person authorized in this behalf by the State Government and shall be admissible in evidence for the purpose of proving the birth, baptism, naming, dedication, death, burial or marriage to which the entry relates.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-35A">
          <num>35A.</num>
          <heading>Constitution of additional Commissions for purposes of this Chapter.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-35A.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may by notification in the Official Gazette appoint more Commission than one for the purposes of section 33, each such Commission consisting of so many and such members, and having its functions restricted to the disposal, under this Act and the rules thereunder, of such registers and records sent under section 32 to the Registrar General, as may be specified in the notification.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-35A.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If more Commissions than one are appointed in exercise of the power conferred by sub- section (1), then references in this Act to the Commissioners shall be construed as references to the members constituting a Commission so appointed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VI">
        <num>VI</num>
        <heading>Rules</heading>
        <section id="section-36">
          <num>36.</num>
          <heading>Rules.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-36.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government, for each State, may make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-36.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-36.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>fix the fees payable under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-36.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>prescribe the forms required for the purposes of this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-36.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>prescribe the time within which, and the mode in which, persons authorized under this Act to give notice of a birth or death to a Registrar of Births and Deaths must give the notice;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-36.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>prescribe the evidence of identity to be furnished to a Registrar of Births and Deaths by persons giving notice of a birth or death in cases where personal attendance before such Registrar is dispensed with;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-36.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>prescribe the registers to be kept and the form and manner in which Registrars of Births and Deaths are to register births and deaths under this Act, and the intervals at which they are to send to the Registrar General of Births, Deaths and Marriages true copies of the entries of births and deaths in the registers kept by them;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-36.2.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>prescribe the conditions and circumstances on and in which Registrars of Births and Deaths may correct entries of births and deaths in registers kept by them;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-36.2.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>prescribe the particulars which the descriptive list or lists to be prepared by the Commissioners appointed under Chapter V are to contain, and the manner in which they are to refer to the registers or records, or portions of registers or records, to which they relate;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-36.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-36.2.list3.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>prescribe the custody in which those registers or records are to be kept.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every power to make rules conferred by this Act is subject to the condition of the rules being made after previous publication.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All rules made under this Act shall be published in the Official Gazette, and on such publication shall have effect as if enacted in this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-37">
          <num>37.</num>
          <heading>Procedure for making and publication of rules.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-37.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Repealed</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
