<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1956/31/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1956/31"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Maharashtra Hindu Places Of Public Worship (Entry Authorization) Act, 1956"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1956/31/eng@2017-03-20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1956/31/eng@2017-03-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-20" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1956/31/eng@2017-03-20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1956/31/eng@2017-03-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-20" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Maharashtra Hindu Places Of Public Worship (Entry Authorization) Act, 1956</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[28th May, 1956]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No. XXXI of 1956</p>
        <p>An Act to make better provision for the throwing open of places of public worship to all classes and sections of Hindus.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to make better provision for the throwing open of places of public worship to all classes and sections of Hindus; It is hereby enacted in the Seventh Year of the Republic of India as follows :—</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Maharashtra Hindu Places of Public Worship (Entry Authorization) Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Bombay.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force in the pre-Reorganisation State of Bombay on such date as the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint; and in that part of the State of Bombay to which it is extended by the Bombay Hindu Places of Public Worship (Entry Authorization) (Extension) Act, 1957, it shall come into force on such other date as the State Government may, by notification published in the like manner, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“place of public worship” means a place, whether a temple or by any other name called, to whomsoever belonging which is dedicated to, or for the benefit of, or is used generally by, Hindus, Jains, Sikhs or Buddhists or any section or class thereof, for the performance of any religious service or for offering prayers therein; and includes all lands and subsidiary shrines appurtenant or attached to any such place, and also any sacred tanks, wells, springs and water courses the waters of which are worshipped, or are used for bathing or for worship;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“section” or “class” of Hindus includes any division, sub-division, caste, sub-caste, sect or denomination whatsoever of Hindus.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Throwing open of Hindu temples to all classes and sections of Hindus.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding any custom, usage or law for the time being in force, or the decree or order of a court, or anything contained in any instrument, to the contrary, every place of public worship which is open to Hindus generally, or to any section or class thereof, shall be open to all sections and classes of Hindus; and no Hindu of whatsoever section or class, shall in any manner be prevented, obstructed or discouraged from entering such place of public worship, or from worshipping or offering prayers thereat, or performing any religious service therein, in the like manner and to like extent as any other Hindu of whatsoever section or class may so enter, worship, pray or perform.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Penalty.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Whoever in contravention of section 3—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>prevents any person belonging to any class or section of Hindus from entering, worshipping or offering prayers, or performing any religious service in any Hindu temple which is used as a place of public worship, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>molests, injures, annoys, obstructs, or causes or attempts to cause obstruction to, or by the threat of molestation, injury, annoyance or obstruction, overawes or discourages any such person doing or performing any of the acts aforesaid, shall, on conviction, be punished with imprisonment which may extend to six months or with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, or with both.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in this section shall be taken to relate to offences relating to the practice of “untouchability”.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Abetment of offence.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever abets any offence under this Act shall be punished with the punishment provided for the offence.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Limitation of Jurisdiction of civil courts.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No civil court shall entertain or continue any suit or proceeding, or shall pass any decree or order, or execute wholly or partially any decree or order, if the claim involved in any such suit or proceeding, or if the passing of any such decree or order or if such execution would in any way be contrary to the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Offences to be cognizable and compoundable.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898, every offence under this Act shall be cognisable, and every such offence may, with the permission of the court, be compounded.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Saving of Act XXII of 1955 and other laws.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of this Act shall not be taken to be in derogation of any of the provisions of the Untouchability (Offences) Act, 1955 or of any other law for the time being in force relating to any of the matters dealt with in this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
