<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1946/25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1946/25"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Delhi Special Police Establishment Act, 1946"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1946/25/eng@1946-11-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1946/25/eng@1946-11-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1946-11-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1946/25/eng@1946-11-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1946/25/eng@1946-11-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-10-05" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Delhi Special Police Establishment Act, 1946</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No. 25 of 1946</p>
      </longTitle>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[19th November, 1946.]</docDate>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>An Act to make provision for the constitution of a special police force in Delhi for the investigation of certain offences in the Union territories, for the superintendence and administration of the said force and for the extension to other of the powers and jurisdiction of members of the said force in regard to the investigation of the said offences.</p>
      <p>WHEREAS it is necessary to constitute a special police force in Delhi for the investigation of certain offences in the Union territories and to make provision for the superintendence and administration of the said force and for the extension to other areas of the powers and jurisdiction of the members of the said force in regard to the investigation of the said offences;</p>
      <p>It is hereby enacted as follows:—</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and extent.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Delhi Special Police Establishment Act, 1946.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1A">
        <num>1A.</num>
        <heading>Interpretation section.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Words and expressions used herein and not defined but defined in the Central Vigilance Commission Act, 2003, shall have the meanings, respectively, assigned to them in that Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Constitution and powers of special police establishment.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything in the Police Act, 1861 (5 of 1861), the Central Government may constitute a special police force to be called the Delhi Special Police Establishment for the investigation in any Union territory of offences notified under section 3.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to any orders which the Central Government may make in this behalf, members of the said police establishment shall have throughout any Union territory in relation to the investigation of such offences and arrest of persons concerned in such offences, all the powers, duties, privileges and liabilities which police officers of that Union territory have in connection with the investigation of offences committed therein.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any member of the said police establishment of or above the rank of Sub-Inspector may, subject to any orders which the Central Government may make in this behalf, exercise in any Union territory any of the powers of the officer in charge of a police station in the area in which he is for the time being and when so exercising such powers shall, subject to any such orders as aforesaid, be deemed to be an officer in charge of a police station discharging the functions of such an officer within the limits of his station.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Offences to be investigated by special police establishment.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify the offences or classes of offences which are to be investigated by the Delhi Special Police Establishment.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Superintendence and administration of Special Police Establishment.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The superintendence of the Delhi Special Police Establishment insofar as it relates to investigation of offences alleged to have been committed under the Prevention of Corruption Act, 1988 (49 of 1988), shall vest in the Commission.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Save as otherwise provided in sub-section (1), the superintendence of the said police establishment in all other matters shall vest in the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The administration of the said police establishment shall vest in an officer appointed in this behalf by the Central Government (hereinafter referred to as the Director) who shall exercise in respect of that police establishment such of the powers exercisable by an Inspector-General of Police in respect of the police force in a State as the Central Government may specify in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4A">
        <num>4A.</num>
        <heading>Committee for appointment of Director.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4A.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government shall appoint the Director on the recommendation of the Committee consisting of —</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4A.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the Prime Minister — Chairperson;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4A.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the Leader of Opposition recognised as such in the House of the People or where there is no such Leader of Opposition, then, the Leader of the single largest Opposition Party in that House—Member;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4A.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the Chief Justice of India or Judge of the Supreme Court nominated by him — Member.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No appointment of a Director shall be invalid merely by reason of any vacancy or absence of a Member in the Committee.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4A.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Committee shall recommend a panel of officers—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4A.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>on the basis of seniority, integrity and experience in the investigation of anti-corruption cases; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4A.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>chosen from amongst officers belonging to the Indian Police Service constituted under the All-India Services Act, 1951 (61 of 1951),</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>for being considered for appointment as the Director.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4B">
        <num>4B.</num>
        <heading>Terms and conditions of service of Director.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4B.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Director shall, notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in the rules relating to his conditions of service, continue to hold office for a period of not less than two years from the date on which he assumes office.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4B.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Director shall not be transferred except with the previous consent of the Committee referred to in sub-section (1) of section 4A.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4BA">
        <num>4BA.</num>
        <heading>Director of Prosecution.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4BA.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be a Directorate of Prosecution headed by a Director who shall be an officer not below the rank of Joint Secretary to the Government of India, for conducting prosecution of cases under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4BA.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Director of Prosecution shall function under the overall supervision and control of the Director.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4BA.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government shall appoint the Director of Prosecution on the recommendation of the Central Vigilance Commission.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4BA.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Director of Prosecution shall notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in the rules relating to his conditions of service, continue to hold office for a period of not less than two years from the date on which he assumes office</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4C">
        <num>4C.</num>
        <heading>Appointment for posts of Superintendent of Police and above, extension and curtailment of their tenure, etc.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4C.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4C.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government shall appoint officers to the posts of the level of Superintendent of Police and above except Director, and also recommend the extension or curtailment of the tenure of such officers in the Delhi Special Police Establishment, on the recommendation of a committee consisting of:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4C.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the Central Vigilance Commissioner — Chairperson;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4C.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>Vigilance Commissioners — Members;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4C.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>Secretary to the Government of India in charge of the Ministry of Home — Member;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4C.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>Secretary to the Government of India in charge of the Department of Personnel — Member:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that the Committee shall consult the Director before submitting its recommendation to the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4C.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On receipt of the recommendation under sub-section (1), the Central Government shall pass such orders as it thinks fit to give effect to the said recommendation.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Extension of powers and jurisdiction of special police establishment to other areas.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may by order extend to any area (including Railway areas), in a State, not being a Union territory the powers and jurisdiction of members of the Delhi Special Police Establishment for the investigation of any offences or classes of offences specified in a notification under section 3.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When by an order under sub-section (1) the powers and jurisdiction of members of the said police establishment are extended to any such area, a member thereof may, subject of any orders which the Central Government may make in this behalf, discharge the functions of a police officer in that area and shall, while so discharging such functions, be deemed to be a member of a police force of that area and be vested with the powers, functions and privileges and be subject to the liabilities of a police officer belonging to that police force.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any such order under sub-section (1) is made in relation to any area, then, without prejudice to the provisions of sub-section (2) any member of the Delhi Special Police Establishment of or above the rank of Sub-Inspector may subject to any orders which the Central Government may make in this behalf, exercise the powers of the officer in charge of a police station in that area and when so exercising such powers, shall be deemed to be an officer in charge of a police station discharging the functions of such an officer within the limits of his station.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Consent of State Government to exercise of powers and jurisdiction.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Nothing contained in section 5 shall be deemed to enable any member of the Delhi Special Police Establishment to exercise powers and jurisdiction in any area in a State, not being a Union territory or railway area, without the consent of the Government of that State.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6A">
        <num>6A.</num>
        <heading>Approval of Central Government to conduct inquiry or investigation.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6A.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Delhi Special Police Establishment shall not conduct any inquiry or investigation into any offence alleged to have been committed under the Prevention of Corruption Act, 1988 (49 of 1988) except with the previous approval of the Central Government where such allegation relates to—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6A.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the employees of the Central Government of the Level of Joint Secretary and above; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6A.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>such officers as are appointed by the Central Government in corporations established by or under any Central Act, Government companies, societies and local authorities owned or controlled by that Government.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), no such approval shall be necessary for cases involving arrest of a person on the spot on the charge of accepting or attempting to accept any gratification other than legal remuneration referred to in clause (c) of the Explanation to section 7 of the Prevention of Corruption Act, 1988 (49 of 1988).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Repeal of Ordinance 22 of 1946.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>***</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
