<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/2003/27/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/2003/27"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Karnataka Inland Fisheries (Conservation Development And Regulation) Act, 1996"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/2003/27/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/2003/27/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/2003/27/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/2003/27/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-27" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Karnataka Inland Fisheries (Conservation Development And Regulation) Act, 1996</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No. 27 of 2003</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for conservation, development and regulation of inland fisheries in the State.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>Whereas it is expedient to provide for conservation, development and regulation of inland fisheries in the State and for matters connected therewith.</p>
      <p>Be it enacted by the Karnataka State Legislature in the Forty Seventh year of the Republic of India as follows:-</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <heading>Preliminary</heading>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title, commencement and application.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This act may be called the Karnataka Inland Fisheries (Conservation, Development and Regulation) Act, 1996.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on such date as the State Government may, by notification, appoint.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in this Act shall apply to fishing and fishery in any specified area within the meaning of clause (i) of section 2 of the Karnataka Marine Fishing (Regulations), Act, 1986 (Karnataka Act 24 of 1986) in National parks and sancturies declared under the Wild Life Protection Act, 1973 (Central Act 53 of 1972) and in any area beyond territorial waters.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In this Act unless the context otherwise requires,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>"Appellate Authority" means the Appellate authority constituted by notification by the State Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>"Authorised officer" means an officer not below the rank of an Assistant Director of Fisheries, authorised by the State Government in this behalf, by notification to exercise the powers conferred on and discharge the duties imposed upon the authorised officer;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>"Board" means the Karnataka Inland Fisheries Advisory Board constituted under section 8;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>"Director" means the Director of Fisheries appointed by the State Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>"Fish" includes shrimp, prawn, crab, lobster, molluscs and their young ones;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>"Fish culture" means any activity connected with the breeding and rearing of fish by process other than natural process;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>"Fishery" means any activity or occupation connected with conservation, development, propagation of fish in any water area where such activity or occupation is carried on;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>"Fishing" means any act or activity connected with the catching of fish from any water;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>"Fishery products" means all products derived from any fish or their parts;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>"Fish Sanctuary" means any area of water declared under sub-section (1) of section 7;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>"Fish seed" means spawn, fry and fingerlings at the appropriate early stages;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>"Private water" means any water which is the exclusive property of any person or in which any person has for the time being an exclusive right of fishing whether as an owner, lessee or in any other capacity;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.m">
                  <num>(m)</num>
                  <p>"Water" means water other than the water specified in clause (1).</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <heading>Licence for Fishing</heading>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Prohibition of fishing.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No person shall fish in any water except under and in accordance with the terms and conditions specified in a licence granted under sub-section (2);</p>
              <p>Provided that the State Government may, subject to such terms and conditions as may be prescribed, exempt any area of water from the provisions of sub-section (1).</p>
              <p>Provided further that a person carrying on fishing in any water immediately before the commencement of this Act, may continue to do so for a period of three months from such commencement and if he has made an application for such licence within the said period of three months till the disposal of such application.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person desiring to obtain a licence referred to in sub-section (1), shall apply to the authorised officer in such form and on payment of such fee as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On receipt of an application under sub-section (2), the authorised officer may after making such enquiry as he thinks fit and having regard to conservation of fish, grant or refuse to grant licence, after recording in writing his reasons for refusal and when the grant of a licence is refused, the fee paid thereon shall be refunded to the applicant.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.4.list1">
                <listIntroduction>A licence granted under this section shall be-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.4.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>in such form as may be prescribed;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.4.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>valid for such period as may be specified;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.4.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>subject to such other terms and conditions and restrictions as may be prescribed;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.4.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>non transferable.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The authorised officer may for good and sufficient reasons to be recorded in writing, order suspension or cancellation of any licence granted under this section:</p>
              <p>Provided that no such suspension or cancellation shall be made except after giving the holder of a licence a reasonable opportunity of being heard.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An appeal from an order refusing to grant a licence under sub-section (3), or an order suspending or cancelling a licence under sub-section (5), shall lie to the Appellate Authority within thirty days from the date of communication to the applicant of the order appealed against:</p>
              <p>Provided that the Appellate Authority may admit an appeal after the expiry of the period aforesaid, if it is satisfied that the applicant had sufficient cause for not preferring the appeal in time.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every order passed in appeal under sub-section (6), shall be final.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Registration for fish breeding.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No person shall breed fish for sale of fish seeds unless he is registered under this Act:</p>
              <p>Provided that a person carrying on breeding of fish for sale of fish seeds immediately before the commencement of this Act, may continue to do so for a period of three months from such commencement; and if he has made an application for such registration within the said period of three months till the disposal of such application.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every application for registration under sub-section (1), shall be made to the authorised officer in such form and on payment of such fee as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On receipt of an application under sub-section (2), the authorised officer may, after making such enquiry as he thinks fit, grant a certificate of registration subject to such terms and conditions as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The certificate of registration shall continue to be in force unless it is otherwise cancelled:</p>
              <p>Provided that no such cancellation shall be made except after giving to the holder of registration certificate a reasonable opportunity of being heard.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Leasing of fishery rights.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The authorised officer or any other officer empowered by the State Government in that behalf, shall lease the fishery rights in any water in the manner prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every person who obtains the lease of fishery rights under sub-section (1), shall execute a lease in the form prescribed and within the prescribed period.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every person aggrieved by the order under sub-section (1), may prefer an appeal to the Appellate Authority within fifteen days from the date of communication of such order to him.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Regulation of fishing.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>No person shall unless he is authorised by a licence under this Act.-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>capture, whether alive or dead, kill or destroy or attempt to capture, kill or destroy fish with chemicals, explosives, poisons, poisonous weapons or noxious materials;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>capture whether alive or dead, kill or destroy or attempt to capture, kill or destroy spawn, fry fingerlings, juveniles or breeding in any kind of fish.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Declaration of sanctuary.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, by notification, declare any area of water to be a fish sanctuary, for the purpose of protecting, propogating or development of fisheries.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, no person shall fish or capture fish whether alive or dead or destroy, or attempt to destroy fish or capture or destroy any fish in a sanctuary declared under sub-section (1).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <heading>Constitution of the Karnataka Inland Fisheries Advisory Board</heading>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Constitution of Inland Fisheries Advisory Board.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, constitute the Karnataka Inland Fisheries Advisory Board consisting of such number of members not exceeding thirteen.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-8.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Board shall consist of the following members, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>The Minister incharge of Fisheries shall be the Chairman;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>The Secretary to Government, incharge of Fisheries;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>The Secretary to Government, Finance Department;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>The Secretary to Government, Irrigation Department;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>The Secretary to Government, Rural Development and Panchayat Raj Department;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.2.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>The Director of Instruction, Fisheries College, Mangalore;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.2.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>The Director of Fisheries shall be the Member Secretary;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.2.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>Two persons of whom one shall be a woman and one shall be a person belonging to the Scheduled Castes or Scheduled Tribes;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.2.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>Two persons who are members of the Karnataka Legislature;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.2.list1.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>Two persons of whom one shall be a person from the Fisheries Co-operative Societies and one shall be a person belonging to Fishermen Community and who is engaged in fishing.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The persons referred to in clauses (h), (i) and (j) shall be nominated by the State Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any officer referred to in clauses (b) to (e), is unable to attend the meeting of the Board, he may in writing depute an officer not below the rank of a Deputy Secretary to Government to attend such meeting.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The members shall be entitled to receive such allowance in respect of expenses incurred by them in the performance of their duties as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-8.6.list1">
                <listIntroduction>It shall be the duty of Board,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.6.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to advice the State Government in any matter connected with the conservation, development and regulation of inland fisheries in the State;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.6.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>to assist the State Government in relation to fisherman welfare;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.6.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>to assist and encourage the development and propagation of fishery and fishery products;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.6.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>to collect statistics regarding fish production;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.6.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>to establish training institutions; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.6.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>to perform such other functions and duties as may be prescribed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Disqualification for the membership of the Board.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-9.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>A person shall be disqualified for being nominated as and for being, a member,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-9.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>if, he has been convicted and sentenced to imprisonment for an offence which, in the opinion of the State Government involves moral turpitude; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>if, he is of unsound mind and is so declared by a competent court; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>if, he is an undischarged insolvent; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>if, he has been removed or dismissed from the service of the Central Government or the State Government or a Corporation owned or controlled by the Central Government or the State Government or from the membership of the Board; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.1.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>if, he has directly or indirectly, by himself or his partner, any share or interest in any work done by the order of the Board or in any contract or employment with or under or by or on behalf of the Board; or</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>(f0 if, he is employed as a legal practitioner on behalf of the Board or accepts employment as legal practitioner against the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A person shall not be disqualified under clause (c) of sub-section (1) or be deemed to have any share or interest in any contract or employment within the meaning of the said clause, by reason only of his having a share or interest in any newspaper in which any advertisement relating to the affairs of the Board is inserted.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Term of office and conditions of service of nominated members.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the pleasure of the State Government and the provisions of section 11, the nominated members of the Board shall hold office for a period of three years from the date of their nomination.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every nominated member may at any time resign his office by sending a letter of resignation addressed to the State Government:</p>
              <p>Provided that the resignation shall not take effect until it is accepted.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Removal of members.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-11.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The State Government shall remove a nominated member, if he,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>becomes subject to any of the disqualifications specified in section 9; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>refuses to act or becomes incapable of acting; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>without obtaining the leave of absence from the chairman absents himself for three consecutive meetings of the Board; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>in the opinion of the State Government he has so abused his position as to render his continuance detrimental to the interest of the Board.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No order of removal of a nominated member under sub-section (1), shall be made unless such member has been given an opportunity of making his representation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Casual vacancies.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-12.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any casual vacancy caused by resignation of a nominated member or by any other reason, may be filled by the State Government by nomination and the person so nominated shall hold the office for remaining period for which the member in whose place he is nominated would have held office.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No act or proceeding of the Board shall be invalidated merely by reason of any vacancy in its membership or any defect in the constitution or reconstitution of the Board or any irregularity in the procedure of the Board not affecting the merits of the case.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Meetings of the Board.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-13.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall meet at least once in three months ordinarily at Bangalore or at such other place as the Board may decide and may regulate its own procedure including the quorum in regard to the transaction of business at its meeting.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chairman or in his absence, any member chosen by the members present from among themselves, shall preside over the meeting of the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <heading>Offences and Penalties</heading>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Power of entry, search, seizure and detention.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-14.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Director or the authorised officer or any Police Officer not below the rank of a Sub-Inspector, may, if he has reason to believe that any person has committed an offence under this Act,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-14.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>require any such person to produce for his inspection any fish or other article in his possession or any licence, permission or other document issued to him or required to be kept by him under the provisions of this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>enter and search any premises, land, vehicle or vessel in the occupation of such person and open and search any baggage or other things in his possession;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>seize any fish together with any weapon, arms, ammunition, tool, or other things used in committing any such offence and unless he is satisfied that such person will appear and answer any charge which may be preferred against him arrest without warrant and detain him.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall be lawful for any of the officers referred to in sub-section (1), to stop and detain any person whom he sees doing any act for which a licence is required under the provisions of this Act, for the purposes of requiring such person to produce his licence and if such person fails to produce his licence or refuses to furnish his name and address or furnishes a false name and address and where there is reason to believe that he will abscond, he may be arrested without warrant.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person detained or things seized under the foregoing powers, shall forthwith be produced before the Magistrate having jurisdiction within twenty four hours of such detention excluding the time necessary for the journey from the place of detention to the Court of Magistrate:</p>
              <p>Provided that if in the opinion of the Officer seizing anything, it is not possible to take it before the Magistrate to be dealt with under this sub-section in time, such officer may sell the property himself, remit the sale proceeds to the nearest Government treasury, and make a report of such seizure, sale and remittance to the Magistrate, and thereupon the Magistrate shall take such action in the case as he deems fit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person, who without reasonable cause, fails to produce anything which under the powers conferred by this section he is required to produce, shall be guilty of an offence against this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Penalties.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-15.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person who contravenes any of the provisions of this Act or the rules or who commits a breach of any of the conditions of any licence granted under this Act shall be guilty of an offence against this Act and shall, on conviction, be punishable with imprisonment which may extend to three months or with fine which may extend to "two thousand rupees" or with both.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When any person is convicted of an offence against this Act, the Court trying the offence may order that any article in respect of which the offence has been committed and any weapon, arms, ammunition, tools, vessel, or other things with which the offence has been committed shall be forfeited to the State Government and that any licence held by such person under the provisions of this Act be cancelled.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Such cancellation of licence shall be in addition to any other punishment awarded for such offence.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Punishment for wrongful seizure.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>If any person exercising powers under this Act, vexatiously seizes the property of any other person on the pretext of seizing it for the reasons mentioned in section 14, he shall on conviction be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years or with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees or with both.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Power to compound offence.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any offence specified in the schedule may be compounded by such officer as may be empowered by the State Government in this behalf, by accepting from any person against whom a reasonable suspicion exists that he has committed an offence punishable under this Act, such sums of money as may be prescribed by way of composition for the offence which such person is suspected to have committed or when any property has been seized as liable to confiscation, to release the same on payment of the value thereon as estimated by such officer.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On the payment of such sum of money or such value or both, as the case may be, to such officer, the suspected person, if in custody, shall be discharged, the property, if any, seized shall be released and no further proceedings in respect of the offence shall be taken against any person or property.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Cognizance of offence.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-18.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>No court shall take cognizance of any offence under this Act,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>except on the complaint or report of the officer authorised by the State Government in this behalf; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>unless the prosecution is instituted within three months from the date on which the offence is alleged to have been committed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Operation of other laws not barred.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in this Act shall be deemed to prevent any person from being prosecuted under any other law, for the time being in force,</p>
              <p>for any act or omission which constitutes an offence against this Act or from being liable under such other law to any higher punishment or penalty than that provided by this Act:</p>
              <p>Provided that no person shall be punished twice.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Offence by companies.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-20.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where an offence against this Act has been committed by a company, every person, who at the time the offence was committed, was in charge of and was responsible to the company for the conduct of the business of the company as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:</p>
              <p>Provided that nothing contained in this section, shall render any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or that he exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1) where an offence against this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of any director, manager, secretary, or other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.</p>
              <blockList id="section-20.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-20.2.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>"Company" means any body corporate and includes a firm or other association of individuals, and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-20.2.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>"Director" in relation to a firm means a partner in the firm.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <heading>Miscellaneous</heading>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Officers to be the public servants.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every officer exercising any of the powers conferred by this Act shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of action 21 of the Penal Code 1860.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against any public servant for anything which is in good faith does or intended to be done under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-23.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may after previous publication, by notification, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-23.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power such rules, may, provided for all or any of the following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-23.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-23.2.list1.a.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>Prohibit or regulate,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-23.2.list1.a.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>erection and use of fixed engines</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-23.2.list1.a.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>the construction, temporary or permanent of bunds, dams and weirs;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-23.2.list1.a.list0.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>the dimensions, kind and size of the mesh or other fishing appliances or implements and the mode of using them;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-23.2.list1.a.list0.iv">
                      <num>(iv)</num>
                      <p>the fishing and using of fishing appliances.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the conditions subject to which any licence under this Act may be granted or would be valid;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the forms to be used for any application or licence required to be made or granted under this Act, and the fees if any, therefor;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the species of fish which shall not be caught or captured;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>conditions subject to which lease of fishing rights may be granted and the mode of granting such lease;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.2.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the purposes for which a fish sanctuary may be declared under section 7;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.2.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>prohibit or regulate the extraction of fish in any water;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.2.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>the measures that may be taken to develop and conserve fisheries resources in any river;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.2.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>regulate fish breeding or development of fish;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.2.list1.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>any other matter which is necessary to carry out the purposes of the Act or which is to be or may be prescribed under this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of the Legislature, which is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions and if before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive session aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect as the case may be; so however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Repeal and savings.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Indian Fisheries Act, 1897 (Central Act IV of 1897) as in force in Belgaum areas in Mangalore and Kollegal areas Coorg District and Bellary District; the Fisheries (Madras Amendment) Act, 1927 (Madras Act II of 1929) as in force in Mangalore and Kollegal area; the Hyderabad Fisheries Act, 1356 Fasli (Hyderabad Fishers Act 23 of 1356 F) as in force in the Gulbarga Area and the Mysore Game and Fish Preservation Act, 1901 (Regulation II of 1901) as in force in the Mysore area in so far as it relates to fish and fisheries are hereby repealed;</p>
              <blockList id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that the repeal shall not affect,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>The previous operation of the repealed Acts, or anything duly done or suffered thereunder; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>any right, privilege obligation or liability acquired, accrued or incurred under the repealed Acts; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>any penalty, forfeiture or punishment incurred or suffered in respect of any offence committed against the provisions of the repealed Act; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>any investigation, legal proceedings or remedy in respect of any such right, privilege, obligations, liability, penalty, forfeiture or punishment as aforesaid and any such investigation, legal proceeding or remedy may be instituted, continued or enforced and any such penalty, forfeiture or punishment may be imposed as if the repealed Act have not been repealed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-theschedule">
      <doc name="theschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/2003/27/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/2003/27"/>
              <FRBRalias value="THE SCHEDULE"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/2003/27/eng@1980-01-01/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/2003/27/eng@1980-01-01"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/2003/27/eng@1980-01-01/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/2003/27/eng@1980-01-01"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-03-27" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="theschedule">
            <paragraph id="theschedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>Offences Compoundable Under Section 17</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <subsection id="theschedule.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Fishing without licence;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Killing or catching or selling or attempt to sell, kill or catch any fish of prohibited species during the closed season;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Fishing or attempting to fish in a fish sanctuary.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
