<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-wbg/act/1932/10/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-wbg/act/1932/10"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Bengal Opium Smoking Act, 1932"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-wbg/act/1932/10/eng@2017-01-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-wbg/act/1932/10/eng@2017-01-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-wbg/act/1932/10/eng@2017-01-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-wbg/act/1932/10/eng@2017-01-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-12-07" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Bengal Opium Smoking Act, 1932</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[20th October, 1932]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[No. 10 of 1932]</p>
        <p>An Act to provided for the control of the practice of smoking prepared opium;</p>
        <p>Whereas it is expedient to control the practice of smoking prepared opium in Bengal;</p>
        <p>And whereas the previous sanction of the Governor General has been obtained under sub-section (3) of section 80A or the Government of India Act to the passing of this Act;</p>
        <p>It is hereby enacted as follows:—</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, local extent and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Bengal Opium Smoking Act, 1932.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of West Bengal.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force in such local areas and on such dates as the State Government may, by notification, direct, and the State Government may, by notification, withdraw this Act from any local area.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context—</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“notification” means a notification published in the Official Gazette;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“prepared opium” means any product of opium obtained by any series of operations designed to transform opium into an extract suitable for smoking and includes the dross or other residue remaining after opium is smoked;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“registered” means registered under the provision of this Act as a smoker of prepared opium;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“place” includes a building, house, shop, booth, tent vessel, raft and vehicle and any part thereof;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.5.list1">
              <listIntroduction>“Collector” means—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.5.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>in the Calcutta district, any person appointed under clause(b) of section 7 of the Bengal Excise Act, 1909, (Ben. Act V of 1909), to exercise all the powers and to perform all the duties of the Collector in that district under that Act ; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.5.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>elsewhere, the chief officer in charge of the revenue administration of a district.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Smoking of prepared opium.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever, not being registered, smokes prepared opium shall be punished for the first offence with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, or with both, and for every such subsequent offence with imprisonment which may extend to one year, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Presumption of smoking prepared opium in certain cases.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any person not being registered, is found in possession of prepared opium or of any apparatus used for the smoking of, or in the manufacture of, prepared opium, it shall be presumed, until the contrary is proved, that such person smokes prepared opium.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Manufacture, possession or sale of prepared opium.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever manufactures, possesses, sells, keeps or exposes for sale or attempts to sell any prepared opium, or assists any other person, whether an opium smoker or not, in the manufacture of prepared opium shall be punished with imprisonment which may extend to two years, or with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees, or both.</p>
            <p>Exception:—Manufacture or possession for his own use by a registered opium smoker of prepared opium not exceeding one tola in weight or such other lesser quantity as the State Government may, by notification direct, shall not be an offence under this section.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Keeping or having charge of place used for smoking prepared opium.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever opens, keeps or uses any place or permits, any place to be used, for the purpose of enabling two or more persons, whether registered or not, to meet together to smoke prepared opium or has the care or management of, or in any way assists in conducting the business of, any place used or kept for the said purpose shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years, or with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Smoking of prepared opium in assembly of two or more.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If two or more persons, whether registered or not, assemble in any place for the purpose of smoking prepared opium, each such person shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Presumption from presence of prepared opium, etc., in certain places.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any prepared opium or any apparatus used for smoking, or in the manufacture of, prepared opium is found in any place where two or more persons, whether registered or not, are assembled, it shall be presumed until the contrary is proved that the place is used, and that the persons are present in such place, for the purpose of smoking prepared opium.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Power of State Government to make rules for registration of opium smokers.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification, make rules providing for— (1) the registration of persons who are opium smokers and for their identification, and (2) the method of registration, the fee payable for such registration, and the form of the register and the maintenance thereof:</p>
            <p>Provided that no person shall be registered as an opium smoker who is below the age of twenty-five years:</p>
            <p>Provided also that, subject to such exceptions as the State Government may by rule prescribe, no person shall be registered as an opium smoker after a date to be fixed in this behalf, by notification, by the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Power to enter and search any place and to seize articles and to arrest persons found in such place.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If a Collector, a Presidency Magistrate, or a Magistrate of the first class, upon information received and after such inquiry, if any, as he considers necessary, has reason to believe that any place is used for the commission of an offence under this Act , he may, after recording the substance of the information, issue a warrant to an Excise Officer not below the rank of Sub-Inspector authorizing him—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to enter such place by day or night with such assistants as such officer may consider necessary; (b) to search all parts of such place in which such officer has reason to believe that any prepared opium or any apparatus for the smoking of such opium or for the manufacture thereof, is concealed and all or any persons whom he may find in such place;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to arrest any person found in such place whom he has reason to believe to be guilty of an offence under this Act; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>to seize all prepared opium and apparatus for the smoking or for the manufacture thereof which may be found in such place.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Application of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898, to warrants and searches under section 10.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898, (Act V of 1898), shall apply to the execution of warrants and to searches made under section 10.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purposes of the said provisions of the said Code, a Collector shall be deemed to be a court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Report to be made in case of arrest or seizure.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whenever any office makes an arrest or seizure under this Act, he shall without delay, and in any case within twenty-four hours, forward every person arrested and everything seized with full particulars of the arrest or seizure to the Collector or to the Magistrate, as the case may be, by whom the warrant was issued. In case of an arrest or seizure under a warrant issued by the Collector the said officer shall, unless the Collector proceeds under section 13, within the aforesaid period of twenty-four hours, forward the person or thing produced before the Collector to a Magistrate having jurisdiction to try the case together with full particulars of the arrest or seizure.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Powers of Collector to investigate offences.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A Collector may, without the order of a Magistrate, investigate any offence punishable under this Act , which a Court having jurisdiction over the local area within the limits of the Collector’s jurisdiction would have power to try.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A Collector may, after recording in writing his reason for suspecting the commission of an offence which he is empowered to investigate, exercise any of the powers conferred upon a police officer making an investigation, or upon an officer in charge of a police-station, by sections 160 to 171 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A Collector may without reference to a Magistrate, and for reasons to be recorded by him in writing, stop further proceedings against any persons concerned, or supposed to be concerned, in any offence which he has investigated.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
