<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1965/05/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1965/05"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Maharashtra Official Languages Act, 1964"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1965/05/eng@2017-02-28/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1965/05/eng@2017-02-28"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-02-28" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1965/05/eng@2017-02-28/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1965/05/eng@2017-02-28"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-02-28" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Maharashtra Official Languages Act, 1964</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>(ACT NO. 5 of 1965)</p>
      </longTitle>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[11th January, 1965]</docDate>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>An Act to provide for the adoption of languages which may be used for the official purposes of the State including purposes of the Legislature of the State.</p>
      <p>WHEREAS, it is expedient to provide for the adoption of languages which may be used for the official purposes of the State including purposes of the Legislature of the State; It is hereby enacted in the Fifteenth Year of the Republic of India as follows:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Maharashtra Official Languages Act, 1964.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Maharashtra.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This section and section 3 shall come into force on the 26th day of January 1965; and the remaining provisions of this Act shall come into force on such date as the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint; and different dates may be appointed for different provisions of this Act or different matters referred to in those provisions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1A">
        <num>1A.</num>
        <heading>Marathi to be the official language of State.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The official language of the State of Maharashtra shall be Marathi.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context requires otherwise,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"appointed day" in relation to section 3 means the 26th day of January 1965; and in relation to any other provision of this Act or any such provision in relation to any matter therein means the day on which that provision or any provision in relation to that matter comes into force;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"Constitution" means the Constitution of India;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>Marathi" means the Marathi language in Devnagari script which is adopted in the State under Government Resolutions issued, from time to time.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Continuance of English language for use in State Legislature</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding the expiration of the period of fifteen years from the commencement of the Constitution mentioned in article 210, the English language may, as from the appointed day, continue to be used, in addition to Hindi and Marathi, for transaction of business in the Legislature of the State.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Official language for official purposes of State</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act, Marathi shall, as from the appointed day, be the language to be used for all official purposes referred to in article 345 of the Constitution, as respects the State of Maharashtra except such purposes as the State Government may, by rules issued from time to time in the Official Gazette, specify, and Hindi may be used as the official language for such excepted purposes.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Marathi language to be used in Bills, etc.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Marathi shall, as from the appointed day, be the language to be used-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in Bills introduced (or amendments thereto to be moved) in either House of the Legislature of the State;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in all Acts passed by the Legislature of the State and in all Ordinances promulgated by the Governor of Maharashtra under article 213 of the Constitution.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>in all orders, rules, regulations and bye-laws issued by the State Government under the Constitution or under any law made by Parliament or the Legislature of the State.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that the State Government may use the English language for the purposes of Clauses (a) to (c), if it is satisfied that it is necessary so to do under special circumstances or for technical reasons.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Powers to make rules</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of the State Legislature while it is in session for a total, period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session in which it is so laid in the session immediately following, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall from the date of publication of a notification in the Official Gazette of such decision have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity to anything previously done or omitted to be done under the rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
