<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-pun/act/2008/26/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-pun/act/2008/26"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Punjab Protection Of Medicare Service Persons And Medicare Service Institutions (Prevention Of Violence And Damage To Property) Act, 2008"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-pun/act/2008/26/eng@2017-01-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-pun/act/2008/26/eng@2017-01-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-24" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-pun/act/2008/26/eng@2017-01-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-pun/act/2008/26/eng@2017-01-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Punjab Protection Of Medicare Service Persons And Medicare Service Institutions (Prevention Of Violence And Damage To Property) Act, 2008</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[10th October, 2008]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[Act No. 26 of 2008]</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the protection of Medicare Service Persons and Medicare Service Institutions in the State of Punjab and for prevention of violence and damage to the property and for the matters connected</p>
        <p>therewith or incidental thereto.</p>
        <p>Be it enacted by the Legislature of the State of Punjab in the Fifty­ninth Year of the Republic of India as follows:­</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Punjab Protection of Medicare Service Persons and Medicare Service Institutions (Prevention of Violence and Damage to Property) Act, 2008.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force at once.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“Medicare Service Institution” means an institution, providing medicare service either in the Medicare Service Institution or through Mobile Medical Unit or by arranging medical camps, which is under the control of the Central Government or the State Government or a local body including any private hospital having facility of treatment of the sick and used for their reception or stay, any private maternity home, where women are usually received and accommodated for the purpose of confinement and ante-natal and post-natal care in connection with the child birth or anything connected therewith, and any private nursing home used or intended to be used for the reception and accommodation of persons suffering from any sickness, injury or infirmity whether of body or mind, and providing of treatment of nursing or both of them and includes convalescent home;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>“Medicare Service Person” in relation to a Medicare Service Institution, shall include,­­</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>Registered Medical Practitioner, Registered Practitioner and Practitioner, working in a Medicare Service Institution;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>Nurse;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>Auxiliary Nurse and Mid-wife;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>Nurse­dai;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.v">
                    <num>(v)</num>
                    <p>trained dai;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.vi">
                    <num>(vi)</num>
                    <p>Medical Student;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.vii">
                    <num>(vii)</num>
                    <p>Nursing Student;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.viii">
                    <num>(viii)</num>
                    <p>Para Medical Worker; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.ix">
                    <num>(ix)</num>
                    <p>other staff or workers directly or indirectly engaged by a Medicare Service Institution for providing the required services;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation.- For the purpose of this Act, the expressions Registered Medical Practitioner, Medical Practitioner, Practitioner, Nurse, Auxiliary Nurse and Midwife, and trained dai, shall have the same meanings, as assigned to them in the Punjab Medical Registration Act. 1916, the Punjab Nurses Registration Act, 1932, the Punjab Ayurvedic and Unani Practitioners Act, 1963 and the Punjab Homeopathic Practitioners Act. 1965;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“Medical Student” means a student, who is undergoing training or studies in medical profession;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>“Mobile Medical Unit” means an ambulance, equipped with medical equipment, used for providing medicare services;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>“Nursing Student” means a student, who is undergoing training or studies in nursing profession;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>“offender” means any person, who either by himself or as a member or leader of a group of persons or organization commits or attempts to commit or abets or incites the commission of violence;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>“Paramedical Worker” means a person, who assists the Medicare Service Person providing medicare services;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>“property” shall include both moveable and immoveable property; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>“violence” means any act, which causes or may cause any harm, injury or endanger life, obstruct or hinder any Medicare Service Person in the discharge of his duty in a Medicare Service Institution or damage to property in Medicare Service Institution.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition of violence.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any act of violence against a Medicare Service Person or damage to property in a Medicare Service Institution, shall be prohibited.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Penalty.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>An offender, who commits any act in contravention of the provisions of this Act, shall be punished with an imprisonment, which may extend to one year or with fine, which may extend to fifty thousand rupees or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Cognizance of offence.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any offence committed under this Act, shall be cognizable and non­bailable and shall be triable by the Court of Judicial Magistrate of the First Class.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Recovery of loss for the damage caused to the property.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In addition to the punishment as specified in section 4, the offender shall also be liable to pay a penalty of twice the amount of purchase price of medical equipment damaged or loss caused to the property, as may be determined by the Court referred to in section 5.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the offender has not paid the penalty, imposed under sub-section (1), the same shall be recoverable as arrears of land revenue.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Act not in derogation of any other law.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of this Act shall be in addition to the provisions of any other law, for the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
