<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-hmp/act/1981/11/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-hmp/act/1981/11"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Punjab Security of State (Himachal Pradesh Amendment) Act, 1980"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-hmp/act/1981/11/eng@1981-05-11/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-hmp/act/1981/11/eng@1981-05-11"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1981-05-11" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-hmp/act/1981/11/eng@1981-05-11/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-hmp/act/1981/11/eng@1981-05-11"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preamble>
      <p>An Act to amend the Punjab Security of State Act, 1953 (XII of 1953) as in force in the territories added to Himachal Pradesh under section 5 of the Punjab Re-organization Act, 1966 and as made applicable to the areas which comprised in Himachal Pradesh immediately before the first November, 1966, vide the Government of India Notification No. 4-6/60-Jud-II-UTL-10, dated 19/1/1960.</p>
      <p>Be it enacted by the Legislative Assembly of Himachal Pradesh in the Thirty-first Year of the Republic of India as follows:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Punjab Security of State (Himachal Pradesh Amendment). Act, 1980.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force at once.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Insertion of section 4A.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>After the existing section 4 of the Punjab Security of State Act, 1953 (12 of 1953), as in force in the territories added to Himachal Pradesh under section 5 of the Punjab Re-organization Act, 1966 (31 of 1966) and as made/applicable to the areas which comprised in Himachal Pradesh immediately before the 1st November, 1966 vide, the Government of India Notification No. 4/6/60-Jud-II-UTL-10, dated 19/1/1960, the following new section 4A along with its heading shall be inserted, namely,-</p>
            <p>"4A. Control of camps, drills, or parades.-</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may in the interest of public prohibit or impose such condition as may be necessary on the holding of, camps for performance of drill, parade or taking out processions etc., with or without arms or any article, weapons or implements capable of being used as arms by any class of persons or organizations whose activities are in the opinion of the of the State Government subversive of law and order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any contravention of an order made under this section shall be punishable with imprisonment which may extend to two years, or with fine, or with both."</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
