<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1954/28/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1954/28"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The High Court Judges (Salaries And Conditions Of Service) Act, 1954"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1954/28/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1954/28/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1954/28/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1954/28/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-02-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The High Court Judges (Salaries And Conditions Of Service) Act, 1954</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 28 OF 1954</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[20th. May, 1954.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to regulate salaries and certain conditions of service of the Judges of High Courts ***</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifth Year of the Republic of India as follows:—</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <heading>Preliminary</heading>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the High Court Judges (Salaries and Conditions of Service) Act, 1954.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-2.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>“acting Chief Justice” means a Judge appointed under article 223 of the Constitution to perform the duties of the Chief Justice;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>“acting Judge" means a person *** appointed to act as a Judge under sub-section (2) of section 222 of the Government of India Act, 1935 or under clause (2) of article 224 of the Constitution;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-2.1.list1.c.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>“actual service” includes—</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-2.1.list1.c.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>time spent by a Judge on duty as a Judge or in the performance of such other functions as he may, at the request of the President of India, undertake to discharge;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.1.list1.c.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>vacations, excluding any time during which the Judge is absent on leave;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.1.list1.c.list0.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>Joining time on transfer from a High Court to the Supreme Court or from one High Court to another or from the Supreme Court to a High Court;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.1.list1.c.list0.iv">
                      <num>(iv)</num>
                      <p>time spent by a Judge on duty as a Judge of a former Indian High Court;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.1.list1.c.list0.v">
                      <num>(v)</num>
                      <p>time spent by a Judge to attend the sittings of the Supreme Court as an ad hoc Judge under article 127 of the Constitution; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.1.list1.c.list0.vi">
                      <num>(vi)</num>
                      <p>vacation (excluding any time during which the Judge was absent on leave) taken by a Judge as a Judge of a former Indian High Court;</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>“additional Judge” means a person *** appointed as an additional Judge under sub-section (3) of section 222 of the Government of India Act, 1935 or under clause (1) of article 224 of the Constitution;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>“former Indian High Court” means the High Court at Rangoon, the High Court at Lahore, the Chief Court of Sind or the Judicial Commissioner‟s Court of North-West Frontier Province;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>“High Court” means a High Court for a State and includes a High Court which was exercising Jurisdiction in a Part A State or in the corresponding Province before the commencement of the Constitution;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>“Judge” means a Judge of a High Court and includes the Chief Justice an acting Chief Justice, an additional Judge and an acting Judge of the High Court;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.gg">
                  <num>(gg)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-2.1.list1.gg.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>“pension” means a pension of any kind whatsoever payable to or in respect of a Judge, and includes any gratuity or other sum or sums so payable by way of death or retirement benefits;(h) “service for pension” includes—</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-2.1.list1.gg.list1.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <blockList id="section-2.1.list1.gg.list1.i.list2">
                        <listIntroduction>actual service;</listIntroduction>
                        <item id="section-2.1.list1.gg.list1.i.list2.i">
                          <num>(i)</num>
                          <p>“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item id="section-2.1.list1.gg.list1.i.list2.ii">
                          <num>(ii)</num>
                          <p>the amount, actually taken, of each period of leave on full allowances at a rate equal to the monthly rate of the salary;(iii) joining time on return from leave out of India;</p>
                        </item>
                      </blockList>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the calculation of service for the purposes of this Act, previous service for any period or periods as acting Judge or additional Judge or as a Judge of a former Indian High Court shall be reckoned as service as a Judge but, save as otherwise expressly provided, previous service as an acting Chief Justice shall not be reckoned as service as Chief Justice.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any period of leave taken by a Judge before the commencement of this Act under the rules then applicable to him as an acting Judge, additional Judge or a Judge shall, for the purposes of this Act, be treated as if it were leave taken by him under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any period of leave taken by a Judge while serving as a Judge of a former Indian High Court before his appointment to a High Court shall for the purposes of this Act be treated as if it were leave taken by him under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <heading>Leave</heading>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Kinds of leave admissible to a judge.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Subject to the provisions of this Act, leave granted to a Judge may be at his option either—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>leave on full allowances (including commuted leave on half allowances into leave or full allowances on medical certificate); or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>leave on half allowances; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>leave partly on full allowances and partly on half allowances.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purposes of this Chapter, any period of leave on full allowances shall be reckoned as double that period of leave on half allowances.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Leave account showing the amount of leave due.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A leave account shall be kept for each Judge showing therein the amount of leave due to him in terms of leave on half allowances.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-4.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In the leave account of a Judge—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-4.2.list1.a.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>there shall be credited to him—</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-4.2.list1.a.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>one-fourth of the time spent by him on actual service; ***</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-4.2.list1.a.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>where the Judge, by reason of his having been detained for the performance of duties not connected with the High Court, cannot enjoy any vacation which would otherwise have been entitled to enjoy had he not been so detained, as compensation for the vacation not enjoyed, a period equal to double the period by which the vacation enjoyed by him in any year falls short of one month; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-4.2.list1.a.list0.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>where the Judge had, prior to his appointment as such, held any pensionable post under the Union or a State, the period of leave earned by him in the said post, and</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>there shall be debited to him all leave with all by him.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4A">
          <num>4A.</num>
          <heading>Leave encashment.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4A.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>A Judge shall be entitled in his entire service, including the period of service rendered in a pensionable post under the Union or State or on re-employment, if any, to claim the cash equivalent of leave salary on his retirement in respect of the period of earned leave at his credit, to the extent of the maximum period prescribed for encashment of such leave under the All India Service (Leave) Rules, 1955.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Aggregate amount of leave which may be granted.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The aggregate amount of leave which may be granted to a Judge during the whole period of his service as such shall not exceed in terms of leave on half allowances three years together with the aggregate of the periods, if any, credited to his leave account under sub-section (2) (a) (ii) of section 4 as compensation for vacation not enjoyed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The aggregate amount of leave on full allowances which may be granted to a Judge during the whole period of his service as such shall not exceed one-twenty-fourth of the period spent by him on actual service together with one-half of the aggregate periods, if any, credited to his leave account under sub-section (2) (a) (ii) of section 4 as compensation for vacation not enjoyed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of sub-section (2) of section 5A, the maximum period of leave which may be granted at one time shall be, in the case of leave on full allowances, five months and in the case of leave with allowances of any kind, sixteen months.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5A">
          <num>5A.</num>
          <heading>Commutation of leave on half allowances into leave on full allowances.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5A.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (2) of section 5, a Judge may be permitted to commute leave on half allowances into leave on full allowances on medical certificate up to a maximum of three months during the whole period of his service as a Judge.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5A.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In computing the maximum period of leave on full allowances which may be granted at one time to Judge under sub-section (3) of section 5, the amount of commuted leave permitted to him under this section shall not be taken into account.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Grant of leave not due.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Subject to the maximum limit specified in sub-section (1) of section 5, leave on half allowances may be granted to a Judge in excess of the amount at his credit—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>on medical certificate; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>otherwise than on medical certificate, for not more than six months or for two or more periods, not exceeding in the aggregate, six months during the whole period of his service as a Judge:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that no such leave shall be granted if the Judge is not expected to return to duty at the end of such leave and earn the leave granted.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Special disability leave.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The rules for the time being in force with respect to the grant of special disability leave in relation to an officer of the Central Civil Services, Class I who has entered service on or after the 16th July, 1931 and who may be disabled by injury caused in, or in consequence of, the due performance of his official duties or in consequence of his official position, shall apply in relation to a Judge.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Extraordinary leave.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Extraordinary leave may be granted to a Judge for a period not exceeding six months, or for two or more periods, not exceeding in the aggregate, six months during the whole period of his service as a Judge in excess of any leave permissible under the foregoing provisions of this Chapter, but no salary or allowances shall be payable during, or in respect of, such leave.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Leave allowances.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The monthly rate of leave allowances payable to a Judge while on leave on full allowances shall be for the first forty-five days of such leave a rate equal to the monthly rate of his salary, and thereafter in the case of the Chief Justice, fifty-five per cent. of the monthly rate of his salary and in the case of each of the other Judges, sixty per cent. of the monthly rate of his salary.</p>
              <p>Provided that where leave on full allowances is granted to a Judge on medical certificate, the monthly rate of leave allowances shall, for the first one hundred and twenty days of such leave, be a rate equal to the monthly rate of his salary.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The monthly rate of leave allowances payable to a Judge while on leave on half allowances shall be ,in the case of the Chief Justice, twenty-seven and a half per cent. of the monthly rate of his salary and in the case of each of the other Judges, thirty per cent. of the monthly rate of his salary.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Allowances for joining time.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>There shall be payable to a Judge in respect of joining time on his return from leave out of India an allowance at the rate of one thousand one hundred and ten rupees a month in lieu of salary.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Combining leave with vacation.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>A Judge may be permitted to combine vacation on full salary with leave, if.—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>where the vacation consists of one continuous period, the leave is taken either at the commencement or at the end of the vacation but not a both;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>where the vacation is divided into two separate periods, the leave is taken for the interval, or part of the interval, between the two periods of that vacation, or for the interval, or part of the interval, between the second period of that vacation and the commencement of the next ensuing vacation:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that no such permission to combine vacation with leave shall be granted if it becomes necessary to appoint an acting Chief Justice during the period of vacation or if the Judge is not expected to return to duty at the end of such leave.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Consequences of overstaying leave or vacation.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>If a Judge overstays his leave or any vacation, whether combined with leave or not, he shall receive no salary for the period of his absence in excess of leave granted to him or beyond the end of the vacation, as the case may be:</p>
              <p>Provided that if such absence is due to circumstances beyond his control, the period thereof may be treated as leave and may be debited to his leave account.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Authority competent to grant leave, etc.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The authority competent to grant or refuse leave to a Judge or revoke or curtail leave granted to a Judge shall be the Governor of the State in which the principal seat of the High Court is situate, after consultation with the Chief Justice of that High Court.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <heading>Salaries and pensions</heading>
        <section id="section-13A">
          <num>13A.</num>
          <heading>Salaries of the Judges.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-13A.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>There shall be paid to the Chief Justice of a High Court, by way of salary, ninety thousand rupees per mensem. (2) There shall be paid to a Judge of a High Court, by way of salary, eighty thousand rupees per mensem.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Pension payable to Judges.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act, every Judge shall, on his retirement, be paid a pension in accordance with the scale and provisions in Part I of the First Schedule:</p>
              <blockList id="section-14.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that no such pension shall be payable to a Judge unless—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>he has completed not less than twelve years of service for pension; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>he has attained the age of sixty-two years, and, in the case of a Judge holding office on the 5th day of October, 1963, sixty years; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>his retirement is medically certified to be necessitated by ill-health:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided further that if a Judge at the time of his appointment is in receipt of a pension (other than a a disability or wound pension) in respect of any previous service in the Union or a State, the pension payable under this Act shall be in lieu of, and not in addition to, that pension.Explanation. —In this section Judge‟ means a Judge who is not member of the Indian Civil Service or has not held any other pensionable post under the Union or a State and includes a Judge who being a a member of the Indian Civil Service or having held any other pensionable post under the Union or a State has elected to receive the pension payable under Part I of the First Schedule.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Special provision of pension in respect of Judges who are members of service.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-15.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-15.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Every Judge—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-15.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>who is a member of the Indian Civil Service shall, on his retirement, be paid a pension in accordance with the scale and provisions in Part II of the First Schedule;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-15.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>who is not a member of the Indian Civil Service but has held any other pensionable post under the Union or a State, shall on his retirement, be paid a pension in accordance with the scale and provisions in Part III of the First Schedule:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that every such Judge shall elect to receive the pension payable to him either under Part I of the First Schedule or, as the case may be, Part II or Part III of the First Schedule, and the pension payable to him shall be calculated accordingly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), any Judge to whom that sub-section applies and who is in service on or after the 1st day of October, 1974, may, if he has elected under the proviso to that sub-section to receive the pension payable to him under Part II or, as the case may be, Part III of the First Schedule before the date on which the High Court Judges (Conditions of Service) Amendment Act, 1976 (35 of 1976) receives the assent of the President, cancel such election and elect afresh to receive the pension payable to him under Part I of the First Schedule and any such Judge who dies before the date of such assent shall be deemed to have elected afresh to be governed by the provisions of the said Part I if the provisions of that Part are more favourable in his case.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Power of President to add to the service for pension.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The President of India may for special reasons direct that any period not exceeding three months shall be added to the service for pension of a Judge:</p>
              <p>Provided that the period so added shall be disregarded in calculating any additional pension under Part I or Part II or Part III of the First Schedule.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Extraordinary pensions.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The rules for the time being in force with respect to the grant of extraordinary pensions and gratuities in relation to an officer of the Central Civil Services, Class I who has entered service on or after the 1st April, 1937 and who may suffer injury or die as a result of violence, shall apply in relation to a Judge, subject, however, to the modification that references in those rules to tables of injury, gratuities and pensions and of family gratuities and pensions, shall be construed as references to the tables in the Second Schedule.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17A">
          <num>17A.</num>
          <heading>Family pensions and gratuities.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17A.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where a Judge who, being in service on or after the commencement of the High Court and Supreme Court Judges (Conditions of Service) Amendment Act, 1986 (38 of 1986), dies, whether before or after retirement in circumstances to which section 17 does not apply, family pension calculated at the rate of fifty per cent. of his salary *** on the date of his death shall be payable to the person or persons entitled thereto and the amount so payable shall be paid from the day following the date of death of the Judge for a period of seven years or for a period up to the date on which the Judge would have attained the age of sixty-five years, had he survived, whichever is earlier, and thereafter at the rate of thirty per cent of his salary ***.</p>
              <p>Provided that in no case the amount of family pension calculated under this sub-section shall exceed exceed the pension payable to the Judge under this Act.</p>
              <p>Explanation.—</p>
              <blockList id="section-17A.1.list4">
                <listIntroduction>For the purposes of determining the person or persons entitled to family pension under this sub-section,—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17A.1.list4.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>in relation to a Judge who elects or is eligible to receive pension under Part I of the First Schedule, the rules, notifications and orders for the time being in force with regard to the person or persons entitled to family pension in relation to an officer of the Central Civil Services, Group A‟, shall apply;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17A.1.list4.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>in relation to a Judge who elects to receive pension under Part II or Part III of the First Schedule, the ordinary rules of his service if he had not been appointed a Judge with respect to the person or persons entitled to family pension shall apply and his service as a Judge being treated as service therein.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17A.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where any Judge, who has elected to receive the pension payable to him under Part II or Part III of the First Schedule, retires, or dies in circumstances to which section 17 does not apply, gratuity, if any, shall be payable to the person or persons entitled thereto under the ordinary rules of his service if he had not been appointed a Judge, his service as a Judge being treated as service therein for the purpose of calculating that gratuity.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17A.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-17A.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The rules, notifications and orders for the time being in force with respect to the grant of death-cum-retirement gratuity benefit to or in relation to an officer of the Central Civil Services, Class I (including the provisions relating to deductions from pension for the purpose) shall apply to or in relation to the grant of death-cum-retirement gratuity benefit to or in relation to a Judge who, being in service on or after the 1st day of October, 1974, retires, or dies in circumstances to which section 17 does not apply, subject to the modifications that—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17A.3.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the minimum qualifying service for the purpose of entitlement to the gratuity shall be two years and six months;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17A.3.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>the amount of gratuity shall be calculated on the basis of ten days salary for each completed six months period of service as a Judge; ***</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Explanation.—</p>
              <p>In sub-section (3), the expression “Judge” has the same meaning as in section 14.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17B">
          <num>17B.</num>
          <heading>Additional quantum of pension or family pension.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-17B.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every retired Judge or after his death, the family, as the case may be, shall be entitled to an additional quantum of pension or family pension in accordance with the following scale:—</p>
              <table id="section-17B.paragraph-0.table1">
                <tr>
                  <td>
                    <p>Age of Pensioner or family Pensioner</p>
                  </td>
                  <td>
                    <p>Additional quantum of pension or family pension.</p>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>
                    <p>From eighty years to less than eighty-five years</p>
                  </td>
                  <td>
                    <p>Twenty per cent. of basic pension or family pension</p>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>
                    <p>From eighty-five years to less than ninety years</p>
                  </td>
                  <td>
                    <p>Thirty per cent. of basic pension or family pension</p>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>
                    <p>From ninety years to less than ninety-five years</p>
                  </td>
                  <td>
                    <p>Forty per cent. of basic pension or family pension</p>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>
                    <p>From ninety-five years to less than hundred years</p>
                  </td>
                  <td>
                    <p>Fifty per cent. of basic pension or family pension</p>
                  </td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>
                    <p>From hundred years or more pension</p>
                  </td>
                  <td>
                    <p>Hundred per cent. of basic pension or family</p>
                  </td>
                </tr>
              </table>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Conversion of sterling pension into rupees.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Pensions expressed in sterling only shall, if paid in India, be converted into rupees at such rate of exchange as the Central Government may, from time to time, specify in this behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Commutation of Pensions.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Civil Pensions (Commutation) Rules for the time being in force shall, with necessary modifications, apply to Judges.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Provided Fund.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every Judge shall be entitled to subscribe to the General Provident Fund (Central Services):</p>
              <p>Provided that a Judge who is a member of the Indian Civil Service or has held any other pensionable civil post under the Union or a State shall continue to subscribe to the Provident Fund to which he was subscribing before his appointment as a Judge:</p>
              <p>Provided further that a Judge who was appointed before the commencement of this Act may continue to subscribe to the Provident Fund to which he was subscribing immediately before such commencement.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20A">
          <num>20A.</num>
          <heading>Deposit Linked Insurance Scheme.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-20A.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Deposit Linked Insurance Scheme for the time being in force under the General Provident Fund (Central Services) Rules, 1960, shall apply to every Judge whether he subscribes to the General Provident Fund (Central Services) or any other Provident Fund referred to in section 20.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Authority competent to grant pension.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Save as may be otherwise expressly provided in the relevant rules relating to the grant of extraordinary pensions and gratuities, the authority competent to grant pension to a Judge under the provisions of this Act shall be the President of India.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <heading>Miscellaneous</heading>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Travelling allowances to a Judge.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every Judge shall receive such reasonable allowances to reimburse him for expenses incurred in travelling on duty within the territory of India and shall be afforded such reasonable facilities in connection with travelling as may, from time to time, be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22A">
          <num>22A.</num>
          <heading>Facility of rent-free houses.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-22A.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every Judge shall be entitled without payment of rent to the use of an official residence in accordance with such rules as may, from time to time, be made in this behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22A.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where a Judge does not avail himself of the use of an official residence, he may be paid every month an allowance equivalent to an amount to thirty per cent. of the salary ***.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22B">
          <num>22B.</num>
          <heading>Conveyance facilities.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-22B.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every Judge shall be entitled to a staff car and two hundred litres of fuel every month or the actual consumption of fuel per month, whichever is less.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22C">
          <num>22C.</num>
          <heading>Sumptuary allowance.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-22C.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Chief Justice and each of the other Judges of every High Court shall be entitled to a sumptuary allowance of fifteen thousand rupees per month and twelve thousand rupees per month respectively.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22D">
          <num>22D.</num>
          <heading>Exemption from liability to pay income-tax on certain perquisites received by a Judge.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-22D.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-22D.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Income-tax Act, 1961 (43 of 1961),—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-22D.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the value of rent-free official residence provided to a Judge under sub-section (1) of section 22A or the allowance paid to him under sub-section (2) of that section;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-22D.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the value of the conveyance facilities provided to a Judge under section 22B;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-22D.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the sumptuary allowance provided to a Judge under section 22C; (d) the value of leave travel concession provided to a judge and members of his family,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>shall not be included in the computation of his income chargeable under the head “Salaries” under section 15 of the Income- tax Act 1961 (43 of 1961).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Facilities for medical treatment and other conditions of service.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-23.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every Judge and the members of his family shall be entitled to such facilities for medical treatment and for accommodation in hospitals as may, from time to time, be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The conditions of service of a Judge for which no express provision has been made in this Act shall be such as may be determined by rules made under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This section shall be deemed to have come into force on the 26th January, 1950 and any rule made under this section may be made so as to be retrospective to any date not earlier than the commencement of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23A">
          <num>23A.</num>
          <heading>Vacation of High Courts.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-23A.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every High Court shall have a vacation or vacations for such period or periods as may, from time to time, be fixed by the President, by order notified in this behalf in the Official Gazette, and every such order shall have effect notwithstanding anything contained in any other law, rule or order regulating the vacation of the High Court.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23A.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every order made under sub-section (1) shall be laid before each House of Parliament.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23B">
          <num>23B.</num>
          <heading>Special provisions in respect of continuing Judges.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-23B.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the calculation of the service for pension of a continuing Judge for the purposes of this act, his previous service for pension as a Chief Justice or as a Judge of a former High Court in a Part B State, under the provisions of the High Court Judges (Part B States) Order, 1953, or any other order or rule then applicable to him, shall be reckoned as service for pension as a Chief Justice or, as the case may be, as a Judge under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23B.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the calculation of the amount of leave at the credit of a continuing Judge for the purposes of this Act, the amount of leave due to him immediately before the 1st day of November, 1956, under the provisions of the High Court Judges (Part B States) Order, 1953, or any order or rule then applicable to him, shall be added to the amount of leave at his credit under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23B.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In this section, “continuing Judge” means a Judge of a former High Court in a Part B State who on the 1 day of November, 1956, or on any date subsequent thereto has become or been appointed as a Judge of a High Court for a State.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23C">
          <num>23C.</num>
          <heading>Special provisions in respect of Judges transferred from the High Court of Jammu and Kashmir.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-23C.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the calculation of service for pension of a Judge of the High Court of Jammu and Kashmir transferred to any other High Court, his service for pension as a Judge of the High Court of Jammu and Kashmir shall also be reckoned as service for pension under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23C.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the calculation of the amount of leave at the credit of a Judge of the High Court of Jammu and Kashmir transferred to any other high Court, the amount of leave due to him as a Judge of the High Court of Jammu and Kashmir shall be added to the amount of leave at his credit under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23D">
          <num>23D.</num>
          <heading>Medical facilities for retired Judges.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-23D.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every retired Judge shall, with effect from the date on which the High Court Judges (Conditions of Service) Amendment Act, 1976 (35 of 1976) receives the assent of the President, be entitled, for himself and his family, to the same facilities as respects medical treatment and on the same conditions as a retired officer of the Central Civil Services, Class I, and his family, are entitled under any rules and orders of the Central Government for the time being in force.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23D.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1) but subject to such conditions and restrictions as the Central Government may impose, a retired Judge of the High Court for a State may avail, for himself and his family, any facilities for medical treatment which the Government of that State may extend to him.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-24.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-24.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-24.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-24.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>leave of absence of a Judge;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-24.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>pension payable to a Judge;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-24.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>travelling allowances to a Judge;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-24.2.list1.ca">
                  <num>(ca)</num>
                  <p>use of official residence by a Judge under sub-section (1) of section 22A;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-24.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>facilities for medical treatment and other conditions of service of a Judge;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-24.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>any other manner which has to be, or may be, prescribed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-24.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Savings.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-25.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing contained in this Act shall have effect so as to give to a Judge who is serving as such at the commencement of this Act less favourable terms in respect of his allowances or his rights in respect of leave of absence (including leave allowances) or pension than those to which he would be entitled if this Act had not been passed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing contained in this Act, as amended by the High Court Judges (Conditions of Service) Amendment Act, 1958 (46 of 1958), shall have effect so as to give to a Chief Justice or a Judge of a former High Court in a Part B State less favourable terms in respect of his allowances) or his rights in respect of leave of absence (including the leave allowances) or pension than those to which he would be entitled under the High Court Judges (Part B States) Order, 1953, or any other order or rule then applicable to him, if he had continued as a Judge of that High Court, his service as a Judge on or after the 1st day of November, 1956, being treated as service in that High Court.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-thefirstschedule">
      <doc name="thefirstschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1954/28/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1954/28"/>
              <FRBRalias value="THE FIRST SCHEDULE"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1954/28/eng@1980-01-01/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1954/28/eng@1980-01-01"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1954/28/eng@1980-01-01/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1954/28/eng@1980-01-01"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-02-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="thefirstschedule">
            <heading>(See sections 14 and 15)</heading>
            <paragraph id="thefirstschedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>PENSIONS OF JUDGES</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <part id="part-I">
              <num>I</num>
              <subsection id="part-I.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The provisions of this Part apply to a Judge who is not a member of the Indian Civil Service or has not held any other pensionable post under the Union or a State and also apply to a Judge who, being a member of the Indian Civil Service or having held any other pensionable post under the Union or a State, has elected to receive the pension payable under this Part.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="part-I.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="part-I.2.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>Subject to the other provisions of this Part, the pension payable to a Judge to whom this Part applies and who has Completed not less than seven years of service for pension shall be,—</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="part-I.2.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>for service as Chief Justice in any High Court, Rs.43,890 per annum for each completed year of service;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="part-I.2.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>for service as any other Judge in any High Court, Rs.34,350 per annum for each completed year of service:</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Provided that the pension under this paragraph shall in no case exceed Rs. 5,40,000 per annum in the case of a Chief Justice and Rs. 4,80,000 per annum in the case of any other Judge.</p>
                  <p>***</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="part-I.6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A Judge who has rendered service for pension both as Chief Justice and other Judge in any High Court may claim that any period of service of less than a completed year rendered by him as Chief Justice, or any portion of any such period, shall be treated for the purposes of paragraph 2 as service rendered by him as other Judge.7. For the purposes of this Part, service as an acting Chief Justice of a High Court or as an ad hoc Judge of the Supreme Court, shall be treated as though it were service rendered as Chief Justice of a High Court.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="part-I.8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing provisions of this Part, the pension payable to a Judge who has completed fourteen years of service for pension, including not less than six years of service as Chief Justice of one or more of the High Courts, shall be Rs. 5,40,000 per annum.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="part-I.9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="part-I.9.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>Where a Judge to whom this Part applies retires or has retired at any time after the 26th January, 1950 without being eligible for a pension under any other provision of this Part, then, notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing provisions, a pension of Rs. 1,57, 670 per annum shall be payable to such a Judge:</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="part-I.9.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>Provided that nothing in this paragraph shall apply—to an additional Judge or acting Judge; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="part-I.9.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>to a Judge who at the time of his appointment is in receipt of a pension (other than a disability or wound pension) in respect of any previous service under the Union or a State.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </part>
            <part id="part-II">
              <num>II</num>
              <subsection id="part-II.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The provisions of this Part apply to a Judge who is a member of the Indian Civil Service and who has not elected to receive the pension payable under Part I.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="part-II.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="part-II.2.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>The pension payable to such a Judge shall be—</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="part-II.2.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the pension to which he is entitled under the ordinary rules of the Indian Civil Service if he had not been appointed a Judge, his service as a Judge being treated as service therein for the purpose of calculating that pension; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="part-II.2.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>the additional pension, if any, to which he is entitled under paragraph 3;</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Provided that the pension under clause (a) and the additional pension under clause (b) together shall shall in no case exceed Rs. 5, 40,000 per annum in the case of a Chief Justice and Rs. 4, 80,000 per annum in the case of any other Judge.3. If such a Judge has completed not less than seven years of service for pension in a High Court, he shall be entitled to an additional pension in accordance with the following scale:—</p>
                  <p>Per annum.</p>
                  <p>For seven completed years of service for pension - 34,696</p>
                  <p>For eight completed years of service for pension - 41,642</p>
                  <p>For nine completed years of service for pension - 48,559</p>
                  <p>For ten completed years of service for pension - 55,508</p>
                  <p>For eleven completed years of service for pension - 62,462</p>
                  <p>For twelve or more completed years of service for pension - 69,402</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </part>
            <part id="part-III">
              <num>III</num>
              <subsection id="part-III.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The provisions of this Part apply to a Judge who has held any pensionable post under the Union or a State (but is not a member of the Indian Civil Service) and who has not elected to receive the pension payable under Part I.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="part-III.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="part-III.2.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>The pension payable to such a Judge shall be—</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="part-III.2.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the pension to which he is entitled under the ordinary rules of his service if he had not been appointed a Judge, his service as a Judge being treated as service therein for the purpose of a calculating that pension; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="part-III.2.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>a special additional pension of Rs. 16,020 per annum in respect of each completed year of service for pension, ***</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Provided that the pension under clause (a) and the additional pension under clause (b) together shall shall in no case exceed Rs. 5,40, 000 per annum in the case of a Chief Justice and Rs.4,80,000 per annum in the case of any other Judge.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </part>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-thesecondschedule">
      <doc name="thesecondschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1954/28/thesecondschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1954/28"/>
              <FRBRalias value="The Second Schedule"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1954/28/eng@1980-01-01/thesecondschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1954/28/eng@1980-01-01"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1954/28/eng@1980-01-01/thesecondschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1954/28/eng@1980-01-01"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-02-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="thesecondschedule">
            <heading>(See section 17)</heading>
            <paragraph id="thesecondschedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>INJURY GRATUITIES AND PENSIONS</p>
                <table id="thesecondschedule.paragraph-0.table1">
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>Officer</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Gratuity</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Annual Pension</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Higher Scale</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Lower Scale</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs.</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs.</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>1. Chief Justice</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>20,000</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>5,400</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>4,700</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>2. Any other Judge</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>13,500</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>4,700</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>4,000</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </table>
                <p>FAMILY GRATUITIES AND PENSIONS</p>
                <p>A. Widow</p>
                <table id="thesecondschedule.paragraph-0.table4">
                  <tr>
                    <th>
                      <p>Officer</p>
                    </th>
                    <td>
                      <p>Gratuity</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Annual Pension</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs.</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>1. Chief Justice</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>15,000</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>5,000</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>2. Any other Judge</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>13,500</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>4,000</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </table>
                <p>B. Children</p>
                <table id="thesecondschedule.paragraph-0.table6">
                  <tr>
                    <th>
                      <p>Officer</p>
                    </th>
                    <td>
                      <p>Annual Pension</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>If motherless</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>If not motherless</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs.</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>1. Chief Justice</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>550</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>320</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>2. Any other Judge</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>550</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>320</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </table>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
