<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-odi/act/1952/24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-odi/act/1952/24"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Orissa Restriction Of Habitual Offenders Act, 1952"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-odi/act/1952/24/eng@2017-01-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-odi/act/1952/24/eng@2017-01-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-odi/act/1952/24/eng@2017-01-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-odi/act/1952/24/eng@2017-01-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Orissa Restriction Of Habitual Offenders Act, 1952</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[Act No.24 of 1952]</p>
        <p>An Act to impose certain restrictions on habitual offenders in the State of Orissa;</p>
        <p>Whereas it is expedient to impose certain restrictions on habitual offenders in the State of Orissa ;</p>
        <p>It is hereby enacted as follows:</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Orissa Restriction of Habitual Offenders Act, 1952.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Orissa.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force at once.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context­</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"habitual offender" means a person who has been sentenced to substantive terms of imprisonment whether before or after the commencement of the Act­</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>i. for one or the other of the offences in Schedule I on two occasions;</p>
            <p>ii. for one or the other of the offences in Schedule II on three occasions;</p>
            <p>iii. for one of the offences in Schedule I and one of the offences in Schedule II on two occasions;</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation - Any order made requiring a person to give security for good behaviour with reference to Section 110 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (V of 1898), shall amount to the passing of a sentence of substantive imprisonment for one or other of the offences under the Indian Penal Code, 1860 (XLV of 1860), as specified in Schedule II within the meaning of this clause;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"notified offender" means a habitual offender in respect of whom a notification has been issued under Section 3 and is in force;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>"prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>"settlement" means a settlement established or deemed to have been established under Section 7.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Power to notify habitual offenders</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The District Magistrate if satisfied that any person is a habitual offender may, for reasons to be recorded in writing, by notification­</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>declare that he shall be subject to the provisions of this Act to such extent and subject to such restrictions, if any, as may be specified in the notification;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>cancel or modify any such declaration.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Before any notification is issued in respect of any person under Clause (a) of Sub¬section (1) or modified to his disadvantage under Clause (b) of the said sub¬section, a reasonable opportunity shall be given to him to show cause against such issue or modification, as the case may be:</p>
            <p>Provided that if the District Magistrate is satisfied, for reasons to be recorded by him in writing, that it is not reasonably practicable to give to any person, as aforesaid, an opportunity of showing cause, he may issue or, as the case may be, modify such notification without giving such opportunity:</p>
            <p>Provided further that when a notification is issued in respect of any person without giving him a reasonable opportunity of showing cause, it shall be notified by a proclamation published in such manner as the District Magistrate may by order direct and a copy thereof shall be affixed at such place or places as may be specified in that order for conveying the information to such person :</p>
            <p>Provided also that issue of such a notification shall not preclude such person from showing cause at any time thereafter.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may cancel any notification issued under Sub¬section (1) or modify the same on the application of a person affected by the same or without such an application.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Notified offenders to intimate residence and change of residence</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>As soon as a person is notified as habitual offender he shall­</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>report himself at such intervals and notify his place of residence and any change or intended change of residence and any absence or intended absence from his residence in such manner and to such authority as may be prescribed ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>allow his finger impressions to be recorded by the prescribed authority:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that the District Magistrate or any officer authorised by him in this behalf may exempt any such offence or from reporting any temporary absence or intended absence from his residence, not exceeding such limit as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Power to restrict movements of notified offenders</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If in the opinion of the State Government it is expedient so to do, they may, by notification declare that any notified offender shall be restricted in his movements to a specified area.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Before making any such declaration, the State Government shall consider­</p>
            <p>i. the nature of the offences, if any, of which the offender has been convicted and the circumstances under which they were committed;</p>
            <p>ii. whether the offender employee himself in any lawful occupation and whether such occupation is a real one or merely a pretence for facilitating the commission of offences;</p>
            <p>iii. the suitability of the area to which his movements are to be restricted; and</p>
            <p>iv. the manner in which it is proposed that he should earn his living in such area and the adequacy of the arrangements therefore.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Power to cancel or alter such restrictions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification, cancel any declaration made under Section 5 or alter any area notified under that section:</p>
            <p>Provided that before issuing any such notification the State Government shall consider the matters referred to in Sub-section (2) of Section 5 in so far as they may be applicable.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Power to place notified offenders in settlements</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, for the purpose of this Act establish industrial, agricultural or reformatory settlement and may order any notified offender to be placed in any such settlement.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Power to discharge or transfer persons from settlements</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government or any officer authorised by them in this behalf may at any time by an order in writing, direct any notified offenders who may be in a settlement to be discharged of transferred to any other settlement.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Power to subject voluntary residents in settlements to restrictions and penalties</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by order, direct that any person voluntarily residing in any settlement shall be subject to all or any of the restrictions and penalties imposed by of under this Act on a notified offender placed in such settlement</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Penalties</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any notified offender who contravenes any of the provisions of this Act or any notification, rule or order made thereunder shall be punishable­</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>on a first conviction, with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to two hundred rupees, or with both;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>on a second or subsequent conviction, with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, or with both</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Arrest of notified offenders</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If a notified offender -</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>is found outside the area to which his movements have been restricted in contravention of the conditions under which he is permitted to leave such area; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>escapes from any settlement in which he has been placed,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>he may be arrested without warrant by any Police Officer, village headman or village watchman and taken before any Magistrate who, on proof of the facts, shall order him to be removed to such area or to such settlement, to be dealt with in accordance with the provisions of this Act and any rules made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Rules for the removal of prisoners to apply in certain cases</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every law or rule for the time being in force governing the removal of prisoners shall apply to all persons ordered to be placed in a settlement under Section 7 or to be removed under Section 8:</p>
            <p>Provided that no order from the State Government or the Inspector General of Prisons shall be necessary for the removal of such persons.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Bar of jurisdiction</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No Court shall question the validity of any notification or order, issued under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13A">
        <num>13A.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken under this Act</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any person for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any rule or order made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for or regulate­</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>all matters required or allowed by this Act to be prescribed;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the intervals manner and the authority to be prescribe under Section 4;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the restrictions to be observed under Section 5 by notified offenders in respect of whom notifications have been issued under Section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the grant of certificates of identity to notified offenders, and the inspection of such certificates;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the conditions under which notified offenders may be permitted to leave the area to which their movements are restricted or the places in which they are set­led;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the inspection of the residences of notified offenders;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the terms upon which notified offenders may be discharged from the operation of this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the management and supervision of settlements including the discipline and conduct of the persons placed in them; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the periodical review of the cases of all persons who have been placed in any settlement under this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All rules made under this section shall be published in the Gazette, and upon such publication shall have effect as if enacted in this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-schedulei">
      <doc name="schedulei">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-odi/act/1952/24/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-odi/act/1952/24"/>
              <FRBRalias value="­ SCHEDULE I"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-odi/act/1952/24/eng@2017-01-19/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-odi/act/1952/24/eng@2017-01-19"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-odi/act/1952/24/eng@2017-01-19/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-odi/act/1952/24/eng@2017-01-19"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-01-19" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="schedulei">
            <heading>[See Section 2 (a)]</heading>
            <paragraph id="schedulei.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>Sections of the Indian Penal Code</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <subsection id="schedulei.302">
              <num>(302)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Murder</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.304">
              <num>(304)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Culpable homicide not amounting to murder</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.307">
              <num>(307)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Attempt to murder</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.308">
              <num>(308)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Attempt to commit culpable homicide</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.311">
              <num>(311)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Being a thug</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.382">
              <num>(382)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Theft after preparation made for causing death, hurt or restraint in order to the committing of the theft</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.392">
              <num>(392)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Robbery</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.393">
              <num>(393)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Attempt to commit robbery</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.394">
              <num>(394)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Voluntarily causing hurt in committing robbery</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.395">
              <num>(395)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Dacoity</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.396">
              <num>(396)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Murder in Dacoit</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.397">
              <num>(397)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Robbery or Dacoity, with attempt to cause death or grievous hurt</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.398">
              <num>(398)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Attempt to commit robbery or Dacoity when armed with deadly weapon</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.399">
              <num>(399)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Making preparation to commit Dacoity</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.400">
              <num>(400)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Belonging to a gang of persona associated for habitually committing dacoity</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.401">
              <num>(401)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Belonging to a wandering gang of persons associated for the purpose of habitually committing theft</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.402">
              <num>(402)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Assembling for purpose of committing Dacoity</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.412">
              <num>(412)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Dishonestly receiving stolen property knowing that it was obtained by Dacoity</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.413">
              <num>(413)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Habitually dealing in stolen property</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.458">
              <num>(458)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Lurking House trespass or house¬breaking by night, after preparation for hurt, assault or wrongful restraint</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.459">
              <num>(459)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Grievous hurt caused whilst committing lurking house trespass or house¬breaking</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.460">
              <num>(460)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All persons jointly concerned in lurking House­trespass or housebreaking by night punishable where death or grievous­hurt is caused by one of them)</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-scheduleii">
      <doc name="scheduleii">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-odi/act/1952/24/scheduleii"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-odi/act/1952/24"/>
              <FRBRalias value="­ SCHEDULE II"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-odi/act/1952/24/eng@2017-01-19/scheduleii"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-odi/act/1952/24/eng@2017-01-19"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-odi/act/1952/24/eng@2017-01-19/scheduleii"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-odi/act/1952/24/eng@2017-01-19"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-01-19" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduleii">
            <heading>[See Section 2 (a)]</heading>
            <paragraph id="scheduleii.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>PART­I</p>
                <p>Sections of the Indian Penal Code</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.170">
              <num>(170)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Personating a public servant</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.171">
              <num>(171)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Wearing garb or carrying token used by public servant with fraudulent intent</p>
                <p>(231. Counterfeiting coin</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.232">
              <num>(232)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Counterfeiting Indian coin</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.233">
              <num>(233)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Making or selling instrument for counterfeiting coin</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.234">
              <num>(234)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Making or selling instrument for counterfeiting Indian coin</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.235">
              <num>(235)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Possession of instrument or material for the purpose of using the same for counterfeiting coin</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.239">
              <num>(239)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Delivery of coin, possessed with the knowledge that it is counterfeit</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.240">
              <num>(240)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Delivery of Indian coin possessed with the knowledge that it is counterfeit</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.242">
              <num>(242)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Possession of counterfeit coin by a person who knew it to be counterfeit when he became possessed thereof</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.243">
              <num>(243)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Possession of Indian coin by person who knew it to be counterfeit when he became possessed thereof</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.326">
              <num>(326)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Voluntarily causing grievous hurt by dangerous weapons or means</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.327">
              <num>(327)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Voluntarily causing hurt to extort property or to constrain to an illegal Act</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.328">
              <num>(328)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Causing hurt by means of poison, etc), with intent to commit an offence</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.329">
              <num>(329)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Voluntarily causing grievous hurt to extort property or to constrain to an illegal Act</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.332">
              <num>(332)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Voluntarily causing hurt to deter public servant from his duty</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.333">
              <num>(333)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Voluntarily causing grievous hurt to deter public servant from his duty</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.364">
              <num>(364)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Kidnapping or abducting in order to murder</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.367">
              <num>(367)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Kidnapping or abducting in order to subject person to grievous hurt slavery, etc)</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.369">
              <num>(369)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Kidnapping or abducting child under ten years with intent to steal from its person</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.370">
              <num>(370)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Buying or disposing of any person as a slave</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.371">
              <num>(371)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Habitual dealing in slaves</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.379">
              <num>(379)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Theft</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.380">
              <num>(380)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Theft in a building, tent or vessel</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.381">
              <num>(381)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Theft by clerk or servant of property in possession of master or employer</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.384">
              <num>(384)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Extortion</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.385">
              <num>(385)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Putting person in fear of injury in order to commit extortion</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.386">
              <num>(386)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Extortion by putting a person in fear of death or grievous hurt</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.387">
              <num>(387)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Putting person in fear of death or of grievous hurt in order to commit extortion</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.411">
              <num>(411)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Dishonestly receiving stolen property</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.414">
              <num>(414)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Assisting in concealment of stolen property</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.419">
              <num>(419)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Punishment for cheating by personation</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.420">
              <num>(420)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Cheating and dishonestly inducing delivery of property</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.454">
              <num>(454)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Lurking House­trespass or house¬breaking in order to commit offence punishable with imprisonment</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.456">
              <num>(456)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Punishment for lurking house trespass or house¬breaking by night</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.457">
              <num>(457)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Lurking House­trespass or house¬breaking by night in order to commit offence punishable with imprisonment</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.485">
              <num>(485)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Making or possession of any instrument for counterfeiting a property mark</p>
                <p>(489A Counterfeiting currency­notes or bank¬notes</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.489B">
              <num>(489B)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Using as genuine, forged or counterfeit currency­notes or banknotes</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.489C">
              <num>(489C)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Possession of forged or counterfeit currency­notes or banknotes</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.489D">
              <num>(489D)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Making or possessing instruments or materials forging or counterfeiting currency­notes or bank¬notes</p>
                <p>PART­II</p>
                <p>Sections of other laws</p>
                <p>Section 9 of the Opium Act, 1878 (1 of 1878)</p>
                <p>Section 5 of the Telegraph Wires (Unlawful Possession) Act, 1950 (74 of 1950)</p>
                <p>Section 16 of the Prevention of Food Adulteration Act, 1954 (37 of 1954)</p>
                <p>Section 7 of the Essential Commodities Act, 1955 (13 of 1955)</p>
                <p>Section 3 of the Railway Property (Unlawful Possession) Act, 1966 (29 of 1966)</p>
                <p>PART­III</p>
                <p>Offences under --</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Suppression of Immoral Traffic in Women and Girls Act. 1956 (10 of 1956)</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Orissa Prevention of Gambling Act, 1955 (Orissa Act 17 of 1955)</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Orissa (Scheduled Areas Money¬lenders) Regulation, 1967 (Orissa Regulation 2 of 1968)]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
