<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1975/23/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1975/23"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Karnataka Government Parks (Preservation) Act, 1975"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1975/23/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1975/23/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1975/23/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1975/23/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-27" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Karnataka Government Parks (Preservation) Act, 1975</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No. 23 of 1975</p>
        <p>An Act to make provision to ensure the preservation of certain Government parks in the State of Karnataka.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>WHEREAS it is expedient in public interest to preserve certain parks vested in the State Government in the State of Karnataka.</p>
      <p>BE it enacted by the Karnataka State Legislature in the Twenty-sixth Year of the Republic of India as follows :-</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Karnataka Government Parks (Preservation) Act, 1975.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force at once.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In this Act unless the context other-wise requires “Park” includes a garden or any land with or without building earmarked by the State Government for development and preservation as parks.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Application of the Act.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act shall apply to all lands and buildings within the limits of such parks belonging to the State Government as the State Government may, from time to time, by notification in the official Gazette, specify.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The notification referred to in sub-section (1) shall specify as nearly as possible, the situation and limits of such parks.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Preservation of parks.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be the duty of the State Government to preserve and maintain as horticultural gardens the parks to which this Act is applicable and take such action as may be necessary to improve the utility of such parks as such gardens.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No land or building within the parks to which this Act is applicable shall be alienated by way of sale, lease, gift, exchange, mortgage or otherwise or no licence for the use of any such land or building shall be granted and any alienation made or licence granted in contravention of this section shall be null and void:</p>
            <p>Provided that the restriction under this sub-section to lease shall not apply in the case of buildings existing on the date of coming force of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Permission in certain cases :-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in section 4, the State Government may subject to such conditions and restrictions as it may impose as regards construction, maintenance, management use and like matters alienate an area of,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>1223. sq. mtrs at Indira Gandhi Musical Fountain Park to the Bruhat Bangalore Mahanagara Palike for the purpose of widening of roads; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>1135. 18 sq. mtrs at Lalbagh gardens along the compound wall of west gate towards western side of the park (presently called R.V. Road) to Bangalore Metro Rail Corporation Limited for the purpose of construction of elevated Station for Metro Rail Project of Bangalore”</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>2126.71 sq.mtrs area of Cubbon Park located between Vidhana Soudha and Karnataka High Court Building, East: Park area of survey No. 1284; West: Survey No. 570; North: Park area in survey No. 1284 linking to the nursery and South: Park area of survey No. 1284 opposite to High Court;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>11,160 sq.mtrs area of Cubbon Park located between East: High Court of Karnataka in survey No. 1284; West: Existing Road between Vidhana Soudha, and High Court in the Cubbon Park area of survey No. 1284; North: General Post Office and South: Cubbon Park area of survey No. 1284.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>18028.35 Square meters between High Court Building and Old KGID Building surrounded by,-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>East: K.G.I.D. Building and High Court Building Security fence 120.65 meters.</p>
            <p>West: Ambedhakar Veedhi 170.68 meters.</p>
            <p>North: K.G.I.D. road to Ambedhakar Veedhi. 137.27 meters.</p>
            <p>South: High Court Building and Road leading from Ambedhakar Veedhi to High Court Building Security fence 170.42 meters.</p>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list7">
              <listIntroduction>to park the Vehicles of High Court Advocates and visitors.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list7.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>49 acres and 34 guntas (approximately) consisting of the buildings of Vidhana Soudha, Vikasa Soudha and other structures with the boundaries specified hereunder for the purposes of repairs and other developmental works,-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>North: Starting from Legislature House circle, running along the road and ending upto car parking gate.</p>
            <p>South: Vidhana Veedhi road starting from Lokayuktha office running along Gopala Gowda circle touching Police Timmaiah circle.</p>
            <p>East: Starting from Legislature circle, running along boundary wall of Rajbhavan and touching Police Timmaiah circle.</p>
            <p>West: Starting from Lokayukta office running along M.S. Building compound and ending at Parking gate.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
