<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1866/23/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1866/23"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Bombay High Court (Letters Patent) Act, 1866"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1866/23/eng@2017-03-20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1866/23/eng@2017-03-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-20" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1866/23/eng@2017-03-20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1866/23/eng@2017-03-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-20" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Bombay High Court (Letters Patent) Act, 1866</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[17th May, 1866]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>ACT No. XXIII of 1866</p>
        <p>An Act to correct two clerical errors in the Letters Patent for the High Court of Judicature for the Presidency of Bombay.</p>
        <p>Preamble.—</p>
        <p>WHEREAS, the twenty-second section of the Letters Patent for the High Court of Judicature for the Presidency of Bombay, dated the 28th December 1865, is as follows:— "And we do further ordain that the said High Court of Judicature at Bombay shall have ordinary original criminal jurisdiction within the local limits of its ordinary original civil jurisdiction, and also in respect of all such persons beyond such limits over whom the said High Court of Judicature at Fort William in Bengal shall have criminal jurisdiction at the date of the publication of these presents ;"</p>
        <p>And whereas it is expedient to correct the two clerical errors in such section which are hereinbefore indicated by italics;</p>
        <p>It is hereby enacted as follows:—</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Clause substituted for section 22 of revised Letters Patent of Bombay High Court.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In lieu of the said recited section, the following shall be substituted:—</p>
            <p>"and we do further ordain that the said High Court of Judicature at Bombay shall have ordinary original criminal jurisdiction within the local limits of its ordinary original civil jurisdiction, and also in respect of all persons beyond such limits over whom the said High Court of Judicature at Bombay shall have criminal Jurisdiction at the date of the publication of these presents."</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
