<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1956/33/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1956/33"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Inter-State River Water Disputes Act, 1956"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1956/33/eng@1956-08-28/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1956/33/eng@1956-08-28"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1956-08-28" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1956/33/eng@1956-08-28/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1956/33/eng@1956-08-28"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-11-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Inter-State River Water Disputes Act, 1956</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and extent. </heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Inter-State River Water Disputes Act, 1956.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India .</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>prescribed means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>Tribunal means a Water Disputes Tribunal constituted under section 4;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>water dispute means any dispute or difference between two or more State Governments with respect to</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>the use, distribution or control of the waters of, or in, any inter-State river or river valley; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>the interpretation of the terms of any agreement relating to the use, distribution or control of such waters or the implementation of such agreement; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>the levy of any water-rate in contravention of the prohibition contained in section 7.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Complaints by State Governments as to water disputes.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If it appears to the Government of any State that a water dispute with the Government of another State has arisen or is likely to arise by reason of the fact that the interests of the State, or of any of the inhabitants thereof, in the waters of an inter-State river or river valley have been, or are likely to be, affected prejudicially by</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any executive action or legislation taken or passed, or proposed to be taken or passed, by the other State; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the failure of the other State or any authority therein to exercise any of their powers with respect to the use, distribution or control of such waters; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the failure of the other State to implement the terms of any agreement relating to the use, distribution or control of such waters;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>the State Government may, in such form and manner as may be prescribed, request the Central Government to refer the water dispute to a Tribunal for adjudication.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of Tribunal. </heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When any request under section 3 is received from any State Government in respect of any water dispute and the Central Government is of opinion that the water dispute cannot be settled by negotiations, the Central Government shall, within a period not exceeding one year from the date of receipt of such request, by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute a Water Disputes Tribunal for the adjudication of the water dispute:</p>
            <p>Provided that any dispute settled by a Tribunal before the commencement of the Inter-State Water Disputes (Amendment) Act, 2002 shall not be re-opened.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Tribunal shall consist of a Chairman and two other members nominated in this behalf by the Chief Justice of India from among persons who at the time of such nomination are Judges of the Supreme Court or of a High Court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, in consultation with the Tribunal, appoint two or more persons as assessors to advise the Tribunal in the proceedings before it.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Adjudication of water disputes. </heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When a Tribunal has been constituted under section 4, the Central Government shall, subject to the prohibition contained in section 8, refer the water dispute and any matter appearing to be connected with, or relevant to, the water dispute to the Tribunal for adjudication.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Tribunal shall investigate the matters referred to it and forward to the Central Government a report setting out the facts as found by it and giving its decision on the matters referred to it within a period of three years:</p>
            <p>Provided that if the decision cannot be given for unavoidable reasons, within a period of three years, the Central Government may extend the period for a further period not exceeding two years.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If, upon consideration of the decision of the Tribunal, the Central Government or any State Government is of opinion that anything therein contained requires explanation or that guidance is needed upon any point not originally referred to the Tribunal, the Central Government or the State Government, as the case may be, within three months from the date of the decision, again refer the matter to the Tribunal for further consideration; and on such reference, the Tribunal may forward to the Central Government a further report within one year from the date of such reference giving such explanation or guidance as it deems fit and in such a case, the decision of the Tribunal shall be deemed to be modified accordingly:</p>
            <p>Provided that the period of one year within which the Tribunal may forward its report to the Central Government may be extended by the Central Government, for such further period as it considers necessary.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the members of the Tribunal differ in opinion on any point, the point shall be decided according to the opinion of the majority.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5A">
        <num>5A.</num>
        <heading>Filling of vacancies. </heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If, for any reason a vacancy (other than a temporary absence) occurs in the office of the Chairman or any other member of a Tribunal, such vacancy shall be filled by a person to be nominated in this behalf by the Chief Justice of India in accordance with the provisions of sub-section (2) of section 4, and the investigation of the matter referred to the Tribunal may be continued by the Tribunal after the vacancy is filled and from the stage at which the vacancy occurred.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Publication of decision of Tribunal. </heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government shall publish the decision of the Tribunal in the Official Gazette and the decision shall be final and binding on the parties to the dispute and shall be given effect to by them.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The decision of the Tribunal, after its publication in the Official Gazette by the Central Government under sub-section (1), shall have the same force as an order or decree of the Supreme Court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6A">
        <num>6A.</num>
        <heading>Power to make schemes to implement decision of Tribunal. </heading>
        <subsection id="section-6A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Without prejudice to the provisions of section 6, the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, frame a scheme or schemes whereby provision may be made for all matters necessary to give effect to the decision of a Tribunal.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6A.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A scheme framed under sub-section (1) may provide for</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6A.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the establishment of any authority (whether described as such or as a committee or other body) for the implementation of the decision or directions of the Tribunal;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6A.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the composition, jurisdiction, powers and functions of the authority, the term of office and other conditions of service of, the procedure to be followed by, and the manner of filling vacancies among the members of the authority;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6A.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the holding of a minimum number of meetings of the authority every year, the quorum for such meetings and the procedure thereat;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6A.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the appointment of any standing, ad hoc or other committees by the authority;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6A.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the employment of a Secretary and other staff by the authority, the pay and allowances and other conditions of service of such staff;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6A.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the constitution of a fund by the authority, the amounts that may be credited to such fund and the expenses to which the fund may be applied;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6A.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the form and the manner in which accounts shall be kept by the authority;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6A.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the submission of an annual report by the authority of its activities;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6A.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the decisions of the authority which shall be subject to review;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6A.2.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>the constitution of a committee for making such review and the procedure to be followed by such committee; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6A.2.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>any other matter which may be necessary or proper for the effective implementation of the decision or directions of the Tribunal.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In making provision in any scheme framed under sub-section (1) for the establishment of an authority for giving effect to the decision of a Tribunal, the Central Government may, having regard to the nature of the jurisdiction, powers and functions required to be vested in such authority in accordance with such decision and all other relevant circumstances, declare in the said scheme that such authority shall, under the name specified in the said scheme, have capacity to acquire, hold and dispose of property, enter into contracts, sue and be sued and do all such acts as may be necessary for the proper exercise and discharge of its jurisdiction, powers and functions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6A.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A scheme may empower the authority to make, with the previous approval of the Central Government, regulations for giving effect to the purposes of the scheme.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6A.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, add to, amend, or vary, any scheme framed under sub-section (1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6A.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every scheme framed under this section shall have effect notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time being in force (other than this Act) or any instrument having effect by virtue of any law other than this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6A.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every scheme and every regulation made under a scheme shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the scheme or the regulation or both Houses agree that the scheme or the regulation should not be made, the scheme or the regulation shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that scheme or regulation.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition of levy of seigniorage, etc. </heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No State Government shall, by reason only of the fact that any works for the conservation, regulation or utilisation of water resources of an inter-State river have been constructed within the limits of the State, impose, or authorize the imposition of, any seigniorage or additional rate or fee (by whatever name called) in respect of the use of such water by any other State of the inhabitants thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any dispute or difference between two or more State Governments with respect to the levy of any water rate in contravention of the prohibition contained in sub-section (1) shall be deemed to be a water dispute.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Bar of reference of certain disputes to Tribunal. </heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in section 3 or section 5, no reference shall be made to a Tribunal of any dispute that may arise regarding any matter which may be referred to arbitration under the River Boards Act, 1956.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Powers of Tribunal. </heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Tribunal shall have the same powers as are vested in a Civil Court under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), in respect of the following matters, namely:</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person and examining him on oath;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-9.1.list1.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>requiring the discovery and production of documents and material objects;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-9.1.list1.b.list0.ba">
                    <num>(ba)</num>
                    <p>requisitioning of any data, as may be required by it;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses or for local investigation;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>any other matter which may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Tribunal may require any State Government to carry out, or permit to be carried out, such surveys and investigation as may be considered necessary for the adjudication of any water dispute pending before it.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A decision of the Tribunal may contain directions as to the Government by which the expenses of the Tribunal and any costs incurred by any State Government in appearing before the Tribunal are to be paid, and may fix the amount of any expenses or costs to be so paid, and so far as it relates to expenses or costs, may be enforced as if it were an order made by the Supreme Court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act and any rules that may be made thereunder, the Tribunal may, by order, regulate its practice and procedure.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9A">
        <num>9A.</num>
        <heading>Maintenance of data bank and information. </heading>
        <subsection id="section-9A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government shall maintain a data bank and information system at the national level for each river basin which shall include data regarding water resources, land, agriculture, and matters relating thereto, as the Central Government may prescribe from time to time. The State Government shall supply the data to the Central Government or to an agency appointed by the Central Government for the purpose, as and when required.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government shall have powers to verify the data supplied by the State Government, and appoint any person or persons for the purpose and take such measures as it may consider necessary. The person or persons so appointed shall have the powers to summon such records and information from the concerned State Government as are considered necessary to discharge their functions under this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Allowances or fees for Chairman of Tribunal and assessors. </heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Chairman and other members of a Tribunal and the assessors shall be entitled to receive such remuneration, allowances or fees as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Bar of jurisdiction of Supreme Court and other courts. </heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law, neither the Supreme Court nor any other court shall have or exercise jurisdiction in respect of any water dispute which may be referred to a Tribunal under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Dissolution of Tribunal. </heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government shall dissolve the Tribunal after it has forwarded its report and as soon as the Central Government is satisfied that no further reference to the Tribunal in the matter would be necessary.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules. </heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government, after consultation with the State Government, may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the form and manner in which a complaint as to any water dispute may be made by any State Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the matters in respect of which a Tribunal may be vested with the powers of a Civil Court ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the procedure to be followed by a Tribunal under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the remuneration, allowances or fees payable to the Chairman and other members of a Tribunal and assessors;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the terms and conditions of service of officers and assessors of the Tribunal;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>any other matter which has to be, or may be, prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty days, which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of Ravi and Beas Waters Tribunal. </heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing provisions of this Act, the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute a Tribunal under this Act, to be known as the Ravi and Beas Waters Tribunal for the verification and adjudication of the matters referred to in paragraphs 9.1 and 9.2, respectively of the Punjab Settlement.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When a Tribunal has been constituted under sub-section (1), the provisions of sub-sections (2) and (3) of section 4, sub-sections (2), (3) and (4) of section 5 and sections 5A to 13 (both inclusive) of this Act relating to the constitution, jurisdiction, powers, authority and bar of jurisdiction shall, so far as may be, but subject to sub-section (3) hereof, apply to the constitution, jurisdiction, powers, authority and bar of jurisdiction in relation to the Tribunal constituted under sub-section (1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When a Tribunal has been constituted under sub-section (1), the Central Government alone may suo motu or at the request of the concerned State Government refer the matters specified in paragraphs 9.1 and 9.2 of the Punjab Settlement to such Tribunal.</p>
            <p>Explanation .For the purposes of this section, Punjab Settlement means the Memorandum of Settlement signed at New Delhi on the 24th day of July, 1985.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
