<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1960/59/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1960/59"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Prevention Of Cruelty To Animals Act, 1960"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1960/59/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1960/59/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1960/59/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1960/59/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-11-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Prevention Of Cruelty To Animals Act, 1960</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals Act, 1960.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint, and different dates may be appointed for different States and for the different provisions contained in this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“animal” means any living creature other than a human being;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“Board” means the Board established under section 4, and as reconstituted from time to time under section 5A;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“captive animal” means any animal (not being a domestic animal) which is in captivity or confinement, whether permanent or temporary, or which is subjected to any appliance or contrivance for the purpose of hindering or preventing its escape from captivity or confinement or which is pinioned or which is or appears to be maimed;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>“domestic animal” means any animal which is tamed or which has been or is being sufficiently tamed to serve some purpose for the use of man or which, although it neither has been nor is being nor is intended to be so tamed, is or has become in fact wholly or partly tamed;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>“local authority” means a municipal committee, district board or other authority for the time being invested by law with the control and administration of any matters within a specified local area;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>“owner”, used with reference to an animal, includes not only the owner but also any other person for the time being in possession or custody of the animal, whether with or without the consent of the owner;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>“phooka” or “doom dev” includes any process of introducing air or any substance into the female organ of a milch animal with the object of drawing off from the animal any secretion of milk;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>“street” includes any way, road, lane, square, court, alley, passage or open space, whether a thoroughfare or not, to which the public have access.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Duties of persons having charge of animals.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>It shall be the duty of every person having the care or charge of any animal to take all reasonable measures to ensure the well-being of such animal and to prevent the infliction upon such animal of unnecessary pain or suffering.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Establishment of Animal Welfare Board of India.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the promotion of animal welfare generally and for the purpose of protecting animals from being subjected to unnecessary pain or suffering, in particular, there shall be established by the Central Government, as soon as may be after the commencement of this Act, a Board to be called the Animal Welfare Board of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall be a body corporate having perpetual succession and a common seal with power, subject to the provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of property and may by its name sue and be sued.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of the Board.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Board shall consist of the following persons, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the Inspector-General of Forests, Government of India, ex officio;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-5.1.list1.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>the Animal Husbandry Commissioner to the Government of India, ex officio;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-5.1.list1.b.list0.ba">
                    <num>(ba)</num>
                    <p>two persons to represent respectively the Ministers of the Central Government dealing with home affairs and education, to be appointed by the Central Government;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-5.1.list1.b.list0.bb">
                    <num>(bb)</num>
                    <p>one person to represent the Indian Board for Wild Life, to be appointed by the Central Government;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-5.1.list1.b.list0.bc">
                    <num>(bc)</num>
                    <p>three persons who, in the opinion of the Central Government, are or have been actively engaged in animal welfare work and are well-known humanitarians, to be nominated by the Central Government;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>one person to represent such association of veterinary practitioners as in the opinion of the Central Government ought to be represented on the Board, to be elected by that association in the prescribed manner;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>two persons to represent practitioners of modern and indigenous systems of medicine, to be nominated by the Central Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>one person to represent each of such two municipal corporations as in the opinion of the Central Government ought to be represented on the Board, to be elected by each of the said corporations in the prescribed manner;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>one person to represent each of such three organisations actively interested in animal welfare as in the opinion of the Central Government ought to be represented on the Board, to be chosen by each of the said organisations in the prescribed manner;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>one person to represent each of such three societies dealing with prevention of cruelty to animals as in the opinion of the Central Government ought to be represented on the Board, to be chosen in the prescribed manner;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>three persons to be nominated by the Central Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>six members of Parliament, four to be elected by the House of the People (Lok Sabha) and two by the Council of States (Rajya Sabha).</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any of the persons referred to in clause (a) or clause (b) or clause (ba) or clause (bb) of sub-section (1) may depute any other person to attend any of the meetings of the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government shall nominate one of the members of the Board to be its Chairman and another member of the Board to be its Vice-Chairman.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5A">
        <num>5A.</num>
        <heading>Reconstitution of the Board.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In order that the Chairman and other members of the Board hold office till the same date and that their terms of office come to an end on the same date, the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, reconstitute, as soon as may be after the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals (Amendment) Act, 1982 comes into force, the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board as reconstituted under sub-section (1) shall be reconstituted from time to time on the expiration of every third year from the date of its reconstitution under sub-section (1)</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be included amongst the members of the Board reconstituted under sub-section (1), all persons who immediately before the date on which such reconstitution is to take effect, are members of the Board but such persons shall hold office only for the unexpired portion of the term for which they would have held office if such reconstitution had not been made and the vacancies arising as a result of their ceasing to be members of the Board shall be filled up as casual vacancies for the remaining period of the term of the Board as so reconstituted:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing in this sub-section shall apply in relation to any person who ceases to be a member of the Board by virtue of the amendment made in sub-section (1) of section 5 by sub-clause (ii) of clause (a) of section 5 of the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals (Amendment) Act, 1982.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Term of office and conditions of service of members of the Board.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The term for which the Board may be reconstituted under section 5A shall be three years from the date of the reconstitution and the Chairman and other members of the Board as so reconstituted shall hold office till the expiry of the term for which the Board has been so reconstituted.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1),—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the term of office of an ex officio member shall continue so long as he holds the office by virtue of which he is such a member;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the term of office of a member elected or chosen under clause (c), clause (e), clause (f), clause (g), clause (h) or clause (i) of section 5 to represent any body of persons shall come to an end as soon as he ceases to be a member of the body which elected him or in respect of which he was chosen;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the term of office of a member appointed, nominated, elected or chosen to fill a casual vacancy shall continue for the remainder of the term of office of the member in whose place he is appointed, nominated, elected or chosen;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the Central Government may, at any time, remove for reasons to be recorded in writing a member from office after giving him a reasonable opportunity of showing cause against the proposed removal and any vacancy caused by such removal shall be treated as casual vacancy for the purpose of clause (c).</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The members of the Board shall receive such allowances, if any, as the Board may, subject to the previous approval of the Central Government, provide by regulations made in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No act done or proceeding taken by the Board shall be questioned on the ground merely of the existence of any vacancy in, or defect in the constitution of, the Board and in particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing, during the period intervening between the expiry of the term for which the Board has been reconstituted under section 5A and its further reconstitution under that section, the ex officio members of the Board shall discharge all the powers and functions of the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Secretary and other employees of the Board.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government shall appoint the Secretary of the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to such rules as may be made by the Central Government in this behalf, the Board may appoint such number of other officers and employees as may be necessary for the exercise of its powers and the discharge of its functions and may determine the terms and conditions of service of such officers and other employees by regulations made by it with the previous approval of the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Funds of the Board.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The funds of the Board shall consist of grants made to it from time to time by the Government and of contributions, donations, subscriptions, bequests, gifts and the like made to it by any local authority or by any other person.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Functions of the Board.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The functions of the Board shall be—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to keep the law in force in India for the prevention of cruelty to animals under constant study and advise the Government on the amendments to be undertaken in any such law from time to time;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to advise the Central Government on the making of rules under this Act with a view to preventing unnecessary pain or suffering to animals generally, and more particularly when they are being transported from one place to another or when they are used as performing animals or when they are kept in captivity or confinement;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to advise the Government or any local authority or other person on improvements in the design of vehicles so as to lessen the burden on draught animals;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>to take all such steps as the Board may think fit for ameliorating of animals by encouraging, or providing for, the construction of sheds, water-troughs and the like and by providing for veterinary assistance to animals;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>to advise the Government or any local authority or other person in the design of slaughter-houses or in the maintenance of slaughter-houses or in connection with slaughter of animals so that unnecessary pain or suffering, whether physical or mental, is eliminated in the pre-slaughter stages as far as possible, as animals are killed, wherever necessary, in as humane a manner as possible;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>to take all such steps as the Board may think fit to ensure that unwanted animals are destroyed by local authorities, whenever it is necessary to do so, either instantaneously or after being rendered insensible to pain of suffering;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>to encourage, by the grant of financial assistance or otherwise, the formation or establishment of pinjrapoles, rescue homes, animal shelters, sanctuaries and the like where animals and birds may find a shelter when they have become old and useless or when they need protection;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>to co-operate with, and co-ordinate the work of, associations or bodies established for the purpose of preventing unnecessary pain or suffering to animals or for the protection of animals and birds;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>to give financial and other assistance to animal welfare organisations functioning in any local area or to encourage the formation of animal welfare organisations in any local area which shall work under the general supervision and guidance of the Board;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>to advise the Government on matters relating to the medical care and attention which may be provided in animal hospitals and to give financial and other assistance to animal hospitals whenever the Board thinks it necessary to do so;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>to impart education in relation to the humane treatment of animals and to encourage the formation of public opinion against the infliction of unnecessary pain or suffering to animals and for the promotion of animal welfare by means of lectures, books, posters, cinematographic exhibitions and the like;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>to advise the Government on any matter connected with animals welfare or the prevention of infliction of unnecessary pain or suffering on animals.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Power of Board to make regulations.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Board may, subject to the previous approval of the Central Government, make such regulations as it may think fit for the administration of its affairs and for carrying out its functions.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Treating animals cruelly.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If any person—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>beats, kicks, over-rides, over-drives, over-loads, tortures or otherwise treats any animal so as to subject it to unnecessary pain or suffering or causes or, being the owner permits, any animals to be so treated; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>employs in any work or labour or for any purpose any animal which, by reason of its age or any disease, infirmity, wound, sore or other cause, is unfit to be so employed or, being the owner, permits any such unfit animal to be so employed; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>wilfully and unreasonably administers any injurious drug or injurious substance to any animal or wilfully and unreasonably causes or attempts to cause any such drug or substance to be taken by any animal; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>conveys or carries, whether in or upon any vehicle or not, any animal in such a manner or position as to subject it to unnecessary pain or suffering; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>keeps or confines any animal in any cage or other receptacle which does not measure sufficiently in height, length and breadth to permit the animal a reasonable opportunity for movement; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>keeps for an unreasonable time any animal chained or tethered upon an unreasonably short or unreasonably heavy chain or cord; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>being the owner, neglects to exercise or cause to be exercised reasonably any dog habitually chained up or kept in close confinement; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>being the owner of any animal, fails to provide such animal with sufficient food, drink or shelter; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>without reasonable cause, abandons any animal in circumstances which render it likely that it will suffer pain by reason of starvation or thirst; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>wilfully permits any animal, of which he is the owner to go at large in any street while the animal is affected with contagious or infectious disease or, without reasonable excuse permits any diseased or disabled animal, of which he is the owner, to die in any street; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>offers for sale or, without reasonable cause, has in his possession any animal which is suffering pain by reason of mutilation, starvation, thirst, overcrowding or other ill-treatment; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>mutilates any animal or kills any animal (including stray dogs) by using the method of strychnine injections in the heart or in any other unnecessarily cruel manner; or;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-11.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>m)  solely with a view to providing entertainment—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.1.list3.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>confines or causes to be confined any animal (including tying of an animal as a bait in a tiger or other sanctuary) so as to make it an object of prey for any other animal; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.1.list3.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>incites any animal to fight or bait any other animal; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.1.list3.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>organises, keeps, uses or acts in the management of, any place for animal fighting or for the purpose of baiting any animal or permits or offers any place to be so used or receives money for the admission of any other person to any place kept or used for any such purposes; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.1.list3.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>promotes or takes part in any shooting match or competition wherein animals are released from captivity for the purpose of such shooting;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>he shall be punishable, in the case of a first offence, with fine which shall not be less than ten rupees but which may extend to fifty rupees, and in the case of a second or subsequent offence committed within three years of the previous offence, with fine which shall not be less than twenty-five rupees but which may extend to one hundred rupees or with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three months, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purposes of sub-section (1), an owner shall be deemed to have committed an offence if he has failed to exercise reasonable care and supervision with a view to the prevention of such offence:</p>
            <p>Provided that where an owner is convicted of permitting cruelty by reason only of having failed to exercise such care and supervision, he shall not be liable to imprisonment without the option of a fine.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Nothing in this section shall apply to—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the dehorning of cattle, or the castration or branding or nose-roping of any animal, in the prescribed manner; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the destruction of stray dogs in lethal chambers or by such other methods as may be prescribed; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.3.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the extermination or destruction of any animal under the authority of any law for the time being in force; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.3.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>any matter dealt with in Chapter IV; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.3.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the commission or omission of any act in the course of the destruction or the preparation for destruction of any animal as food for mankind unless such destruction or preparation was accompanied by the infliction of unnecessary pain or suffering.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Action upon the report of Advisory Board.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In any case where the Advisory Board has reported that there is, in its opinion, sufficient cause for the detention of a person, the appropriate Government may confirm the detention order and continue the detention of the concerned for such period as it thinks fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In any case where the Advisory Board has reported that there is, in its opinion, no sufficient cause for the detention of the person concerned, the appropriate Government shall revoke the detention order and cause the person to be released forthwith.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Destruction of suffering animals.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the owner of an animal is convicted of an offence under section 11, it shall be lawful for the court, if the court is satisfied that it would be cruel to keep the animal alive, to direct that the animal be destroyed and to assign the animal to any suitable person for that purpose, and the person to whom such animal is so assigned shall, as soon as possible, destroy such animal or cause such animal to be destroyed in his presence without unnecessary suffering, and any reasonable expense incurred in destroying the animal may by ordered by the court to be recovered from the owner as if it were a fine:</p>
            <p>Provided that unless the owner assents thereto, no order shall be made under this section except upon the evidence of a veterinary officer in charge of the area.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When any magistrate, commissioner of police or district superintendent of police has reason to believe that an offence under section 11 has been committed in respect of any animal, he may direct the immediate destruction of the animal, if in his opinion, it would be cruel to keep the animal alive.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any police officer about the rank of a constable or any person authorised by the State Government in this behalf who finds any animal so diseased or so severely injured or in such a physical condition that in his opinion it cannot be removed without cruelty, may, if the owner is absent or refuses his consent to the destruction of the animal, forthwith summon the veterinary officer in charge of the area in which the animal is found, and if the veterinary officer certifies that the animal is mortally injured or so severely injured or in such a physical condition that it would be cruel to keep it alive, the police officer or the person authorised, as the case may be, may, after obtaining orders from a magistrate, destroy the animal injured or cause it to be destroyed. in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No appeal shall lie from any order of a magistrate for the destruction of an animal.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Experiments on animals.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Nothing contained in this Act shall render unlawful the performance of experiments (including experiments involving operations) on animals for the purpose of advancement by new discovery of physiological knowledge or of knowledge which will be useful for saving or for prolonging life or alleviating suffering or for combating any disease, whether of human beings, animals or plants.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Committee for control and supervision of experiments on animals.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If at any time, on the advice of the Board, the Central Government is of opinion that it is necessary so to do for the purpose of controlling and supervising experiments on animals, it may, by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute a Committee consisting of such number of officials and non-officials, as it may think fit to appoint thereto.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government shall nominate one of the members of the Committee to be its Chairman.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Committee shall have power to regulate its own procedure in relation to the performance of its duties.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The funds of the Committee shall consist of grants made to it from time to time by the Government and of contributions, donations, subscriptions, bequests gifts and the like made to it by any person.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15A">
        <num>15A.</num>
        <heading>Sub-committees.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Committee may constitute as many sub-committees as it thinks fit for exercising any power or discharging any duty of the Committee or for inquiring into or reporting and advising on any matter which the Committee may refer.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A sub-committee shall consist exclusively of the members of the Committee.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Staff of the Committee.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the control of the Central Government, the Committee may appoint such number of officers and other employees as may be necessary to enable it to exercise its powers and perform its duties, and may determine the remuneration and other terms and conditions of service of such officers and other employees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Duties of the Committee and power of the Committee to make rules relating to experiments on animals.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be the duty of the Committee to take all such measures as may be necessary to ensure that animals are not subject to unnecessary pain or suffering before, during or after the performance of experiments on them, and for that purpose it may, by notification in the Gazette of India and subject to the condition of previous publication, make such rules as it may think fit in relation to the conduct of such experiments.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.1A">
          <num>(1A)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-17.1A.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for the following matters, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.1A.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the registration of persons or institutions carrying on experiments on animals;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.1A.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the reports and other information which shall be forwarded to the Committee by persons and institutions carrying on experiments on animals.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-17.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, rules made by the Committee shall be designed to secure the following objects, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>that in cases where experiments are performed in any institution, the responsibility therefor is placed on the person in charge of the institution and that, in cases where experiments are performed outside an institution by individuals, the individuals are qualified in that behalf and the experiments are performed on their full responsibility;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>that experiments are performed with due care and humanity, and that as far as possible experiments involving operations are performed under the influence of some anaesthetic of sufficient power to prevent the animals feeling pain;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>that animals which, in the course of experiments under the influence of anaesthetics, are so injured that their recovery would involve serious suffering, are ordinarily destroyed while still insensible;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>that experiments on animals are avoided wherever it is possible to do so; as for example, in medical schools, hospitals, colleges and the like, if other teaching devices such as books, models, films and the like may equally suffice;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>that experiments on larger animals are avoided when it is possible to achieve the same results by experiments upon small laboratory animals like guinea-pigs, rabbits, frogs and rats;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>that, as far as possible, experiments are not performed merely for the purpose of acquiring manual skill;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>that animals intended for the performance of experiments are properly looked after both before and after experiments;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>that suitable records are maintained with respect to experiments performed on animals.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In making any rules under this section, the Committee shall be guided by such directions as the Central Government (consistently with the objects for which the Committee is set up) may give to it, and the Central Government is hereby authorised to give such directions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All rules made by the Committee shall be binding on all individuals performing experiments outside institutions and on persons in charge of institutions in which experiments are performed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Power of entry and inspection.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-18.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>For the purpose of ensuring that the rules made by it are being complied with, the Committee may authorise any of its officers or any other person in writing to inspect any institution or place where experiments are being carried on and report to it as a result of such inspection, and any officer of person so authorised may—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>enter at any time considered reasonable by him and inspect any institution or place in which experiments on animals are being carried on; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>require any person to produce any records kept by him with respect to experiments on animals.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Power to prohibit experiments on animals.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If the Committee is satisfied, on the report of any officer or other person made to it as a result of any inspection under section 18 or otherwise, that the rules made by it under section 17 are not being complied with by any person or institution carrying on experiments on animals, the Committee may, after giving an opportunity to the person or institution of being heard in the matter, by order, prohibit the person or institution from carrying on any such experiments either for a specified period or indefinitely, or may allow the person or institution to carry on such experiments subject to such special conditions as the Committee may think fit to impose.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Penalties.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-20.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If any person—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>contravenes any order made by the Committee under section 19; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>commits a breach of any condition imposed by the Committee under that section;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to two hundred rupees, and, when the contravention or breach of condition has taken place in any institution, the person in charge of the institution shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be punishable accordingly.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>“Exhibit” and “train” defined.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In this Chapter, “exhibit” means exhibit at any entertainment, to which the public are admitted through sale of tickets and “train” means train for the purpose of any such exhibition, and the expressions “exhibitor” and “trainer” have respectively the corresponding meanings.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Restriction on exhibition and training of performing animals.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-22.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>No person shall exhibit or train—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-22.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>any performing animal unless he is registered in accordance with the provisions of this Chapter ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-22.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>as a performing animal, any animal which the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify as an animal which shall not be exhibited or trained as a performing animal.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Procedure for registration.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-23.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every person desirous of exhibiting or training any performing animal shall, on making an application in the prescribed form to the prescribed authority and on payment of the prescribed fee, be registered under this Act unless he is a person who, by reason of an order made by the court under this Chapter, is not entitled to be so registered.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An application for registration under this Chapter shall contain such particulars as to the animals and as to the general nature of the performances in which the animals are to be exhibited or for which they are to be trained as may be prescribed, and the particulars so given shall be entered in the register maintained by the prescribed authority.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The prescribed authority shall give to every person whose name appears on the register kept by them, a certificate of registration in the prescribed form containing the particulars entered in the register.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every register kept under this Chapter shall at all reasonable times be open for inspection on payment of the prescribed fee, and any person shall, on payment of the prescribed fee, be entitled to obtain copies thereof or make extracts therefrom.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person whose name is entered in the register shall, subject to the provisions of any order made under this Act by any court, be entitled, on making an application for the purpose, to have the particulars entered in the register with respect to him varied, and where any such particulars are so varied, the existing certificate shall be cancelled and a new certificate issued.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Power of court to prohibit or restrict exhibition and training of performing animals.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-24.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where it is proved to the satisfaction of any magistrate on a complaint made by a police officer or an officer authorised in writing by the prescribed authority referred to in section 23, that the training or exhibition of any performing animal has been accompanied by unnecessary pain or suffering and should be prohibited or allowed only subject to conditions, the court may make an order against the person in respect of whom the complaint is made, prohibiting the training or exhibition or imposing such conditions in relation thereto, as may be specified by the order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any court by which an order is made under this section shall cause a copy of the order to be sent, as soon as may be after the order is made, to the prescribed authority by which the person against whom the order is made is registered, and shall cause the particulars of the order to be endorsed upon the certificate held by that person, and that person shall produce his certificate on being so required by the court for the purposes of endorsement, and the prescribed authority to which a copy of an order is sent under this section shall enter the particulars of the order in that register.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Power to enter premises.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-25.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-25.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any person authorised in writing by the prescribed authority referred to in section 23 and any police officer not below the rank of a sub-inspector may—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-25.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>enter at all reasonable times and inspect any premises in which any performing animals are being trained or exhibited or kept for training or exhibition, and any such animals found therein; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-25.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>require any person who, he has reason to believe, is a trainer or exhibitor of performing animals to produce his certificate or registration.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No person or police officer referred to in sub-section (1) shall be entitled under this section to go on or behind the stage during a public performance of performing animals.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Offences.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-26.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If any person—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>not being registered under this Chapter, exhibits or trains any performing animal; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>being registered under this Act, exhibits or trains any performing animal with respect to which, or in a manner with respect to which, he is not registered; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>exhibits or trains as a performing animal, any animal which is not to be used for the purpose by reason of a notification issued under clause (ii) of section 22; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>obstructs or wilfully delays any person or police officer referred to in section 25 in the exercise of powers under this Act as to entry and inspection; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>conceals any animal with a view to avoiding such inspection; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>being a person registered under this Act, on being duly required in pursuance of this Act to produce his certificate under this Act, fails without reasonable excuse so to do; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>applies to be registered under this Act when not entitled to be so registered;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>he shall be punishable on conviction with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, or with imprisonment which may extend to three months, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Exemptions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-27.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Nothing contained in this Chapter shall apply to—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the training of animals for bona fide military or police purposes or the exhibition of any animals so trained; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any animals kept in any zoological garden or by any society or association which has for its principal object the exhibition of animals for educational or scientific purposes.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28">
        <num>28.</num>
        <heading>Saving as respects manner of killing prescribed by religion.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Nothing contained in this Act shall render it an offence to kill any animal in a manner required by the religion of any community.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29">
        <num>29.</num>
        <heading>Power of court to deprive person convicted of ownership of animal.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-29.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the owner of any animal is found guilty of any offence under this Act, the court, upon his conviction thereof, may, if it thinks fit, in addition to any other punishment, make an order that the animal with respect to which the offence was committed shall be forfeited to Government and may, further, make such order as to the disposal of the animal as it thinks fit under the circumstances.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No order under sub-section (1) shall be made unless it is shown by evidence as to a previous conviction under this Act or as to the character of the owner or otherwise as to the treatment of the animal that the animal, if left with the owner, is likely to be exposed to further cruelty.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Without prejudice to the provisions contained in sub-section (1), the court may also order that a person convicted of an offence under this Act shall, either permanently or during such period as is fixed by the order, be prohibited from having the custody of any animal of any kind whatsoever, or, as the court thinks fit, of any animal of any kind or species specified in the order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-29.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>No order under sub-section (3) shall be made unless—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-29.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>it is shown by evidence as to a previous conviction or as to the character of the said person or otherwise as to the treatment of the animal in relation to which he has been convicted that an animal in the custody of the said person is likely to be exposed to cruelty;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-29.4.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>it is stated in the complaint upon which the conviction was made that it is the intention of the complainant upon the conviction of the accused to request that an order be made as aforesaid; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-29.4.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the offence for which the conviction was made was committed in an area in which under the law for the time being in force a licence is necessary for the keeping of any such animal as that in respect of which the conviction was made.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any law for the time being in force, any person in respect of whom an order is made under sub-section (3) shall have no right to the custody of any animal contrary to the provisions of the order, and if he contravenes the provisions of any order, he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to one hundred rupees, or with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three months, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any court which has made an order under sub-section (3) may at any time, either on its own motion or on application made to it in this behalf, rescind or modify such order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-30">
        <num>30.</num>
        <heading>Presumption as to guilt in certain cases.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-30.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any person is charged with the offence of killing a goat, cow or its progeny contrary to the provisions of clause</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-30.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of sub-section (1) of section 11, and it is proved that such person had in his possession, at the time the offence is alleged to have been committed, the skin of any such animal as is referred to in this section with any part of the skin of the head attached thereto, it shall be presumed until the contrary is proved that such animal was killed in a cruel manner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-31">
        <num>31.</num>
        <heading>Cognizability of offences.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-31.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898), an offence punishable under clause</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-31.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>, clause (n) or clause (o) of sub-section (1) of section 11 or under section 12 shall be a cognizable offence within the meaning of that Code.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-32">
        <num>32.</num>
        <heading>Powers of search and seizure.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-32.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If a police officer not below the rank of sub-inspector or any person authorised by the State Government in this behalf has reason to believe that an offence under clause (1) of sub-section (1) of section 11 in respect of any such animal as is referred to in section 30 is being or is about to be, or has been, committed in any place, or that any person has in his possession the skin of any such animal with any part of the skin of the head attached thereto, he may enter and search such place or any place in which he has reason to believe any such skin to be, and may seize such skin or any article or thing used or intended to be used in the commission of such offence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-32.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If a police officer not below the rank of sub-inspector, or any person authorised by the State Government in this behalf, has reason to believe that phooka or doom dev or any other operation of the nature referred to in section 12 has just been, or is being, performed on any animal within the limits of his jurisdiction, he may enter any place in which he has reason to believe such animal to be, and may seize the animal and produce it for examination by the veterinary officer in charge of the area in which the animal is seized.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-33">
        <num>33.</num>
        <heading>Search warrants.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-33.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If a magistrate of the first or second class or a presidency magistrate or a sub-divisional magistrate or a commissioner of police or district superintendent of police, upon information in writing, and after such inquiry as he thinks necessary, has reason to believe that an offence under this Act is being, or is about to be, or has been committed in any place, he may either himself enter and search or by his warrant authorise any police officer not below the rank of sub-inspector to enter and search the place.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-33.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898), relating to searches shall, so far as those provisions can be made applicable, apply to searches, under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-34">
        <num>34.</num>
        <heading>General power of seizure for examination.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-34.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any police officer above the rank of a constable or any person authorised by the State Government in this behalf, who has reason to believe that an offence against this Act has been or is being, committed in respect of any animal, may, if in his opinion the circumstances to require, seize the animal and produce the same for examination by the nearest magistrate or by such veterinary officer as may be prescribed, and such police officer or authorised person may, when seizing the animal, require the person in charge thereof to accompany it to the place of examination.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-35">
        <num>35.</num>
        <heading>Treatment and care of animals.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-35.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by general or special order, appoint infirmaries for the treatment and care of animals in respect of which offences against this Act have been committed, and may authorise the detention therein of any animal pending its production before a magistrate.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-35.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The magistrate before whom a prosecution for an offence against this Act has been instituted may direct that the animal concerned shall be treated and cared for in an infirmary, until it is fit to perform its usual work or is otherwise fit for discharge, or that it shall be sent to a pinjrapole, or, if the veterinary officer in charge of the area in which the animal is found or such other veterinary officer as may be authorised in this behalf by rules made under this Act certifies that it is incurable or cannot be removed without cruelty, that it shall be destroyed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-35.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An animal sent for care and treatment to an infirmary shall not, unless the magistrate directs that it shall be sent to a pinjrapole or that it shall be destroyed, be released from such place except upon a certificate of its fitness for discharge issued by the veterinary officer in charge of the area in which the infirmary is situated or such other veterinary officer as may be authorised in this behalf by rules made under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-35.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The cost of transporting the animal to an infirmary or pinjrapole, and of its maintenance and treatment in an infirmary, shall be payable by the owner of the animal in accordance with a scale of rates to be prescribed by the district magistrate, or, in presidency-towns, by the commissioner of police:</p>
            <p>Provided that when the magistrate so orders on account of the poverty of the owner of the animal, no charge shall be payable for the treatment of the animal.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-35.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any amount payable by an owner of an animal under sub-section (4) may be recovered in the same manner as an arrear of land revenue.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-35.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the owner refuses or neglects to remove the animal within such time as a magistrate may specify, the magistrate may direct that the animal be sold and that the proceeds of the sale be applied to the payment of such cost.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-35.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The surplus, if any, of the proceeds of such sale shall, on application made by the owner within two months from the date of the sale, be paid to him.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-36">
        <num>36.</num>
        <heading>Limitation of prosecutions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-36.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A prosecution for an offence against this Act shall not be instituted after the expiration of three months from the date of the commission of the offence.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-37">
        <num>37.</num>
        <heading>Delegation of powers.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-37.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that all or any of the powers exercisable by it under this Act, may, subject to such conditions as it may think fit to impose, be also exercisable by any State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-38">
        <num>38.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-38.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, and subject to the condition of previous publication, make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-38.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-38.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the forgoing power, the Central Government may make rules providing for all or any of the following matters, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-38.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-38.2.list1.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>the conditions of service of members of the Board, the allowances payable to them and the manner in which they may exercise their powers and discharge their functions;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-38.2.list1.a.list0.aa">
                    <num>(aa)</num>
                    <p>the manner in which the persons to represent municipal corporations are to be elected under clause (e) of sub-section (1) of section 5;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-38.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the maximum load (including any load occasioned by the weight of passengers) to be carried or drawn by any animal;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-38.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the conditions to be observed for preventing the over-crowding of animals;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-38.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the period during which, and the hours between which, any class of animals shall not be used for draught purposes;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-38.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <blockList id="section-38.2.list1.e.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>prohibiting the use of any bit or harness involving cruelty to animals;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-38.2.list1.e.list1.ea">
                    <num>(ea)</num>
                    <p>the other methods of destruction of stray dogs referred to in clause (b) of sub-section (3) of section 11;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-38.2.list1.e.list1.eb">
                    <num>(eb)</num>
                    <p>the methods by which any animal which cannot be removed without cruelty may be destroyed under sub-section (3) of section 13;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-38.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>requiring persons carrying on the business of a farrier to be licensed and registered by such authority as may be prescribed and levying a fee for the purposes;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-38.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the precautions to be taken in the capture of animals for purposes of sale, export or for any other purpose, and the different appliances or devices that may alone be used for the purpose; and the licensing of such capture and the levying of fees for such licences;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-38.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the precautions to be taken in the transport of animals, whether by rail, road, inland waterway, sea or air and the manner in which and the cages or other receptacles in which they may be so transported;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-38.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>requiring persons owning or in charge of premises in which animals are kept or milked to register such premises, to comply with such conditions as may be laid down in relation to the boundary walls or surroundings of such premises, to permit their inspection for the purpose of ascertaining whether any offence under this Act is being, or has been, committed therein, and to expose in such premises copies of section 12 in a language or languages commonly understood in the locality;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-38.2.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <blockList id="section-38.2.list1.j.list2">
                  <listIntroduction>the form in which applications for registration under Chapter V may be made, the particulars to be contained therein, the fees payable for such registration and the authorities to whom such applications may be made;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-38.2.list1.j.list2.ja">
                    <num>(ja)</num>
                    <p>the fees which may be charged by the Committee constituted under section 15 for the registration of persons or institutions carrying on experiments on animals or for any other purpose;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-38.2.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>the purposes to which fines realised under this Act may be applied, including such purposes as the maintenance of infirmaries, pinjrapole and veterinary hospitals;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-38.2.list1.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>any other matter which has to be, or may be, prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-38.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person contravenes, or abets the contravention of, any rules made under this section, he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to one hundred rupees, or with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three months, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-38A">
        <num>38A.</num>
        <heading>Rules and regulations to be laid before Parliament.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-38A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made by the Central Government or by the Committee constituted under section 15 and every regulation made by the Board shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or regulation, as the case may be, or both Houses agree that the rule or regulation, as the case may be, should not be made, the rule or regulation shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule or regulation.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-39">
        <num>39.</num>
        <heading>Persons authorised under section 34 to be public servants.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-39.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every person authorised by the State Government under section 34 shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-40">
        <num>40.</num>
        <heading>Indemnity.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-40.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any person who is, or who is deemed to be, a public servant within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860) in respect of anything in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-41">
        <num>41.</num>
        <heading>Repeal of Act 11 of 1890.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-41.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where in pursuance of a notification under sub-section (3) of section 1 any provision of this Act comes into force in any State, any provision of the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals Act, 1890 (11 of 1890), which corresponds to the provision so coming into force, shall there upon stand repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
