<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1887/02/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1887/02"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Protection of Pilgrims Act, 1887"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1887/02/eng@2017-03-10/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1887/02/eng@2017-03-10"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-10" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1887/02/eng@2017-03-10/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1887/02/eng@2017-03-10"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-10" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Protection Of Pilgrims Act, 1887</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[4th June, 1887.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No. 02 of 1887</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the protection of pilgrims at the ports of Bombay and Karachi.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the protection of pilgrims at the ports of Bombay and Karachi;</p>
        <p>It is hereby enacted as follows: —</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be cited as “The Protection of Pilgrims Act, 1887”.</p>
            <p>Extent – It extends only to the city and port of Bombay.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“pilgrim” means a Muhmmadan who is about to proceed from the port of Bombay on a pilgrimage to the Hedjaz, whether he is going direct to Jeddah, or via any other part;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“pilgrim-broker” means a person who buys and resells, or sells on commission, or takes any reward for the purchase or sale of passage-tickets for pilgrims;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“agent” includes a person who has chartered a vessel for the conveyance of pilgrims;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>“commissioner” means the Commissioner of Police, Bombay, or his deputy.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for acting as a pilgrim broker without license.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any person who, without a license from the Commissioner, acts as a pilgrim-broker shall be liable for each such offence to a fine which may extend to five hundred rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Persons may be licensed to act as pilgrim-brokers.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the orders of the Central Government, the Commissioner may grant to such persons as he thinks fit licenses to act as pilgrim-brokers.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>License what to specify.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Every license so granted shall specify—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the name and business address of the licensee;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the period for which it is to be in force;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the conditions on which, and the restrictions and limitations subject to which, it is granted;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>and shall be granted on payment to the Central Government of such fee, if any, as that Government may from time to time direct:</p>
            <p>Provided that, until provision to the contrary is made by the Parliament by law, all such fees shall be payable to the State Government under this section as were being lawfully taken thereunder immediately before the commencement of the Constitution.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for misbehavior of licensed pilgrim broker.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any licensed pilgrim-broker who shall—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>commit a breach of any of the terms or conditions of his licence;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>purchase for or sell to any pilgrim a passage-ticket by any vessel to which the provisions of the Pilgrim Ships Act, 1895, apply, at any time before notice has been given by the master, owner or agent of such vessel, under section of the said Act, of the date on which it is proposed that such vessel shall sail, and unless, in the case of any vessel the proposed date of sailing is printed on the passage-ticket;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>charge a pilgrim more than the cost price of any passage-ticket, provisions or other articles purchased for him, or receive from him any fee or commission on account of such ticket;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>receive from the master, owner or agent of a vessel any fee or commission in respect of the sale of any ticket, exceeding five per centum of the price of such ticket;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>purchase for any pilgrim a passage-ticket, on which there is not printed the price charged by the master, owner or agent of the vessel for each class of accommodation;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>by fraud or by false representation as to the size of, or accommodation, on board, such vessels, or otherwise, or by any false pretence whatever, induce any person to purchase a passage-ticket;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall be liable for each such offence to a fine which may extend to five hundred rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Power to suspend and cancel licenses.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Commissioner may suspend the license of any pilgrim-broker pending inquiry into any accusation against him of misconduct for which, if proved, he would be liable to a penalty under the last preceding section, and may cancel any license granted by him if the licensee is convicted of any offence under the said section or of any criminal offence.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>to 10.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>to 12.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12A">
        <num>12A.</num>
        <heading>to 12B.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for issue of tickers in excess.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any master, owner or agent of any vessel carrying pilgrims, who shall issue any passage-ticket in excess of the number allowed by the certificate granted under Section 11 of the Pilgrim Ships Act, 1895, shall for every passage-ticket so issued be liable to a fine not exceeding four times the cost price of such ticket.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Passage-tickets how to be numbered. Penalty for issue of tickets bearing the same number.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>All passage-tickets shall be numbered consecutively according to order of issue; and any master, owner or agent, who shall issue two or more tickets bearing the same number, shall be liable to a fine not exceeding one thousand rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Provisions of Pilgrim Ships Act, 1895, to apply to offences and penalties.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of sections 51, 52 and 54 of the Pilgrim Ships Act, 1895, shall apply to all offences punishable, and to all penalties leviable, under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Penalties to be enforced only at the instance of the Commissioner.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The penalties to which masters and owners of vessels are made liable by this Act shall be enforced only by information laid at the instance of the Commissioner.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
