<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1966/32/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1966/32"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Beedi and Cigar Workers (Conditions of Employment) Act, 1966"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1966/32/eng@1966-11-30/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1966/32/eng@1966-11-30"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1966-11-30" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1966/32/eng@1966-11-30/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1966/32/eng@1966-11-30"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-11-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Beedi And Cigar Workers (Conditions Of Employment) Act, 1966</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[30th November, 1966]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No. 32 of 1966</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the welfare of the workers in beedi and cigar establishments and to regulate the conditions of their work and for matters connected therewith.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Seventeenth Year of the Republic of India as follows:—</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Beedi and cigar Workers (Conditions of Employment) Act, 1966.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force in a State on such date as the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint and different dates may be appointed by the State Government for different areas and for different provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“adult” means a person who has completed eighteen years of age;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“child” means a person who has not completed fourteen years of age;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“competent authority” means any authority authorised by the State Government by notification in the Official Gazette to perform all or any of the functions of the competent authority under this Act and for such areas as may be specified therein;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>“contractor” means a person who, in relation to a manufacturing process, undertakes to produce a given result by executing the work through contract labour or who engages labour for any manufacturing process in a private dwelling house and includes a sub-contractor, agent, munshi, thekedar or sattedar.”</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>“contract labour” means any person engaged or employed in any premises by or through a contractor, with or without the knowledge of the employer, in any manufacturing process;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>“employee” means a person employed directly or through any agency, whether for wages or not, in any establishments or godown to do any work skilled, unskilled, manual or clerical, and includes —</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>any labour who is given raw materials by an employer or a contractor for being made into beedi or cigar or both at home (herein after referred to in this Act as “home worker”), and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>any person not employed by an employer or a contractor but working with the permission of, or under agreement with, the employer or contractor</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>or both;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>“employer” means,—</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in relation to contract labour, the principal employer; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in relation to other labour, the person who has the ultimate control over the affairs of any establishment or who has, by reason of his advancing money, supplying goods or otherwise, a substantial interest in the control of the affairs of any establishment, and includes any other person to whom the affairs of the establishment are entrusted, whether such other person is called the managing agent, manager, superintendent or by any other name;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>“establishment” means any place or premises including the precincts thereof in which or in any part of which any manufacturing process connected with the making of beedi or cigar or both is being, or is ordinarily, carried on and includes an industrial premises;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5">
              <listIntroduction>( hh) “godown” means any warehouse or other place, by whatever name called, used for the storage of—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>any article substance required for any manufacturing process; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>beedi or cigar or both;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>“industrial premises” means any place or premises (not being a private dwelling house), including the precincts thereof, in which or in any part of which any industry or manufacturing process connected with the making of beedi or cigar or both is being or is ordinarily carried on with or without the aid of power and includes a godown attached thereto;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>“Inspector” means an Inspector appointed under sub-section (1) of section 6;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>“manufacturing process” means any process for, or incidental to, making, finishing or packing or otherwise treating any article or substance with a view to its use, sale, transport, delivery or disposal as beedi or cigar or both;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made by the State Government under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>“principal employer” means a person for whom or on whose behalf any contract labour is engaged or employed in an establishment;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>“private dwelling house” means a house in which persons engaged in the manufacture of beedi or cigar or both reside;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>“State Government” in relation to a Union territory, means the Administrator thereof;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.p">
                <num>(p)</num>
                <p>“week” means a period of seven days, beginning at midnight on Saturday;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.q">
                <num>(q)</num>
                <p>“young person” means a person who has completed fourteen years of age but has not completed eighteen years of age.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Industrial premises to be licensed.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Save as otherwise provided in this Act, no employer shall use or allow to be used any place or premises as an industrial premises unless he holds a valid licence issued under this Act and no such premises shall be used except in accordance with the terms and conditions of such licence.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Licences.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person who intends to use or allows to be used any place or premises as industrial premises shall make an application in writing to the competent authority, in such form on payment of such fees as may be prescribed, for a licence to use, or allow to be used, such premises as an industrial premises.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The application shall specify the maximum number of employees proposed to be employed at any time of the day in the place or premises and shall be accompanied by a plan of the place or premises prepared in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The competent authority shall, in deciding whether to grant or refuse a licence, have regard to the following matters:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the suitability of the place or premises which is proposed to be used for the manufacture of beedi or cigar or both;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the previous experience of the applicant;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the financial resources of the applicant including his financial capacity to meet the demands arising out of the provisions of the laws for the time being in force relating to welfare of labour;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>whether the application is made bona fide on behalf of the applicant himself or in benami of any other person;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>welfare of the labour in the locality, the interest of the public generally and such other matters as may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.4.list0">
              <item id="section-4.4.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>A licence granted under this section shall not be valid beyond the financial year in which it is granted but may be renewed from financial year to financial year.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.4.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>An application for the renewal of a licence granted under this Act shall be made at least thirty days before the expiry of the period thereof, on payment of such fees as may be prescribed, and where such an application has been made, the licence shall be deemed to continue, notwithstanding the expiry of the period thereof, until the renewal of the licence, or, as the case may be, the rejection of the application for the renewal thereof.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.4.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>The competent authority shall, in deciding whether to renew a licence or to refuse a renewal thereof, have regard to the matters specified in sub-section (3).</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The competent authority shall not grant a renew a licence unless it is satisfied that the provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder have been substantially complied with.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The competent authority may, after giving the holder of a licence an opportunity of being heard, cancel or suspend any licence granted or renewed under this Act if it appears to it that such licence has been obtained by misrepresentation or fraud or that the licensee has contravened or failed to comply with any of the provisions of this Act or the rules made thereunder or any of the terms or conditions of the licence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may issue in writing to a competent authority such directions of a general character as that Government may consider necessary in respect of any matter relating to the grant or renewal of licences under this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the foregoing provisions of this section, the competent authority may grant or renew licences under this Act on such terms and conditions as it may determine and where the competent authority refuses to grant or renew any licence, it shall do so by an order communicated to the applicant, giving the reasons in writing for such refusal.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Appeals.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any person aggrieved by the decision of the competent authority refusing to grant or renew a licence or cancelling or suspending a licence may, within such time and on payment of such fees, not exceeding twenty rupees, as may be prescribed, appeal to such authority as the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf, and such authority may by order confirm, modify or reverse any order refusing to grant or renew a licence or cancelling or suspending a licence.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Inspectors.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint such of its officers or such officers of any local authority as it thinks fit to be Inspectors for the purposes of this Act and may assign to them such local limits as it may think fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint any person to be a Chief Inspector who shall exercise the powers of an Inspector throughout the State.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Chief Inspector and Inspector shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Powers of Inspectors. —</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Subject to any rules by the State Government in this behalf, an Inspector may, within the local limits for which he is appointed,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>make such examination and hold such inquiry as may be necessary for ascertaining whether the provisions of this Act have been or are being complied within any place or premises:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-7.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that no person shall be compelled under this section to answer any question or to give any evidence which may tend to incriminate himself:</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.1.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>require the production of any prescribed register and any other document relating to the manufacture of beedi or cigar or both;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>enter, with such assistants as he thinks fit, at all times any place or premises including the residences of employees if he has reasonable grounds for suspecting that any manufacturing process is being carried on or is ordinarily carried on in any such place or premises;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>exercise such other powers as may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If an Inspector has reasonable grounds for suspecting that any manufacturing process is being carried on in any establishment in contravention of the provisions of this Act, he may, after giving due notice to the employer or, in the absence of the employer, to the occupier, enter such establishment with such assistants, if any, as he may think fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every employer or occupier shall accord to the chief Inspector or the Inspector, as the case may be, all reasonable facilities in the discharge of his duties under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7A">
        <num>7A.</num>
        <heading>Inspector not to disclose the source of any complaint, etc. —</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No Inspector shall disclose the source of any complaint made to him regarding the contravention of any of the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No Inspector shall, while making an inspection under this Act in pursuance of a complaint received by him, disclose to the employer or contractor concerned or any of his representatives that the inspection is being made in pursuance of a complaint:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing in this section shall apply to any case in which the person who has made the complaint has consented to disclose his name.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Cleanliness.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every industrial premises shall be kept clean and free from effluvia arising from any drain, privy or other nuisance and shall also maintain such standard of cleanliness including white washing, colour washing, varnishing or painting, as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Ventilation.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of preventing injury to the health of the persons working therein, every industrial premises shall maintain such standards of lighting, ventilation and temperature, as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Wherever dust or fume or other impurity of such a nature and to such an extent as is likely to be injurious or offensive to the persons employed in any industrial premises is given off by reason of the manufacturing process carried on in such premises, the competent authority may require the employer to take such effective measures as may prevent the inhalation of such dust, fume or other impurity and accumulation thereof in any work room.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Overcrowding.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No room in any industrial premises shall be overcrowded to an extent injurious to the health of the persons employed therein.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Without prejudice to the generality of sub-section (1) there shall be in any work room of such premises at least four and a quarter cubic metres of space for every person employed therein, and for the purposes of this sub-section, no account shall be taken of any space which is more than three metres above the level of the floor of the work room.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Drinking water.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The employer shall make in every industrial premises effective arrangements to provide and maintain at suitable points conveniently situated for all persons employed therein, a sufficient supply of wholesome drinking water.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All such points shall be legibly marked “drinking water” in language understood by the majority of the persons employed in the industrial premises and no such point shall be situated within six metres of any washing place, urinal or latrine except with the prior approval in writing of the competent authority.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Latrines and urinals.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In every industrial premises, sufficient latrine and urinal accommodation of such types as may be prescribed shall be provided and shall be so conveniently situated as may be accessible to the employees at all times while they are in the industrial premises:</p>
            <p>Provided that it shall not be necessary to provide separate urinals in industrial premises where less than fifty persons are employed or where the latrines are connected to a water-borne sewage system.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may specify the number of latrines and urinals which shall be provided in any industrial premises in proportion to any number of male and female employees ordinarily employed therein, and may provide for such further matters in respect of sanitation in the industrial premises including obligation of the employees in this regard as it may consider necessary in the interest of the health of the persons employed therein.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Washing facilities.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In every industrial premises, where blending or sieving or both of tobacco or warming of beedi in hot ovens is carried on, the employer shall provide such washing facilities for the use of the employees, as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Creches.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In every industrial premises wherein more than thirty female employees are ordinarily employed, there shall be provided and maintained a suitable room or rooms for the use of children under the age of six years of such female employees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Such rooms shall—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>provide adequate accommodation;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>be adequately lighted and ventilated;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>be maintained in a clean and sanitary condition;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>be under the charge of women trained in the care of children and infants.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The State Government may make rules—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>prescribing the location and the standards in respect of construction, accommodation, furniture and other equipment of rooms to be provided under this section.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>requiring the provision in any industrial premises to which this section applies, of additional facilities for the care of children belonging to female employees, including suitable provisions of facilities for washing and changing their clothing;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.3.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>requiring the provision in any industrial premises of free milk or refreshment or both for such children;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.3.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>requiring that facilities shall be given in any industrial premises for the mothers of such children to feed them at necessary intervals.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>First aid.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every industrial premises shall provide such first aid facilities as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Canteens.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by rules, require the employer to provide and maintain in every industrial premises wherein not less than two hundred and fifty employees are ordinarily employed, a canteen for the use of the employees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Working hours.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No employee shall be required or allowed to work in any industrial premises for more than nine hours in any day or for more than forty-eight hours in any week:</p>
            <p>Provided that any adult employee may be allowed to work in such industrial premises for any period in excess of the limit fixed under this section subject to the payment of overtime wages if the period of work including overtime work, does not exceed ten hours in any day and in the aggregate fifty-four hours in any week.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Wages for overtime work.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any employee employed in any industrial premises is required to work overtime, he shall be entitled in respect of such overtime work, to wages at the rate of twice his ordinary rate of wages.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the employees in an industrial premises are paid on a piece rate basis, the overtime rate shall be calculated, for the purposes of this section, at the time rates which shall be as nearly as possible equivalent to the daily average of their full time earnings for the days on which they had actually worked during the week immediately preceding the week in which the overtime work has been done.</p>
            <p>Explanation.— Where an employee had not worked on any day of the week immediately preceding the week in which the overtime work has been done, any week preceding such week in which he had actually worked shall be taken into account in calculating the overtime rate for the purposes of this sub-section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purposes of this section, “ordinary rates of wages” means the basic wages plus such allowance, including the cash equivalent of the advantage accruing through the concessional sale to the employees of foodgrains and other articles as the employee is for the time being entitled to but does not include bonus.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The cash equivalent of the advantage accruing through the concessional sale to an employee of foodgrains and other articles shall be computed as often as may be prescribed on the basis of the maximum quantity of foodgrains and other articles admissible to a standard family.</p>
            <p>Explanation I.— “Standard family” means a family consisting of the employee, his or her spouse and two children requiring in all three adult consumption units.</p>
            <p>Explanation II.— “Adult consumption units” means the consumption unit of a male above the age of fourteen years; and the consumption unit of a female above the age of fourteen years and that of a child shall be calculated at the rate of eight-tenths and six-tenths, respectively, of one adult consumption unit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Interval for rest.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The periods of work for employees in an industrial premises each day shall be so fixed that no period shall exceed five hours and that no employee shall work for more than five hours before he has an interval for rest of at least half an hour.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Spread over.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The periods of work of an employee in an industrial premises shall be so arranged that inclusive of his intervals for rest under section 19, they shall not spread over more than ten and a half hours in any day:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Chief Inspector may, for reasons to be specified in writing, increase the spread over to twelve hours.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Weekly holidays.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-21.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every industrial premises shall remain entirely closed, except for wetting of beedi or tobacco leaves, on one day in the week which day shall be specified by the employer in a notice exhibited in a conspicuous place in the industrial premises and the day so specified shall not be altered by the employer more often than once in three months and except with the previous written permission of the Chief Inspector.</p>
            <p>Provided that a copy of every such notice shall be sent to the Inspector having jurisdiction over the industrial premises within two weeks from the date on which such notice is exhibited in the industrial premises.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-21.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), an employee employed in the said premises for wetting of beedi or tobacco leaves on the day on which it remains closed in pursuance of sub-section (1), shall be allowed a substituted holiday on one of the three days immediately before or after the said day.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-21.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For a holiday under this section, an employee shall be paid, notwithstanding any contract to the contrary, at the rate equal to the daily average of his total full time earnings for the days on which he had worked during the week immediately preceding the holiday exclusive of any overtime earnings and bonus but inclusive of dearness and other allowances.</p>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <p>The expression “total full time earnings” shall have the meaning assigned to it in section 27.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Notice of periods of work.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-22.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be displayed and correctly maintained in every industrial premises a notice of periods of work in such form and in such manner as may be prescribed, showing clearly for every day the periods during which the employees may be required to work.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-22.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-22.2.list0">
              <item id="section-22.2.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>A copy of the notice referred to in sub-section (1) shall be sent in triplicate to the Inspector having jurisdiction over the industrial premises within two weeks from the date of the grant of a licence for the first time under this Act, in the case of any industrial premises carrying on work at the commencement of this Act, and in the case of any industrial premises beginning work after such commencement, before the day on which the work is begun in the industrial premises.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-22.2.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>Any proposed change in the system of work which will necessitate a change in the notice referred to in sub-section (1) shall be notified to the Inspector in triplicate before the change is made and except with the previous sanction of the Inspector, no such change shall be made until one week has elapsed since the last change.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Hours of work to correspond with notice under section 22.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No employee shall be employed in any industrial premises otherwise than in accordance with the notice of work displayed in the premises under section 22.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition of employment of children.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No child shall be required or allowed to work in any industrial premises.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition of employment of women or young persons during certain hours.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No woman or young person shall be required or allowed to work in any industrial premises except between 6 a.m. and 7 p.m.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Annual leave with wages.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-26.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-26.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Every employee in an establishment shall be allowed in a calendar year leave with wages—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-26.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>in the case of an adult, at the rate of one day for every twenty days of work performed by him during the previous calendar year;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-26.1.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>in the case of a young person at the rate of one day for every fifteen days of work performed by him during the previous calendar year.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Explanation.— The leave admissible under this sub-section shall be exclusive of all holidays whether occuring during, or at the beginning or at the end of, the period of leave.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If an employee is discharged or dismissed from service or quits employment during the course of the year, he shall be entitled to leave with wages at the rate laid down in sub-section (1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In calculating leave under this section, any fraction of leave of half a day or more shall be treated as one full day’s leave and any fraction of less than half a day shall be omitted.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any employee does not, in any calendar year take the whole of the leave allowed to him under sub-section (1), the leave not taken by him shall be added to the leave to be allowed to him in the succeeding calendar year:</p>
            <p>Provided that the total number of days of leave that may be carried forward to a succeeding year shall not exceed thirty in the case of an adult or forty in the case of a young person.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An application of an employee for the whole or any portion of the leave allowed under sub-section (1) shall be in writing and ordinarily shall have to be made sufficiently in advance of the day on which he wishes the leave to begin.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the employment of an employee who is entitled to leave under sub-section (1) is terminated by the employer before he has taken the entire leave to which he is entitled, or if having applied for leave, he has not been granted such leave, or if the employee quits his employment before he has taken the leave, the employer shall pay him the amount payable under section 27 in respect of leave not taken and such payment shall be made, where the employment of the employee is terminated by the employer, before the expiry of the second working day after such termination and where the employee quits his employment, on or before the next pay day.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The leave not availed of by an employee shall not be taken into consideration in computing the period of any notice required to be given before discharge or dismissal.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Wages during leave period.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-27.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the leave allowed to him under section 26, an employee shall be paid at the rate equal to the daily average of his total full time earnings for the days on which he had worked during the month immediately preceding his leave exclusive of any overtime earnings and bonus but inclusive of dearness and other allowances.</p>
            <p>Explanation I.— In this sub-section, the expression “total full time earnings” includes the cash equivalent of the advantage accruing through the concessional sale to employees of foodgrains and other articles, as the employee is for the time being entitled to, but does not include bonus.</p>
            <p>Explanation II.— For the purposes of determining the wages payable to a home worker during leave period or for the purpose of payment of maternity benefit to a woman home worker, “day” shall mean any period during which such home worker was employed during a period of twenty-four hours commencing at midnight, for making beedi or cigar or both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An employee who has been allowed leave for not less than four days in the case of an adult and five days in the case of a young person, shall, before his leave begins, be paid wages due for the period of the leave allowed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28">
        <num>28.</num>
        <heading>Application of the Payment of Wages Act, 1936 to industrial premises.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-28.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Payment of Wages Act, 1936 (4 of 1936) (hereinafter referred to in this section as the said Act), the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that all or any of the provisions of the said Act or the rules made thereunder shall apply to all or any class of employees in establishment or class of establishments to which this Act applies and on such application of the provisions of the said Act, an Inspector appointed under this Act shall be deemed to be the Inspector for the purposes of the enforcement of such provisions of the said Act within the local limits of his jurisdiction.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-28.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by a like notification, cancel or vary any notification issued under sub-section (1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29">
        <num>29.</num>
        <heading>Special provisions.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-29.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may permit the wetting or cutting of beedi or tobacco leaves by employees outside the industrial premises on an application made to it by the employer on behalf of such employees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The employer shall maintain in the prescribed form a record of the work permitted under sub-section (1) to be carried on outside the industrial premises.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Save as otherwise provided in this section, no employer shall require or allow any manufacturing process connected with the making of beedi or cigar or both to be carried on outside the industrial premises:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing in this sub-section shall apply to any labour who is given raw material by an employer or a contractor for being made into beedi or cigar or both at home.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-30">
        <num>30.</num>
        <heading>Onus as to age.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-30.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When any act or omission would, if a person were under a certain age, be an offence punishable under this Act and such person is, in the opinion of the court, prima facie under such age, the burden shall be on the accused to prove that such person is not under such age.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-30.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A declaration in writing by a medical officer not below the rank of a Civil Assistant Surgeon relating to an employee that he has personally examined him and believes him to be under the age stated in such declaration, shall, for the purposes of this Act and the rules made thereunder, be admissible as evidence of the age of that employee.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-31">
        <num>31.</num>
        <heading>Notice of dismissal.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-31.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No employer shall dispense with the services of an employee who has been employed for a period of six months or more, except for a reasonable cause, and without giving such employee at least one month’s notice or wages in lieu of such notice:</p>
            <p>Provided that such notice shall not be necessary if the services of such employee are dispensed with on a charge of misconduct supported by satisfactory evidence recorded at an inquiry held by the employer for the purpose.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-31.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-31.2.list0">
              <item id="section-31.2.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>The employee discharged, dismissed or retrenched may appeal to such authority and within such time as may be prescribed either on the ground that there was no reasonable cause for dispensing with his services or on the ground that he had not been guilty of misconduct as held by the employer or on the ground that such punishment of discharge or dismissal was severe.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-31.2.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>The appellate authority may, after giving notice in the prescribed manner to the employer and the employee, dismiss the appeal or direct the reinstatement of the employee with or without wages for the period during which he was kept out of employment or direct payment of compensation without reinstatement or grant such other relief as it deems fit in the circumstances of the case.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-31.2A">
          <num>(2A)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-31.2A.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The appellate authority shall have the same powers as vested in a civil court under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908, (5 of 1908) when trying a suit, in respect of the following matters, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-31.2A.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>enforcing the attendance of any person and examining him on oath; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-31.2A.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>compelling the production of documents and material objects.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-31.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The decision of the appellate authority shall be final and binding on both the parties and be given effect to within such time as may be specified in the order of the appellate authority.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-32">
        <num>32.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for obstructing Inspector.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-32.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever obstructs the Chief Inspector or an Inspector in the exercise of any powers conferred on him by or under this Act, or fails to produce on demand by the Chief Inspector or an Inspector any register or other document kept in his custody in pursuance of this Act or of any rules made thereunder, or conceals or prevents any employee in an industrial premises from appearing before or being examined by the Chief Inspector or an Inspector, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months which may extend to five thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-33">
        <num>33.</num>
        <heading>General penalty for offence.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-33.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Save as otherwise expressly provided in this Act, any person who contravenes any of the provisions of this Act or of any rule made thereunder, or fails to wages or compensation in accordance with any order of the appellate authority passed under clause (b) of sub-section (2) of section 31, shall, be punishable, for the first offence, with fine which may extend to two hundred and fifty rupees and for a second or any subsequent offence with imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than one month or more than six months or with fine which shall not be less than one hundred rupees or more than five hundred rupees or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-33.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-33.2.list0">
              <item id="section-33.2.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>Any employer who fails to reinstate any employee in accordance with the order of the appellate authority passed under clause (b) of sub-section (2) of section 31, shall be punishable with fine which may extend to two hundred and fifty rupees.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-33.2.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>Any employer, who, after having been convicted under clause (a), continues, after the date of such conviction, to fail to reinstate an employee in accordance with the order mentioned in that clause, shall be punishable, for each day of such default, with fine which may extend to twenty rupees.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-33.2.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>Any court trying an offence punishable under this sub-section may direct that the whole or any part of the fine, if realised, shall be paid, by way of compensation, to the person, who, in its opinion, has been injured by such failure.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-33.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Payment of Wages Act, 1936 (4 of 1936) with regard to the definition of wages, any compensation required to be paid by an employer under clause (b) of sub-section (2) of section 31 but not paid by him shall be recoverable as delayed wages under the provisions of that Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-33.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be no defence in a prosecution of any person for the contravention of the provisions of section 3 that any manufacturing process connected with the making of beedi or cigar or both was carried on by such person himself of by any member of his family or by any other person living with or dependant on such person.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-34">
        <num>34.</num>
        <heading>Offences by companies.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-34.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an offence under this Act has been committed by a company, every person who, at the time the offence was committed was incharge of, and was responsible to, the company for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to any punishment provided in this Act if he proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or that he exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-34.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is attributable to, any neglect on the part of any director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such director, manager; secretary or other officer shall also deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.</p>
            <blockList id="section-34.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation.— For the purposes of this section—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-34.2.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“company” means any body corporate and includes a firm, and other association of individuals; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-34.2.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“director”, in relation to a firm, means a partner in the firm.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-35">
        <num>35.</num>
        <heading>Indemnity.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-35.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against any person for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or any rule or order made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-35.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No suit or other legal proceedings shall lie against the Government for any damage caused or likely to be caused by anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any rule or order made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-36">
        <num>36.</num>
        <heading>Cognizance of offences.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-36.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No Court shall take cognizance of any offence punishable under this Act except upon a complaint made by, or with the previous sanction in writing of the Chief Inspector or an Inspector within three months of the date on which the alleged commission of the offence came to the knowledge of the Inspector:</p>
            <p>Provided that where the offence consists of disobeying a written order made by the competent authority, the Chief Inspector or an Inspector, complaint thereof may be made within six months of the date on which the offence is alleged to have been committed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-36.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No Court inferior to that of a presidency magistrate or a magistrate of the first class shall try any offence punishable under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-37">
        <num>37.</num>
        <heading>Application of the Industrial Employment (Standing Orders) Act, 1946 and the Maternity Benefit Act, 1961.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-37.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of the Industrial Employment (Standing Orders) Act, 1946 (20 of 1946) shall apply to every industrial premises wherein fifty or more persons are employed or were employed on any one day of the preceding twelve months as if such industrial premises were an industrial establishment to which that Act has been applied by a notification under sub-section (3) of section 1 thereof, and as if the employee in the said premises were a workman within the meaning of that Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-37.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1) the State Government may, after giving not less than two months’ notice of its intention so to do, by notification in the Official Gazette, apply all or any of the provisions of the Industrial Employment (Standing Orders) Act, 1946 (20 of 1946), to any industrial premises wherein less than fifty employees are employed or were employed on any one day of the preceding twelve months as if such industrial premises were an industrial establishment to which Act has been applied by a notification under sub-section (3) of section 1 thereof, and as if the employee in the said premises were a workman within the meaning of that Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-37.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Maternity Benefit Act, 1961 (53 of 1961), the provisions of that Act shall apply to every establishment as if such establishment were an establishment to which that Act has been applied by a notification under sub-section (1) of section 2 thereof:</p>
            <blockList id="section-37.3.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that the said Act shall, in its application to a home worker, apply subject to the following modifications, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-37.3.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in section 5, in the Explanation to sub-section (1), the words “or one rupee a day, whichever is higher” shall be omitted; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-37.3.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>sections 8 and 10 shall be omitted.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-38">
        <num>38.</num>
        <heading>Certain provisions not to apply to industrial premises.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-38.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>'(1) Chapter IV and section 85 of the Factories Act, 1948 (62 of 1948) shall apply to an industrial premises and the rest of the provisions in that Act shall not apply to any industrial premises.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-38.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing contained in any law relating to the regulation of the conditions of work of workers in shops or commercial establishments shall apply to any establishment to which this Act applies.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-39">
        <num>39.</num>
        <heading>Application of the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-39.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 (14 of 1947) shall apply to matters arising in respect of every industrial premises.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-39.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-39.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), a dispute between an employer and employee relating to—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-39.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the issue by the employer of raw materials to the employees,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the rejection by the employer of beedi or cigar or both made by an employee,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the payment of wages for the beedi or cigar or both rejected by the employer,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall be referred for settlement within such time and by such authority as the State Government may, by rules, specify in this behalf and such rules may also provide for the summary manner in which such dispute shall be settled.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-39.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person aggrieved by a settlement made by the authority specified under sub-section (2) may prefer an appeal to such authority and within such time as the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-39.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The decision of the authority specified under sub-section (3) shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-40">
        <num>40.</num>
        <heading>Effect of law and agreements inconsistent with this Act.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-40.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained in any other law for the time being in force or in the terms of any award, agreement or contract of service whether made before or after the commencement of this Act.</p>
            <p>Provided that where under any such award, agreement, contract of service or otherwise an employee is entitled to benefits in respect of any matters which are more favourable to him than those to which he will be entitled to under this Act, the employee shall continue to be entitled to the more favourable benefits in respect of that matter notwithstanding that he receives benefits in respect of other matters under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-40.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing contained in this Act shall be construed as precluding any employee from entering into an agreement with an employer for granting him rights or privileges in respect of any matter which are more favourable to him than those to which he would be entitled under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-41">
        <num>41.</num>
        <heading>Power to exempt.­—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-41.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, exempt, subject to such conditions and restrictions as it may impose, any class of industrial premises or class of employers or employees from all or any of the provisions of this Act or of any rules made thereunder:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing in this section shall be constructed as empowering the State Government to grant any exemption in respect of any woman employee from any of the provisions of this Act or any rules made thereunder relating to annual leave with wages, maternity benefits, creches, wages, rejection of beedi or cigar and night work.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-42">
        <num>42.</num>
        <heading>Powers of Central Government to give directions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-42.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may give directions to a State Government as to the carrying into execution of the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-43">
        <num>43.</num>
        <heading>Act not to apply to self-employed persons in private dwelling houses.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-43.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Nothing contained in this Act shall apply to the owner or occupier of a private dwelling house who carries on any manufacturing process in such private dwelling house with the assistance of the members of his family living with him in such dwelling house and dependant on him:</p>
            <p>Provided that the owner or occupier thereof is not an employee of an employer to whom this Act applies.</p>
            <p>Explanation.— For the purposes of this section, “family” means the spouse and children of the owner or occupier.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-44">
        <num>44.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-44.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-44.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-44.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-44.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the terms and conditions subject to which a licence may be granted or renewed under this Act and the fees to be paid in respect of such licence;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the form of application for a licence under this Act and the documents and plans to be submitted together with such application;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>other matters which are to be taken into consideration by the competent authority for granting or refusing a licence;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the time within which, the fees on payment of which and the authority to which, appeals may be preferred against any order granting or refusing to grant a licence;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the submission of a monthly return by an employer to the competent authority specifying the quantity of tobacco released by the Central Excise Department and the number of beedi or cigar or both manufactured by him;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the powers which may be conferred on the Inspectors under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the standards of cleanliness required to be maintained under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the standards of lighting, ventilation and temperature required to be maintained under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the types of urinals and latrines required to be provided under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.2.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>the washing facilities which are to be provided under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.2.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>canteens;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.2.list1.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>the form and manner of notice regarding the periods of work;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.2.list1.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>the form in which records of work done outside an establishment shall be maintained;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.2.list1.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>the authority to which and the time within which an appeal may be filed by a dismissed, discharged or retrenched employee;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.2.list1.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>the manner in which the cash equivalent of the advantage accruing through the concessional sale to an employee of foodgrains and other articles shall be computed;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.2.list1.p">
                <num>(p)</num>
                <p>the records and registers that shall be maintained in an establishment for the purpose of securing compliance with the provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.2.list1.q">
                <num>(q)</num>
                <p>the maintenance of first aid boxes or cupboards and the contents thereof and the persons in whose charge such boxes shall be placed;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.2.list1.r">
                <num>(r)</num>
                <p>the manner in which sorting or rejection of beedi or cigar or both and disposal of rejected beedi or cigar or both shall be carried out;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.2.list1.s">
                <num>(s)</num>
                <p>the fixation of maximum limit of the percentage of rejection of beedi or cigar or both manufactured by an employee;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.2.list1.t">
                <num>(t)</num>
                <p>specifying the place at which wages shall be paid to persons who receive directly or through an agent raw materials for the manufacture of beedi or cigar or both at home;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.2.list1.u">
                <num>(u)</num>
                <p>supervision by the Inspectors over distribution of raw materials including beedi and tobacco leaves to the employees;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.2.list1.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>precautions to be taken against fire for the safety of workers;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.2.list1.w">
                <num>(w)</num>
                <p>the time within which a dispute specified in sub-section (2) of section 39 shall be referred for settlement, the authority by which and the summary manner in which such dispute shall be settled and the authority to which an appeal shall be from the settlement made by the first-mentioned authority;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.2.list1.x">
                <num>(x)</num>
                <p>any matter which is required to be, or may be, prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-44.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All rules made under this Act shall be published in the Official Gazette and shall be subject to the condition of previous publication; and the dates to be specified under clause (3) of section 23 of the General Clauses Act, 1897 (10 of 1897), shall not be less than three months from the date on which draft of the proposed rules was published.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-44.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made, before each house of the State Legislature, where it consists of two Houses, or where such Legislature consists of one house, before that House, while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session in which it is so laid or the session immediately following the Legislatures agree in making any modification in the rule or the Legislatures agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however, that any such modification or annulment, shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
