<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-wbg/act/1866/2/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-wbg/act/1866/2"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Calcutta Suburban Police Act, 1866"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-wbg/act/1866/2/eng@2017-01-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-wbg/act/1866/2/eng@2017-01-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-wbg/act/1866/2/eng@2017-01-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-wbg/act/1866/2/eng@2017-01-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Calcutta Suburban Police Act, 1866</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[21st March, 1866]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[NO. 2 of 1866]</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the better regulation of the police within the suburbs of the town of Calcutta.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to exclude the suburbs of the town of Calcutta form the general police-district of Bengal, and to make provision for the better regulation of the police within the limits so excluded.</p>
        <p>It is enacted as follows:—</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Suburbs may be excluded from general police-district.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>It shall be lawful for the State Government of West Bengal to exclude the suburbs of the town of Calcutta, or any portion thereof, from the general police-district of the States subject to its control; and the limits of the tract of country so excluded shall be defined in a notification to be published in the Official Gazette and the operation of this Act shall be confined to such limits:</p>
            <p>Provided that it shall be lawful for the said State Government from time to time to alter such limits by such notification as aforesaid.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Police for suburbs.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>For the suburbs of the town of Calcutta so defined as aforesaid there shall be a police-force, which shall consist of such number of officers and shall be otherwise constituted in such manner, as shall be from time to time ordered by the State Government of West Bengal.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Police to be under control of Commissioner of Police, Calcutta.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The police-force of the suburbs of the town of Calcutta shall be under the exclusive direction and control of the Commissioner of Police for the town of Calcutta, who may from time to time, subject to the control of the said State Government, frame such orders and regulations as he shall deem expedient relative to the general Government of the force, the places of residence, the classification, rank, distribution and particular service of the several members thereof, their inspection, and the description of arms, accoutrements and other necessaries to be furnished to them, and all such other orders and regulations relative to the said police-force as the said Commissioner shall from time to time deem expedient for preventing neglect or abuse, and for rendering such force efficient in the discharge of all its duties.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3A">
        <num>3A.</num>
        <heading>Power of State Government to frame rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act , the State Government may make rules relating to recruitment, conditions of service, disciplinary proceedings and punishments, in respect of members of the subordinate ranks of the Police-force.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any rules, orders or regulations made before the commencement of the Calcutta and Suburban Police (Amendment) Act, 1962 (West Ben. Act XV of 1962), by any authority in respect of the aforesaid matters shall, in so far as they are not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, be deemed to have been validly made and shall continue in force until other provisions are made in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3B">
        <num>3B.</num>
        <heading>Appointment, dismissal and punishment of subordinate ranks of the Police force.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3B.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to such rules as the State Government may make in this behalf, the Commissioner of Police shall have the power to appoint all members of the subordinate ranks of the Police-force:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Commissioner of Police may, with the approval of the State Government, delegate such power of appointment in respect of all subordinate ranks of the Police-force except Inspectors, to any Additional, Joint, Deputy, Additional Deputy or Assistant Commissioner of Police appointed under section 5 of the Calcutta Police Act, 1866 (Ben. Act IV of 1866).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3B.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of sections 4 and 5, the appointing authority or an officer not lower in rank than the appointing authority, shall be competent to inflict all punishments on the members of the subordinate ranks of the Police-force in disciplinary cases.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3C">
        <num>3C.</num>
        <heading>Validity of appointment, dismissal and punishment of subordinate ranks in certain cases.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3C.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained elsewhere in this Act or any decision of any court to the contrary, all appointments made by the Commissioner of Police or any other authority subordinate to him, all orders of dismissal or removal from office passed by any such appointing authority or other authority not subordinate to such appointing authority and all orders inflicting any other punishment passed by any authority, before the commencement of the Calcutta and Suburban Police (Amendment) Act, 1962, in respect of members of the subordinate ranks of the Police-force shall be deemed to be and to have always been validly passed as if the said Act were in force when such appointments were made or such orders were passed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Suspension or dismissal or other punishment of subordinate ranks of police-force by Commissioner.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commissioner of Police may, at any time, suspend or dismiss or inflict any other punishment on any member of the subordinate ranks of the police force whom he shall think remiss or negligent in the discharge of his duty or otherwise unfit for the same.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A Police-officer shall not by reason of being suspended from office cease to be a Police-officer. During the term of such suspension the power, privileges and duties conferred or imposed upon him as a Police-officer shall be in abeyance, but he shall continue subject to the same responsibilities, discipline and penalties, and to the same authorities, as if he had not been suspended.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4A">
        <num>4A.</num>
        <heading>Duties of Police-officers.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4A.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>It shall be the duty of every Police-officer—all be the duty of every Police-officer—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4A.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>promptly to serve every summons and obey and execute every warrant or other order lawfully issued to him by competent authority, and to endeavour by all lawful means to give effect to the lawful commands of his superiors;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4A.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to the best of his ability, to obtain intelligence concerning the commission of cognizable offences, or designs to commit such offences and to lay such information and to take such other steps, consistent with law and with the orders of his superiors as are best calculated to bring offenders to justice or to prevent the commission of cognizable offences, or the commission of non-cognizable offences, within his view</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4A.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to the best of his ability, to prevent the commission of public nuisances;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4A.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>to apprehend all persons whom he is legally authorised to apprehend, and for whose apprehension there is sufficient reason;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4A.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>to aid any other police-officer, when called on by him or in case of need in the discharge of his duty, in such ways as would be lawful and reasonable on the part of the officer aided;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4A.1.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>to discharge such duties as are imposed upon him by any law for the time being in force;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4A.1.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>to afford every assistance within his power to disabled or helpless persons in the streets, and to take charge of intoxicated persons and of lunatics at large who appear to be dangerous or to be incapable of taking care of themselves;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4A.1.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>to take prompt measures to produce necessary help for any person under arrest or in custody who is wounded or sick and, while guarding or conducting any such person to have due regard to his condition;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4A.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>to arrange for the proper sustenance and shelter of every person who is under arrest or in custody;elter of every person who is under arrest or in custody;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4A.1.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>in conducting searches, to refrain from needless rudeness and the causing of unnecessary annoyance;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4A.1.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>in dealing with woman and children, to act with strict regard to decency and with reasonable gentleness;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4A.1.list1.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <blockList id="section-4A.1.list1.l.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>to use his best endeavours—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-4A.1.list1.l.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>to prevent any loss or damage by fire, and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-4A.1.list1.l.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>to avert any accident or danger to the public;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4A.1.list1.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>to regulate and control the traffic in the streets, to prevent obstruction therein, and to the best of his ability to prevent the infraction of any rule or order made under this Act or under any other law for the time being in force for observance by the public in or near the streets;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4A.1.list1.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>to keep order in the streets, and at and within public bathing, washing and landing places, fairs and all other places of public resort, and in the neighbourhood of places of public worship during the time of public worship;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4A.1.list1.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>to regulate resort to public bathing, washing and landing places, to prevent overcrowding thereat and in public ferryboats, and, to the best of his ability, to prevent the infraction of any rule or order lawfully made for observance by the public at any such place or any such boat;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4A.1.list1.p">
                <num>(p)</num>
                <p>to perform all duties imposed on him by rules for the time being in force under this Act , in the manner and subject to the conditions therein prescribed.ject to the conditions therein prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All persons shall be bound to confirm to the reasonable directions of a Police-officer given in fulfilment of any of the said duties.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A Police-officer may restrain or remove any person resisting, or refusing to confirm to, any such direction as aforesaid.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Commissioner may fine for lesser breaches of discipline.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>For any lesser breach of discipline or other misconduct not requiring the suspension or dismissal of the offender, a member of the subordinate ranks of the police-force may be fined by the Commissioner any sum not exceeding one-half of his monthly pay.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Additional penalties for neglect of duty, etc.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Rep. by section 34 of the Calcutta and Suburban Police (Amendment) Act , 1910 (Ben. Act III of 1910).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Police not to resign without notice.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No member of the subordinate ranks of the police-force to be enrolled under this Act shall be at liberty to resign his office, or to withdraw himself from the duties thereof, unless expressly allowed so to do in writing by the Commissioner, or unless he shall have given to the Commissioner six months’ notice of his intention if a member of the mounted branch of the said force, and two months’ notice if a member of any other branch;</p>
            <p>and every member of the said force who shall so resign or withdraw himself without such leave or notice shall be liable, on the order of the Commissioner, to forfeit all arrears of pay then due to him, and, on the sentence of a Magistrate, to pay a fine not exceeding fifty rupees, or to undergo imprisonment of either description for any term not exceeding two months.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>On enrolment, Police-officer to receive certificate.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every member of the police-force shall receive on his enrolment a certificate in the form hereunto annexed under the signature of the Commissioner of Police, by virtue of which he shall be vested with the powers, functions and privileges of a Police-officer.</p>
            <p>Such certificate shall cease to have effect whenever the person named in it is suspended or dismissed, or otherwise removed from employment in the force.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8A">
        <num>8A.</num>
        <heading>Member of subordinate ranks of the police-force prohibited from other employment.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8A.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A member of the subordinate ranks of the police-force shall not, without the permission of the Commissioner of Police, either as principal or agent,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8A.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>engage in any trade, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8A.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>be in any way concerned in the purchase or sale of any immovable property within the town or suburbs of Calcutta or of any interest therein, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8A.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>hold any office or practise any profession or engage in any employment whatever other than his office or duties as such Police-officer.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8B">
        <num>8B.</num>
        <heading>Offences by Police-officers.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8B.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8B.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any Police-officer who—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8B.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>contravenes any provision of the last foregoing section, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8B.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>is guilty of cowardice, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8B.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>is guilty of any wilful breach or neglect of any provision of law or of any rule or order which it is his duty as such Police-officer to observe or obey, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8B.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>is guilty of any violation of duty for which no punishment is expressly provided by any other law for the time being in force,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall be liable to imprisonment, with or without hard labour, for a term which may extend to three months, or to fine which may extend to one hundred rupees and which may be deducted from any salary due to him, or to both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8C">
        <num>8C.</num>
        <heading>Vexatious entry, search, seizure, arrest, detention, etc., by Police-officers.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8C.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8C.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any Police-officer who—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8C.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>without lawful authority or reasonable cause, enters or searches, or causes to be entered or searched, any building, vessel, tent or place, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8C.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>vexatiously and unnecessarily seizes the property of any person, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8C.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>vexatiously and unnecessarily detains, searches or arrests any person, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8C.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>vexatiously and unnecessarily delays forwarding any person arrested to a Magistrate or to any other authority to whom he is legally bound to forward such person, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8C.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>offers any unnecessary personal violence to any person in his custody, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8C.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>holds out to an accused person any threat or promise not warranted by law,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall be liable to imprisonment, with or without hard labour, for a term which may extend to six months, or to fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, or to both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8D">
        <num>8D.</num>
        <heading>False statement to obtain employment or release.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8D.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any person who knowingly makes a false statement or uses a false document, for the purpose of obtaining for himself or any other person employment or release from employment as a Police-officer, shall be liable to imprisonment, with or without hard labour, for a term which may extend to three months, or to fine which may extend to one hundred rupees, or to both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for dismissed members not delivering up clothing, etc.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every member of the police-force who shall be dismissed from or shall cease to hold and exercise his office, and who shall not forth with deliver up his certificate, and all the clothing, accoutrements and appointments and other necessaries which may have been supplied to him for the execution of his duty, to the Commissioner or to such person and at such time and place as shall be directed by the said Commissioner, shall be liable, on conviction before a Magistrate, to imprisonment of either description for any term not exceeding one month.</p>
            <p>And it shall be lawful for the Commissioner, or for any Magistrate, to issue his warrant to search for and seize all the clothing, accoutrements, appointments and other necessaries which shall not be delivered over, wherever the same may be found.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-11. Omitted.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Appointment of special constables.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Commissioner of Police may, of his own authority, appoint special constables to assist on any temporary emergency.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Powers of special constables.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every special constable so appointed shall have the same powers, privileges and protection, and shall be liable to perform the same duties, and shall be amendable to the same penalties, and be subordinate to the same authorities, as the ordinary officers of police.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for special constable neglecting or refusing to serve etc.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any person, being appointed a special constable as aforesaid, shall, without sufficient excuse, neglect or refuse to serve as such, or to obey such lawful order or direction as may be given to him for the performance of his duties, he shall be liable, upon conviction before a Magistrate to a fine not exceeding fifty rupees for every such neglect, refusal or disobedience.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14A">
        <num>14A.</num>
        <heading>Special Police-Officers and Traffic Wardens.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the control of the State Government, the Commissioner of Police may raise a force of special police-officers and a force of Traffic Wardens for the suburbs of the town of Calcutta and may also disband such a force without assigning any reason or serving any notice and without payment of any compensation or damages whatsoever to any member of the force.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The strength of the forces of special Police-officers and Traffic Wardens shall be such as may be determined from time to time by the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commissioner of Police shall be the appointing authority in respect of the special police officers and Traffic Wardens:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Commissioner of Police may, in respect of special police officers and Traffic Wardens, belonging to such class or holding such rank as may be specified by him, delegate his power of appointment to any Additional, Joint, Deputy, Additional Deputy or Assistant Commissioner of Police authorised by him in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14A.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14A.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Commissioner of Police may, with the previous approval of the State Government, frame separate regulations for the special police officers and the Traffic Wardens relating to the following matters, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14A.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the method of recruitment and the form of certificate of appointment,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14A.4.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>classification and rank,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14A.4.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>uniform, equipment and badges,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14A.4.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>training, including attendance at drills and parades,ills and parades,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14A.4.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>allocation of duties and hours of duty,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14A.4.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>promotion, discipline and punishment, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14A.4.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>all other terms and conditions of their service. terms and conditions of their service.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14A.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A special police officer or a Traffic Warden appointed under this section shall, except in so far as it is not inconsistent with the other sub-sections of this section and any regulations framed under sub-section (4), have the same powers, privileges and protection and the same duties and shall be liable to the same penalties as ordinary officers of police.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14A.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A special police officer or a Traffic Warden appointed under this section shall be a part-time officer who shall not be entitled to any remuneration for his services as such special police officer or Traffic Warden and whose appointment shall be liable to termination by the appointing authority any time after giving him one month’s notice but without payment of any compensation or damages whatsoever.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Appointment of additional Police-officers on application of private persons.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may also, if it shall think fit, on the application of any person, showing the necessity of it, appoint any additional number of Police-officers to keep the peace at any place within the limits of the operation of this Act , at the charge of the person applying, but subject to the orders of the Commissioner of Police and for such time as it shall think fit; and every such Police-officer shall receive a certificate, by virtue of which he shall be vested with all the powers, privileges and duties of the Police-officers belonging to the ordinary force:</p>
            <p>Provided that the person upon whose application such appointment shall have been made may, upon giving one month’s notice in writing to the Commissioner of Police, require that the Police-officers so appointed at his expense, shall be discontinued, and thereupon the State Government shall discontinue such additional Police-officers; and all moneys received by the State Government for the payment of any such additional Police-officers shall be accounted by it.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15A">
        <num>15A.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of divisions and sections.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-15A.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Subject to the control of the State Government, the Commissioner of Police shall, by order,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15A.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>constitute such and so many police divisions as he thinks fit, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15A.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>sub-divide such divisions into such and so many sections as he thinks fit,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15A.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>define the limits and extent of such division and sections.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every such order shall be published in the Official Gazette and in the manner prescribed by this Act for the publication of public notices.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15B">
        <num>15B.</num>
        <heading>Wrongfully entering or remaining in or on building, land, vehicle, etc.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15B.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever, without satisfactory excuse, wilfully enters or remains in or upon any dwelling-house or private premises or any land or ground attached thereto; or any ground, building, monument or structure belonging to the Government or appropriate to public purposes, or any vehicle, boat or vessel, shall, whether he causes any act ual damage or not, be liable to fine which may extend to twenty rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Apprehension and punishment of reputed thieves, etc.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A Police-officer may arrest without a warrant—</p>
            <p>any person found, between sunset and sunrise, armed with any dangerous or offensive instrument whatsoever, with intent to commit any offence against the person or property of another;</p>
            <p>any reputed thief found, between sunset and sunrise, on board any vessel or boat, or lying or loitering in any bazar, street, yard, thoroughfare or other place, who shall not give a satisfactory account of himself;</p>
            <p>any person found, between sunset and sunrise, having his face covered or otherwise disguised, with intent to commit any such offences as aforesaid;</p>
            <p>any person found, between sunset and sunrise, in any dwelling-house or other building whatsoever, without being able satisfactorily to account for his presence therein; and</p>
            <p>any person having in his possession, without lawful excuse (the proof of which excuse shall be on such person), any implement of house-breaking;</p>
            <p>and such person shall be liable to imprisonment, with or without hard labour, for a term not exceeding three months.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-17B. Omitted.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17C">
        <num>17C.</num>
        <heading>Power to order discontinuance of music in certain cases.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17C.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commissioner of Police may, upon complaint made to him in writing by any person, by written order direct the discontinuance in any place of music or singing, the beating of drums or tomtoms, and the blowing or sounding of horns or other noisy instruments if he is satisfied that the same is a nuisance and ought to be summarily stopped either on account of the dangerous illness of, or because if seriously interferes with the reasonable occupation of, any person resident or lawfully engaged in the neighbourhood:</p>
            <p>Provided that in any case where the discontinuance of music, or other sounds as aforesaid, is so ordered, it shall be lawful for a Magistrate, upon the complaint of any person aggrieved and if satisfied that the order complained of is unreasonable under the circumstances, to alter or reverse such order as he deems fit, and the Commissioner of Police shall give effect to any such alteration or reversal:</p>
            <p>Provided also that nothing in this section shall apply to music or other sounds as aforesaid in any place of public worship, or on the occasion of any religious observance or ceremony.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17C.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person who contravenes an order of the Commissioner of Police passed under sub-section (1) shall be punished with a fine which may extend to one hundred rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17D">
        <num>17D.</num>
        <heading>Power to prohibit, restrict, regulate or impose conditions on the use of micro-phones, etc.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17D.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-17D.1.list0">
              <item id="section-17D.1.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>If, in the opinion of the Commissioner of Police, it is necessary so to do for the purpose of preventing annoyance to, or injury to the health of, the public or any section thereof, or for the purpose of maintaining public peace and tranquillity, he may, by order prohibit, restrict, regulate or impose conditions on, the use or operation in any area within the suburbs of the town of Calcutta or in any vehicle within such area, of microphones, loudspeakers, or other apparatus for amplifying human voice or amplifying music or other sounds.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17D.1.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>The State Government may, on its own motion or on the representation of any person or persons aggrieved, modify, alter or cancel any such order.er.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17D.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A Police-officer, not below the rank of a Sub-Inspector or a Sergeant, may take such steps or use such force as may be reasonably necessary for securing compliance with any order made under clause (a) of sub-section (1) or any such order as modified or altered by the State Government under clause (b) of that sub-section and may seize any microphone, loudspeaker or other apparatus used or operated in contravention of the order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17D.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A police officer referred to above, who seizes any microphone, loudspeaker or other apparatus under sub-section (2), may also at the same time seize any vehicle in which such micro-phone, loudspeaker or other apparatus is being carried or conveyed or is being kept at that time:</p>
            <p>Provided that any officer of the police-station within the limits of which the vehicle is seized not below the rank of a Sub-Inspector may release such vehicle on a bond for such sum, not exceeding five hundred rupees, as he deems reasonable, being executed by the owner of the vehicle in favour of the State Government to produce the vehicle at the time of the investigation or the trial, and to surrender the vehicle, if directed to be forfeited under sub-section (4).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17D.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person who contravenes any order of the Commissioner of Police made under clause (a) of sub-section (1) or who contravenes any such order as modified or altered by the State Government under clause (b) of that sub-section, shall be punished with a fine which may extend to one hundred rupees and the court trying an offence under this section may also direct the forfeiture of any microphone, loudspeaker or other apparatus seized under sub-section (2) or any vehicle seized under sub-section (3) or released under the proviso to that sub-section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17D.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of this section shall be in addition to and not in derogation of the powers conferred by any other section of this Act .</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for keeping hotel, etc., without license.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever has or keeps any hotel, tavern, punch-house, alehouse, arrack or toddy shop, or place for the sale or consumption of ganja, chandu or other preparation of opium, hemp or other intoxicating drug, plant or substance,</p>
            <p>or has or keeps any lodging-house whether provisions, liquors or refreshments are sold or consumed therein or not,</p>
            <p>or has or keeps any coffee-house, boarding-house, eating-house, other place of public resort and entertainment, wherein provisions, liquors or refreshments are sold or consumed (Whether the same be kept or retained therein or procured elsewhere),</p>
            <p>without a license to be obtained in the manner hereinafter mentioned,</p>
            <p>shall be liable, on summary conviction before a Magistrate, to imprisonment, with or without hard labour, for a term not exceeding six months or to a fine not exceeding one thousand rupees or to both and for a second or subsequent offence also to forfeiture of all movable properties found in or on such hotel, tavern, house, shop or place:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing in this Act shall apply to the sale, in reasonable quantities, of any drug, plant or substance in any chemist’s or druggist’s shop for medicinal purposes only.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Excise license not to be granted without certificate of Commissioner of Police.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No license shall be granted under the provisions of the Bengal Excise Act, 1909 (Ben. Act V of 1909), unless the person applying for such license shall produce a certificate from the Commissioner of Police, stating that a license may be granted to him for the sale of spirituous liquors or intoxicating drugs, as the case may be, without risk or detriment to the preservation of peace and good order and containing a full statement of such conditions as may have been imposed and shall have remained in force, under the provisions hereinafter contained, at the date when such license shall be granted.</p>
            <p>No license so granted shall be renewable without a fresh certificate as aforesaid previously obtained from the Commissioner of Police.</p>
            <p>The Commissioner of Police shall, in granting or refusing certificates under this section, be subject to the direction and control of the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Duration and condition of license.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>It shall be competent to the Commissioner of Police, subject to the direction and control of the said State Government, to limit in such certificate as aforesaid, the period for which the license may be granted, and also to fix such conditions as he may deem necessary for securing the good behaviour of the keepers of the houses and places of entertainment as aforesaid, and for the prevention of drunkenness and disorder among the persons frequenting the same, and from time to time to vary such conditions, subject to such direction and control as aforesaid; and no license granted under the Bengal Excise Act, 1909 (Ben. Act V of 1909), shall be valid unless it shall contain such conditions as shall have been imposed and shall remain in force for the time being under this section.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for keeping up sign-board or notice after expiry of license.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whenever any license granted as aforesaid shall have ceased to have effect, it shall be lawful for the Commissioner of Police to order the person to whom such license shall have been granted to remove or cause to be removed any sign-board or other notice which such person might have been therefore bound, under the terms of his said license, to keep affixed on or near the house or place of public resort or entertainment for which such license had been granted; and any person who shall fail to obey any such order forthwith shall be liable, on conviction, to a fine of ten rupees for every day thereafter during which he shall so fail.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Commissioner may grant license for places for which no licenses are required under the Bengal Excise Act, 1909.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-22.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commissioner of Police may, at his descretion, from time to time, grant licenses to the keepers of such houses or places of public resort and entertainment as aforesaid for which no such license as is specified in the Bengal Excise Act, 1909, is required, upon such conditions, to be inserted in every such license as he, with the sanction of the said State Government from time to time shall order, for securing the good behaviour of the keepers of the said houses or places of public resort of entertainment, and the prevention of drunkenness and disorder among the persons frequenting or using the same; and the said licenses may be granted, by the said Commissioner for any term not exceeding one year:</p>
            <blockList id="section-22.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that the said Commissioner may, by order, refuse to grant any license under this sub-section, if, for reasons to be recorded in writing, he is of the opinion that—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-22.1.list2.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the character or antecedents of the applicant for such licence or the nature of the trade or calling pursued by him, make him unsuitable for the grant of such licence; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-22.1.list2.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>the location of the house or place of public resort and entertainment in respect of which such licence is required is unsuitable for the grant of such licence on the ground of congestion of traffic, want of adequate space for parking vehicle or difficulty in maintaining public peace, order or safety or on any other similar grounds.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-22.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person aggrieved by an order refusing to grant a licence under the proviso to sub-section (1) may, within thirty days from the date of such order, prefer an appeal against such order to the State government and the State Government may, after giving the appellant an opportunity of being heard, confirm, modify or set aside such order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for breach of condition of license.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any person committing a breach of any of the conditions of a license granted either under section 19 or section 22 of this Act shall, on conviction before a Magistrate, be punishable by a fine not exceeding one hundred rupees, and such fine shall be recovered from the person licensed, notwithstanding that such breach may have been owing to the default or carelessness of the servant or other person in charge of the shop or place of sale.</p>
            <p>Any person so convicted shall also be liable to the forfeiture of his license, at the discretion of the Commissioner of Police, subject to the direction and control of the said State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Fees for certificates, licenses and passes.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>For every certificate, license or pass granted by the Commissioner of Police under this Act there shall be levied a fee at the rate specified in the Schedule of fees annexed to this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-32. Omitted.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-33">
        <num>33.</num>
        <heading>Pawn-brokers and money-changers to report stolen property under penalty for neglect.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-33.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any property answering the description set forth in any information which shall be given by any Police-officer to any pawn-broker or dealer in second-hand property, or moneychanger, regarding property stolen or fraudulently obtained, shall then be or thereafter come into the possession of, or be offered in pawn or for sale or change to, such pawn-broker, dealer or money-changer, he shall without unnecessary delay, give information to that effect at the nearest police-station, and shall also state the name and address given by the party by whom the same was offered, or from whom the same was received:</p>
            <p>Provided always that, in the case of wearing apparel or other articles which it may be difficult for such pawn-broker or dealer to trace out and identity, no fine shall be exigible in respect of not reporting such articles, unless it shall appear to the Magistrate that such articles had been knowingly concealed by such pawn-broker or dealer.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-33A">
        <num>33A.</num>
        <heading>Possession of or dealing with thing stolen or fraudulently obtained.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-33A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever has in his possession, or conveys in any manner, or offers for sale or pawn, anything which there is reason to believe to have been stolen or fraudulently obtained shall, if he fails to account for such possession or act to the satisfaction of the Magistrate, be liable to fine which may extend to one hundred rupees, or to imprisonment, with or without hard labour, for a term which may extend to three months.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-33A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person charged under sub-section (1) in respect of anything declares that he received such thing from some other person, or that he was employed as a carrier, agent or servant to convey such thing for some other person.</p>
            <p>the Magistrate, after such further inquiry (if any) as he may deem necessary, may summon such other person, and any former or pretended purchaser or other person through whose possession such thing is alleged to have passed, to appear before him, and may examine such person and any witnesses who are produced to testify to such, receipt employment or possession;</p>
            <p>and if it appears to the Magistrate, that any such person had possession of such thing and had reasonable cause to believe that it was stolen or fraudulently obtained, the Magistrate may punish him with fine which may extend to one hundred rupees or with imprisonment, with or without hard labour, for a term which may extend to three months.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-34">
        <num>34.</num>
        <heading>Manufacture or possession of gun-powder.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-34.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever shall manufacture gunpowder or, without a license from the Commissioner of Police, shall have in his possession, in any house, shop, warehouse or other building, at any one time, a greater quantity of gunpowder than ten pounds shall be liable to a fine not exceeding five hundred rupees, and also to forfeit such gunpowder so manufactured or possessed, together with the vessel or receptable in which it may be contained.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-35">
        <num>35.</num>
        <heading>Omitted.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-36">
        <num>36.</num>
        <heading>Licenses for conveying and removing gunpowder.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-36.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Commissioner of Police may grant to any person a license for the transit and carrying of gunpowder from one place to another, in such manner and in such quantity as he may deem advisable; and any person, not being duly licensed in that behalf, who shall carry or convey a greater quantity of gunpowder than one pound from one place to another, shall be liable to a fine not exceeding fifty rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-37">
        <num>37.</num>
        <heading>Commissioner may issue warrant to search for explosive substance.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-37.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Commissioner of Police, on credible information laid before him on oath, and reduced to writing, may issue his warrant authorising a Police-officer not below the rank of Sub-Inspector to search any house, shop, magazine or other building or place in which he shall have reasonable ground to suspect that any explosive substance is manufactured, sold or kept, or any boat, carriage, cart or other vehicle in which any explosive substance may be suspected to be carried, or any person suspected of carrying the same, contrary to the provisions of this Act or any other law or any rule made thereunder; and all explosive substance found on such search shall, together with the vessels or receptacles in which it may be stored, be immediately seized and kept, pending the judgment of a Magistrate.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-38">
        <num>38.</num>
        <heading>Act not to apply to explosive substances belonging to the Government.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-38.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>None of the three last preceding sections shall extend to any magazine or store belonging to the Government, or building for the making or deposit of explosive substances under the authority or for the use of any Government or to any explosive substance belonging to the Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-38A">
        <num>38A.</num>
        <heading>Power of Commissioner to prohibit the use or the driving of certain types of vehicles in streets of public places.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-38A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>With the previous sanction of the State Government, the Commissioner of Police may, from time to time, by notification in the Official Gazette, prescribed the types of vehicles which shall not be driven or used in streets or public places within such limits as may be specified in this behalf by the Commissioner of Police in the said notification.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-38A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever uses or drives in a street or public place within the limits specified under sub-section (1), a vehicle of a type the use or driving of which has been prohibited under that sub-section, shall be liable to fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, and the vehicle in respect of which the offence has been committed shall be forfeited to the Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-39">
        <num>39.</num>
        <heading>Power of Commissioner to make rules for regulation of traffic, etc.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-39.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-39.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>With the previous sanction of the State Government, the Commissioner of Police may, after previous publication, from time to time, make rules—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-39.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for licensing and controlling persons offering themselves for employment at quays, wharves or landing places for the carriage of passengers’ baggage, and fixing and providing for the enforcement of a scale of charges for the labour of such persons when so employed;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>regulating traffic of all kinds in streets and public places, and the use of streets and public places by persons riding, or driving, leading or riding in vehicles, or leading or accompanying cattle, or walking, so as to prevent danger, obstruction or inconvenience to the public;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>regulating the conditions under which vehicles may remain standing streets and public places, and the use of streets as halting places, for vehicles or cattle;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>prescribing the number and position of lights to be used on vehicles in streets and public places;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>regulating and controlling conveyance of timber, bamboos, scaffold-poles, ladders, iron girders, beams or bars, boilers and other unwidely articles, or coal or bricks, lime or other building materials through the streets, and the route and hours for such conveyance;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39.1.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>for licensing, controlling, or in view to preventing obstruction, inconvenience or annoyance to residents or passengers in the vicinity, prohibiting the playing of music in streets or in public places other than public buildings and the precincts thereof;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39.1.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>for licensing, controlling, or, in view to preventing risk, danger or damage to residents or passengers in the vicinity, prohibiting the carrying of any explosive substance in streets or public places;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39.1.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>for controlling, in the interests of the public convenience and safety, the illumination of streets and public places, and the erection of structures on or over any street or public place, or against the exterior of any building abutting thereon, for the purposes of illumination;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>for authorising and regulating the removal by the police, of any structures referred to in clause (h) of this section or any appliances for illumination placed on or over any street or public places or against the exterior of any building abutting thereon, when the Commissioner of Police considers that the same are likely to cause obstruction, danger or damage to residents or passengers in the vicinity; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39.1.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>regulating the means of entrance and exit at places of public amusement, entertainment and assembly, and the lighting thereof when used by the public, and providing for the maintenance of public safety and the prevention of disturbance therein:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that nothing in this section shall affect the provisions of the Indian Arms Act, 1878 (XI of 1878), or the Indian Explosives Act, 1884 (IV of 1884).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-39.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any rules made under this section may, with the like section, be altered or rescinded by the Commissioner of Police after previous publication of the alteration or rescission.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-39.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule and alteration of a rule made under this section, and every rescission of any such rule, shall be published in the Official Gazette and in the manner prescribed by this Act for the publication of public notices.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-39.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-39.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Whoever contravenes any rule made under this section shall be liable—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-39.4.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>if the rule were made under clause (a), clause (b), clause (c) or clause (f) of sub-section (1)—to fine which may extend to fifty rupees, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39.4.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>if the rule were made under clause (d), clause (e) or clause (g) of sub-section (1)—to imprisonment with or without hard labour, for a term which may extend to eight days, or to fine which may extend to fifty rupees, or to both, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39.4.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>if the rule were made under clause (h), clause (i) or clause (j) of sub-section (1)—to fine which may extend to one hundred rupees.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-39A">
        <num>39A.</num>
        <heading>Power of Commissioner and other officers to give directions to the public.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-39A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-39A.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Commissioner of Police, and, subject to the orders of the Commissioner of Police every Police-officer of a rank not inferior to that of Sub-Inspector, may, with a view to securing the public safety or convenience, but not so as to contravene any rule made under the last foregoing section, or the provisions of any license granted under any such rule, give all such directions, either orally or in writing, as he may consider necessary to—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-39A.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>secure the orderly conduct of persons constituting processions and assemblies in streets;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39A.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>prescribe the rules by which, and the times at which, any such procession may, or may not, pass;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39A.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>prevent obstruction on the occasion of all processions and assemblies and in the neighbourhood of all places of worship during the time of public worship, and in all cases when any street or public place or place of public resort may be thronged or liable to be obstructed;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39A.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>keep order on and in streets, quays, wharves and landing places, and all other public place or places of public resort; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39A.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>regulate and control music, the beating of drums, tomtoms and other instruments and the blowing or sounding of horns or other noisy instruments in any street or any public place other than public buildings and the precincts thereof.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-39A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-39A.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Commissioner of Police may also, subject to the control of the State Government, whenever and for such time as he may consider it necessary to do so for the preservation of the public peace or public safety, by notification, publicly promulgated or addressed to individuals prohibit—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-39A.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the carrying of swords, speras, bludgeons, guns or other offensive weapons in any public place;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39A.2.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>the carrying, collection and preparation of stones or other articles extended to be used as missiles, or of instruments of means of casting or impelling missiles;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39A.2.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>the exhibition of persons, corpses, figures or effigies, in any public place; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39A.2.list1.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>the public utterance of cries, singing of songs or playing of music.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-39A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-39A.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Commissioner of Police may also, subject of the control of the State Government, whenever and for such time as he may consider necessary, by notification publicly promulgated or addressed to individuals, prohibit the delivery of public harangues the use of gestures or mimetic representations, and the preparation, exhibition or dissemination of pictures, symbols, placards or any other object or thing, which—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-39A.3.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>may for a nature to outrage morality or decency, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39A.3.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>are likely in the opinion of the Commissioner of Police, to inflame religious animosity or hostility between different classes, or to incite to the commission of an offence, to a disturbance of the public peace, or to resistance to, or contempt of, the law or lawful authority.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-39A.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commissioner of Police may also, by order in writing prohibit any procession or public assembly, whenever and for so long as he considers such prohibition to be necessary for the preservation of the public peace or public safety:</p>
            <p>Provided that no such prohibition shall remain in force for more than seven days without the sanction of the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-39A.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commissioner of Police may also, subject to the orders of the State Government by public notice, temporarily reserve for any public purpose any street or public place, and prohibit persons from entering the area so reserved, save under such conditions as may be prescribed by the Commissioner of Police.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-39A.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-39A.6.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Whoever contravenes any direction, order or prohibition lawfully given or made under this section shall be liable,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-39A.6.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>if the direction, order or prohibition were given or made under sub-section (1) or sub-section (5) to fine which may extend to one hundred rupees, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39A.6.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>if the prohibition were made under sub-section (2), sub-section (3) or sub-section (4), to imprisonment, with or without hard labour, for a term which may extend to one month, or to a fine which may extend to one hundred rupees, or to both.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-39B">
        <num>39B.</num>
        <heading>Enforcement of orders issued under the last foregoing section.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-39B.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-39B.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>whenever a notification, order in writing or public notice has been duly issued under sub-section (2), sub-section (3), sub-section (4) or sub-section (5) of the last foregoing section, then,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-39B.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in the case of a notification issued under clause (i), clause (ii) or clause (iii) of the said sub-section (2), or in the case of a public notice issued under the said sub-section (5) any Magistrate or any Police-officer, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39B.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in the case of a notification issued under clause (iv) of the said sub-section (2), or under the said sub-section (3), or in the case of an order issued under the said sub-section (4)—any Magistrate or any Police-officer of or above the rank of sub-Inspector,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>may require any person act ing or about to act contrary thereto to desist or to abstain from such act ion, and, in case of refusal or disobedience, may arrest such person.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-39B.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any Magistrate or Police-officer acting under sub-section (1) may also seize anything used or about to be used in contravention of such notification, order or notice as aforesaid, and anything so seized shall be disposed of as any Magistrate having jurisdiction may order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-39C">
        <num>39C.</num>
        <heading>Power to give directions to prevent disorder at places of public amusements, etc.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-39C.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of preventing serious disorder or manifest and imminent danger to the persons assembled at any place of public amusement; or at any assembly or meeting to which the public are invited or which is open to the public,the Police-officer of highest rank, superior to that Head Constable, who is present, may, subject to such rules, directions and orders as may have been lawfully made,give such reasonable directions as he may think necessary as to the mode of admission of the public to, and for securing the peaceful and orderly conduct of persons attending at, such place, assembly or meeting; and all persons shall be bound to confirm to such directions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-39C.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Police shall have free access to every such place of public amusement, assembly or meeting, for the purpose of giving effect to the provisions of sub-section (1) and to any direction given thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-39C.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever disobeys or fails to conform to any lawful and reasonable direction given any Police-officer under sub-section (1) shall be liable to fine which may extend to one hundred rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-39CC">
        <num>39CC.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition of sale at a higher price of tickets once issued for admission to an entertainment.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-39CC.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of preventing disorder or disturbance at or near any place where any entertainment is held, the Commissioner of Police may, with the previous sanction of the State Government, by order (of which public notice shall be given), prohibit within a radius of one furlong from the place of entertainment, the sale or the offer for sale of tickets once issued for admission as spectators to such entertainment at a price higher than the price at which such tickets were originally issued.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-39CC.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever contravenes any order referred to in sub-section (1) shall be liable to imprisonment for a term which may extend to three months or to fine which may extend to one hundred rupees or to both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-39CC.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any Police-officer below the rank of Sub-Inspector may arrest without warrant any person committing an offence punishable under this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-39CC.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In this section the expression ‘entertainment’ means any exhibition, performance, amusement, game or sport to which persons are admitted as spectators on production of tickets.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-39D">
        <num>39D.</num>
        <heading>Power of Commissioner to cause reports to be taken of the Proceedings of public meeting.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-39D.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Commissioner of Police may, by order in writing, depute one or more Police-officers, not below the rank of Head Constable, or other persons, to attend any public meeting for the purpose of causing a report to be taken of the Proceedings of such meeting if in the opinion of the Commissioner of Police, to be recorded in writing, the meeting is likely to promote sedition or disaffection or to cause disturbance of the public peace and tranquility.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-40">
        <num>40.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for committing in public streets offences of.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-40.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever, within such limits as shall be from time to time defined by the Commissioner of Police, with the sanction of the said State Government, in any street, thoroughfare or place of public resort, shall commit any of the following offences shall be liable to a fine not exceeding fifty rupees—Driving, etc., elephant or camel</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-40.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever shall drive, ride or lead any elephant or camel without a pass from the Commissioner of Police;</p>
            <p>Driving vehicle without sufficient light</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-40.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever shall drive any vehicle 6, at any time between three-quarters of an hour after sunset and one hour before sunrise, without a sufficient light;</p>
            <p>Driving otherwise than on left side of road</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-40.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever, without reasonable cause, shall drive a vehicle otherwise than on the left or near side of the road;</p>
            <p>Exposing for show horses, cleaning or repairing conveyances or training horses, in places not allowed by Commissioner</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-40.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever shall expose for show, hire or sale any horse or other animal, or any carriage, or shall clean or dress any horse or other animal, or shall clean any carriage or other conveyance, or shall make or repair any part of any cart or carriage, except in cases of accident where repair on the spot it necessary or shall train or break any horse, except in such place and at such times as may be allowed by the Commissioner;</p>
            <p>Exposing or Keeping articles so as to cause obstruction</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-40.4a">
          <num>(4a)</num>
          <content>
            <p>whoever exposes or keeps any article so as to cause obstruction in any public thoroughfare;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-40.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to (9) Omitted</p>
            <p>Lighting fires and discharging guns, fire-works, etc.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-40.10">
          <num>(10)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever shall set fire to burn any straw or other matter, or light any bonfire; or wantonly discharge any firearm or air-gun, or let off, or throw any fire-work, or send up any fire baloon, except at such times and places as shall from time to time be allowed by the Commissioner of Police;</p>
            <p>Driving cart with insufficient greased wheels</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-40.11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever, by driving a hackery or cart with insufficiently greased wheels shall create noise which is reasonably calculated to cause annoyance to persons frequenting or residing near the throughfare in which such hackery or cart is driven;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-40.12">
          <num>(12)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Omitted</p>
            <p>Affixing bills or otherwise defacing houses, etc.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-40.13">
          <num>(13)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever, without the consent of the owner or occupier, shall affix any bill or notice or any paper, against or upon any building, wall, tree, fence, post, pole or other erection, or shall write upon, deface or mark any such building, wall, tree, fence, post, pole or other erection, with chalk or paint, or in any way whatsoever;</p>
            <p>Bathing etc., in public street aqueduct.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-40.14">
          <num>(14)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever shall bathe or wash himself in any street, or in, upon, or by the side of, any public tank, reservoir or aqueduct, not being a place set apart for such purpose;</p>
            <p>Obstructing persons at bathing places</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-40.15">
          <num>(15)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever shall obstruct or incommode a person bathing at any place set apart as a bathing place, by wilful intrusion, or by using such place as a landing place, or by anchoring or otherwise fastening or keeping boats, or by washing cattle or dogs, at or near such place, or in any other way;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-40.16">
          <num>(16)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Omitted</p>
            <p>Beggars</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-40.17">
          <num>(17)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever, in any public street, thoroughfare or place shall beg or apply for alams, or shall expose or exhibit any sores, wounds, bodily ailment or deformity with the object of exciting charity or of obtaining alms, or shall seek for or obtain alams, by means of any false statement or pretences;</p>
            <p>Exposing person, etc.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-40.18">
          <num>(18)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever, wilfully and indecently exposes his person or commits a nuisance by easing himself.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-40A">
        <num>40A.</num>
        <heading>Refuges for reception of certain classes of convicted beggars.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-40A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Repealed by section. 27 of the Bengal Vagrancy Act, 1943 (Ben. Act VII of 1943).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-41">
        <num>41.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for drunkenness riotous or indecent behaviour in public.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-41.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever is found drunk and is incapable of taking care of himself, or is guilty of any riotous or indecent behaviour in any public street or thoroughfare, or in any place of public amusement or resort, shall be liable, on summary conviction before a Magistrate, to a fine not exceeding twenty rupees, or to imprisonment, with or without hard labour, for a term not exceeding eight days.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-41B">
        <num>41B.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for solicitation in a public place.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-41B.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Rep. by section. 2 and the schedule to the Bengal Suppression of Immoral Traffic Act, 1933 (Ben. Act IV of 1933).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-42">
        <num>42.</num>
        <heading>Stray dogs.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-42.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>It shall be lawful for the Commissioner of Police, by order in writing to be affixed at the principal police-stations, and also to be published in some public newspaper, to appoint, from time to time, certain periods within which any dogs found straying in the streets, or beyond the enclosures of the house of the owners of such dogs, may be destroyed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-42A">
        <num>42A.</num>
        <heading>Restrictions as to bringing, keeping of possession dangerous animals.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-42A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No person shall bring, keep or possess in the suburbs of the town of Calcutta any animal or class or classes of animals which the State Government may, for the purposes of this section by notification in the Official Gazette, specify as likely to cause danger to human life or property except under, and in accordance with the terms and conditions of a licence obtained from such authority, in such manner and on payment of such fee, not exceeding ten rupees, as the state Government may specify by rules made in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-42A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever contravenes the provisions of sub-section (1) shall be liable, on conviction before a magistrate, to a fine not exceeding two hundred rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-43">
        <num>43.</num>
        <heading>Powers to arrest without warrant.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-43.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-43.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Subject to the restrictions imposed by clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 39B in the case of offences there referred to, any Police-officer may arrest without a warrant any person committing in his presence in any street or public place any offence punishable under—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-43.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any section of this Act , or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-43.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any rule made under this Act, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-43.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <blockList id="section-43.1.list1.c.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>any other law for the time being in force, if such person,—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-43.1.list1.c.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>after being warned by a Police-officer, persists in committing such offence, or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-43.1.list1.c.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>is unknown to such Police-officer and, when asked by such Police-officer to give his name and address, refuses to give the same, or gives a name or address which such Police-officer has reason to believe to be false, or cannot then and there ascertain to be true, or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-43.1.list1.c.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>is unknown to such Police-officer, and his name and address cannot be ascertained then and there and he refuses to accompany the Police-officer to a police-station on being required so to do.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Explanation.—The sub-section does not restrict the exercise by any Police-officer of any power of arrest conferred upon him by sub-section (3) of section 39CC or by any other law.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-43.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Should be true name and residence of any such person not be ascertained within twenty-four hours from the time of arrest, or should he fail to execute a recognizance for his appearance before a Magistrate, or, if so required, to furnish sureties, he shall forthwith be forwarded to a Magistrate having jurisdiction.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-43A">
        <num>43A.</num>
        <heading>Omitted.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-44">
        <num>44.</num>
        <heading>Arrest of person committing offence with respect to person or property of another.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-44.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever commits an offence on or with respect to the person or property of another, or, in committing an offence under this Act , injures or damages the person or property of another, may, if his name and address be unknown, be apprehended by the person injured, or by any person who may be using the property to which the injury may be done, or by the servant either of such persons or by any person authorised by or acting in aid of him, and may be detained until he gives his name and adress and satisfy such person that the name and address so given are correct, or until he can be delivered into the custody of a Police-officer.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-45">
        <num>45.</num>
        <heading>Persons taken into custody by Police-officer without warrant may be detained in Police-station until brought before Magistrate or bailed.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-45.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every person taken into custody without a warrant by a Police-officer under this Act shall be taken to the nearest police-station in order that such person may be detained until he can be brought before the Magistrate or until he shall enter into recognizances, with or without sureties, for his appearance before the Magistrate.</p>
            <p>Any person so detained and not entering into recognizances, with or without such sureties, shall be carried before the Magistrate within twenty-four hours from the time of his being taken into custody.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-46">
        <num>46.</num>
        <heading>Power to take recognizance at police-station.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-46.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whenever any person shall be brought to a police-station charged with any offence against this Act , it shall be lawful for the officer in charge of such police-station, or any superior officer of police, if he shall deem it prudent, to enlarge such person on his own recognizance, with or without sureties, conditioned as hereinafter mentioned.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-47">
        <num>47.</num>
        <heading>Condition of recognization.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-47.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every recognizance so taken shall be without fee or reward, and shall be conditioned for the appearance of the person thereby bound before a Magistrate at his next siting;</p>
            <p>and all the persons executing the said recognizance shall acknowledge themselves jointly and severally bound in the sum—not exceeding one thousand rupees—thereby acknowledged;</p>
            <p>and the time and the place of appearance shall be specified in the said recognizance, or in the condition thereof;</p>
            <p>and the officer taking the recognizance shall enter in a book, to be kept for the purpose, the name, residence and occupation of the party, and his surety or sureties (if any) entering into such recognizance, together with the condition thereof and the sum thereby acknowledged, and shall return every such recognizance to the Magistrate present at the time and place when and where the party is bound to appear.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-47A">
        <num>47A.</num>
        <heading>Power of Commissioner of Police to require attendance and obtain statements of witnesses.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-47A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If, in the course of any investigation, the Commissioner of Police has reason to believe that a cognizable offence has been committed, he may, by order in writing, require the attendance, before himself or before any officer serving under him not below the rank of Sub-Inspector, who is investigating a cognizable offence, of any person then being within the limits of the town or suburbs of Calcutta, or within thirty miles of such limits, who, from the information given or otherwise, appears to be acquainted with the facts or circumstances of the case; and such person shall attend as so required.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-47A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commissioner of Police, or any officer aforesaid may examine orally any person so attending, and may reduce into writing any statement made by him; and such person shall be bound to answer all question relating to the case put to him by the Commissioner or such officer, other than questions the answers to which would have a tendency to expose him to a criminal charge or to a penalty or forfeiture.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-47A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commissioner of Police may, in any case, forward to the Superintendent of Police of the district in which any person, from whom any information is required relating to the facts or circumstances of the case under investigation, is believed to be, such questions and such statement as may be necessary for the purpose of obtaining the information desired; and such Superintendent shall, on receipt thereof, cause such person to be examined orally, and his statement to be reduced into writing, in the same manner and subject to the same provisions as if an investigation were being made into such offence in such district, and shall forward the statement reduced into writing to the Commissioner of Police.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-47A.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to any rules made by the State Government, the Commissioner of Police may, if he thinks fit, order payment, on the part of the State Government, of the reasonable expenses of any person residing in the town or suburbs of Calcutta who attends for the purposes of any investigation before himself or any other Police-officer under this section, and shall order payment, as aforesaid, of the reasonable expenses of any person not so residing who attends as aforesaid.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-47B">
        <num>47B.</num>
        <heading>Power to search for persons wrongfully confined.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-47B.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If information is given on oath to the Commissioner of Police that any person is confined under such circumstances that the confinement amounts to an offence, and if it is for any reason impracticable to make an application to a Magistrate under section 100 or section 552 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (Act V of 1898), the Commissioner may issue a search-warrant to any Police-officer not below the rank of Sub-Inspector; and the officer to whom such warrant is directed may search for the person indicated in such warrant, in accordance with such directions as may be given therein; and the person, if found, shall immediately be taken before a Magistrate, who shall make such order as in the circumstances of the case seems proper.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-47C">
        <num>47C.</num>
        <heading>Procedure in making searches.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-47C.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Before any officer makes a search under this Act , he shall call upon two or more respectable persons to attend and witness the search.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-47C.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The search shall be made in the presence of such persons and a list of all things seized in the course of the search, and of the places in which they are respectively found, shall be prepared by the said officer and signed by the said witnesses; but no person witnessing a search under this section shall be required to attend the court as a witness of the search unless specially summoned by it.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-47C.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The occupant of the place searched or some person in his behalf, shall, in very instance, be permitted to attend during the search; and a copy of the list prepared under sub-section (2), signed by the said witnesses, shall be delivered to such occupant or person at his request.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-48">
        <num>48.</num>
        <heading>Recovery and appropriation of fines.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-48.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>All fines imposed under the authority of this Act shall be recoverable in the manner prescribed by section 61 of the Code of Criminal Procedure (Act XXV of 1861), and the amount so levied shall be appropriated to any fund applicable to Police purposes:</p>
            <p>Provided that it shall be lawful for the Magistrate, when it shall appear to him that the fine cannot be realised by recourse to the provisions above mentioned, to sentence the offender to imprisonment in lieu of any fine to which such offender is liable under this Act, and the term of such imprisonment shall be fixed in accordance with the scale laid down in section 67 of the Indian Penal Code (Act XLV of 1860).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-48A">
        <num>48A.</num>
        <heading>Police to take charge of unclaimed movable property.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-48A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-48A.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Police shall, for the purpose of safe custody, take temporary charge of—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-48A.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>all unclaimed movable property found by them, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-48A.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>all movable property found lying in any public street, if the owner or the person in charge of such property on being directed to remove the same, refuse or omits to do so within a reasonable time;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>and may, for the said purpose, take temporary charge of any unclaimed movable property made over to them.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-48A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Property of which the Police have taken charge under sub-section (1) shall be handed over to the Commissioner of Police.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-48B">
        <num>48B.</num>
        <heading>Disposal of such property.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-48B.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the said property appears to have been left by a person who has died intestate, and not to be under two hundred rupees in value, the Commissioner of Police shall communicate with the Administrator-General with a view to its being dealt with under the Administrator-General’s Act , 1913 (III of 1913), or any other law for the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-48B.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In every other case the Commissioner of Police shall issue a proclamation specifying the articles of which such property consists, and requiring any person who may have a claim thereto to appear before himself or some other officer whom he appoints in this behalf and establish his claim within six months from the date of proclamation.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-48B.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the property, or any part thereof, is subject to speedy and natural decay, or consists of live-stock, or if the appears to be of less value than five rupees, it may forthwith be sold by auction under the orders of the Commissioner of Police and the net preceeds of such sale shall be dealt with in the same manner as is hereinafter provided for the disposal of the said property.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-48B.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commissioner of Police shall, on being satisfied of the title of any claimant to the possession or administration of any property referred in sub-section (2), order the same to be delivered to him, after deduction or payment of the expenses properly incurred by the Police in the seizure and detention thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-48B.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commissioner of Police may, at his discretion, before making any order under sub-section(4), take such security as he may think proper from the person to whom the said property is to be delivered; and nothing hereinbefore contained shall affect the right of any person to recover the whole or any part of such property from the person to whom it may have been delivered pursuant to such order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-48B.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If no persons establishes his claim to such property within the period prescribed in sub-section (2), it shall be at the disposal of the State Government and the property or such part thereof as has not already been sold under sub-section (3), may be sold by auction under orders of the Commissioner of Police.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-49">
        <num>49.</num>
        <heading>Omitted.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-49A">
        <num>49A.</num>
        <heading>Public notice how to be given.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-49A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any public notice required to be given under any of the provisions of this Act shall be in writing, shall be signed by the Commissioner of Police, and shall be published, in the locality to be affected thereby, by affixing copies thereof in conspicuous public places, or by proclaiming the same with beat of drum or by advertising the same in such local newspapers, English or vernacular, as the Commissioner of Police may deem fit, or by any two or more of these means and by any other means he may think suitable.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-49B">
        <num>49B.</num>
        <heading>Consent, etc., of Commissioner of Police or Police-officer how to be proved.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-49B.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whenever under this Act or any rule made hereunder the doing or the omitting to do anything or the validity of anything depends upon the consent, approval, declaration, opinion or statisfaction of the Commissioner of Police or of any Police-officer, a written document signed by the Commissioner of Police or by such officer, purporting to convey or set forth such consent, approval, declaration, opinion or satisfaction shall be sufficient evidence thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-49C">
        <num>49C.</num>
        <heading>Stamping of signature.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-49C.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every license, written permission, notice or other document not being a summons of warrant or search-warrant, or a notification issued under sub-section (3) of section 39A or an order made under sub-section (4) of that section, or an order made under section 47A required by this Act , or any rule made hereunder, to bear the signature of the Commissioner of Police shall be deemed to be properly signed if it bears a facsimile of his-signature stamped thereon.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-50">
        <num>50.</num>
        <heading>Powers of Deputy Commissioner.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-50.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Additional, Joint, Deputy, Additional Deputy or Assistant Commissioner of Police for the town of Calcutta may, under the orders of the Commissioner, perform all or any of the duties, exercise all or any of the powers of perform all or any of the functions vested in the latter by the provisions of this Act .</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-51">
        <num>51.</num>
        <heading>Interpretation.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-51.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The following words and expression in this Act hall have the meanings hereby assigned to them, unless there be something in the subject or context repugnant to such construction (that is to say):—</p>
            <p>the word “property” shall include any chattel, money or valuable security;</p>
            <p>the word “person” shall include a corporation;</p>
            <p>the word “month” shall mean calendar month;</p>
            <p>the word “oath” shall include any affirmation or declaration lawfully substituted for an oath;</p>
            <p>the word “cattle” shall, besides horned cattle, include horses, asses, mules, sheep, goats and swine;</p>
            <p>“explosive substance”</p>
            <p>shall be deemed to include any material for making any explosive substance, also any apparatus, machine, implement or material used, or intended to be used, or adapted for causing, or aiding in causing, any explosion in or with any explosive substance; also any part of any such apparatus, machine or implement.</p>
            <p>“place of public amusement”</p>
            <p>shall mean any place, enclosure, building, tent, booth or other erection, whether permanent or temporary, where music, singing, dancing or any diversion or game, or the means of carrying on the same is provided, and to which the public are admitted, either on payment of money or with the intention that money may be collected from those admitted, otherwise than for a bona fide charitable purpose, and shall include a race-course, circus, theatre, music-hall, billiard-room, bagatelle-room, gymnasium and fencing-school;</p>
            <p>“place of public entertainment”</p>
            <p>shall mean any place, whether enclosed or open, to which the public are admitted, and where any kind of food, drink, drug, betel or tobacco is supplied for consumption on or off the premises for the profit or gain of any person owning or having an interest in or managing such place; and shall include a lodging-house where any kind of food, drink, drug, betel or tobacco is supplied for consumption therein or not and a refreshment-room, eating-house, coffee-house, tea-shop, snack-shop, snack-bar, sweetmeat-shop, liquor-house, boarding-house, hotel, restaurant, tavern, wine-shop, beer-shop, spirit-shop, arrack-shop, today-shop, ganja-shop, bhang-shop, opium-shop, tobacco-shop, bidi-shop, cigarette-shop, zarda-shop, betel-shop and betel leaf massalla-shop;</p>
            <p>“Police-officer”</p>
            <p>shall mean any member of the Calcutta Police force and shall include the Commissioner of Police, an Additional Commissioner of Police, a Joint Commissioner of Police, a Deputy Commissioner of Police, an Additional Deputy Commissioner of Police and an Assistant Commissioner of Police;</p>
            <p>“police-station”</p>
            <p>shall mean any post or place declared generally or specially, by the State Government, to be a police-station, and shall include any local area specified by the State Government in this behalf;</p>
            <p>“public place”</p>
            <p>shall include the banks of river, the docks, the jetties, warehouses to which the public have access, every public building and monument and the precincts thereof and all places accessible to the public for drawing water, washing or bathing, or for purposes of recreation;</p>
            <p>“street”</p>
            <p>shall mean any road, lane, footway, square, court, alley or passage, whether a thoroughfare or not, to which the public have, permanently or temporarily, a right of access;</p>
            <p>“subordinate ranks”</p>
            <p>shall mean the ranks below Assistant Commissioner;</p>
            <p>“vehicle”</p>
            <p>shall include any locomotive, automobile, tram-car, carriage, cart, van, dray, truck, hand-cart, bicycle, tricycle, motorcycle or other wheeled conveyance of any description capable of being used on the Streets.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-52">
        <num>52.</num>
        <heading>Omitted.</heading>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-schedule">
      <doc name="schedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-wbg/act/1866/2/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-wbg/act/1866/2"/>
              <FRBRalias value="Schedule"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-wbg/act/1866/2/eng@2017-01-19/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-wbg/act/1866/2/eng@2017-01-19"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-wbg/act/1866/2/eng@2017-01-19/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-wbg/act/1866/2/eng@2017-01-19"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-12-07" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="schedule">
            <paragraph id="schedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>FORM OF CERTIFICATE</p>
                <p>[Referred to in section 8]</p>
                <p>A B has been appointed a member of the Calcutta Police-force, and is vested with the powers, functions and privileges of a Police-officer.</p>
                <p>THE SCHEDULE OF FEES</p>
                <p>[See section 24]</p>
                <p>A. Fees for licenses.</p>
                <p>Description of items Fees</p>
                <p>For every tea-shop, aerated water shop, cold-drink shop, soda fountain. Rs 100 per year and also an additional fee of Rs 10 per month or fraction of a month if music is to be played in such place.</p>
                <p>For every coffee-house, boarding house, eating house or sweetmeat shop. Rs 250 per year and also an additional fee of Rs 15 per month or fraction of a month if music is to be played in such place.</p>
                <p>For every hotel run in western style. Rs 1,000 per year for hotel, Rs 2,000 per year for hotel and restaurant</p>
                <p>For every betel shop or shops selling bidi or cigarette or tobaccos or zarda or massalla for betel leaf Rs 60 per year</p>
                <p>For every restaurant, snack shop, snack bar Rs 250 per year</p>
                <p>For every lodging house for pilgrims Rs 50 per year</p>
                <p>For every lodging house for seamen Rs 100 per year</p>
                <p>For every other case Rs 10 per year</p>
                <p>Provided that no fee shall be payable in respect of any establishment the keeper of which is required to take out a license under section 218 of the Calcutta Municipal Act , 1951, the fee for which is not more than Rs 15 per year, or is required to pay a tax under clause (f) of sub-section (1) of section 123 of the Bengal Municipal Act, 1932 which is not more than Rs 4 per year</p>
                <p>B. Fees for certificate</p>
                <p>Description of items Fees</p>
                <p>For every restaurant with permanent bar with a foreign liquor shop or with India-made foreign liquor shop or hotel where spirituous liquor or foreign liquor or India-made foreign liquor are sold Rs 350 per year</p>
                <p>For every foreign liquor shop or India-made foreign liquor shop Rs 300 per year</p>
                <p>For every arrack or toddy shop Rs 200 per year</p>
                <p>For every ganja-shop, bhang-shop or opium-shop Rs 20 per year</p>
                <p>For every temporary bar Rs 50 per day</p>
                <p>In every other case Rs 10 per year</p>
                <p>C. Fees for passes</p>
                <p>For every animal. Rs. 10.00</p>
                <p>Explanation—If any question arises as to whether any place or establishment or thing comes within any of the items described above, the matter shall be referred to the Commissioner of Police and the decision of the Commissioner of Police shall be final.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
