<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1897/8/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1897/8"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Reformatory Schools Act, 1897"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1897/8/eng@1897-03-11/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1897/8/eng@1897-03-11"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1897-03-11" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1897/8/eng@1897-03-11/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1897/8/eng@1897-03-11"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-10-13" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Reformatory Schools Act, 1897</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <part id="part-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <heading>Preliminary</heading>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Title and extent.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the Reformatory Schools Act, 1897</p>
              <p>***</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It extends to the whole of India except the territories which, immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised in Part B States.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>***</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>***</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Definitions.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>"youthful offender" means any boy who has been convicted of any offence punishable with transportation or imprisonment and who, at the time of such conviction, was under the age of fifteen years;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>"Inspector General" includes any officer appointed by the State Government to perform all or any of the duties imposed by this Act on the Inspector General; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>"District Magistrate" shall include a Chief Presidency Magistrate.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <heading>Reformatory Schools</heading>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Power to establish and discontinue reformatory schools.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The State Government may-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>establish and maintain Reformatory Schools at such places as it may think fit;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>use as Reformatory Schools schools kept by persons willing to act in conformity with such rules, consistent with this Act, as the State Government may prescribe in this behalf;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>direct that any school so established or used shall cease to exist as a Reformatory School or to be used as such.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Requisites of Schools.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Every school so established or used must provide-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>sufficient means of separating the inmates at night;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>proper sanitary arrangements, water- supply, food, clothing and bedding for the youthful offenders detained therein;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the means of giving such youthful offenders industrial training;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>an infirmary or proper place for the reception of such youthful offenders when sick.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Inspection of Reformatory Schools.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every school intended to be established or used as a Reformatory School shall, before being used as such, be inspected by the Inspector General, and if he finds that the requirements of section 6 have been complied with, and that, in his opinion, such school is fitted for the reception of such youthful offenders as may be sent there under this Act, he shall certify to that effect, and such certificate shall be published in the Official Gazette, together with an order of the State Government establishing the school as a Reformatory School or directing that it shall be used as such, and the school shall thereupon be deemed to be a Reformatory School.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every such school shall, from time to time, and at least once in every year, be visited by the said Inspector General, who shall send to the State Government a report on the condition of the school in such form as the State Government may prescribe.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Power to Courts to direct youthful offenders to be sent to Reformatory Schools.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Whenever any youthful offender is sentenced to transportation or imprisonment, and is, in the judgment of the Court by which he is sentenced, a proper person to be an inmate of a Reformatory School, the Court may, subject to any rules made by the State Government, direct that, instead of undergoing his sentence, he shall be sent to such a school, and be there detained for a period which shall be not less than three or more than seven years.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The powers so conferred on the Court by this section shall be exercised only by (a) the High Court, (b) a Court of Session, (c) a District Magistrate, and (d) any Magistrate specially empowered by the State Government in this behalf, and may be exercised by such Courts whether the case comes before them originally or on appeal.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-8.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The State Government may make rules for-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>defining what youthful offenders should be sent to Reformatory Schools, having regard to the nature of their offences or other considerations, and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.3.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>regulating the periods for which youthful offenders may be sent to such schools according to their ages or other considerations.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Procedure where Magistrate is not empowered to pass an order under section 8.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When any Magistrate not empowered to pass an order under the last foregoing section is of opinion that a youthful offender convicted by him is a proper person to be an inmate of a Reformatory School, he may, without passing sentence, record such opinion and submit his proceedings and forward the youthful offender to the District Magistrate to whom he is subordinate.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Magistrate to whom the proceedings are so submitted may make such further inquiry (if any) as he may think fit and pass such sentence and order for the detention in a Reformatory School of the youthful offender, or otherwise, as he might have passed if such youthful offender had been originally tried by him.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Power of Magistrates to direct boys under fifteen sentenced to imprisonment to be sent to Reformatory Schools.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The officer in charge of a prison in which a youthful offender is confined, in execution of a sentence of imprisonment, may bring him, if he has not then attained the age of fifteen years, before the District Magistrate within whose jurisdiction such prison is situate; and such Magistrate may, if such youthful offender appears to be a proper person to be an inmate of a Reformatory School, direct that, instead of undergoing the residue of his sentence, he shall be sent to a Reformatory School, and there detained for a period which shall be subject to the same limitations as are prescribed by or under section 8, with reference to the period of detention thereby authorised.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Preliminary inquiry and finding as to age of youthful offender.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Before directing any youthful offender to be sent to a Reformatory School under section 8, section 9 or section 10, the Court or Magistrate shall inquire into the question of his age and, after taking such evidence (if any) as may be deemed necessary, shall record a finding thereon, stating his age as nearly as may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A similar inquiry shall be made and finding recorded by every Magistrate not empowered to pass an order under section 8 before submitting his proceedings and forwarding the youthful offender to the District Magistrate as required by section 9, sub- section (1).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Government to determine Reformatory School to which such offenders shall be sent.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every youthful offender directed by a Court or Magistrate to be sent to a Reformatory School shall be sent to such Reformatory School as the State Government may, by general or special order, appoint for the reception of youthful offenders so dealt with by such Court or Magistrate:</p>
              <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that, if accommodation in a Reformatory School is not immediately available for such youthful offender, he may be detained in the juvenile ward or such other suitable part of a prison as the State Government may direct-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>until he can be sent to a Reformatory School, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>until the term of his original sentence expires,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>whichever event may first happen. Should the term of his original sentence first expire, he shall thereupon be released, but, should he be sent to a Reformatory School, then the period of detention previously undergone shall be treated as detention in a Reformatory School.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Persons found to be over eighteen years not to be detained in Reformatory School.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-13.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If at any time after a youthful offender has been sent to a Reformatory School it appears to the Committee of Visitors or Board of Management, as the case may be, that the age of such youthful offender has been understated in the order for detention, and that he will attain the age of eighteen years before the expiration of the period for which he has been ordered to be detained, they shall report the case for the orders of the State Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No person shall be detained in a Reformatory School after he has been found by the State Government to have attained the age of eighteen years.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Discharge or removal by order of Government.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The State Government may at any time order any youthful offender-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to be discharged from a Reformatory School;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>to be removed from one Reformatory School to another such school situate within the territories subject to such Government: Provided that the whole period of his detention in a Reformatory School shall not be increased by such removal.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Agreement between States.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Governments of any two States may after mutual agreement, generally or specially, notify in their respective Official Gazettes that any Reformatory School situated in one of the States shall be available for the reception of youthful offenders directed to be sent to a Reformatory School by any Court or Magistrate in the other State and may thereupon make provision for the removal of youthful offenders accordingly.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Certain orders not subject to appeal or revision.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Nothing contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1882 (10 of 1882), shall be construed to authorise any Court or Magistrate to alter or reverse in appeal or revision any order passed with respect to the age of a youthful offender or the substitution of an order for detention in a Reformatory School for transportation or imprisonment.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <heading>Management of Reformatory Schools</heading>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Appointment of Superintendent and Committee of Visitors or Board of Management.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the control and management of every Reformatory School, the State Government shall appoint either (a) a Superintendent and a Committee of Visitors, or (b) a Board of Management.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every Committee and every Board so appointed must consist of not less than five persons.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may suspend or remove any Super intendent or any Member of a Committee or Board so appointed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Superintendent may license youthful offenders to employers of labour.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-18.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every Superintendent so appointed may, with the sanction of the Committee, by license under his hand, permit any youthful offender sent to a Reformatory School, who has attained the age of fourteen years, to live under the charge of any trustworthy an respectable person named in the license, or any officer of Government or of a Municipality, being an employer of labour and willing to receive and take charge of him, on the condition that the employer shall keep such youthful offender employed at some trade, occupation or calling.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The license shall be in force for three months and no longer but may, at any time and from time to time until the expiration of the period for which the youthful offender has been directed to be detained, be renewed for three months at a time.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Cancellation of license.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The license shall be cancelled at the desire of the employer named in the license.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Determination of license.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>If during the term of the license the employer named therein dies, or ceases from business or to employ labour, or the period for which the youthful offender has been directed to be detained in the Reformatory School expires, the license shall thereupon cease and determine.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Cancellation of license in case of ill-treatment.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>If it appears to the Superintendent that the employer has illtreated the youthful offender, or has not adequately provided for his lodging and maintenance, the Superintendent may cancel the license.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Superintendent to be deemed guardian of youthful offenders.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-22.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Superintendent of a Reformatory School shall be deemed to be the guardian of every youthful offender detained in such school, within the meaning of Act No. 19 of 1850 (concerning the binding of apprentices).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If it appears to the Superintendent that any youthful offender licensed under section 18 has behaved well during one or more periods of his license, the Superintendent may, with the sanction of the Committee, apprentice him under the provisions of the said Act, and on such apprenticement the right to detain such youthful offender in a Reformatory School shall cease and the unexpired term (if any) of his sentence shall be cancelled.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Duties of Committee of Visitors.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-23.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-23.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Every Committee of Visitors appointed under section 17 for a Reformatory School shall. at least once in every month,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-23.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>visit the school, to hear complaints and see that the requirements of section 6 have been complied with, and that the at management of the school is proper in all respects</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>examine the punishment- book;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>bring any special cases to the notice of the Inspector-General; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>see that no person is illegally detained in the school.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any member of a Committee of Visitors so appointed fails or neglects, during a period of six consecutive months, to visit the school and assist in the discharge of the duties aforesaid, he shall cease to be a member of such Committee.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Powers of Board of management.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>If, in exercise of the power conferred by section 17, the State Government appoints a Board of Management for any Reformatory School, such Board shall have the powers and perform the functions of the Superintendent under sections 18 to 22, both inclusive; and the license mentioned in section 18 may be under the hand of their chairman; and they shall be deemed to be the guardians of the youthful offenders detained in such school.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>power to appoint trustees or other managers of a school to be a Board of Management.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may declare any body of trustees or managers of a school, who are willing to act in conformity with the rules referred to in section 5, clause (b), to be a Board of Management under this Act, and thereupon such body or manager shall have all the powers and perform all the functions of such Board of Management.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Power of Board to make rules.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-26.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-26.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>With the previous sanction of the State Government, every Board of Management of a Reformatory School may from time to time make rules consistent with this Act-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-26.1.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>to prescribe the articles which are to be deemed to be "prohibited articles"; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.1.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>to regulate-</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the conduct of business of the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the management of the school;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the education and industrial training of youthful offenders;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>visits to, and communication with, youthful offenders;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.1.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the terms and conditions under which any articles declared by the Board to be" prohibited articles" may be introduced into or removed out of the school;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.1.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which such articles are to be removed when introduced without due authority;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.1.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the conditions and limitations under which such articles may be supplied outside the school to any youthful offender under order of detention therein;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.1.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>the conditions on which the possession by any such youthful offender of such articles may be sanctioned;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.1.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the penalties to be imposed for the supply or possession of such articles when supplied or possessed without due authority;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.1.list1.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>the punishment of offences committed by youthful offenders; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.1.list1.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>the granting of licenses for the employment of youthful offenders.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-26.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the absence of a Board of Management the State Government may make rules consistent with this Act to regulate for any Reformatory School the matters mentioned in any clause of sub-section (1), other than clause (ii) a, and also the mode in which the Committee of Visitors shall conduct their business.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <heading>Offences in Relation to Reformatory Schools</heading>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Penalty for introduction or removal or supply of prohibited articles and communication with youthful offenders.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Whoever, contrary to any rule made under section 26, introduces or removes or attempts by any means whatever to introduce or remove into or from any Reformatory School, or supplies or attempts to supply outside the limits of any Reformatory School to any youthful offender under order of detention therein, any prohibited article, and every officer or person in charge of a Reformatory School who, contrary to any such rule, knowingly suffers any such article to be introduced into or removed from any Reformatory School, to be possessed by any youthful offender detained therein, or to be supplied to any such youthful offender outside its limits, and whoever, contrary to any such rule, communicates or attempts to communicate with any such youthful offender, and whoever abets any offence made punishable under this section, shall, on conviction before a Magistrate, be liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding six months, or to fine not exceeding two hundred rupees, or to both.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Penalty for abetting escape of youthful offender.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Whoever abets an escape, or an attempt to escape, on the part. of a youthful offender from a Reformatory School, or from the employer of such youthful offender, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine not exceeding two hundred rupees, or with both.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Arrest of escaped youthful offender.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-29.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>A Police-officer may, without orders from a Magistrate and without a warrant, arrest any youthful offender sent to a Reformatory School under this Act, who has escaped from such school or from his employer, and take him back to such school or to his employer.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <heading>Miscellaneous</heading>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading>***</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading>Power to deal in other ways with youthful offenders, includind girls.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-31.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-31.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act or in any other enactment for the time being in force, any Court may, if it shall think fit, instead of sentencing any youthful offender to transportation or imprisonment or directing him to be detained in a Reformatory School, order him to be-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-31.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>discharged after due admonition, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-31.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>delivered to his parent or to his guardian or nearest adult relative, on such parent, guardian or relative executing a bond, with or without sureties, as the Court may require, to be responsible for the good behaviour of the youthful offender for any period not exceeding twelve months.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purposes of this section the term" youthful offender shall include a girl.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The powers conferred on the Court by this section shall be exercised only by Courts empowered by or under section 8.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When any youthful offender is convicted by a Court not empowered to act under this section and the Court is of opinion that the powers conferred by this section should be exercised in respect of such youthful offender, it may record such opinion and submit the proceedings and forward the youthful offender to the District Magistrate to whom such Court is subordinate.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The District Magistrate to whom the proceedings are so submitted may thereupon make such order or pass such sentence as he might have made or passed if the case had originally been tried by him.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>Procedure when youthful offender under detention in a Reformatory School is again convicted and sentenced.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-32.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>When a youthful offender during his period of detention in a Reformatory School is again convicted by a Criminal Court, the sentence of such Court shall commence at once, notwithstanding anything to the contrary in section 397 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1882 (10 of 1882), but the Court shall forthwith report the matter to the State Government, which shall have power to deal with the matter in any way in which it thinks fit.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
