<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-asm/act/1935/09/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-asm/act/1935/09"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Assam Muslim Marriages And Divorces Registration Act, 1935"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-asm/act/1935/09/eng@2017-03-15/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-asm/act/1935/09/eng@2017-03-15"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-15" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-asm/act/1935/09/eng@2017-03-15/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-asm/act/1935/09/eng@2017-03-15"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-15" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Assam Muslim Marriages And Divorces Registration Act, 1935</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No. 09 of 1935</p>
      </longTitle>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[19th February, 1936]</docDate>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>An Act to provide for the voluntary registration of Muslim Marriages and Divorces.</p>
      <p>Whereas it is expedient to provide for the voluntary registration of Muslim Marriages and Divorces.</p>
      <p>It is hereby enacted as follows :--</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called "The Assam Muslim Marriages and Divorces Registration Act, 1935."</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Commencement.</p>
            <p>It shall come into force in any part of the province on such date as the Provincial Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette appoint in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Extent.</p>
            <p>It extends to the whole of Assam.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Interpretation</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In this Act-unless there be something repugnant in the subject or context:--</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" Inspector General of Registration" and "Registrar " respectively mean the officers so designated and appointed under the Indian Registration Act, 1908 (Act XVI of 1908), or other law for the time being in force for the registration of documents.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>"Muslim Registrar" means any person who is duly authorised under this Act to register Muslim marriages and divorces.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>"District" means a district formed under the provisions of the Registration Act, 1908 (Act XVI of 1908).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>"Pardanasheen" designates a woman who according to custom objects to appear in a public office.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2A">
        <num>2A.</num>
        <heading>Registration of Muslim marriages compulsory</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Subject to other provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder, registration of Muslim marriages and divorces are compulsory within the State of Assam.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Provincial Government may grant Licenses to register</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Provincial Government may grant a license to any person, being a Muslim, authorising him to register Muslim marriages and divorces which have been effected within certain specified limits, on application being made for such registration; and may revoke or suspend such license:</p>
            <p>Provided that not more than two persons shall be licensed to exercise the said functions within the same limits: and provided further that, when two persons are so licensed to act within the same limits, the one shall be a member of the Sunni, and the other of the Shia, sect.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Muslim Registrar to use seals</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every Muslim Registrar shall use a seal bearing the following inscriptions in the Persian character and language :</p>
            <p>“The seal of the Muslim Registrar of …..”</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Provincial Government to provide seal and books</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Provincial Government shall supply for the office of every Muslim Registrar the seal and the books necessary for the purposes of this Act. The pages of such books shall be consecutively numbered in print, and the number of pages in each book shall be certified on the title page by the officer by whom such books are issued.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Muslim Registrar to keep registers</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every Muslim Registrar shall maintain the following register-books :--</p>
            <p>Book I.-- Register of marriages, in the Form (A) contained in the Schedule I to this Act.</p>
            <p>Book II.-- Register of divorces other than those of the kind known as "Khula" in the Form (B) contained in the Schedule II to this Act.</p>
            <p>Book III.-- Register of divorces of the kind known as "Khula' in the Form (G) contained in the Schedule III to this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Entries to be numbered</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>All entries in each register prescribed by the last preceding section shall be numbered in a consecutive series, which shall commence and terminate with the year, a fresh series being commenced at the beginning of each year.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Applications by whom to be made</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every application for registration under this Act shall be made to the Muslim Registrar orally as follows :--</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the application be for the registration of a marriage - by the parties to the marriage jointly: provided that if the bridegroom or the bride, or both, be minors, application shall be made on their behalf by their respective lawful guardians : and provided further that, if the bride be pardanasheen, such application may be made on her behalf by her duly authorised Vakil;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the application be for the registration of a divorce other than of the kind known as Khula - by the man who has effected the divorce;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the application be for the registration of a divorce of the kind known as Khula- by the parties jointly : provided that if the woman be pardanasheen, such application may be made on her behalf by her duly authorised Vakil or lawful guardian.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Duties of Muslim Registrar on application</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>On application being made to a Muslim Registrar for registration under this Act of a marriage or divorce within one month of marriage or divorce being effected, and not otherwise and on payment to him of a fee prescribed as per Schedule IV to this Act, the Muslim Registrar shall--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>satisfy himself whether or not such marriage or divorce was effected by the person or persons by whom it is represented to have been effected;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>satisfy himself as to the identity of the person appearing before him and alleging that the marriage or divorce has been effected;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>in the case of any person appearing as representative of the man or woman (whether he appears as guardian or Vakil) satisfy himself of the right of such person to appear.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>If the Muslim Registrar be satisfied on the above points and not otherwise, he shall make an entry of the marriage or divorce in the proper register :</p>
            <p>Provided that no such entry shall be made otherwise than in the presence of every person who, by section 10 of this Act, is required to sign such entry.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Entries by whom to be signed</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Every entry in a register kept under this Act shall be signed as follows :--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>If the entry be of a marriage in a register in the Form (A) contained in the Schedule I to this Act--</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>by the parties to the marriage, or, if either or both of them be minors, by their lawful guardians respectively:</p>
            <p>Provided that if the woman be pardanasheen the entry may be signed on her behalf by her duly authorised Vakil;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>by two witnesses who were present at the marriage ceremony;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>in cases in which the woman is represented by a Vakil by two witnesses to the fact of the Vakil having been duly authorised to represent her;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>by the Muslim Registrar;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.4.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>If the entry be of a divorce other than the kind known as Khula in a register in the Form (B) contained in the Schedule II to this Act--</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>by the man who has effected the divorce;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>by the witness who identifies the man who has effected the divorce;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>if the man be of the Shia sect, by two witnesses to the divorce being effected;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>by the Muslim Registrar;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.4.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>If the entry be of a divorce of the kind known as Khula in a register in the Form (C) contained in the Schedule HI to this Act--</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>by the parties to the Khula, provided that, if the woman be pardanasheen, the entry may be signed on her behalf by her duly authorised Vakil or lawful guardian;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>by the person who identifies the man;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>by the person who identifies the woman;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>if the application for registration has been made by a Vakil on behalf of the woman, by two witnesses to the fact of the Vakil having been duly authorised to represent her;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>if the man be of the Shia sect, by two witnesses to the divorce being effected;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>by the Muslim Registrar.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Copies of entry to be given to parties</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>On completion of the registration of any marriage or divorce, the Muslim Registrar shall deliver to each of the applicants for registration an attested copy of the entry; and for such copy no charge shall be made.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Index to be kept</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In every office in which any register hereinbefore mentioned is kept, there shall be prepared a current index of the contents of such register; and every entry in such index shall be made, so far as practicable, immediately after the Muslim Registrar has made an entry in any such register.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Particulars to be shown in index</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The index mentioned in the last preceding section shall contain the name, place of residence and father's name of each party to every marriage, or divorce and the date of registration. It shall also contain such other particulars, and shall be prepared in such form, as the [Provincial Government]1 may direct.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Index may be inspected and copies of entries in registers taken</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the previous payment of the fees prescribed, the index, whether it be in the office of the Muslim Registrar or of the Registrar of the district, and the copies of the entries in such index which are filed in the office of the Registrar of the district under the provisions of section 21 of this Act, shall be at all times open to inspection by any person applying to inspect the same; and copies of entries in any of the registers, and of the certified copies of such entries, which are filed in the office of the Registrar of the district under section 21 of this Act, shall be given to all persons applying for such copies.</p>
            <p>Such copies shall be signed and sealed by the Registrar of the district or by the Muslim Registrar, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Fees for searches and copies</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every Registrar of a district and every Muslim Registrar shall, for the purposes of this Act, be entitled to levy the following fees:--</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>for every search or permission to search in any index or register under his charge—Rupees ten;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>for every certified copy of any entry in a register other than the first copy referred to in section 11 of this Act—Rupees thirty.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Muslim Registrars to be subject to control of District Registrars</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every Muslim Registrar shall perform the duties of his office under the superintendence and control of the Registrar in whose district the office of such Muslim Registrar is situated. Every Registrar shall have authority to issue (whether on complaint or otherwise) any order consistent with this Act, which he considers necessary in respect of any act or omission of any Muslim Registrar subordinate to him.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Powers of State Government to make rules</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-17.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The State Government may, from time to time by notification in the Official Gazette frame rules, provided that such rules shall not been consistent with any provisions of this Act:--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for determining the qualifications to be required from persons to whom licences under section 3 of this Act may be granted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>for regulating the attendance of Muslim Registrars at the celebration of marriages, and their remuneration for such attendance;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>for regulating the grant of copies by Registrars and Muslim Registrars;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>for regulating the payment by the Muslim Registrars of the cost of the seals, forms of registers, stationery and any other articles which may be supplied to them by [the Provincial Government]3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>for regulating the application of the fees levied by Registrars of Districts and by Muslim Registrars under this Act; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>for regulating such other matters as appear to the State Government necessary to effect the purposes of the Act. The State Government may, from time to time, cancel or alter any such rules :</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-17.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that all rules made under this section shall be subject to the condition of previous publication.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.paragraph-0.list3.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>for regulating and fixing of rates of Registration and other connected fees for carrying out the provisions of this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Inspector General of Registration to exercise general superintendence</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Inspector General of Registration shall exercise a general superintendence over offices of the Muslim Registrars, and shall have power to frame regulations, from time to time, consistent with the rules made under this Act, for the guidance of the said Muslim Registrars and their offices generally.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Refusal to register to be recorded</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every Muslim Registrar refusing to register a marriage or divorce shall make an order of refusal, and record his reasons for such order in a book to be kept for that purpose.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Appeal against refusal to register</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>An appeal shall lie against an order of a Muslim Registrar refusing or admitting to register a marriage or divorce, to the Registrar to whom such Muslim Registrar is subordinate, if presented to such Registrar within thirty days from the date of the order, and the Registrar may revise or alter such order.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Copies of entries to be sent monthly to Registrar of District</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every Muslim Registrar shall, at the expiration of every month, send certified copies of all entries made by him during the month in the registers mentioned in section 6 of this Act, and also of the entries which have been made in the index referred to in sections 12 and 13 of this Act, to the Registrar of the district within which such Muslim Registrar has been authorised to act, and the Registrar, on receiving such copies, shall file them in his office.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Registers to be given up</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every Muslim Registrar shall keep safely each register until the same shall be filled, and shall then or earlier, if he shall leave the district or cease to hold a license, make over the same to the Registrar of the district for safe custody, or to such other person as the Registrar may direct.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Muslim Registrar to be a public servant</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every Muslim Registrar shall be, and be deemed to be a public servant, and his duties under this Act shall be deemed to be public duties.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Saving clause</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-24.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Nothing in this Act contained shall be construed to--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>render invalid merely by reason of its not having been registered any Muslim marriage or divorce which would otherwise be valid;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>rendered valid, by reason of its having been registered, any Muslim marriage or divorce which would otherwise be invalid;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>authorise the attendance of any Muslim Registrar at the celebration or dissolution of a marriage or divorce except at the request of all the parties concerned.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>affect the religion or religious rites and usages of [any citizen of India.]1</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>prevent any person, who is unable to write, from putting his mark, instead of the signature required by this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Nothing contained in this Act, or in the rules made under the authority of this Act, shall be deemed to affect the jurisdiction of the Civil Courts.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-schedulei">
      <doc name="schedulei">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-asm/act/1935/09/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-asm/act/1935/09"/>
              <FRBRalias value="SCHEDULE I"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-asm/act/1935/09/eng@2017-03-15/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-asm/act/1935/09/eng@2017-03-15"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-asm/act/1935/09/eng@2017-03-15/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-asm/act/1935/09/eng@2017-03-15"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-03-15" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="schedulei">
            <heading>[See Sections 6 and 10]</heading>
            <paragraph id="schedulei.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>Form (O)--Book--I</p>
                <p>Register of Marriages</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <subsection id="schedulei.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Consecutive number.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Name of the bridegroom and that of his father, with their respective residences.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Name of the bride and that of her father, with their respective residences.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.4">
              <num>(4)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Whether the bride is a spinster, a widow, or divorced by a former husband, or she herself divorced her husband, whether she is adult or otherwise?</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.5">
              <num>(5)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Name of the guardian of the bridegroom (if the bridegroom be a minor) and that of the guardian's father, with specification of the guardian's residence, and of relationship in which he stands to the bridegroom.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.6">
              <num>(6)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Name of guardian of the bride (if she be a minor) and that of her father, with specification of his residence and the relationship in which he stands to the bride.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.7">
              <num>(7)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Name of the bride's Vakil, and of his father and their residences, with specification of the relationship in which the Vakil stands to the bride.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.8">
              <num>(8)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Names of the witnesses to the due authorisation of the bride's Vakil, with names of their fathers, and residences and specification of relationship in which they stand to the bride.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.9">
              <num>(9)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Date of marriage.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.10">
              <num>(10)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Amount of dower. How much is m'uajjal (prompt) and how much is muwajjal (deferred).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.11">
              <num>(11)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Whether any portion of the dower was paid at the moment. If so, how much and how?</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.12">
              <num>(12)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Whether any property was given in lieu of the whole or any portion of the dower, with specification of the same?</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.13">
              <num>(13)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Special conditions, if any.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.14">
              <num>(14)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Names of village or town, police jurisdiction, and district in which the marriage took place.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.15">
              <num>(15)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Name of the person in whose house the marriage ceremony took place, and that of his father with his residence.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedulei.16">
              <num>(16)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Date of Registration.</p>
                <p>NOTE.-- Columns 5 and 6 will be blank if the bride and bridegroom, respectively, are not represented by guardians and columns 7 and 8 will be blank when the bride is not represented by a Vakil.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-scheduleii">
      <doc name="scheduleii">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-asm/act/1935/09/scheduleii"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-asm/act/1935/09"/>
              <FRBRalias value="SCHEDULE II"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-asm/act/1935/09/eng@2017-03-15/scheduleii"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-asm/act/1935/09/eng@2017-03-15"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-asm/act/1935/09/eng@2017-03-15/scheduleii"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-asm/act/1935/09/eng@2017-03-15"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-03-15" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduleii">
            <heading>[See Sections 6 and 10]</heading>
            <paragraph id="scheduleii.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>Form (B)--Book II</p>
                <p>Register of divorces other than those of the kind known as Khula</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Consecutive number.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Name of the husband and of his father and their residences.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Names of the wife and of her father, and their residences.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.4">
              <num>(4)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Date of divorce.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.5">
              <num>(5)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Description of divorce.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.6">
              <num>(6)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Manner in which the divorce was effected.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.7">
              <num>(7)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Names of the village or town, police jurisdiction, and district in which the divorce took place.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.8">
              <num>(8)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Name of the person in whose house the divorce took place and of his father with residences.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.9">
              <num>(9)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Names of witnesses to the divorce, if any, the names of their father and their respective rasidences.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.10">
              <num>(10)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Name of the person identifying the husband before the Muslim Registrar and that of his father, and their residences.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleii.11">
              <num>(11)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Date of Registration.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-scheduleiii">
      <doc name="scheduleiii">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-asm/act/1935/09/scheduleiii"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-asm/act/1935/09"/>
              <FRBRalias value="SCHEDULE III"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-asm/act/1935/09/eng@2017-03-15/scheduleiii"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-asm/act/1935/09/eng@2017-03-15"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-asm/act/1935/09/eng@2017-03-15/scheduleiii"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-asm/act/1935/09/eng@2017-03-15"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-03-15" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduleiii">
            <heading>[See Sections 6 and 10]</heading>
            <paragraph id="scheduleiii.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>Form (C)-- Book III</p>
                <p>Register of divorces of the kind known as Khula</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <subsection id="scheduleiii.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Consecutive number,</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleiii.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Name of the husband and that of his father, and their residences.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleiii.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Name of the wife and that of her father, and their residences.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleiii.4">
              <num>(4)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Date of Khula.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleiii.5">
              <num>(5)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Amount of dower.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleiii.6">
              <num>(6)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Whether Khula was acknowledged by the wife in person before the Muslim Registrar.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleiii.7">
              <num>(7)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If so, name of the party identifying her before the Muslim Registrar, and that of her father and their residences with specification of the relationship which he bears to her, if any.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleiii.8">
              <num>(8)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If the Khula be acknowledged before the Muslim Registrar, by the wife's guardian, his name and that of his father and their residences with specification of the relationship which the guardian bears to the wife.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleiii.9">
              <num>(9)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Names of the two witnesses to the due authorisation of the wife's Vakil and those of their fathers, with their residences.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleiii.10">
              <num>(10)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Name of village or town, police jurisdiction, and district where the Khula took place.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleiii.11">
              <num>(11)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Name of the person in whose house the Khula took place and that of his father.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleiii.12">
              <num>(12)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Names of the witnesses, if any, to the divorce being effected, the names of their fathers and their residences.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleiii.13">
              <num>(13)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Name of the person identifying the husband and that of his father, and their residences.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduleiii.14">
              <num>(14)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Date of registration.</p>
                <p>NOTE.- Column 8 will be blank if the woman is not represented by a Vakil.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-scheduleiv">
      <doc name="scheduleiv">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-asm/act/1935/09/scheduleiv"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-asm/act/1935/09"/>
              <FRBRalias value="SCHEDULE IV"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-asm/act/1935/09/eng@2017-03-15/scheduleiv"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-asm/act/1935/09/eng@2017-03-15"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-asm/act/1935/09/eng@2017-03-15/scheduleiv"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-asm/act/1935/09/eng@2017-03-15"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-03-15" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduleiv">
            <heading>(See section 9)</heading>
            <paragraph id="scheduleiv.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>TABLE OF FEES</p>
                <table id="scheduleiv.paragraph-0.table1">
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>When the dower does not exceed Rs. 500</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 50</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>When the dower exceed Rs. 500 but does not exceed Rs. 5000</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 250</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>When the dower exceed Rs. 5,000 but does not exceed Rs. 10,000</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 500</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>When the dower exceed Rs. 10,000 but does not exceed Rs. 50,000</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 1,000</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>When the dower exceed Rs. 50,000 but does not exceed Rs. 1,00,000</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 1,500</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>When the dower exceed Rs. 1,00,000 and above</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 2,000</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>For divorces of any kind</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 2,000</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </table>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
