<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1980/65/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1980/65"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The National Security Act, 1980"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1980/65/eng@1980-12-27/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1980/65/eng@1980-12-27"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-12-27" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1980/65/eng@1980-12-27/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1980/65/eng@1980-12-27"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-24" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The National Security Act, 1980</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[27th December, 1980.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for preventive detention in certain cases and for matters connected therewith.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty-first Year of the Republic of India as follows:—</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and extent.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the National Security Act, 1980.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"appropriate Government" means, as respects a detention order made by the Central Government or a person detained under such order, the Central Government, and as respect a detention order made by a State Government or by an officer subordinate to a State Government or as respects a person detained under such order, the State Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"detention order" means an order made under section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>"foreigner" has the same meaning as the Foreigners Act, 1946 (31 of 1946);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>"person" includes a foreigner;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>"State Government", in relation to a Union territory, means the administrator thereof.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Power to make orders detaining certain persons.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government or the State Government may,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>if satisfied with respect to any person that with a view to preventing him from acting in any manner prejudicial to the defence of India, the relations of India with foreign powers, or the security of India, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>if satisfied with respect to any foreigner that with a view to regulating his continued presence in India or with a view to making arrangements for his expulsion from India,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>it is necessary so to do, make an order directing that such person be detained.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government or the State Government may, if satisfied with respect to any person that with a view to preventing him from acting in any manner prejudicial to the security of the State or from acting in any manner prejudicial to the maintenance of public order or from acting in any manner prejudicial to the maintenance of supplies and services essential to the community it is necessary so to do, make an order directing that such person be detained.</p>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <p>For the purposes of this sub-section, "acting in any manner prejudicial to the maintenance of supplies and services essential to the community" does not include "acting in any manner prejudicial to the maintenance of supplies of commodities essential to the community" as defined in the Explanation to sub-section (1) of section 3 of the Prevention of Blackmarketing and Maintenance of Supplies of Essential Commodities Act, 1980 (7 of 1980), and accordingly, no order of detention shall be made under this Act on any ground on which an order of detention may be made under that Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If, having regard to the circumstances prevailing or likely to prevail in any area within the local limits of the jurisdiction of a District Magistrate or a Commissioner of Police, the State Government is satisfied that it is necessary so to do, it may, by order in writing, direct, that during such period as may be specified in the order, such District Magistrate or Commissioner of Police may also, if satisfied as provided in sub-section (2), exercise the powers conferred by the said sub-section:</p>
            <p>Provided that the period specified in an order made by the State Government under this sub-section shall not, in the first instance, exceed three months, but the State Government may, if satisfied as aforesaid that it is necessary so to do, amend such order to extend such period from time to time by any period not exceeding three months at any one time.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When any order is made under this section by an officer mentioned in sub-section (3), he shall forthwith report the fact to the State Government to which he is subordinate together with the grounds on which the order has been made and such other particulars as, in his opinion, have a bearing on the matter, and no such order shall remain in force for more than twelve days after the making thereof unless, in the meantime, it has been approved by the State Government:</p>
            <p>Provided that where under section 8 the grounds of detention are communicated by the officer making the order after five days but not later than ten days from the date of detentions, this sub-section shall apply subject to the modification, that, for the words "twelve days", the words "fifteen days" shall be substituted.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When any order is made or approved by the State Government under this section, the State Government shall, within seven days, report the fact to the Central Government together with the grounds on which the order has been made and such other particulars as, in the opinion of the State Government, have a bearing on the necessity for the order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Execution of detention order.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A detention order may be executed at any place in India in the manner provided for the execution of warrants of arrest under the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Power to regulate place and conditions of detention.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Every person in respect of whom a detention order has been made shall be liable—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to be detained in such place and under such conditions, including conditions as to maintenance, discipline and punishment for breaches of discipline, as the appropriate Government may, by general or special order, specify; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to be removed from one place of detention to another place of detention, whether within the same State or in another State, by order of the appropriate Government:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that no order shall be made by a State Government under clause (b) for the removal of a person from one State to another State except with the consent of the Government of that other State.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5A">
        <num>5A.</num>
        <heading>Grounds of detention severable.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5A.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where a person has been detained in pursuance of an order of detention whether made before or after the commencement of the National Security (Second Amendment) Act, 1984 under section 3 which has been made on two or more grounds, such order of detention shall be deemed to have been made separately on each of such grounds and accordingly—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5A.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-5A.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>such order shall not be deemed to be invalid or inoperative merely because one or some of the grounds is or are—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-5A.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>vague,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-5A.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>non-existent,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-5A.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>not relevant,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-5A.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>not connected or not proximately connected with such person, or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-5A.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.v">
                    <num>(v)</num>
                    <p>invalid for any other reason whatsoever,</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5A.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>and it is not, therefore, possible to hold that the Government or officer making such order would have been satisfied as provided in section 3 with reference to the remaining ground or grounds and made the order of detention;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5A.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the Government or officer making the order of detention shall be deemed to have made the order of detention under the said section after being satisfied as provided in that section with reference to the remaining ground or grounds.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Detention orders not to be invalid or in-operative on certain grounds.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>No detention order shall be invalid or in-operative merely by reason—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>that the person to be detained thereunder is outside the limits of the territorial jurisdiction of the Government or officer making the order, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>that the place of detention of such person is outside the said limits.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Powers in relation to absconding persons.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If the Central Government or an officer mentioned in sub-section (3) of section 3, as the case may be, has reason to believe that a person in respect of whom a detention order has been made has absconded or is concealing himself so that the order cannot be executed, that Government or officer may—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>make a report in writing of the fact to a Metropolitan Magistrate or a Judicial Magistrate of the first class having jurisdiction in the place where the said person ordinarily resides;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>by order notified in the Official Gazette direct the said person to appear before such officer, at such place and within such period as may be specified in the order.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon the making of a report against any person under clause (a) of sub-section (1), the provisions of sections 82, 83, 84 and 85 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), shall apply in respect of such person and his property as if the detention order made against him were a warrant issued by the Magistrate.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person fails to comply with an order issued under clause (b) of sub-section (1) he shall, unless he proves that it was not possible for him to comply therewith and that he had, within the period specified in the order, informed the officer mentioned in the order of the reason which rendered compliance therewith impossible and of his whereabouts, be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or with fine, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), every offence under sub-section (3) shall be cognizable.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Grounds of order of detention to be disclosed to persons affected by the order.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When a person is detained in pursuance of a detention order, the authority making the order shall, as soon as may be, but ordinarily not later than five days and in exceptional circumstances and for reasons to be recorded in writing, not later than ten days from the date of detention, communicate to him the grounds on which the order has been made and shall afford him the earliest opportunity of making a representation against the order to the appropriate Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in sub-section (1) shall require the authority to disclose facts which it considers to be against the public interest to disclose.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of Advisory Boards.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government and each State Government shall, whenever necessary, constitute one or more Advisory Boards for the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every such Board shall consist of three persons who are, or have been, or are qualified to be appointed, as Judges of a High Court, and such persons shall be appointed by the appropriate Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The appropriate Government shall appoint one of the members of the Advisory Board who is, or has been, a Judge of a High Court to be its Chairman, and in the case of a Union territory, the appointment to the Advisory Board of any person who is a Judge of the High Court of a State shall be with the previous approval of the State Government concerned.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Reference to Advisory Board.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Save as otherwise expressly provided in this Act, in every case where a detention order has been made under this Act, the appropriate Government shall, within three weeks from the date of detention of a person under the order, place before the Advisory Board constituted by it under section 9, the grounds on which the order has been made and the representation, if any, made by the person affected by the order, and in case where the order has been made by an officer mentioned in sub-section (3) of section 3, also the report by such officer under sub-section (4) of that section.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Procedure of Advisory Board.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Advisory Board shall, after considering the materials placed before it and, after calling for such further information as it may deem necessary from the appropriate Government or from any person called for the purpose through the appropriate Government or from the person concerned, and if, in any particular case, it considers it essential so to do or if the person concerned desires to be heard, after hearing him in person, submit its report to the appropriate Government within seven weeks from the date of detention of the person concerned.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The report of the Advisory Board shall specify in a separate part thereof the opinion of the Advisory Board as to whether or not there is sufficient cause for the detention of the person concerned.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When there is a difference of opinion among the members forming the Advisory Board, the opinion of the majority of such members shall be deemed to be the opinion of the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in this section shall entitle any person against whom a detention order has been made to appear by any legal practitioner in any matter connected with the reference to the Advisory Board; and the proceedings of the Advisory Board and its report, excepting the part of the report in which the opinion of the Advisory Board is specified, shall be confidential.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Action upon the report of the Advisory Board.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In any case where the Advisory Board has reported that there is, in its opinion, sufficient cause for the detention of a person, the appropriate Government may confirm the detention order and continue the detention of the person concerned for such period as it thinks fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In any case where the Advisory Board has reported that there is, in its opinion, no sufficient cause for the detention of a person, the appropriate Government shall revoke the detention order and cause the person concerned to be released forthwith.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Maximum period of detention.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The maximum period for which any person may be detained in pursuance of any detention order which has been confirmed under section 12 shall be twelve months from the date of detention:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing contained in this section shall affect the power of the appropriate Government to revoke or modify the detention order at any earlier time.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Revocation of detention orders.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Without prejudice to the provisions of section 21 of the General Clauses Act, 1897 (10 of 1897), a detention order may, at any time, be revoked or modified,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>notwithstanding that the order has been made by an officer mentioned in sub-section (3) of section 3, by the State Government to which that officer is subordinate or by the Central Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>notwithstanding that the order has been made by a State Government, by the Central Government.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The expiry or revocation of a detention order (hereafter in this sub-section referred to as the earlier detention order) shall not whether such earlier detention order has been made before or after the commencement of the National Security (Second Amendment) Act, 1984 bar the making of another detention order (hereafter in this sub-section referred to as the subsequent detention order) under section 3 against the same person:</p>
            <p>Provided that in a case where no fresh facts have arisen after the expiry or revocation of the earlier detention order made against such person, the maximum period for which such person may be detained in pursuance of the subsequent detention order shall, in no case, extend beyond the expiry of a period of twelve months from the date of detention under the earlier detention order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14A">
        <num>14A.</num>
        <heading>Circumstances in which persons may be detained for periods longer than three months without obtaining the opinion of Advisory Boards.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14A.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Nothwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing provisions of this Act, or in any judgment, decree or order of any court or other authority, any person in respect of whom an order of detention has been made under this Act at any time before the 8th day of June, 1989 may be detained without obtaining the opinion of the Advisory Board for a period longer than three months, but not exceeding six months, from the date of his detention where such person had been detained with a view to preventing him, in any disturbed area—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14A.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>from interfering with the efforts of Government in coping with the terrorist and disruptive activities; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14A.1.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>from acting in any manner prejudicial to—</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14A.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the defence of India; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14A.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the security of India; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14A.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the security of the State; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14A.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the maintenance of public order; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14A.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the maintenance of supplies and services essential to the community.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Explanation 1.—</p>
            <p>The provisions of the Explanation to sub-section (2) of section 3 shall apply for the purposes of this sub-section as they apply for the purposes of that sub-section.</p>
            <p>Explanation 2.—</p>
            <p>In this sub-section, "disturbed area" means any area which is for the time being declared by notification under section 3 of the Punjab Disturbed Areas Act, 1983 (32 of 1983), or under section 3 of the Chandigarh Disturbed Areas Act, 1983 (33 of 1983), to be a disturbed area.</p>
            <p>Explanation 3.—</p>
            <p>In this sub-section, "terrorist and disruptive activities" means "terrorist acts" and "disruptive activities" within the meaning of the Terrorist and Disruptive Activities (Prevention) Ordinance, 1987 (Ord. 2 of 1987).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14A.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In the case of any person to whom sub-section (1) applies, sections 3, 8 and 10 to 14 shall have effect subject to the following modifications, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14A.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-14A.2.list1.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>in section 3,—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-14A.2.list1.a.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <blockList id="section-14A.2.list1.a.list0.i.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>in sub-section (4), in the proviso,—</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-14A.2.list1.a.list0.i.list1.A">
                        <num>(A)</num>
                        <p>for the words "ten days", the words "fifteen days" shall be substituted;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-14A.2.list1.a.list0.i.list1.B">
                        <num>(B)</num>
                        <blockList id="section-14A.2.list1.a.list0.i.list1.B.list0">
                          <listIntroduction>for the words "ten days" the words "twenty days" shall be substituted;</listIntroduction>
                          <item id="section-14A.2.list1.a.list0.i.list1.B.list0.ii">
                            <num>(ii)</num>
                            <p>in sub-section (5), for the words "seven days", the words "fifteen days" shall be substituted;</p>
                          </item>
                        </blockList>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14A.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in section 8, in sub-section (1), for the words "ten days", the words "fifteen days" shall be substituted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14A.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>in section 10, for the words "shall, within three weeks", the words "shall, within four months and two weeks" shall be substituted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14A.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <blockList id="section-14A.2.list1.d.list2">
                  <listIntroduction>in section 11,—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-14A.2.list1.d.list2.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>in sub-section (1), for the words "seven weeks", the words "five months and three weeks" shall be substituted;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-14A.2.list1.d.list2.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>in sub-section (2), for the words "detention of the person concerned", the words "continued detention of the person concerned" shall be substituted;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14A.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>in section 12, for the words "for the detention", at both the places where they occur, the words "for the continued detention" shall be substituted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14A.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>in section 13, for the words "twelve months", the words "two years" shall be substituted:</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14A.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>in section 14, in the proviso to sub-section (2), for the words "twelve months" the words "two years" shall be substituted.]</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Temporary release of persons detained.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The appropriate Government may, at any time, direct that any person detained in pursuance of a detention order may be released for any specified period either without conditions or upon such conditions specified in the direction as that person accepts, and may, at any time, cancel his release.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In directing the release of any person under sub-section (1), the appropriate Government may require him to enter into a bond with or without sureties for the due observance of the conditions specified in the direction.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person released under sub-section (1) shall surrender himself at the time and place, and to the authority, specified in the order directing his release or cancelling his release, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person, fails without sufficient cause, to surrender himself in the manner specified in sub-section (3), he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years, or with fine, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person released under sub-section (1) fails to fulfil any of the conditions imposed upon him under the said sub-section or in the bond entered into by him, the bond shall be declared to be forfeited and any person bound thereby shall be liable to pay the penalty thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central Government or a State Government, and no suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any person, for anything in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Act not to have effect with respect to detentions under State laws.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-17.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Nothing in this Act shall apply or have any effect with respect to orders of detention, made under any State law, which are in force immediately before the commencement of the National Security Ordinance, 1980 (Ord. 11 of 1980), and accordingly every person in respect of whom an order of detention made under any State law is in force immediately before such commencement, shall be governed with respect to such detention by the provisions of such State law or where the State law under which such order of detention is made is an Ordinance (hereinafter referred to as the State Ordinance) promulgated by the Governor of the State and the State Ordinance has been replaced—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>before such commencement, by an enactment passed by the Legislature of the State, by such enactment; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.1.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>after such commencement, by an enactment which is passed by the Legislature of the State and the application of which is confined to orders of detention made before such commencement under the State Ordinance, by such enactment,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>as if this Act had not been enacted.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in this section be deemed to bar the making under section 3, of a detention order against any person referred to in sub-section (1) after the detention order in force in respect of him as aforesaid immediately before the commencement of the National Security Ordinance, 1980 (Ord. 11 of 1980), ceases to have effect for any reason whatsoever.</p>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <p>For the purposes of this section, "State law" means any law providing for preventive detention on all or any of the grounds on which an order of detention may be made under sub-section (2) of section 3 and in force in any State immediately before the commencement of the said Ordinance.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Repeal and saving.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The National Security Ordinance, 1980 (Ord. 11 of 1980), is hereby repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act, as if this Act had come into force on the 23rd day of September, 1980, and, in particular, any reference made under section 10 of the said Ordinance and pending before any Advisory Board immediately before the date on which this Act receives the assent of the President may continue to be dealt with by that Board after that date as if such Board had been constituted under section 9 of the Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
