<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-meg/act/1971/8/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-meg/act/1971/8"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Meghalaya Subsidiary Force Act, 1971"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-meg/act/1971/8/eng@2017-01-21/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-meg/act/1971/8/eng@2017-01-21"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-meg/act/1971/8/eng@2017-01-21/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-meg/act/1971/8/eng@2017-01-21"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-12-20" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Meghalaya Subsidiary Force Act, 1971</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>(As passed by the Assembly)</p>
        <p>[Received the assent of the Governor on the Third July, 1971]</p>
        <p>(Published in the Gazette of Meghalaya, Extraordinary, dated the 6th July, 1971)</p>
        <p>An</p>
        <p>Act</p>
        <p>to provide for the constitution of a force in Meghalaya to be known as the Meghalaya Subsidiary Force.</p>
        <p>Be it enacted by the Legislature of Meghalaya in the Twenty-second Year of the Republic of India as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called Meghalaya Subsidiary Force Act, 1971.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 4th day of June, 1971.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In the Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“Force” means the Meghalaya Subsidiary Force constituted under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“Government” means “the Government of Meghalaya”;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“Prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>“Relief Camp” includes any place, locality or area as may be declared as Relief Camp by Government for the purpose of this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of Meghalaya Subsidiary Force.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In Meghalaya or part thereof, the Government may raise and</p>
            <p>maintain a Force to be called Meghalaya Subsidiary Force which shall consist of such number of persons and shall be constituted in such manner as the Governments may, by order, direct.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Force in Meghalaya shall for the purpose of this Act, be deemed to be a single force and the members thereof shall be formally appointed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be paid to each officer and member of the Force such monthly salary, remuneration or honorarium as may be determined by the Government from time to time.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>General superintendance</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The general superintendence of the Force throughout</p>
            <p>Meghalaya shall vest in and shall be exercised by the Government through an Officer to be styled as the Director of the Subsidiary Force in such manner and to such extent as the Government of Meghalaya may deem fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to sub-section (2) of section 3, there shall be a Commandant of the Force for every district, or part thereof and such other officers subordinate to him as may be necessary.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Appointment of officers and members.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Director of the Subsidiary Force and the Commandant</p>
            <p>shall be appointed by the Government in such manner as may be determined by the Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The appointment of other officers and members shall be made in such manner and by such authority as may be determined by the Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Duties and functions of the Force.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The following shall be the duties and functions of the Force,</p>
            <blockList id="section-6.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to assist aid the police in the maintenance of law and order in Meghalaya;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to report to the Deputy Commissioner, in such a manner as the latter may direct, all crimes, unnatural deaths or serious accidents;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to prevent commission of any cognizable offence;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>to apprehend and deliver to the competent authority vagrant or bad and suspicious character, found within their jurisdiction;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list2.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>to collect and communicate to the Deputy Commissioner intelligence affecting law and order and any matter relating to any village or town administration.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list2.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>to protect Government and other public properties;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list2.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>to obey and execute promptly all orders and warrants lawfully issue by any court;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list2.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>to act under the orders of the Deputy Commissioner and to furnish such returns and information as may be called by the Deputy Commissioner and his subordinate officers;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list2.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>to assist the Deputy Commissioner and the subordinate officers in maintaining order and discipline in Relief Camp;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list2.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>to do other social work as my be entrusted by competent authority; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list2.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>to perform such other duties as are specified under other provisions of this Act and as the Government may, from time to time, by general or special order specify in this behalf.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every officer of member shall have the power to arrest any proclaimed offender or any person who in his view commits a non-bailable and cognizable offence. Any person so arrested shall without unnecessary delay be taken or caused to be taken in custody to the nearest Police Station or Magistrate. The arrested person shall be produced before the nearest Magistrate within a period of 24 hours of such arrest excluding the time necessary for the journey from the place of arrest to the court of the Magistrate.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Duty , Training of officer and member.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to any rules made in this behalf, it shall be the duty of</p>
            <p>every officer and member of the Force promptly to obey and execute all orders issued to him by any competent authority.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to any rules made in this behalf the officers and members of the Force may be required to undergo such training as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Uniform.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The officers and members of the Force shall wear such uniform and shall use such equipments as may be prescribed by the Government from time to time.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Bar to prosecution.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No prosecution shall be instituted against any officer or member of the Force in respect of anything done or purported to be done by him in the discharge of his duties, except with the previous section of the Government or some officer empowerment by the Government in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Penalty.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every officer or member of the Force who is guilty of any</p>
            <p>violation of duty or wilful breach or neglect of any provision of this Act or any rule or lawful order made by competent authority, of withdrawal from the duties of his office without permission or who being required to undergo training without sufficient cause neglects or refuses to obey the requirements for training, shall be punishable with imprisonment of either description for a term which may extend to three months or with fine which may extend to rupees two hundred and fifty or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The offence punishable under sub-section (1) shall be cognizable.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Suits, etc., against officers and members acting in good faith.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit, prosecution or legal proceeding shall lie against any officer or member of the Force for anything done in good faith under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-12.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the foregoing powers, such rules may provide for or regulate all or any of the following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>all matters which are required by this Act to be prescribed;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the organisation, appointment, conditions of service, functions, discipline, equipments, or uniform of the Force and the manner in which they may be called out for service or required to undergo training, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any other matter.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Repeal of Meghalaya Ordinance 4 of 1971.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Meghalaya Subsidiary Force Ordinance, 1971, is hereby repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
