<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1974/36/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1974/36"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Karnataka Electricity Supply Undertakings (Acquisition) Act, 1974"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1974/36/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1974/36/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1974/36/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1974/36/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Karnataka Electricity Supply Undertakings (Acquisition) Act, 1974</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No. 36 of 1974</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the acquisition of electrical undertakings in the State of Karnataka, supplying electricity for the purpose of ensuring better supply of electricity to the general public.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>WHEREAS it is expedient for the purpose of ensuring better supply of electricity to the general public, to provide for the acquisition of electrical undertakings in the State of Karnataka supplying electricity to the public other than such undertakings belonging to and under the control of, (a) the Karnataka Electricity Board constituted under section 5 of the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1948 (Central Act LIV of 1948) and (b) a co-operative society, and matters connected therewith and incidental thereto;</p>
      <p>BE it enacted by the Karnataka State Legislature in the Twenty-fifth Year of the Republic of India as follows:-</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Karnataka Electricity Supply Undertakings (Acquisition) Act, 1974.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Karnataka.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Government may, by notification, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Declaration.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In pursuance of Article 31C of the Constitution of India, it is hereby declared that the provisions of this Act are enacted for giving effect to the policy of the State towards securing the principles specified in clauses (b) and (c) of Article 39 of the Constitution.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>‘account year’ means the company’s financial year;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>‘annual account’ means the account of the undertaking rendered to the Government annually under and in accordance with the Electricity Act, or where no such account has to be rendered under that Act, the account of the undertaking normally made up for the account year of the undertaking and audited by a Chartered Accountant in practice within the meaning of the Chartered Accountants Act, 1949 (Central Act XXXVIII of 1949);</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>‘appointed date’ means the date appointed under sub-section (3) of section 1;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>‘Board” means the Karnataka Electricity Board constituted under section 5 of the Electricity Supply Act, 1948 (Central Act LIV of 1948);</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.5.list1">
              <listIntroduction>‘companies’ means the Amalgamated Electricity Company Limited, Belgaum, the Nipani Electricity Company Limited, Nipani, the Karwar, Electric Supply and Trading Company Limited, Karwar, the Kanara Electric Supply Company Limited, Sirsi and includes the following concerns engaged in the business of supplying electricity to the public, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.5.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>Manvi Brothers, Gadag;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.5.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>Manvi Brothers, Byadgi;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.5.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>Manvi Brothers, Ranebennur; and ‘company’ means any of the companies aforesaid;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>‘document’ in relation to an undertaking, includes its books, accounts, registers, maps, plans, section drawings, records of survey and all other documents of whatever nature relating to the undertaking;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>‘Electricity Act’ means the Indian Electricity Act, 1910 (Central Act 9 of 1910);</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>‘Electricity (Supply) Act’ means the Electricity Supply Act, 1948 (Central Act LIV of 1948);</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>‘fixed assets’ includes works, spare parts, stores, stocks, instruments, tools, motor and other vehicles, office and other equipments and furniture;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.10">
          <num>(10)</num>
          <content>
            <p>‘Government’ means the State Government;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>‘intangible assets’ means any amount paid on account of goodwill, under-writers’ commission and such preliminary and promotional expenditure shown as a debit in the capital account of the undertaking, as has fairly arisen in promoting electricity supply;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.12">
          <num>(12)</num>
          <content>
            <p>‘Tribunal’ means the Tribunal constituted under section 14;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.13">
          <num>(13)</num>
          <content>
            <p>‘undertaking; means an undertaking engaged in the business of supplying electricity to the public;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.14">
          <num>(14)</num>
          <content>
            <p>‘vesting date’ means the date on which the undertaking vest in the Government under sub-section (1) of section 4;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.15">
          <num>(15)</num>
          <content>
            <p>‘works’ includes electric supply-lines and any lands, buildings, workshops, projects, machinery, plant or apparatus, required to supply electricity and to carry into effect the objects of a licence granted for the supply of electricity under the Electricity Act;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.16">
          <num>(16)</num>
          <content>
            <p>words and expressions used herein and not defined in this Act but defined in the Electricity Act, or the rules made under that Act, shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in that Act or those rules.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Undertakings of the Companies to vest in the Government.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>With effect on and from the appointed date the undertakings of the companies shall, by virtue of this Act, stand transferred to and vest in the Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every company which after the vesting date, was in possession of, or deriving any benefit from the undertaking vested in the Government under sub-section (1) shall be liable to pay to the Government, for the period, after such vesting for which it was in such possession or deriving such benefit, an amount as compensation for the use, occupation or enjoyment of that undertaking as the prescribed authority may fix in the prescribed manner. Such authority shall take into consideration such factors as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Amount to be given to Companies.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The amount to be given to a company, the undertaking of which vests in the Government under this Act, shall be determined and paid in the manner hereinafter provided.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The amount to be given shall be the aggregate value of the sums specified below:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the book value of all completed works in beneficial use pertaining to the undertaking and handed over to the Government (excluding works paid for by consumers) less depreciation calculated in the manner specified in the Schedule;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>the book value of all works in progress handed over to the Government, excluding works paid for by consumers or prospective consumers;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>the book value of all stores including spare parts handed over to the Government and in the case of used stores and spare parts, such sum as may be decided upon by mutual agreement between the Government and the companies;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>the book value of all other fixed assets in use on the vesting date and handed over to the Government less depreciation calculated in the manner specified in the Schedule;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>the book value of all plant and equipment existing on the vesting date but no longer in use owing to wear and tear or to obsolescence, to the extent such value has not been written off in the books of the company less depreciation calculated in the manner specified in the Schedule;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.vi">
                <num>(vi)</num>
                <p>the book value of all intangible assets to the extent such value has not been written off in the books of the companies;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.vii">
                <num>(vii)</num>
                <p>the sum due from consumers in respect of every hire-purchase agreement referred to in section 6 (1) (ii) less a sum which bears to the difference between the total sum of the instalments and the original cost of the material or equipment, the same proportion as the sum due bears to the total sum of the instalments;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.viii">
                <num>(viii)</num>
                <p>any sum paid actually by the company in respect of every contract referred to in section 6 (1) (iii).</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.ix">
                <num>(ix)</num>
                <p>a sum equal to ten percent of the aggregate of the amounts specified in clauses (i) to (vi), in consideration of the compulsory nature of acquisition;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation.- (a) For the purposes of this sub-section the book value of any fixed asset means its original cost, and shall comprise,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.2.list3.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the purchase price paid by the company for the asset, including the cost of delivery and all charges properly incurred in erecting and bringing the asset into beneficial use as shown in the books of the undertaking;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list3.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>interest charges on capital expenditure incurred from borrowed money and shown in the books of the undertaking as properly attributable to the asset up to the date of bringing it into beneficial use, at a rate not exceeding six percent per annum;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list3.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>cost of supervision actually incurred, but not exceeding fifteen percent of the sum referred to in paragraph (i).</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>Where any asset was acquired after the expiry of the period to which the latest annual account relates, or where no annual account has to be rendered under the Electricity Act, the book value of the asset shall be such sum as may be decided upon by the Government after giving an opportunity of being heard to the companies.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The amount to be given according to sub-section (2) less the amounts to be deducted therefrom as provided in this Act shall be the amount due and shall carry interest at the rate of five percent per annum from the vesting date.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The amount due may, subject to rules made in this behalf, be paid in full or in instalments not exceeding five or in bonds, negotiable or non-negotiable carrying interest at the rate specified in sub-section (3) and of guaranteed face value maturing within a specified period not exceeding ten years.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>General effect of vesting.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Undertakings of the companies vesting in the Government under section 4 shall be deemed to consist only of property, rights, liabilities and obligations specified hereunder,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>all the fixed assets of the companies and all documents relating to the undertakings;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>all the rights, liabilities and obligations of the companies under hire purchase agreements, if any, for the supply of materials or equipment made bona fide before the vesting date;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>all the rights, liabilities and obligations of the companies under any other contract entered into bona fide before the vesting date not being a contract relating to the borrowing or lending of money.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All the assets specified in item (i) of sub-section (1) shall vest in the Government free from any debts, mortgages or similar obligations of the companies for attaching to the undertakings:</p>
            <p>Provided that such debts, mortgages or obligations shall attach to the amount to be given under this Act for the assets.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the case of undertakings which vest in the Government under this Act, the licence granted or deemed to be granted for supplying electricity shall be deemed to have been terminated on the vesting date and all the rights, liabilities and obligations of the companies under any agreement to supply electricity entered into before that date shall devolve on the Government:</p>
            <p>Provided that where any such agreement is not in conformity with the rates and conditions of supply approved by the Government and in force on the vesting date, the agreement shall be voidable at the option of the Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification, provide for the transfer to, and vesting in, the Board, in such manner and subject to such conditions as may be specified in the notification, of property, rights, liabilities and obligations which have vested in the Government under this Act and thereupon, such property, rights, liabilities and obligations shall stand transferred to, and vest in the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Deductions from the amount.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Government shall be entitled to deduct the following sums from the amount to be given to a company under this Act:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the sum, if any, already given in advance by way of any amount to be given under section 5;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the sum, if any, specified under sub-section (2) of section 4;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the sum, if any, which may be, or ordered to be, deducted under section 9 or 11;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the sum due, if any, from the company to the Government or the Board for electricity supplied by the Board for any period prior to one month immediately preceding the vesting date;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>all other sums and arrears of interest, if any, thereon due from the company to the Government or the Board except loans and arrears of interest, if any, thereon:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that instalments of such loans and arrears of interest, if any, thereon which have accrued due during any period prior to one month immediately preceding the vesting date and outstanding on that date shall be deducted;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list3.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the sum, if any, equivalent to the loss sustained by the Government by reason of any property or rights belonging to the undertaking not having been handed over to the Government, the sum of such loss being deemed to be the sum by which the market value of such property or rights exceeds the amount payable therefor under this Act, together with any income which might have been realised as aforesaid;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list3.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>all sums paid by consumers by way of security deposit and arrears of interest due thereon on the vesting date in so far as they have not been paid over by the company to the Government, less the sums which according to the books of the company are due from the consumers to the company for electricity supplied by it before the date;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list3.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>all advances from consumers and prospective consumers, and all sums which have been or ought to be set aside to the credit of the consumer’s fund in so far as such advances or sums have not been paid over by the Company to the Government.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation.- For the purposes of this clause, “Consumers’ fund” shall, for any account year prior to the date on which the Sixth Schedule to the Electricity Supply Act came into force mean the amount referred to as such in the bulk supply agreement and, for any account year on and from the said date, it shall mean the amount specified in paragraph II (1) of the said Schedule as the amount to be set apart for distribution to consumers;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list5.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>if, under any law, award, agreement, contract of service or otherwise, the salary, wages, leave salary, bonus, pension, gratuity, provident fund, security deposit or other payment, becomes payable to a member of the staff after a specified period of service rendered by such member in connection with the undertaking, such member having been transferred to the Government,-</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list5.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>before the expiry of such specified period, a sum equal to the sum which bears to the full salary, wages, leave salary, bonus, pension, gratuity, provident fund, security deposit or other payment payable after the expiry of the said specified period, the same proportion as the period upto the vesting date bears to the whole of the said specified period;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list5.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>after the expiry of such specified period, a sum equal to full such salary, wages, leave salary, bonus, pension, gratuity, provident fund, security deposit or other payment:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list7">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that where any reserve fund has been created towards the salary, wages, leave salary, bonus, pension, gratuity, provident fund, security deposit or other payment referred to in this clause and such reserve fund shall vest in the Government under this Act, the amount of such reserve fund so vested shall not be deducted under this clause;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list7.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>sums, if any, in the credit of development rebate reserve, contingencies, reserves, tariff and dividend control reserve, consumers rebate reserve, reserve for bad and doubtful debts or any other reserve fund.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7A">
        <num>7A.</num>
        <heading>Application to the Tribunal.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7A.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any person disputing,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7A.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the amount determinable and payable under section 5; or,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7A.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>as to which property, rights, liabilities and obligations of the companies vest in the Government under section 6; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7A.paragraph-0.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>the amount liable to be deducted under section 7;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>may within three months from the date of commencement of the Karnataka Electricity Supply Undertakings (Acquisition) (Amendment) Act, 1995, apply to the Tribunal.</p>
            <p>Provided that the Tribunal may entertain such application after the period specified above if it is satisfied that the person making the application had sufficient cause for not making the application within that period.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Duty to deliver possession of property acquired and documents relating thereto.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In respect of property vesting in the Government under section 4 every person in whose possession or custody or under whose control the property may be, shall deliver up the property to such officer or authority appointed by the Government for the purpose, forthwith and until it is delivered such person shall from the vesting date be deemed to be in possession, custody or control of the property on behalf of the Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person who on the vesting date has in his possession or custody or under his control any document which has vested in the Government under this Act shall be liable to account for such document to the Government and shall deliver it up to the officer or authority referred to in sub-section (1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Without prejudice to the other provisions contained in this section it shall be lawful for such officer or authority to take all necessary steps for securing possession of all the assets and document which have vested in the Government under section 4.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Duty of the company to supply particulars.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In respect of the undertaking of a company vesting in the Government under this Act, the company shall, within two months from the vesting date or such further period as the Government may allow in this behalf, furnish to the Government,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>particulars of the book debts and investments belonging to and all liabilities and obligations of the company subsisting immediately before the vesting date; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>particulars of all agreements entered into by the company and in force on the vesting date including any agreements whether express or implied relating to leave, pension, gratuity and other terms of service of any officer or other employee of the company under which by virtue of this Act the Government has or will or may have liabilities or obligations and for this purpose the Government shall afford the company all reasonable facilities.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the company fails to supply to the Government particulars of book debts, liabilities and agreement within the time allowed to it for the purpose under sub-section (1), nothing contained in this Act shall have effect so as to transfer any such book debts, liabilities and agreements or to vest the same in the Government:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing in this sub-section shall apply to any agreement if any party to such agreement supplies to the Government, particulars of the agreements within two months from the vesting date and the Government, within a period of six months after such submission of particulars accept the liabilities under the agreement.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notice in writing within a period of six months after submission of the particulars referred to under sub-section (1) intimate to the company that such book debts and investments as are specified in the notice are not included in the property vesting in the Government, whereupon the amount provided by section 5 shall stand reduced by the amount of such excluded book debts and investments and the right of the company to recover and retain such excluded book debts shall remain unaffected by this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Right of Government to disclaim certain agreement.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where it appears to the Government that the making of any such agreement as is referred to in section 9 or any of the terms thereof under which the Government has or will have liabilities was not reasonably necessary for the purposes of the activities of the company or has not been entered into in good faith, the Government may, make an order cancelling or varying (either unconditionally or subject to such conditions as it may think fit to impose) such agreement and thereafter the agreement shall have effect accordingly:</p>
            <p>Provided that no agreement shall be cancelled or varied except after giving to the parties to the agreement a reasonable opportunity of being heard.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person, aggrieved by an order made under sub-section (1) may within such time as may be prescribed make an application to the Tribunal for the variation or reversal of such order and thereupon the Tribunal may confirm, modify or vary such order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Provisions respecting the officers and employees of the company.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of sections 10 and 13, every officer or other employee (except a Director, Advisor, Consumer or Auditor) employed before the vesting date in connection with the affairs of the undertakings which have vested in the Government by virtue of this Act, shall become as from that date, an officer or other employee as the case may be, of the Government and shall hold his office or service by the same tenure, at the same remuneration and upon the same terms and conditions and with the same rights and privileges as to pension, gratuity and other matters as he would have held under the company if its undertakings had not vested in the Government and shall continue to do so unless and until his employment under the Government is terminated after giving him three calendar months notice in writing or paying him three months pay in lieu of such notice or until his remuneration, terms and conditions including the privileges as to pension and gratuity are altered by rules or orders made by the Government:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub-section shall apply to any officer or employee who has by notice in writing given to the Government or to any person nominated in this behalf by the Government, within thirty days from the appointed day intimated his intention of not becoming an officer or other employee of the Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 (Central Act 14 of 1947) or in any other law for the time being in force, the transfer of the services of any officer or other employee of the company by virtue of this Act shall not entitle any such officer or other employee to any compensation under this Act or other law and no such claim shall be entertained by any court, tribunal or other authority.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Provident and other funds.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a company has established a provident fund, superannuation, welfare or other fund for the benefit of its officers or other employees, the moneys relatable to the officers or other employees whose services have become transferred by or under this Act to the Government shall out of the moneys standing on the vesting date to the credit of such provident fund, superannuation, welfare or other fund, stand transferred to and vest in the Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The moneys which stand transferred under sub-section (1) to the Government shall be dealt with by the Government in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Transaction resulting in dissipation of assets.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>This section shall apply where the company has, after the first day of January 1972 and before the vesting date,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>made any payment to any person without consideration or for an inadequate consideration;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>sold or disposed of any of its properties or rights without consideration or for an inadequate consideration;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>acquired any property or rights for an excessive consideration;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>entered into or varied any agreement so as to require an excessive consideration to be paid or given by the company;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>entered into any other transaction of such an onerous nature as to cause a loss to or impose a liability on the company exceeding any benefit accruing to the company; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.1.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>sold or otherwise transferred any equipment or machinery or other property of book value exceeding rupees ten thousand; and</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>the payment, sale, disposal, acquisition, agreement or variation thereof or other transaction or transfer, was not reasonably necessary for the purpose of carrying on the undertakings of the company, or was made with lack of prudence on the part of the company regard being had, in either case, to the circumstances at the time.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, at any time, within five year from the vesting date, apply for relief to the Tribunal in respect of any transaction to which in the opinion of the Government this section applies and all parties to the transaction shall, unless the Tribunal otherwise directs, be made parties to the application.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the Tribunal is satisfied that the transaction in respect of which an application is made is a transaction to which this section applies, then, unless, the Tribunal is also satisfied that the transaction was a proper transaction made in the ordinary course of business, regard being had to the circumstances at the time, and was not in any way connected with any provisions made by this Act, or in anticipation of the making of any such provision, the Tribunal shall make such order against any of the parties to the application as it thinks just having regard to the extent to which the parties were respectively responsible for the transaction or benefited from it and all the circumstances of the case.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an application is made to the Tribunal under this section in respect of any transaction and the application is determined in favour of the Government, the Tribunal shall have exclusive jurisdiction to determine any claims outstanding in respect of the transaction. On any such application, the Tribunal may order that Government deduct from the amount payable to the company under this Act, such amount as it may consider to be the loss sustained by the Government by virtue of any transaction referred to in sub-section (1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any amount ordered by the Tribunal to be deducted from the amount under subsection (4) shall be a first charge on the amount payable to the company and shall have priority over the claims of any person in respect of the amount payable to the company.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of satisfying the first charge referred to in sub-section (5), the Government shall withhold ten per centum of the amount payable to the company under section 5.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>After satisfying the first charge in favour of the Government under sub-section (5), the balance, if any of the amount withheld under sub-section (6), shall be paid to the company:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Tribunal may at any earlier time order payment of such amount as is in excess of the amount which in its opinion would be sufficient to satisfy the first charge under sub-section (5):</p>
            <p>Provided further that all payments under this sub-section shall be made in cash with interest at half percent from the vesting date.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Constitution and powers of Tribunal.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government shall by notification constitute a tribunal consisting of an officer not below the rank of a District judge.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of deciding any matter under sections 5, 6, 7, 7A, 10 and 13 the Tribunal may require any or all the parties to state their case in respect of such matter and may call upon them to adduce such evidence as may be necessary for the determination of the case.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Tribunal shall have the powers of a Civil Court while trying a suit under the Code of Civil Procedure 1908 (Central Act V of 1908) in respect of the following matters:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>summoning and enforcing attendance of any person and examining him on oath;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>requiring the discovery and production of documents;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.3.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>receiving evidence on affidavits;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.3.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses or documents;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.3.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>such other matters as may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Tribunal may regulate its own procedure and review its decision in the event of there being a mistake on the fact of the record or correct any arithmetical or clerical error therein but subject thereto and subject to the provisions of sub-section (5), the decision of the Tribunal on any matter within it's jurisdiction shall be final and shall not be called in question in any court of law.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government or any person aggrieved by any order of the Tribunal may, within thirty days from the date of the order, appeal to the High Court of Karnataka and the High Court may pass such orders thereon as it thinks fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Penalties.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person wilfully withholds or fails to deliver to the Government as required by section 8 any documents which may be in his possession or wrongfully obtains possession of any property of the company which has vested in the Government under this Act, or having any such property in his possession wrongfully withholds it from the Government, or wilfully applies to purposes other than those expressed in or authorised by this Act, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years or with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees, or with both and in the cases of a continuing offence with additional fine which may extend to five hundred rupees for every day after the first during which the offence continues and may be ordered by the court trying the offence to deliver up or refund within the time to be fixed by the court any such document or property improperly obtained or wrongfully withheld or wilfully misapplied, and in default, to suffer imprisonment for a further period which may extend to one year.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever fails without reasonable cause, to comply with any of the provisions of this Act or the rules made thereunder, or any direction or order issued in pursuance thereof shall, if the case be not governed by sub-section (1), be punishable with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees and in the case of a continuing offence with additional fine which may extend to five hundred rupees for every day after the first during which the offence continues.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No court shall take cognizance of any offence punishable under this section except with the previous sanction of the Government or of an officer authorised by it in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Offences by companies.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-16.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an offence under this Act has been committed by a company, every person who at the time the offence was committed was in charge of and was responsible to , the company for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where any offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is attributable to, any neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company such director, manager, secretary or other officer shall be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.</p>
            <blockList id="section-16.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation.- For the purpose of this section,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-16.2.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“company” means any body corporate and includes a firm or other association of individuals; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“director”, in relation to a firm, means a partner in the firm.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken under the Act.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit, prosecution, or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Government or any officer or servant of the Government or any person acting under the direction of the Government or of any officer or servant of the Government in respect of anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any rules or orders made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Government may by notification make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Power to remove difficulties.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Government may, by notified order, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act remove the difficulty:</p>
            <p>Provided that no such power shall be exercised after the expiry of a period of two years from the commencement of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Laying of rules and orders before the State Legislature.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this Act and every order issued under section 19 shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made or issued before each House of the State Legislature while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two successive sessions and if, before the expiry of the session in which it is so laid or the session immediately following both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or order or both Houses agree that the rule, or order should not be made, the rule or order shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under such rule or order.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Effect of other laws.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-21.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No provision of the Electricity Act or of the Electricity Supply Act or of any rule made under any of those Acts or of any instrument having effect by virtue of any of those Acts or any rule made thereunder shall in so far as it is inconsistent with any of the provisions of this Act have any effect.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-21.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Save as otherwise provided in this Act, the provisions of this Act shall be in addition to and not in derogation of the Electricity Act and the Electricity Supply Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Act to apply to undertaking voluntarily handed over to Government.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where an undertaking has been voluntarily handed over by a company to the Government before the commencement of this Act, and the Government have taken possession of such undertaking, the provisions of this Act shall apply to such undertaking as if such undertaking vests in the Government under this Act. All the provisions of this Act shall accordingly apply to such undertaking:</p>
            <p>Provided that where under this Act any period is to be computed from the vesting date, such period shall, in relation to any undertaking to which this section applies, be computed from the date of the publication of this Act in the official Gazette.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-schedule">
      <doc name="schedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1974/36/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1974/36"/>
              <FRBRalias value="Schedule"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1974/36/eng@1980-01-01/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1974/36/eng@1980-01-01"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1974/36/eng@1980-01-01/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1974/36/eng@1980-01-01"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-03-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="schedule">
            <paragraph id="schedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>(See Section 5)</p>
                <p>For purposes of payment of amount under section 5 the depreciation shall be calculated at annual rates arrived at by dividing ninety percent of the book value of each asset by the number of years of life of the asset as specified in the Table below. For the account year in which an asset was brought into beneficial use, the depreciation shall be calculated at half the annual rate and for the period after the last completed account year till the vesting date, the depreciation shall be calculated pro rata. Depreciation shall not be calculated for any period beyond the life of the asset as prescribed herein.</p>
                <p>TABLE</p>
                <table id="schedule.paragraph-0.table3">
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Description of assets</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Number of years or period</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>1</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>2</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Land owned under full title</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Infinite</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>B</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Land held under lease-</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>(a) for investment in the land</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The period of lease or the period remaining unexpired on the assignment of the lease.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>(b) for cost of clearing site</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The period of the lease remaining unexpired at the date of clearing the site.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>C</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Assets purchased new, -</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>(a) Building and Civil engineering works of a permanent character, not mentioned above -</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Fifty</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>(i) Offices and show rooms</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Five</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>(ii) Temporary erections such as wooden tructures</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Fifty</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>(iii) Others</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>(b) Transformer, transformer kiosk, sub-station equipment and other fixed apparatus (including plant foundations),-</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>(i) Transformers (including foundations) having a rating of 100 kilovolt amperes and over</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Thirty-five</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>(ii) Others</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Twenty-five</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>(c) Switchgear, including cable connections</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Twenty</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>(d) Batteries</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Ten</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>(e) (1) Underground cables, including joint boxes and disconnecting boxes</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Forty</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>(2) Cable duct system</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Sixty</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>(f) Overhead lines including supports -</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>(i) lines or steel or reinforced concrete supports operating at nominal voltages higher than 13.2 kilo volts</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Thirty</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>(ii) other lines on steel or reinforced concrete supports</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Twenty-five</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>(iii) Lines on wood supports</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Twenty</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>(g) Meters</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Fifteen</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>(h) Self-propelled vehicles</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Seven</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>(i) Station machine tools</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Twenty</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>(j) (i) Office furniture and fittings</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Twenty</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>(ii) Office equipment</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Ten</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>(k) Apparatus let on hire,-</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>(i) Other than Motors</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Seven</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>(ii) Motors</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Twenty</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>D</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Assets purchased second hand and assets not otherwise provided for in this table.</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Such reasonable period as the Government determine in each case having regard to the nature, age and condition of the asset at the time of its acquisition by the Government.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </table>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
