<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1963/26/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1963/26"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Karnataka Official Language Act, 1963"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1963/26/eng@2017-07-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1963/26/eng@2017-07-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-07-24" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1963/26/eng@2017-07-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1963/26/eng@2017-07-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-07-24" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Karnataka Offical Language Act, 1963</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[10th October 1963]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No. 26 of 1963</p>
        <p>Preamble—</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the adoption of Kannada as the language to be used for the official purposes of the State and for continuance of the use of English for transaction of business of the State Legis-lature.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the adoption of Kannada as the language to be used for official purposes of the State of Karnataka and for continuance of the use of English for transaction of business of the State Legislature after the expiration of the period of fifteen years from the com-mencement of the Constitution;</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>BE it enacted by the Karnataka State Legislature in the Fourteenth Year of the Republic of India as follows:—</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Karnataka Official Language Act, 1963.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extend to the whole of the State of Karnataka</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Kannada to be the official language of the State.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The official language of the State of Karnataka shall be Kannada.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>English to be continued to be used for official purposes until the Government otherwise directs.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything in section 2 and without prejudice to the provisions of Articles 346 and 347 of the Constitution, the English language shall continue to be used for all the official purposes of the State for which it was being used before the commencement of this Act until the State Government, by notification under section 4, otherwise directs in respect of any offi-cial purpose specified in such notification.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Government’s power to notify the official purposes for which Kannada to be used.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, from time to time, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that Kannada shall be used in respect of such official purposes and in such areas as may be spe-cified in the notification.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Language to be used in the legislature etc.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding the expiration of the period of fifteen years from the commencement of the Constitution, the English language may, as from the twenty-sixth day of January 1965, continue to be used, in addition to Kannada and Hindi for the transaction of business in the Legislature of the State.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Kannada Language may also be used,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in any Bill to be introduced or in amendments thereto to be moved in, or in any Act passed by, the Karnataka State Legislature; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in any Ordinance promulgated by the Governor of the State of Karnataka; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>in any order, rule, regulation or bye-law issued by the State Government under the Constitution or under any law made by the Parliament or the Karnataka State Legisla-ture.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5A">
        <num>5A.</num>
        <heading>Authorised Kannada translation of Central and State Acts.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5A.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>With effect from such date as the State Government may, by notification in the official Gazette, specify a translation in the Kannada language published under the authority of the Governor in the official Gazette,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5A.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>of any Central Act or of any Ordinance promulgated by the President with respect to any of the matters enumerated in List III of the Seventh Schedule to the Constitution or of any State Act or of any Ordinance or rules made by the Governor; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5A.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>of any order, rule, regulation or bye-law issued by the State Government or other authority or officer of the State Government under the Constitution or under any Central Act or any State Act or any other law in force in the State, shall be deemed to be the authoritative text thereof in the Kannada language.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Notifications issued under section 4 to be placed before the Legislature.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every notification issued under section 4, shall be laid as soon as may be after it is issued, be-fore each House of the State Legislature while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two successive sessions and if, before the expiry of the session in which it is so laid or the session immediately following, both Houses agree in making any modification in the notification or both Houses agree that the notification should not be issued, the notification shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however, that any modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that notification.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
