<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-utp/act/1948/11/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-utp/act/1948/11"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Uttar Pradesh Pradeshik Armed Constabulary Act, 1948"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-utp/act/1948/11/eng@2017-01-20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-utp/act/1948/11/eng@2017-01-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-20" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-utp/act/1948/11/eng@2017-01-20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-utp/act/1948/11/eng@2017-01-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-20" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Uttar Pradesh Pradeshik Armed Constabulary Act, 1948</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>(Act No. XI of 1948)</p>
        <p>An Act for the regulation of the Pradeshik Armed Constabulary</p>
        <p>Preamble —</p>
        <p>Whereas it is expedient to provide for the constitution and regulation of the United Provinces Armed Constabulary; it is hereby enacted as follows: -</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement, -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the United Provinces Pradeshik Armed Constabulary Act, 1948.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of Uttar Pradesh.</p>
            <table id="section-1.2.table1">
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p>Areas</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>Act or Orderunder which extended</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>Notification, if any, under which enforced</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>Date from which enforced</p>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p>1</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>2</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>3</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>4</p>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p>1. Rampur District</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>Rampur (Application of Laws) Act, 1950.</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p/>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>December 20, 1949.</p>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p>2. Banaras District</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>Banaras (Do.) Order, 1949</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>3261 (I) and (2), dated November</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>November 30, 1949</p>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p>3. Tehri-Garhwal District</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>Tehri-Garhwal (Do.) Order 1945</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>Ditto</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>Ditto</p>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p>4. Jaunsar- Bawar Pargana in Dehra Dun District</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>U.P. Act No. XXVII</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p/>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>September 2, 1950</p>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p>5. Portion of Mirzapur District south of the Kaimur Range</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>Ditto</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p/>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>Ditto</p>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </table>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force at once.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definition,-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context, -</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>"Commandant", "Assistant Commandant" and "Adjutant" mean persons appointed by the State Government to those offices of the Pradeshik Armed Constabulary;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>"Officer of the Pradeshik Armed Constabulary" means a person appointed to the Pradeshik Armed Constabulary under this Act, who has, in accordance with the provisions of this Act, signed a statement in the form given in the Schedule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The expressions "reason to believe", "criminal force" and "assault", have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Indian Penal Code.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>"Superior officer" means in relation to an officer of the Pradeshik Armed Constabulary any officer of a rank which as prescribed is higher than that of such officer.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>***</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>"prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of P. A. C. —</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>There shall be raised and maintained by the State Government a force to be called the Pradeshik Armed Constabulary and it shall be constituted in one or more companies in such manner and for such period as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Enrolment and discharge of officers of the Pradeshik Armed Constabulary (Act V of 1861). -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Before any person, whether already enrolled in Uttar Pradesh Police Force under Police Act, 1861, or not so enrolled is appointed to be an officer of the Pradeshik Armed Constabulary, the statement in the Schedule shall be read, and if necessary, explained to him by a Magistrate, Commandant or Assistant Commandant, shall be signed by him in acknowledgment of its having been so read and explained to him and shall be attested by the Magistrate, Commandant or assistant Commandant as the case may be</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Members of P.A.C. to be deemed Police officers. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Subject always to the provisions of sections 6 to 8 every member of the Pradeshik Armed Constabulary shall upon his appointment and as long as he continues to be a member thereof, be deemed to be a Police officer, and subject to any terms, conditions and restrictions, s may be prescribed, to have and be subject to, in so far as they are not inconsistent with this act or any rules made there under, all the powers, privileges, liabilities, penalties, punishments and protection as a Police Officer duly enrolled has or is subject to by virtue of the Police Act, 1861, or any other law for the time being in force, or any rules or regulations made there under.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>More heinous offences,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>An officer of the Pradeshik Armed Constabulary who-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>begins, excites, causes or joins in any mutiny or sedition, or being present at any mutiny or sedition does not use his utmost endeavors to suppress it , or knowing or having reason to believe in the existence of any mutiny or of any intention to mutiny' does not without delay give information thereof to his commanding or other superior other; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>uses or attempts to use criminal against or commits an assault on his other superior officer„ whether on or off duty; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>abandons or delivers up any post or guard which is committed to his charge or which it is his duty to defend; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>directly or indirectly holds correspondence with or assists or relieves any person in arms against or hostile to the Union or omits to disclose immediately to his commanding or other superior officer any such correspondence to his knowledge; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>deserts the service; shall, on convictions, be punished with imprisonment for life or with imprisonment for a term which may extend to fourteen years and shall also be liable to fine.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Less heinous offences, -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>An officer of Pradeshik Armed Constabulary who-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>strikes or assaults any sentry; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>being under arrest or in confinement, escapes from arrest or commitment; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>is grossly insubordinate or insolent to his superior officer in the execution of his office; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>strikes or maliciously ill-treats any officer of the Pradeshik Armed Constabulary subordinate to him in rank or position ; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>malingers or feigns or produce disease or infirmity in himself, or intentionally delays his cure, or aggravates his disease or infirmity; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>being a sentry sleeps while upon his post; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>quits his post guard, piquet, party or patrol without being regularly relieved or without leave;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall, on conviction, be punished with imprisonment for term which may extend to seven years or fine with or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Minor punishments,--</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Commandant and subject to the control of the Commandant, an Assistant Commandant or such other officer as may be prescribed, may, without formal trial, award to any officer of the Pradeshik Armed Constabulary of and below the rank of head constable, who is subject to authority, any of the following punishments for the commission of any offence against discipline which is not otherwise provided for in this Act or which, in the opinion of the Commandant, Assistant Commandant or officer, as the case may be, is not of a sufficiently serious nature to call for prosecution before a criminal court, that is to say.-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>Imprisonment in the quarter-guard, or such other place, as may be considered suitable for a term which may extend to twenty-eight days when the order is passed by a Commandant, or, to seven days when it is passed any other officer. Such imprisonment shall involve the forfeiture of all pay allowances for the period of imprisonment.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>Punishment—drill, extra guard, fatigue or other duty, not exceeding twenty-eight days, in duration, with or without confinement to the lines.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>Fine—not exceeding seven day's pay.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any of the punishments specified in sub-section (I) may be awarded separately or with any one or more of the orders; provided always that imprisonment and confinement to the lines shall not exceed twenty-eight consecutive days, and fine shall not be combined with imprisonment</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No appeal shall lie from an order passed under this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Discharge from Pradeshik Armed Constabulary,-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Police Act, 1861, or in any other law no officer of the Pradeshik Armed Constabulary shall be entitled to be discharged from the Pradeshik Armed Constabulary.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Reversion,-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Commandant or an assistant Commandant may notwithstanding anything contained in Section 9, at any time revert to Uttar Pradesh Police and officer of the Pradeshik Armed constabulary who has been seconded from the Police Force.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Place of imprisonment,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list0.I">
                <num>(I)</num>
                <p>A person sentenced under this Act to imprisonment for a period exceeding three months, shall notwithstanding anything contained in the Police Act, 1861, be deemed to have been dismissed from Uttar Pradesh Police Force and from the Pradeshik Armed Constabulary and shall be imprisoned in the nearest or such other jail as the State Government may, by general or special order direct.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A person sentenced under this Act to imprisonment for a period not exceeding three months may if the Commandant, or subject to the control, an Assistant Commandant, so directs, be confined in the quarter-guard or such other place as the Commandant, or Assistant Commandant may consider suitable.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Saving of prosecution under other laws,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in this Act shall prevent any person from being prosecuted under the Police Act, 1861 or under any order, or rule made under that Act or any other enactment for the time being in force for any act of omission publishable there under, or from being liable, if so prosecuted to any other or higher penalty than is provided for that act or omission by this Act:</p>
            <p>Provided that no person shall be punished twice for the same offence.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Disciplinary and other powers of Commandant and 2nd -in-Command of Uttar Pradesh Armed Constabulary otherwise than in respect of the Pradeshik Armed Constabulary,-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Subject to such rules as the State Government may make in this behalf a Commandant or Assistant Commandant shall have with respect to Police officers appointed to Uttar Pradesh Police Force under Police Act, 1861, who are not officers of the Pradeshik Armed Constabulary the same disciplinary powers as a Superintendent of Police of district has with respect to them under that Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Disbandment and reconstitution,-- Discharge of an officer, disbandment and reconstitution,--</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may by notification in the official Gazette disband or reconstitute the Pradeshik Armed Constabulary or any Company thereof</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whenever the Pradeshik Armed Constabulary or any Company thereof is disbanded or reconstituted under sub-section (1) it shall notwithstanding anything contained in this Act or any other enactment for the time being in force and subject to such conditions as may be prescribed, be lawful for the State Government with a view to such disbandment or reconstitution, to discharge any officer from the Pradeshik Armed Constabulary and if he is enrolled under the Police Act, 1861 and has not been confirmed from the Police Force also.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules,--</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-15.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing powers, the rules may provide for the following matters, that is to say-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>The number of companies to be constituted.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>The pay and other terms and conditions of service of officers of the Pradeshik Armed Constabulary</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>The manner in which and the persons who may be appointed to be officers of the Pradeshik Armed Constabulary.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>Any other matter which is to be or may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Repeal. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Special Armed Constabulary Act, 1942 as amended from time to time is hereby repealed:</p>
            <blockList id="section-16.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that (without prejudice to the general application of Sections 6 and 24 of the United Provinces General Clauses Act, 1901 with regard to the effect or repeals)-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any form, order, rule or direction made issued of given under the said Act and in force immediately before the commencement of this Act, shall, in so far as it applies to the Pradeshik Armed Constabulary and is not inconsistent with this Act continue in force as if it had been prescribed., made, issued or given under this Act and may be repealed, revoked, varied or amended accordingly;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any officer or person appointed to act or enrolled under or by virtue of the said Act in the Pradeshik Armed Constabulary shall continue and be deemed to have been appointed under or by virtue of this Act; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>Any statement executed by any member of the Special Armed Constabulary or the Pradeshik Armed Constabulary in accordance with Sections 3 and 13 of the said Act shall be so read and construed as if it had been executed under the corresponding provisions of this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-statement">
      <doc name="statement">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-utp/act/1948/11/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-utp/act/1948/11"/>
              <FRBRalias value="STATEMENT"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-utp/act/1948/11/eng@2017-01-20/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-utp/act/1948/11/eng@2017-01-20"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-utp/act/1948/11/eng@2017-01-20/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-utp/act/1948/11/eng@2017-01-20"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-01-20" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="statement">
            <heading>(See Sections 2,3 and 4)</heading>
            <paragraph id="statement.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>At no time during the period of your service in the Pradeshik Armed Constabulary you will be entitled to obtain your discharge at your own request. On the liquidation of the force or of the company in which you may, for the time being, be poised you will be discharge from the Pradeshik Armed Constabulary and unless you were already a confirmed member of Uttar Pradesh Police force before joining the Pradeshik Armed constabulary from Uttar Pradesh Police also, you will, however, be eligible for re-enlistment in Uttar Pradesh Police in the event of your continuing in Uttar Pradesh Police for your re-enlistment therein, your services in the Uttar Pradesh Pradeshik Armed Constabulary will count for promotion and pension in Uttar Pradesh Police.</p>
                <p>Signature of Police officer in acknowledgment of the above having been read over to him.</p>
                <p>Signed in my presence, after I had ascertained</p>
                <p>That ……………… understood the purport of what he signed.</p>
                <p>Magistrate, Commandant or Assistant Commandant</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
