<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1956/32/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1956/32"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Hindu Minority And Guardianship Act, 1956"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1956/32/eng@1956-08-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1956/32/eng@1956-08-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1956-08-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1956/32/eng@1956-08-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1956/32/eng@1956-08-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-11-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Hindu Minority And Guardianship Act, 1956</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and extent.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Hindu Minority and Guardianship Act, 1956.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir and applies also to Hindus domiciled in the territories to which this Act extends who are outside the said territories.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Act to be supplemental to Act 8 of 1890.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The provision of this Act shall be in addition to, and not, save as hereinafter expressly provided, in derogation of, the Guardian and Wards Act, 1890 (8 of 1890).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Application of the Act.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>This Act applies—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to any person who is a Hindu by religion in any of its forms or developments, including a Virashaiva, a Lingayat or a follower of the Brahmo, Prarthana or Arya Samaj,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to any person who is a Buddhist, Jaina or Sikh by religion, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to any other person domiciled in the territories to which this Act extends who is not a Muslim, Christian, Parsi or Jew by religion unless it is proved that any such person would not have been governed by the Hindu law or by any custom or usage as part of that law in respect of any of the matters dealt with herein if this Act had not been passed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list4">
              <listIntroduction>The following persons are Hindus, Buddhists, Jainas, or Sikhs by religion, as the case may be:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list4.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>any child, legitimate or illegitimate, both of whose parents are Hindus, Buddhist, Jainas or Sikhs by religion;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list4.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>any child, legitimate or illegitimate, one of whose parents is a Hindu, Buddhist, Jaina or Sikh by religion and who is brought up as a member of the tribe, community, group or family to which such parent belongs or belonged; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list4.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>any person who is a convert or re-convert to the Hindu, Buddhist, Jaina or Sikh religion.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), nothing contained in this Act shall apply to the members of any Scheduled Tribe within the meaning of clause (25) of Article 366 of the Constitution unless the Central Government, by notification in the Official Gazette, otherwise directs.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The expression “Hindu” in any provision of this Act shall be construed as if it included a person who, though not a Hindu by religion, is, nevertheless, a person to whom this Act applies by virtue of the provisions contained in this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“minor” means a person who has not completed the age of eighteen years;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>“guardian” means a person having the care of the person of a minor or of his property or of both his person and property, and includes—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>a natural guardian,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>a guardian appointed by the will of the minor’s father or mother,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>a guardian appointed or declared by a court, and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>a person empowered to act as such by or under any enactment relating to any court of wards;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“natural guardian” means any of the guardians mentioned in section 6.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Over-riding effect of Act.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Save as otherwise expressly provided in this Act,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any text, rule or interpretation of Hindu Law or any custom or usage as part of that law in force immediately before the commencement of this Act shall cease to have effect with respect to any matter for which provision contained in this Act.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any other law in force immediately before the commencement of this Act shall cease to have effect in so far as it is inconsistent with any of the provisions contained in this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Natural guardians of a Hindu minor.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The natural guardian of a Hindu minor, in respect of the minor’s person as well as in respect of the minor’s property (excluding his or her undivided interest in joint family property), are—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in the case of a boy or an unmarried girl—the father, and after him, the mother: provided that the custody of a minor who has not completed the age of five years shall ordinarily be with the mother;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in case of an illegitimate boy or an illegitimate unmarried girl—the mother, and after her, the father;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>in the case of a married girl—the husband:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that no person shall be entitled to act as the natural guardian of a minor under the provisions of this section—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>if he has ceased to be a Hindu, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>if he has completely and finally renounced the world by becoming a hermit (vanaprastha) or an ascetic (yati or sanyasi).</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <p>In this section, the expression “father” and “mother” do not include a step-father and a step-mother.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Natural guardianship of adopted son.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The natural guardianship of an adopted son who is a minor passes, on adoption, to the adoptive father and after him to the adoptive mother.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Powers of natural guardian.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The natural guardian of a Hindu minor has power, subject to the provisions of this section, to do all acts which are necessary or reasonable and proper for the benefit of the minor or for the realisation, protection or benefit of the minor’s estate; but the guardian can in no case bind the minor by a personal covenant.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The natural guardian shall not, without the previous permission of the court,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>mortgage or charge, or transfer by sale, gift, exchange or otherwise, any part of the immovable property of the minor; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>lease any part of such property for a term exceeding five years or for a term extending more than one year beyond the date on which the minor will attain majority.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any disposal of immovable property by a natural guardian, in contravention of sub-section (1) or sub-section (2), is voidable at the instance of the minor or by any person claiming under him.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No court shall grant permission to the natural guardian to do any of the acts mentioned in sub-section (2) except in the case of necessity or for an evident advantage to the minor.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.5.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Guardians and Wards Act, 1890 (8 of 1890), shall apply to and in respect of an application for obtaining permission of the court under sub-section (2) in all respects as if it were an application for obtaining the permission of the court under section 29 of that Act, and in particular—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.5.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>proceedings in connection with the application shall be deemed to be proceedings under that Act within the meaning of section 4A thereof;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.5.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the court shall observe the procedure and have the powers specified in sub-sections (2), (3) and (4) of section 31 of that Act; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.5.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>an appeal shall lie from an order of the court refusing permission to the natural guardian to do any of the acts mentioned in sub-section (2) of this section to the court to which appeals ordinarily lie from the decisions of that court.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In this section “court” means the city civil court or a district court or a court empowered under section 4A of the Guardian and Wards Act, 1890 (8 of 1890), within the local limits of whose jurisdiction the immovable property in respect of which the application is made is situate, and where the immovable property is situate within the jurisdiction of more than one such court, means the court within the local limits of whose jurisdiction any portion of the property is situate.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Testamentary guardians and their powers.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A Hindu father entitled to act as the natural guardian of his minor legitimate children, may, by will, appoint a guardian for any of them in respect of the minor’s person or in respect of the minor’s property (other than the undivided interest referred in section 12) or in respect of both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An appointment made under sub-section (1) shall have no effect if the father predeceases the mother, but shall revive if the mother dies without appointing by will, any person as guardian.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A Hindu widow entitled to act as the natural guardian of her minor legitimate children, and a Hindu mother entitled to act as the natural guardian of her minor legitimate children by reason of the fact that the father has become disentitled to act as such, may, by will, appoint a guardian for any of them in respect of the minor’s person or in respect of the minor’s property (other than the undivided interest referred to in section 12) or in respect of both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A Hindu mother entitled to act as the natural guardian of her minor legitimate children may, by will, appoint a guardian for any of them in respect of the minor’s person or in respect of the minor’s property or in respect of both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The guardian so appointed by will has the right to act as the minor’s guardian after the death of the minor’s father or mother, as the case may be, and to exercise all the rights of a natural guardian under this Act to such extent and subject to such restrictions, if any, as are specified in this Act and in the will.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The right of the guardian so appointed by will shall, where the minor is a girl, cease on her marriage.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Incapacity of minor to act as guardian of property.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A minor shall be incompetent to act as guardian of the property of any minor.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>De facto guardian not to deal with minor’s property.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>After the commencement of this Act, no person shall be entitled to dispose of, or deal with, the property of a Hindu minor merely on the ground of his or her being the de facto guardian of the minor.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Guardian not to be appointed for minor’s undivided interest in joint family property.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where a minor has an undivided interest in joint family property and the property is under the management of an adult member of the family, no guardian shall be appointed for the minor in respect of such undivided interest:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing in this section shall be deemed to affect the jurisdiction of a High Court to appoint a guardian in respect of such interest.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Welfare of minor to be paramount consideration.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the appointment or declaration of any person as guardian of a Hindu minor by a court, the welfare of the minor shall be the paramount consideration.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No person shall be entitled to the guardianship by virtue of the provisions of this Act or of any law relating to guardianship in marriage among Hindus, if the court is of opinion that his or her guardianship will not be for the welfare of the minor.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
