<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1956/36/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1956/36"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Andhra Pradesh (Telangana Area) Abolition Of Whipping Act, 1956"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1956/36/eng@2017-01-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1956/36/eng@2017-01-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-24" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1956/36/eng@2017-01-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1956/36/eng@2017-01-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-17" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Andhra Pradesh (Telangana Area) Abolition Of Whipping Act, 1956</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[Act No. 36 of 1956]</p>
      </longTitle>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[05th September, 1956]</docDate>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>An Act to provide for the abolition of whipping as a punishment by repealing the relevant provisions of the Hyderabad Penal Code, 1324 Fasli (V of 1324 Fasli) and amending the Andhra Pradesh (Telangana Area) Children Act, 1951 (Act XXXII of 1951).</p>
      <p>Be it enacted in the Seventh Year of Our Republic as follows:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Andhra Pradesh (Telangana Area) Abolition of Whipping Act, 1956.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the Telangana area of the State of Andhra Pradesh:</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force at once.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Repeal of the provisions of the Hyderabad Penal Code, 1324 Fasli (V of 1324 Fasli) relating to whipping</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of section 12 (so far as it prescribes whipping as a form of judicial punishment) and sections 21 to 23 (both inclusive) of the Hyderabad Penal Code, 1324 Fasli (V of 1324 Fasli) hereinafter in this section referred to as the said Code, are hereby repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If at the commencement of this Act any sentence of whipping imposed upon an offender by a Court under the aforesaid provisions of the said Code has not been executed for any reason, whether wholly or partly, the offender shall be dealt within the manner provided in section 395 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898, (Central Act V of 1898) as if that section had not been repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of the Andhra Pradesh (Telangana Area) Children Act, 1951</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the Andhra Pradesh (Telangana Area) Children Act, 1951 (Act XXXII of 1951) (hereinafter in this section referred to as the said Act) clause (b) of section 2 and clause (f) of sub-section (1) of section 29 shall be omitted.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If at the commencement of this Act any sentence of caning imposed upon an offender by a Court under clause (f) of sub-section (1) of section 29 of the said Act has not been executed for any reason, whether wholly or partly, the Court may, at its discretion, deal with the case in the manner provided in that section as if the said Clause (f) had never existed in sub-section (1) of that section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
