<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-sik/act/1988/3/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-sik/act/1988/3"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Sikkim Prevention of Defacement of Property Act, 1988"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-sik/act/1988/3/eng@2017-01-21/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-sik/act/1988/3/eng@2017-01-21"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-sik/act/1988/3/eng@2017-01-21/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-sik/act/1988/3/eng@2017-01-21"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Sikkim Prevention Of Defacement Of Property Act, 1988</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 3 OF 1988.</docNumber>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>AN ACT to provide for the prevention of defacement of property and matters connected therewith and incidental thereto.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>BE it enacted by the Legislative Assembly of Sikkim in the Thirty-ninth Year of the Republic of India as follows:—</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Sikkim Prevention of Defacement of Property Act, 1988.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Sikkim.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 15th day of December, 1987.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>‘defacement’ includes impairing or interfering with the appearances or beauty, damaging, disfiguring, spoiling or injuring in any other way whatsoever and the word “deface” be construed accordingly;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>‘property’ includes any building, hut, wall, tree, fence, pole or any other erection;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>‘Writing’ includes decoration, lettering ornamentation etc., produced by stencil.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for defacement of property.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever defaces any property in public view by writing or marking with ink, chalk, paint or any other material, except for the purpose of indicating the name and address of the owner or occupier of such property, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees of with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any offence committed under sub-section (1) is for the benefit of some other person or a company or other body corporate or an association of persons (whether incorporated or not), then such other person and every President, Chairman, Director, Partner, Manager, Secretary, Agent or any other officer or person concerned with the management therefore, as the case may be, shall unless he proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or consent, be deemed to guilty of such offence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Offences to be cognizable.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any offence punishable under this Act shall be a cognizable offence.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Power of State Government to erase writing etc.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Without prejudice to the provisions of section 3, it shall be competent for the State Government to take such steps as may be necessary for erasing any writing, freeing any defacement or removing any mark from any property.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Act to override other laws.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The provision of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in other law for the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Repeal and Saving.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Sikkim Prevention of Defacement of Property Ordinance, 1987 is hereby repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken in the exercise of the powers conferred by or under this Ordinance, shall be deemed to have been done or taken in exercise of the powers conferred by or under this Act, as if this Act was in force on the day on which such thing was done or such action was taken.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
