<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1932/23/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1932/23"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Criminal Law Amendment Act, 1932"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1932/23/eng@1932-12-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1932/23/eng@1932-12-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1932-12-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1932/23/eng@1932-12-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1932/23/eng@1932-12-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-10-05" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Criminal Law Amendment Act, 1932</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 19th December, 1932.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No. 23 of 1932</p>
        <p>An Act to supplement the criminal law.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to supplement the criminal law and to that end to amend the Indian Press (Emergency Powers) Act, 1931 (23 of 1931), and further to amend the Indian Criminal Law Amendment Act, 1908 (14 of 1908), for the purposes hereinafter appearing;</p>
        <p>It is hereby enacted as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent, duration and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Criminal Law Amendment Act, 1932.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India except the territories which, immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised in Part B States.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>***</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The whole of the Act except section 7 shall come into force at once, and the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette direct that section 7 shall come into force in any area on such date as may be specified in the notification.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Dissuasion from enlistment.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>***</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Tampering with public servants.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>***</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Boycotting a public servant.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>***</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Dissemination of contents of prescribed document.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever publishes, circulates or repeats in public any passage from a newspaper, book or other document copies whereof have been declared to be forfeited to Government under any law for the time being in force, shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No Court shall take cognizance of an offence punishable under this section unless the State Government has certified that the passage published, circulated or repeated contains, in the opinion of the State Government, seditious or other matter of the nature referred to in sub- section (1) of section 99A of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898) or sub- section (1) of section 4 of the Indian Press (Emergency, Powers) Act, 1931 (23 of 1931),</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Dissemination of false rumours.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>***</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Molesting a person to prejudice of employment or business.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Whoever —</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>with intent to cause any person to abstain from doing or to do any act which such person has a right to do or to abstain from doing, obstructs or uses violence to or intimidates such person or any member of his family or person in his employ, or loiters at or near a place where such person or member or employed person resides or works or carries on business or happens to be, or persistently follows him from place to place, or interferes with any property owned or used by him or deprives him of or hinders him in the use thereof,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-7.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.1.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>loiters or does any similar act at or near the place where a person carries on business, in such a way and with intent that any person may thereby be deterred from entering or approaching or dealing at such place,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, or with both.</p>
            <p>Explanation.— Encouragement of indigenous industries or advocacy of temperance, without the commission of any of the acts prohibited by this section is not an offence under this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No Court shall take cognizance of an offence punishable under this section except upon a report in writing of facts which constitute such offence made by a police-officer not below the rank of officer in charge of a police-station.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Power to order parent or guardian to pay line imposed on young person.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>***</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Procedure in offences under the Act.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898),</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>no Court inferior to that of a Presidency Magistrate or Magistrate of the first class shall try any offence under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>an offence punishable under sections 5 or 7 shall be cognizable by the police;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>***</p>
            <blockList id="section-9.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list4.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>an offence punishable under section 7 shall be non-bailable.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Power of State Government to make certain offences cognizable and non-bailable.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare that any offence punishable under section 186, 188, 189, 190, 228, 295A, 298, 505, 506 or 507 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860), when committed in any area specified in the notification shall, notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898), be cognizable, and thereupon the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898), shall, while such notification remains in force, be deemed to be amended accordingly.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, in like manner and subject to the like conditions, and with the like effect, declare that an offence punishable under section 188 or section 506 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860) shall be non- bailable.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of s. 16, Act 14 of 1908.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>***</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of s. 17, Act 14 of 1908.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>***</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Insertion of new ss. 17A to 17F in Act 14 of 1908.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>***</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of title and preamble of Act 23 of 1931.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>***</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of s. 1, Act 23 of 1931.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>***</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of s. 4, Act 23 of 1931.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>***</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Cessation of effect of s. 62, Ordinance 10 of 1932.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>***</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Adoption and continuance of action taken under Ordinance 10 of 1932.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Anything done or any proceedings commenced in pursuance of the provisions of Chapter VI of the Special Powers Ordinance, 1932(10 of 1932), shall, upon the commencement of this Act, be deemed to have been done or to have been commenced in pursuance of the corresponding provisions of the Indian Criminal Law Amendment Act, 1908 (45 of 1908), as amended by this Act, and shall have effect as if this Act was already in force when such thing was done or such proceedings were commenced.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Adoption and continuance of action taken under Act 23 of 1931. as amended by Ordinance 10 of 1932.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Anything done or any proceedings commenced in pursuance of the provisions of the Indian Press (Emergency Powers) Act, 1931 (23 of 1931), as amended by section 77 of the Special Powers Ordinance, 1932 (10 of 1932), shall, upon the commencement of this Act, be deemed to have been done or to have been commenced in pursuance of the corresponding provisions of the Indian Press (Emergency Powers) Act, 1931, as amended by this Act, and shall have effect as if this Act was already in force when such thing was done or such proceedings were commenced.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Trial of, and completion of trials of, offences against Ordinance 10 of 1932.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>***</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
