<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-jnk/act/1994/4/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-jnk/act/1994/4"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Identification of Prisoners Act, Svt. 1994 [Jammu and Kashmir]"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-jnk/act/1994/4/eng@2017-01-16/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-jnk/act/1994/4/eng@2017-01-16"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-16" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-jnk/act/1994/4/eng@2017-01-16/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-jnk/act/1994/4/eng@2017-01-16"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-16" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Identification Of Prisoners Act, 1994 (1937 A.D.)</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[Act. No. 4 of 1994]</p>
      </longTitle>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[8th Assuj, 1994]</docDate>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to authorise the taking of measurements and photographs of convicts and others;</p>
      <p>It is hereby enacted as follows:-</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and extent</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-1.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list0.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>This Act may be called the Identification of Prisoners Act No. IV of 1994.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list0.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>It extends to the whole of Jammu and Kashmir State.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"measurements" includes finger impressions and foot print impressions;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"Police officer" means an officer in charge of a Police station, a Police officer making an investigation under Chapter XIV of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1989, or any other Police officer not below the rank of Sub-Inspector; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>"prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Taking of measurements, etc., of convicted persons</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Every person who has been-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>convicted of any offence punishable with rigorous imprisonment for a term of one year or upwards, or of any offence which would render him liable to enhanced punishment on a subsequent conviction, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>ordered to give security for his good behavior under section 118 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1989, shall, if so required, allow his measurements and photograph to be taken by a Police officer in the prescribed manner.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Taking of measurements, etc., of non-convicted persons</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any person who has been arrested in connection with an offence punishable with rigorous imprisonment for a term of one year or upwards shall, if so required by a Police officer, allow his measurements to be taken in the prescribed manner.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Power of Magistrate to order a person to be measured or photographed</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If a Magistrate is satisfied that, for the purposes of any investigation or proceeding under the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1989, it is expedient to direct any person to allow his measurements or photograph to be taken, he may make an order to that effect, and in that case the person to whom the order relates shall be produced or shall attend at the time and place specified in the order and shall allow his measurements or photograph to be taken, as the case may be, by a Police officer:</p>
            <p>Provided that, no order shall be made directing any person to be photographed except by a Magistrate of the first class:</p>
            <p>Provided further that, no order shall be made under this section unless the person has at some time been arrested in connection with such investigation or proceeding.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Resistance to the taking of measurements, etc</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person who under this Act is required to allow his measurements or photograph to be taken resists or refuses to allow the taking of the same, it shall be lawful with permission of a Magistrate to use all means necessary to secure the taking thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Resistance to or refusal to allow the taking of measurements or photographs under this Act shall be deemed to be an offence under section 186 of the Ranbir Penal Code.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Destruction of photographs and records of measurements, etc., on acquittal</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where any person who, not having been previously convicted of an offence punishable with rigorous imprisonment for a term of one year or upwards, has had his measurements taken or has been photographed in accordance with the provisions of this Act is released without trial or discharged or acquitted by any Court, all measurements and all photographs (both negatives and copies) so taken shall, unless the Court or (in a case where such person is released without trial) the District Magistrate for reasons to be recorded in writing otherwise directs, be destroyed or made over to him.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may make rules for the purpose of carrying into effect the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing provisions, such rules may provide for-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>restrictions on the taking of photographs of persons under section 5;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the place at which measurements and photographs may be taken;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the nature of the measurements that may be taken;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the method in which any class or classes of measurements shall be taken;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the dress to be worn by a person when being photographed under section 3; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the preservation, safe custody, destruction and disposal of records of measurements and photographs.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Bar of suits</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit or other proceeding shall lie against any person for anything done or intended to be done, in good faith under this Act or under any rule made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
