<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1984/03/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1984/03"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Prevention Of Damage To Public Property Act, 1984"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1984/03/eng@1984-03-16/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1984/03/eng@1984-03-16"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1984-03-16" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1984/03/eng@1984-03-16/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1984/03/eng@1984-03-16"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Prevention Of Damage To Public Property Act, 1984</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[16th March, 1984.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for prevention of damage to public property and for matters connected therewith.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty-fifth Year of the Republic of India as follows:—</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Prevention of Damage to Public Property Act, 1984.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 28th day of January, 1984.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“mischief” shall have the same meaning as in section 425 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>“public property” means any property, whether immovable or movable (including any machinery) which is owned by, or in the possession of, or under the control of—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>the Central Government; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>any State Government; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>any local authority; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>any corporation established by, or under, a Central, Provincial or State Act; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.v">
                    <num>(v)</num>
                    <p>any company as defined in section 617 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956); or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.vi">
                    <num>(vi)</num>
                    <p>any institution, concern or undertaking which the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf:</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that the Central Government shall not specify any institution, concern or undertaking under this sub-clause unless such institution, concern or undertaking is financed wholly or substantially by funds provided directly or indirectly by the Central Government or by one or more State Governments, or partly by the Central Government and partly by one or more State Governments.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Mischief causing damage to public property.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever commits mischief by doing any act in respect of any public property, other than public property of the nature referred to in sub-section (2), shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years and with fine.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Whoever commits mischief by doing any act in respect of any public property being—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any building, installation or other property used in connection with the production, distribution or supply of water, light, power or energy;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any oil installations;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any sewage works;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>any mine or factory;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>any means of public transportation or of tele-communications, or any building, installation or other property used in connection therewith,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall be punished with rigorous imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than six months, but which may extend to five years and with fine:</p>
            <p>Provided that the court may, for reasons to be recorded in its judgment, award a sentence of imprisonment for a term of less than six months.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Mischief causing damage to public property by fire or explosive substance.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever commits an offence under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) of section 3 by fire or explosive substance shall be punished with rigorous imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than one year, but which may extend to ten years and with fine:</p>
            <p>Provided that the court may, for special reasons to be recorded in its judgment, award a sentence of imprisonment for a term of less than one year.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Special provisions regarding bail.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No person accused or convicted of an offence punishable under section 3 or section 4 shall, if in custody, be released on bail or on his own bond unless the prosecution has been given an opportunity to oppose the application for such release.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Saving.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of this Act shall be in addition to, and not in derogation of, the provisions of any other law for the time being in force, and nothing contained in this Act shall exempt any person from any proceeding (whether by way of investigation or otherwise) which might apart from this Act, be instituted or taken against him.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Repeal and saving.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Prevention of Damage to Public Property Ordinance, 1984 (Ord. 3 of 1984), is hereby repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
