<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-goa/act/2013/24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-goa/act/2013/24"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Goa Medicare Service Personnel and Medicare Service Institutions (Prevention  of Violence and Damage or Loss to Property) Act, 2013"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-goa/act/2013/24/eng@2013-11-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-goa/act/2013/24/eng@2013-11-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2013-11-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-goa/act/2013/24/eng@2013-11-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-goa/act/2013/24/eng@2013-11-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-02" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Goa Medicare Service Personnel And Medicare Service Institutions (Prevention Of Violence And Damage Or Loss To Property) Act, 2013</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[Act No. 24 of 2013]</p>
      </longTitle>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[25th November 2013]</docDate>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>AN</p>
      <p>ACT</p>
      <p>to provide for the prevention of violence against Medicare Service Personnel and prevention of damage or loss to property of Medicare Service Institutions in the State of Goa and for matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.</p>
      <p>Be it enacted by the Legislative Assembly of Goa in the Sixty-fourth Year of the Republic of India, as follows:—</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Goa Medicare Service Personnel and Medicare Service Institutions (Prevention of Violence and Damage or Loss to Property) Act, 2013.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall extend to the whole of the State of Goa.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“Government” means the Government of Goa;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>“Medicare Service Institution” means,—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>a hospital, maternity home, nursing home, dispensary, clinic, sanatorium or an organization or an institution by whatever name called that provides services in any recognized system of medicine and having facilities requiring diagnosis and/or treatment or care for illness, injury, deformity, abnormality, pregnancy or first aid, emergency medical services or any other medical services, either within its premises or through mobile medical unit or medical checkup camps or otherwise, or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>a place established as an independent entity or part of an institution referred to in sub-clause (i), in connection with the diagnosis and treatment of diseases where pathological, bacteriological, genetic, radiological, chemical, biological investigations or other diagnostic or investigative services with the aid of laboratory or other medical equipment, are usually carried on, owned, controlled or managed by,—</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the Central, or State Government; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>a trust, whether public or private; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>a corporation (including a society) registered under a Central, or State Act, whether owned by the Central, or State Government or not; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>a local authority; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>a medical practitioner.;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>“Medicare Service Personnel”, in relation to a Medicare Service Institution, shall include,—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>registered medical practitioner;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>registered nurses, nursing aids, mid-wives;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>Medical Students;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>Nursing Students; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.v">
                    <num>(v)</num>
                    <p>para-medical workers, ambulance service providers, and diagnostic services providers;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.vi">
                    <num>(vi)</num>
                    <p>any other personnel who are working in the medicare service institution for the purpose of training, studies etc.;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>“medical student” means a student, who is undergoing training or studies in medical profession;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>“mobile medical unit” means an ambulance equipped with medical equipment, used for providing medicare services;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>“nursing student” means a student, who is undergoing training or studies in nursing profession;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>“offender” means any person, who either by himself or as a member or leader of a group of persons or organization commits or attempts to commit or abets or incites the commission of violence;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>“para-medical worker” means a person, who assists the Medicare Service Personnel for providing medicare services;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>“property” means any property, movable or immovable or medical equipment or medical machinery owned by or in possession of, or under the control of any Medicare Service Personnel or Medicare Service Institution;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>“section” means section of this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>“violence” means an act, which causes or may cause any harm, injury or intimidation or obstruction or hindrance to or endangers the life of any Medicare Service Personnel while discharging his duty in a Medicare Service Institution or which causes damage or loss to the property in a Medicare Service Institution.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition of Violence.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any act of violence against a medicare service personnel or damage or loss to property in a Medicare Service Institution is hereby prohibited.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Punishment for attempt to commit violence.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever commits violence or abets or incites the commission of violence against medicare service personnel or causes damage or loss to the property of Medicare Service Institution shall, upon conviction be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years, or with fine which may extend to fifty thousand rupees or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Offence to be cognizable and non-bailable.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any offence punishable under this Act shall be cognizable and non-bailable.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Recovery of loss for the damage caused to the property.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In addition to the punishment specified in section 4, the offender shall be liable to pay compensation of twice the amount of purchase price of medical equipment damaged and loss caused to the property as determined by the Court trying the offender.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the offender has not paid the compensation imposed under sub-section (1), the same sum shall be recovered as if it were arrears of land revenue, due from him.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any person who is convicted under section 4 of this Act shall deposit such sum of money as specified below, with the Court of the Judicial Magistrate First Class. This sum shall remain with the Court until disposal of the case,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.3.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>in the event of an assault on any Medicare Service Personnel resulting in a simple injury not requiring absence from duty, Rs. 50,000.00;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.3.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>in the event of an assault on any Medicare Service Personnel resulting in a simple injury requiring a period of absence from duty, Rs. 75,000.00;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.3.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>in the event of an assault on any Medicare Service Personnel resulting in grievous injury, requiring a period of absence from duty Rs. 1,00,000.00.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the event the accused is found not guilty by the Court of the Judicial Magistrate First class, the sum deposited with the Court under sub-section (3) of section 6 above shall be returned to the person.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the accused is found guilty then this sum shall be adjusted against any fines, penalties imposed by the court of the Judicial Magistrate.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Committee to aid and advise victims of medical negligence.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute the Committee to hear grievances of victims of medical negligence or mismanagement and to aid and advise such victims for taking recourse to an appropriate forum for suitable relief.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Committee shall consist of experts one each from the field of medical, law, consumer movement and health management.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The conditions of service of the experts mentioned in sub-section (2), and the procedure to be followed by the Committee shall be such as may be specified by the Government by an order in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Provision of this Act to be in addition to any other law for the time being in force.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in this Act shall be deemed to affect the operation of any other law and the rules made thereunder and the provisions of this Act shall be in addition to and not in derogation of the provisions of such other law and rules made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
