<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-tmn/act/1993/17/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-tmn/act/1993/17"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Tamil Nadu Special Security Group Act, 1993"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-tmn/act/1993/17/eng@1993-05-17/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-tmn/act/1993/17/eng@1993-05-17"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1993-05-17" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-tmn/act/1993/17/eng@1993-05-17/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-tmn/act/1993/17/eng@1993-05-17"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-12-20" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Tamil Nadu Special Security Group Act, 1993</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[17th May, 1993]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No. 17 of 1993</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the constitution and regulation of a separate security force in the State of Tamil Nadu for providing proximate security to the Chief Minister of Tamil Nadu and the former Chief Ministers of Tamil Nadu and members of their immediate family and for matters connected therewith.</p>
      </longTitle>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by the Legislative Assembly of the State of Tamil Nadu in the Forty-fourth Year of the Republic of India as follows:—</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Tamil Nadu Special Security Group Act, 1993.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Government may, by notification, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"active duty” in relation to a member of the Group means any duty as such member during the period when he is posted to physically protect the Chief Minister of Tamil Nadu and the members of his immediate family or a former Chief Minister of Tamil Nadu and the members of his immediate family, or any class of persons referred to in clause (c) of sub-section (1) of section 4, wherever he or they may be;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"Director” means the Director of the Group appointed under sub-section (1) of section 5;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>"Government” means the State Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>"Group”means the Tamil Nadu Special Security Group constituted under section 4;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>"member of the Group” means a person who has been appointed to the Group by the prescribed authority;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>"members of immediate family” means wife, husband, children and parents;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>"proximate security” means protection provided from close quarters, during journey by road, rail, aircraft, watercraft or on foot or any other means of transport and shall include the places of functions, engagements, residence or halt and shall comprise ring round teams, isolation cordons, the sterile zone around, convoy security and the rostrum and access control to the person or members of his immediate family;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>all words and expressions used and not defined in this Act but defined in the Indian Penal Code shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in that Code (Central Act XLV of 1860).</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Members subject to this Act.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every member of the Group shall be subject to this Act , wherever he may be.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of the Group.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>There shall be a separate security force in the State of Tamil Nadu called the Tamil Nadu Special Security Group for providing proximate security to—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the Chief Minister of Tamil Nadu and the members of his immediate family;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any former Chief Minister of Tamil Nadu or to the members of his immediate family; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any such class of persons and for such period as the Government may, by Notification, specify:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that any former Chief Minister or any member of the immediate family of the Chief Minister or of a former Chief Minister may decline such proximate security.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act , the Group shall be constituted in such manner as may be prescribed and the terms and conditions of service of the members of the Group shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, any person or any member of any other Police force of the State of Tamil Nadu may be appointed to the Group by the Government, by a general or special order, and for such period as may be specified in such order and the person so appointed shall, during the period of his appointment, be deemed to be a member of the Group, and the provisions of this Act shall, so far as may be, apply to such person or member.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Control, direction, etc.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The general superintendence, direction and control of the Group shall vest in, and be exercised by, the Government and subject thereto and to the provisions of this Act and the rules, the command and supervision of the Group shall vest in an officer to be appointed by the Government as the Director of the Group:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Government may, by general or special order, delegate all or any of their powers under this sub-section, to such officer or authority as may be specified in such order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Director shall, in the discharge of his duties under this Act, be assisted by such number of Deputy Directors, Assistant Directors and other officers as may be appointed by the Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The scale and level of proximate security shall be such as may be determined by the Director.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Liability for service in any part of State of Tamil Nadu and elsewhere.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every member of the Group shall be liable to serve in any part of the State of Tamil Nadu or in any other part of India as well as outside India.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Members of the Group always on active duty.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every member of the Group, not on leave or under suspension, shall, for all purposes of this Act , be always on active duty and may, at any time, be employed or deployed in any manner which is consistent with the duties and responsibilities of the Group under this Act .</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Resignation and withdrawal from the Post.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>No member of the Group shall be at liberty—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to resign his appointment during the term of his engagement; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to withdraw himself from all or any of the duties of his appointment, except with the previous permission in writing of the prescribed authority.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Tenure of service.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every member of the Group shall hold office during the pleasure of the Governor.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Restrictions respecting right to form associations, freedom of speech, etc.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>No member of the Group shall, without the previous sanction, in writing, of the Government or of the prescribed authority,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>be a member of, or be associated in any way with, any trade union, labour union, political association or with any class of trade unions, labour unions or political associations; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>be a member of, or be associated in any way with, any society, institution association or organisation that is not of a purely social, recreational or religious nature; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>communicate with the press or publish or cause to be published any book, letter or other document except where such communication or publication is in the bona fide discharge of his duties or is of a purely literary, artistic or scientific character or is of a prescribed nature.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Explanation.—If any question arises as to whether any society, institution, association or organisation is of a purely social, recreational or religious nature under clause (b) or whether any book, letter or document is a communication or publication in the bona fide discharge of his duties or is of a purely literary artistic or scientific character or is of a prescribed nature under clause (c), the decision of the Government thereon shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No member of the Group shall participate in, or address, any meeting or take part in any demonstration organised by anybody of persons for any political purposes or for such other purposes as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Termination of service.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The prescribed authority may, by order in writing, terminate the appointment of any member of the Group in the public interest and such termination shall be deemed to be discharge simpliciter and shall not amount to dismissal or removal.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Appeal.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any member of the Group aggrieved by an order under section 11 may, within thirty days from the date of such order, prefer an appeal to a Board to be constituted by the Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall consist of such persons as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The decision of the Board shall be final and shall not be called in question in any court or tribunal.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall have power to regulate its own procedure.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Powers and duties conferrable on members of the Group.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by general or special order published in the Tamil Nadu Government Gazette, direct that, subject to such conditions and limitations as may be specified in that order, any member of the Group may exercise or discharge such powers or duties as may be specified in the said order for giving effect to the provisions of this Act .</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Assistance to Group.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>It shall be the duty of every Department in the Government or every Department under the control of the Government or every local or other authority to act , in aid of the Director or any member of the Group whenever called upon to do so in furtherance of the duties and responsibilities assigned to such Director or member.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken under this Act .—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Group or any member thereof on whom powers have been conferred or duties have been imposed under this Act or any order issued or any rule made thereunder for anything which is in good faith done or purported to be done or omitted to be done in pursuance of this Act or any order issued or any rule made thereunder or any order issued under any such rule.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-16.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may make rules for carrying out all or any of the purposes of this Act .</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-16.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the manner in which the Group shall be constituted and the terms and conditions of service of its members under sub-section (2) of section 4;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the authorities to be prescribed under section 8, sub-section (1) of section 10 and section 11;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the nature of the communication or publication under clause (c) of sub-section (1) of section 10;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the purposes, other than political purposes, for which a person subject to this Act shall not participate in, or address, any meeting or take part in any demonstration under sub-section (2) of section 10;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the persons who shall be members of the Board under sub-section (2) of section 12;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>any other matter which is required to be, or may be, prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-16.3.list0">
              <item id="section-16.3.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>All rules made under this Act , shall be published in the Tamil Nadu Government Gazette and, unless they are expressed to come into force on a particular day shall come into force on the day on which they are so published.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.3.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>All notifications issued under this Act shall, unless they are expressed to come into force on a particular day, come into force on the day on which they are published.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made or notification issued under this Act or every order issued under section 13 shall, as soon as possible after it is made or issued, be placed on the table of the Legislative Assembly, and if before the expiry of the session in which it is so placed or the next session, the Assembly makes any modification in any such rule, notification or order or the Assembly decides that the rule, notification or order should not be made or issued, the rule, notification or order shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form, or be of no effect, as the case may be, so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule notification or order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
