<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1981/28/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1981/28"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Export-Import Bank Of India Act, 1981"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1981/28/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1981/28/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1981/28/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1981/28/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-06-08" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Export-Import Bank Of India Act, 1981</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[11th September, 1981.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 28 OF 1981</docNumber>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to establish a corporation to be known as the Export-Import Bank of India for providing financial assistance to exporters and importers, and for functioning as the principal financial institution for co-ordinating the working of institutions engaged in financing export and import of goods and services with a view to promoting the country’s international trade and for matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty-second Year of the Republic of India as follows:—</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Export-Import Bank of India Act, 1981.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force no such date1 as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint, and different dates may be appointed for different provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“Board” means the Board of Directors of the Exim Bank referred to in section 6;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“Development Bank” means the Industrial Development Bank of India established under the Industrial Development Bank of India Act, 1964 (18 of 1964);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“Exim Bank” means the Export-Import Bank of India established under section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>“export” and “import” mean respectively, export from or import into India or any other country of goods or services, or both;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>“goods” includes all materials, commodities and articles in a solid, liquid or gaseous state and all forms of energy;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>“notification” means a notification published in the Official Gazette;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>“prescribed” means prescribed by regulations made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>“Reserve Bank” means the Reserve Bank of India constituted under the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>“scheduled bank” means a bank, for the time being, included in the Second Schedule to the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.j.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>“services” includes,—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.j.list0.I">
                    <num>(I)</num>
                    <p>providing personnel (including skilled or unskilled workmen and persons for rendering technical or other services) for the purposes of any work or project (by whatever name called) or any activity;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.j.list0.II">
                    <num>(II)</num>
                    <p>transferring of technology, including transferring, or securing the transfer of rights, knowhow, expertises or other skill with respect to any patent, invention, model, design, secret formula or process or similar property;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.j.list0.III">
                    <num>(III)</num>
                    <p>furnishing any information, blueprints, plans, or advice with respect to any matter; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.j.list0.IV">
                    <num>(IV)</num>
                    <p>making available any other resources.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Establishment and incorporation of Export-Import Bank of India.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>With effect from such date1 as the Central Government may, by notification, appoint, there shall be established for the purposes of this Act a corporation to be known as the Export-Import Bank of India.—</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>With effect from such date1 as the Central Government may, by notification, appoint, there shall be established for the purposes of this Act a corporation to be known as the Export-Import Bank of India."</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Exim Bank shall be a body corporate with the name aforesaid having perpetual succession and a common seal with power, subject to the provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of property and to contract, and may, by that name, sue or be sued.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The head office of the Exim Bank shall be at Bombay or at such other place as the Central Government may, by notification, specify.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Exim Bank may establish offices, branches or agencies at such plances in or outside India as it may consider necessary.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Authorised capital.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The authorised capital of the Exim Bank shall be ten thousand crores of rupees:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Central Government may, by notification, increase the said capital up to an amount that it may deem necessary from time to time.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The issued capital of the Exim Bank shall be wholly subscribed by the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Management.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The general superintendence, direction and management of the affairs and business of the Exim Bank shall vest in the Board, which may exercise all powers and do all acts and things which may be exercised or done by the Exim Bank.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Save as otherwise provided in the regulations made under this Act,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the chairman, if he is a whole-time director or if he is holding offices both as the chairman and the managing director, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the managing director, if the chairman is not a whole-time director, or, if the chairman being a whole-time director, is absent,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall also have powers of general superintendence, direction and management of the affairs and business of the Exim Bank and may also exercise all powers and do all acts and things which may be exercised or done by the Exim Bank.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Board in discharging its functions shall act on business principles with due regard to public interest.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the discharge of its functions under this Act, the Exim Bank shall be guided by such directions in matters of policy involving public interest as the Central Government may give to it in writing.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of Board.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Board of Directors of the Exim Bank shall consist of the following, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>a chairman and a managing director appointed by the Central Government:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-6.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that the same person may be appointed to function both as chairman and as managing director;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.1.list3.aa">
                <num>(aa)</num>
                <p>two whole-time directors appointed by the Central Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>one director nominated by the Reserve Bank;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>one director nominated by the Development Bank;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>one director nominated by the Export Credit and Guarantee Corporation Limited, being a Government Company within the meaning of section 617 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>not more than twelve directors nominated by the Central Government of whom—</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list3.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>five directors shall be officials of the Central Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list3.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>not more than three directors shall be from the scheduled banks;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list3.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>not more than four directors shall be persons who have special knowledge of, or professional experience in, export or import or financing thereof.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The chairman and the managing director or the whole-time director shall hold office for such term, not exceeding five years, as the Central Government may specify in this behalf and any person so appointed shall be eligible for re-appointment.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), the Central Government shall have the right to terminate the term of office of the chairman or the managing director or the whole-time director, as the case may be, at any time before the expiry of the term specified under sub-section (2), by giving him notice of not less than three months in writing or three months’ salary and allowances in lieu thereof, and the chairman or the managing director, as the case may be, shall also have the right to relinquish his office at any time before the expiry of the term specified under sub-section (2) by giving to the Central Government notice of not less than three months in writing or three months’ salary and allowances in lieu thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The chairman and the managing director shall receive such salary and allowances as may be determined by the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, at any time, remove the chairman or the managing director or the whole-time director, as the case may be, from office:</p>
            <p>Provided that no person shall be removed from his office under this sub-section unless he has been given an opportunity of showing cause against his removal.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions contained in sub-section (7), any director nominated under clause (b) or clause (c) or clause (d) or clause (e) of sub-section (1) and not being an official of Government or not being a whole-time director or official of the Reserve Bank or the Development Bank or the said Export Credit and Guarantee Corporation Limited or a scheduled bank, shall hold office for such term, not exceeding three years, as the Central Government or, as the case may be, the authority nominating him, may specify in this behalf, and shall be eligible for re-nomination:</p>
            <p>Provided that no such director shall hold office continuously for a period exceeding six years.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any director nominated under this section shall hold office during the pleasure of the authority nominating him.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall meet at such times and places and shall observe such rules of procedure in regard to the transaction of business of its meetings as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The chairman or, if for any reason he is unable to attend a meeting of the Board, the managing director or the whole-time director or, in the event of both the chairman and the managing director or the whole-time director being unable to attend a meeting, any other director nominated by the chairman in this behalf and in the absence of such nomination any director elected by the directors present from among themselves, shall preside at the meeting.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.10">
          <num>(10)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All questions which come up before any meeting of the Board shall be decided by a majority of votes of the directors present and voting, and in the event of an equality of votes, the chairman, or in his absence, the managing director or the whole-time director, or in the absence of both the chairman and the managing director or the whole-time director, the person presiding, shall have and exercise a second or casting vote.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Save as otherwise provided in sub-section (10), every director of the Board shall have one vote.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Committees.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board may constitute such Committees whether consisting wholly of directors or wholly of other persons or partly of directors and partly of other persons for such purpose or purposes as it may think fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any Committee constituted under sub-section (1) shall meet at such times and places and shall observe such rules of procedure in regard to the transaction of business at its meetings as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Fees and allowances of directors and members of Committees.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The directors and the members of a Committee shall be paid such fees and allowances as may be prescribed for attending the meetings of the Board or of any Committee constituted in pursuance of this Act and for attending to any other work of the Exim Bank:</p>
            <p>Provided that no fees shall be payable to the chairman, if he is appointed as a whole-time chairman, or to the managing director or to any other director or member who is an official of the Government, the Reserve Bank or the Development Bank.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Disqualifications.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>No person shall be a director of the Board constituted under this Act, who—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>is, or at any time has been, adjudged insolvent, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>is of unsound mind and has been so declared by a competent court, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>is, or has been, convicted of an offence which, in the opinion of the Central Government, involves moral turpitude, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>has, in the opinion of the Central Government, so abused his position as a director, as to render his continuance on the Board detrimental to the interests of the general public, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>has been, for any reason, removed from the Board.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Business of Exim Bank.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Exim Bank may grant in or outside India loans and advances by itself or in participation with any bank or financial institution whether in or outside India for the purposes of export or import and shall also function as the principal financial institution for co-ordinating the working of institutions engaged in financing of the export and import in such manner as it may deem appropriate.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Exim Bank may also carry on and transact all or any of the following kinds of business, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>granting loans and advances to a scheduled bank or any other bank or financial institution notified in the Official Gazette by the Central Government in this behalf by way of refinance of loans and advances granted by it for purposes of export or import;.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>underwriting the issue of stocks, shares, bonds or debentures of any company engaged in export or import;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>issuing bid bonds or guarantees in or outside India by itself or in participation with any Government, bank or financial institution in or outside India;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>accepting, collecting, discounting, re-discounting, purchasing, selling or negotiating in or outside India, bills of exchange or promissory notes arising out of transactions relating to export or import and granting of loans and advances in or outside India against such bills or promissory notes;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>granting, opening, issuing, confirming or endorsing letters of credit and negotiating or collecting bills and other documents drawn thereunder;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>undertaking any transaction involving a combination of government to government and commercial credit for purposes of export or import;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>granting lines of credit to the government of any foreign State or any financial institution or person outside India for purposes of export or import;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>granting loans and advances outside India for any Indian joint venture;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>granting loans and advances to any person in India in connection with his equity contribution in any joint venture in any country outside India;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>financing export or import of machinery and equipment on lease basis;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>subscribing to, or investing in, or purchasing of, stocks, shares, bonds or debentures of any development bank or Export-Import Bank of any country outside India;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>buying or selling of, or entering into such other dealings in, foreign exchange, as may be necessary for the discharge of its functions;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>opening of any account in any bank in or outside India or the making of any agency arrangement with, or acting as an agent or correspondent of, any bank or other institution in or outside India;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>transferring, for consideration, any instrument relating to loans and advances granted by it;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>issuing participation certificates;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.p">
                <num>(p)</num>
                <p>subscribing to, or investing in, or purchasing of stocks, shares, bonds or debentures to the extent necessary for the enforcement of a lien, pledge or other contractual right;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.q">
                <num>(q)</num>
                <p>undertaking and financing of research, surveys, techno-economic or any other study in connection with the promotion and development of international trade;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.r">
                <num>(r)</num>
                <p>providing technical, administrative and financial assistance of any kind for export or import;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.s">
                <num>(s)</num>
                <p>planning, promoting, developing and financing export-oriented concerns;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.t">
                <num>(t)</num>
                <p>forming or conducting subsidiaries for carrying out its functions;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.u">
                <num>(u)</num>
                <p>acting as agent of the Central Government, any State Government, the Reserve Bank, the Development Bank or any other person as the Central Government may authorise;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>collecting, compiling and disseminating market and credit information in respect of international trade;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.w">
                <num>(w)</num>
                <p>doing any other kind of business which the Central Government may authorise;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.x">
                <num>(x)</num>
                <p>generally doing such other acts and things as may be incidental to, or consequential upon, the exercise of its powers or the discharge of its duties under this Act or any other law for the time being in force, including sale or transfer of any of its assets.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Exim Bank may receive in consideration of any of the services mentioned in sub-sections (1) and (2) such commission, brokerage, interest, remuneration or fees as may be agreed upon.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Exim Bank shall not grant any loan or advance or other financial accommodation on the security of its own bonds or debentures.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Loans by Central Government.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in this behalf, advance to the Exim Bank—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>a loan of twenty crores of rupees at a rate of interest of five and a quarter per cent. per annum repayable in fifteen equal annual instalments, commencing on the expiry of a period of fifteen years from the date of receipt of the loan; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>such further sums of money by way of loan on such terms and conditions as may be agreed upon:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that the Central Government may, on a request being made to it by the Exim Bank, increase the number of instalments or alter the amount of any instalment or vary the date on which any instalment is payable under clause (a).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Borrowings and acceptance of deposits by Exim Bank.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-12.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Exim Bank may, for the purposes of carrying out its functions under this Act,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>issue and sell bonds and debentures with or without the guarantee of the Central Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-12.1.list1.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>borrow money from the Reserve Bank—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-12.1.list1.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>repayable on demand or on the expiry of fixed periods not exceeding ninety days from the date on which the money is so borrowed against the security of stocks, funds and securities (other than immovable property) in which a trustee is authorised to invest trust money by any law for the time being in force in India;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-12.1.list1.b.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>against bills of exchange or promissory notes arising out of bona fide commercial or trade transactions and bearing two or more good signatures and maturing within five years from the date of the borrowing;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-12.1.list1.b.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>out of the National Industrial Credit (Long Term Operations) Fund established under section 46C of the Reserve Bank of India Act 1934 (2 of 1934), for any of the purposes specified in that section;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>borrow money from such other authority, organisation or institution in India as may generally or specially be approved by the Central Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>accept deposits repayable after the expiry of a period which shall not be less than twelve months from the date of the making of the deposit on such terms as may generally or specially be approved by the Reserve Bank.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, on a request being made to it by the Exim Bank, guarantee the bonds and debentures issued by that Bank as to the repayment of principal and the payment of interest at such rate as may be fixed by that Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Loans in foreign currency.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Foreign Exchange Regulation Act, 1973 (46 of 1973), or in any other law for the time being in force relating to foreign exchange, the Exim Bank may, for the purpose of granting loans and advances under this Act, borrow, with the previous consent of the Central Government, foreign currency from any foreign State or from any bank or financial institution in any foreign country or otherwise.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Grants, donations, etc., to Exim Bank.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Exim Bank may receive gifts, grants, donations or benefactions from Government or any other source in or outside India.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Export Development Fund.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>With effect from such date as the Central Government may, by notification, appoint, the Exim Bank shall establish a special fund to be called the Export Development Fund.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Credits to Export Development Fund.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>To the Export Development Fund shall be credited—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>all amounts received for the purposes of that Fund by way of loans, gifts, grants, donations or benefactions from Government or any other source in or outside India;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>repayments or recoveries in respect of loans, advances or other facilities granted from the Fund;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>income or profits from investments made from the Fund; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>income accruing or arising to the Fund by way of interest or otherwise, on account of the application of the Fund in accordance with the provisions of section 17.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Utilisation of Export Development Fund.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the Exim Bank considers it necessary or desirable so to do, it may, subject to the provisions of sub-sections (2) and (3), disburse or spend from the Export Development Fund any amount on account or in consequence of the grant of any loan or advance, or on account or in consequence of entering into any arrangement under sub-section (1) or clause (b) or clause (c) or clause (d) or clause (q) or clause (r) or clause (s) or clause (w) or clause (x) of sub-section (2) of section 10:</p>
            <p>Provided that before granting any such loan or advance or entering into any such arrangement, the Exim Bank shall obtain the prior approval of the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Before seeking the approval of the Central Government under sub-section (1), the Exim Bank shall satisfy itself that banking or other financial institutions or other agencies are not likely to grant such loan or advance, or to enter into any such arrangement in the ordinary course of business.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government shall, before giving its approval, satisfy itself that such loan, advance or arrangement is necessary as a matter of priority in the interests of the international trade of the country.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that nothing contained in this section shall be deemed to preclude the Exim Bank from granting any loan or advance or from entering into any arrangement under sub-section (1) or clause (b) or clause (c) or clause (d) or clause (q) or clause (r) or clause (s) or clause (w) or clause (x) of sub-section (2) of section 10 without the approval of the Central Government; if no amount in respect thereof is to be disbursed or spent from the Export Development Fund.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Debits to Export Development Fund.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-18.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>To the Export Development Fund shall be debited—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>such amounts as may from time to time be disbursed or spent under sub-section (1) of section 17;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>such amounts as may be required for discharging the liabilities in respect of loans received for the purposes of that Fund;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any loss arising on account of investment made out of that Fund; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>such expenditure arising out of, or in connection with, the administration and application of the Fund as may be determined by the Board.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No amount shall be debited to the Export Development Fund except as provided for in sub-section (1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Accounts and audit of Export Development Fund.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-19.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The balance-sheet and accounts of the Export Development Fund shall be prepared in such form and manner as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall cause the books and accounts of the Export Development Fund to be closed and balanced as on the 31st day of December</p>
            <p>or such other date in each year as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Export Development Fund shall be audited by one or more auditors appointed by the Central Government under section 24 who shall make a separate report thereon.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of sub-sections (2), (3), (4) and (6) of section 24 shall, so far as may be, apply in relation to the audit of the Export Development Fund.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Exim Bank shall furnish to the Central Government within four months from the date on which the accounts of the Export Development Fund are closed and balanced, a copy of the balance-sheet and accounts together with a copy of the auditor’s report and a report on the operation of the Fund during the relevant year and the Central Government shall, as soon as may be after they are received by it, cause the same to be laid before each House of Parliament:</p>
            <p>Provided that with a view to facilitating the transition from one period of accounting to another period of accounting under this sub-section, the Central Government may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions as it considers necessary or expedient for the closing and balancing of, or for other matters relating to, the books or accounts in respect of the concerned years.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Liquidation of Export Development Fund.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Export Development Fund shall not be closed or wound up save by order of the Central Government and in such manner as that Government may direct.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>General Fund.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>All receipts of the Exim Bank other than those which are to be credited to the Export Development Fund under this Act shall be credited to a Fund to be called the General Fund and all payments by the Exim Bank, other than those which are to be debited to the Export Development Fund, shall be made out of the General Fund.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Preparation of accounts and balance-sheet.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-22.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The balance-sheet and accounts of the Exim Bank shall be prepared in such form and manner as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-22.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall cause the books and accounts of the Exim Bank to be closed and balanced as on the 31st day of December</p>
            <p>or such other date in each year as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify:</p>
            <p>Provided that with a view to facilitating the transition from one period of accounting to another period of accounting under this sub-section, the Central Government may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions as it considers necessary or expedient for the closing and balancing of, or for other matters relating to, the books or accounts in respect of the concerned years.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Disposal of profits accruing to General Fund.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-23.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Exim Bank may establish a Reserve Fund to which may be transferred such sums as that Bank may deem fit out of the annual profits accruing to the General Fund.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>After making provision for bad and doubtful debts, depreciation of assets and for all other matters for which provision is necessary or expedient or which is usually provided for by bankers and for the Reserve Fund referred to in sub-section (1), the Exim Bank shall transfer the balance of the net profits to the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Audit.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-24.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The accounts of the Exim Bank shall be audited by auditors duly qualified to act as auditors under sub-section (1) of section 226 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), who shall be appointed by the Central Government for such term and on such remuneration as the Central Government may fix.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The auditors shall be supplied with a copy of the annual balance-sheet of the Exim Bank and it shall be their duty to examine it together with the accounts and vouchers relating thereto and they shall have a list delivered to them of all books kept by the Exim Bank and shall at all reasonable times have access to the books, accounts, vouchers and other documents of the Exim Bank.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The auditors may, in relation to such accounts, examine any director or any officer or other employee of the Exim Bank and shall be entitled to require from the Board or officer or other employee of the Exim Bank such information and explanation as they may think necessary for the performance of their duties.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The auditors shall make a report to the Exim Bank upon the annual balance-sheet and accounts examined by them and in every such report they shall state whether in their opinion the balance-sheet is a full and fair balance-sheet containing all necessary particulars and properly drawn up so as to exhibit a true and fair view of the state of affairs of the Exim Bank and in case they had called for any explanation or information from the Board or any officer or other employee of the Exim Bank whether it has been given and whether it is satisfactory.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Exim Bank shall furnish to the Central Government within four months from the date on which its accounts are closed and balanced, a copy of its balance- sheet and accounts together with a copy of the auditors’ report and a report of the working of the Exim Bank during the relevant year, and the Central Government shall, as soon as may be after they are received by it, cause the same to be laid before each House of Parliament.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Without prejudice to anything contained in the preceding sub-sections, the Central Government may, at any time, appoint the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India to examine and report upon the accounts of the Exim Bank and any expenditure incurred by him in connection with such examination and report shall be payable by the Exim Bank to the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Saving.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Save as otherwise provided in sub-section (4) of section 19, nothing contained in this Chapter shall apply to the Export Development Fund.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Transfer of part of business of Development Bank.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-26.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On such date as the Central Government may, by notification, appoint, all business, property, assets and liabilities, rights, interests, privileges and obligations of whatever nature of the Development Bank in so far as they relate to the export financing functions of that Bank shall stand transferred to, and vest in, the Exim Bank.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the transfer to, and vesting in, the Exim Bank under sub-section (1), the Exim Bank shall pay to the Development Bank such amount in such manner and in such number of instalments as may be determined by the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-26.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>All contracts, deeds, bonds, agreements, powers-of-attorney, grants of legal representation and other instruments of whatever nature of the Development Bank which relate to the export financing functions of that Bank and which are subsisting or having effect immediately before the date referred to in sub-section (1) and to which the said Bank is a party or which are in favour of that Bank shall,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-26.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>if they relate exclusively to the export financing functions of that Bank, be of full force and effect against or in favour of the Exim Bank, as the case may be, and may be enforced and acted upon as fully and effectively as if instead of the Development Bank the Exim Bank had been a party thereto or as if they had been issued in favour of the Exim Bank; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-26.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>if they relate not only to the export financing functions of the Development Bank but also to any of the other functions of that Bank, be of full force and effect against or in favour of both the Development Bank and the Exim Bank and may be enforced or acted upon as fully and effectively as if in addition to the Development Bank the Exim Bank had also been a party thereto or as if they had been issued in favour of the Development Bank and also the Exim Bank.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-26.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If, on the date referred to in sub-section (1), any suit appeal or other legal proceeding of whatever nature relating to the export financing functions of the Development Bank is pending, the same shall not abate, be discontinued or be in any way prejudicially affected by reason of the transfer to the Exim Bank of the business of the Development Bank or of anything contained in this Act, but the suit, appeal or other proceeding may,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-26.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>where it relates exclusively to the export financing functions of the Development Bank, be continued, prosecuted and enforced by or against the Exim Bank; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-26.4.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>where it relates not only to the export financing functions of the Development Bank but also to any of the other functions of that Bank, be continued, prosecuted and enforced by or against the Development Bank and the Exim Bank or, if the Central Government by special order in writing so directs, by or against such one of the said two Banks, as may be specified in such order.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any question arises as to whether any contract, deed, bond, agreement, powers- of-attorney, grant of legal representation or other instrument referred to in sub-section (3) or any suit, appeal or other legal proceeding referred to in sub-section (4) relates or relates exclusively to the export financing functions of the Development Bank, it shall be referred to the Central Government for decision and the decision of the Central Government thereon shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of this section shall have effect notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial Development Bank of India Act, 1964 (8 of 1964), or any other law or any instrument having force by virtue of the said Act or other law.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Staff of Exim Bank.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-27.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Exim Bank may appoint such number of officers and other employees as it considers necessary or desirable for the efficient performance of its functions and determine the terms and conditions of their appointment and service.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Without prejudice to the provisions of sub-section (1), it shall be lawful for the Exim Bank to utilise, and for the Development Bank to make available the services of, such staff of the Development Bank having experience relating to export financing functions on such terms and conditions as may be agreed upon between the Exim Bank and the Development Bank.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The duties and conduct, terms and conditions of service and the establishment and maintenance of a provident Fund or any other Fund for the benefit of the officers and other employees of the Exim Bank shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28">
        <num>28.</num>
        <heading>Delegation of powers.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Board may, by general or special order, delegate to any director or any officer or other employee of the Exim Bank, subject to such conditions and limitations, if any, as may be specified in the order, such of its powers and functions under this Act as it may deem necessary.</p>
            <p>The Board has been authorised to delegate to any director or any officer or any other employee of the Exim Bank, such powers and functions as may be deemed necessary.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29">
        <num>29.</num>
        <heading>Returns.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-29.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Exim Bank shall furnish, from time to time, to the Central Government such returns as the Central Government may require.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-30">
        <num>30.</num>
        <heading>Obligation as to fidelity and secrecy.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-30.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Exim Bank shall not, except as otherwise required by this Act or any other law, divulge any information relating to or to the affairs of, its constituents except in circumstances in which it is, in accordance with the law or practice and usage customary among bankers, necessary or appropriate for the Exim Bank to divulge such information.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-30.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Exim Bank may, for the purpose of efficient discharge of its functions under this Act, collect from, or furnish to, the Central Government, the Development Bank or any scheduled bank or such other financial institution, as may be notified in the Official Gazette by the Central Government in this behalf, credit information or other information as it may consider useful for the purpose, in such manner and at such times, as it may think fit.</p>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <p>For the purpose of this sub-section, the expression “credit information” shall have the same meaning as in clause (c) of section 45A of the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934), subject to the modification that “banking company” referred to therein shall mean the Development Bank, any scheduled bank or other financial institution as aforesaid.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-30.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every director, member of a committee, auditor or officer or other employee of the Exim Bank or of the Development Bank whose services are utilised by the Exim Bank under the provisions of this Act, shall, before entering upon his duties, make a declaration of fidelity and secrecy in the form set out in the First Schedule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-30.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing contained in this section shall apply to the credit information disclosed under the Credit Information Companies (Regulation) Act, 2005.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-31">
        <num>31.</num>
        <heading>Defects in appointments not to invalidate acts, etc. —</heading>
        <subsection id="section-31.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No act or proceeding of the Board or of any committee of the Exim Bank shall be questioned on the ground merely of the existence of any vacancy in, or defect in the constitution of, the Board or the committee, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-31.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No act done by any person acting in good faith as a director shall be deemed to be invalid merely on the ground that he was disqualified to be a director or that there was any other defect in his appointment.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-32">
        <num>32.</num>
        <heading>Arrangement with Exim Bank on appointment of directors to prevail.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-32.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any arrangement entered into by the Exim Bank with a company provides for the appointment by the Exim Bank of one or more directors of such company, such provision and any appointment of directors made in pursuance thereof shall be valid and effective notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), or in any other law for the time being in force or in the memorandum, articles of association or any other instrument relating to the company, and any provision regarding share qualification, age limit, number of directorships, removal from office of directors and such like conditions contained in any such law or instrument aforesaid, shall not apply to any director appointed by the Exim Bank in pursuance of the arrangement as aforesaid.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-32.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-32.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any director appointed as aforesaid shall—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-32.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>hold office during the pleasure of the Exim Bank and may be removed or substituted by any person by order in writing of the Exim Bank;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-32.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>not incur any obligation or liability by reason only of his being a director or for anything done or omitted to be done in good faith in the discharge of his duties as a director or anything in relation thereto;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-32.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>not be liable to retirement by rotation and shall not be taken into account for computing the number of directors liable to such retirement.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-33">
        <num>33.</num>
        <heading>Indemnity of directors.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-33.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every director shall be indemnified by the Exim Bank against all losses and expenses incurred by him, in, or in relation to, the discharge of his duties, except such as are caused by his own wilful act or default.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-33.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A director shall not be responsible for any other director or for any officer or other employee of the Exim Bank or for any loss or expenses resulting to the Exim Bank from the insufficiency or deficiency of the value of, or title to, any property or security acquired or taken on behalf of the Exim Bank or the insolvency or wrongful act of any debtor or any person under obligation to the Exim Bank or anything done in good faith in the execution of the duties of his office or in relation thereto.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-34">
        <num>34.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-34.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Exim Bank or any director or any officer or other employee of the Exim Bank or any other person authorised by the Exim Bank to discharge any functions under this Act for any loss or damage caused or likely to be caused by anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any other law or provision having the force of law.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-35">
        <num>35.</num>
        <heading>Act 18 of 1891 to apply in relation to Exim Bank.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-35.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Bankers’ Books Evidence Act, 1891 shall apply in relation to the Exim Bank as if it were a Bank as defined in section 2 of that Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-36">
        <num>36.</num>
        <heading>Section 34A and section 36AD only of Act 10 of 1949 to apply to Exim Bank.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-36.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Nothing contained in the Banking Regulation Act, 1949, except section 34A and section 36AD thereof, shall apply to the Exim Bank.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-37">
        <num>37.</num>
        <heading>Act 43 of 1961 and Act 7 of 1964 not to apply to Exim Bank.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-37.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>[Rep. by the Finance (No. 2) Act, 1998 (21 of 1998), sec. 117 (w.e.f. 1-4-1999).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-38">
        <num>38.</num>
        <heading>Liquidation of Exim Bank.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-38.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No provision of any law relating to the winding up of companies or corporations shall apply to the Exim Bank and the Exim Bank shall not be placed in liquidation save by an order of the Central Government and in such manner as it may direct.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-39">
        <num>39.</num>
        <heading>Power to make regulations.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-39.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board may, with the previous approval of the Central Government</p>
            <p>by notification in the Official Gazette, make regulations not inconsistent with this Act to provide for all matters for which provision is necessary or expedient for the purpose of giving effect to the provisions of this Act.—</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-39.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board may, with the previous approval of the Central Government</p>
            <p>by notification in the Official Gazette, make regulations not inconsistent with this Act to provide for all matters for which provision is necessary or expedient for the purpose of giving effect to the provisions of this Act."</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-39.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-39.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such regulations may provide for—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-39.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the times and places of the meetings of the Board or of any committee constituted under this Act and the procedure to be followed at such meetings including the quorum necessary for the transaction of business;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the fees and allowances that may be paid to the directors and the members of a committee;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the form and manner in which the balance-sheets and the account of the Export Development Fund and the Exim Bank shall be prepared:</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the duties and conduct, and the terms and conditions of service of the officers and other employees of the Exim Bank;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the establishment and maintenance of provident fund or any other fund for the benefit of the officers and other employees of the Exim Bank; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>any other matter which is to be, or may be, prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-39.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every regulation made by the Board under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the regulation or both Houses agree that the regulation should not be made, the regulation shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that regulation.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-40">
        <num>40.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of certain enactments.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-40.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1988 (19 of 1988), sec. 2 and Sch. I (w.e.f. 31-3-1988).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-41">
        <num>41.</num>
        <heading>Power to remove difficulty.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-41.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government may, by order, do anything, not inconsistent with such provisions for the purpose of removing the difficulty:</p>
            <p>Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiration of three years from the date on which this Act receives the assent of the President.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-thefirstschedule">
      <doc name="thefirstschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1981/28/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1981/28"/>
              <FRBRalias value="THE FIRST SCHEDULE"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1981/28/eng@1980-01-01/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1981/28/eng@1980-01-01"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1981/28/eng@1980-01-01/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1981/28/eng@1980-01-01"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-06-08" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="thefirstschedule">
            <paragraph id="thefirstschedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>See section 30(3)</p>
                <p>DECLARATION OF FIDELITY AND SECRECY</p>
                <p>I,........................., do hereby declare that I will faithfully, truly and to the best of my skill and ability execute and perform the duties required of me as director, member of ......................... committee, auditor, officer or other employee (as the case may be) of the Export-Import Bank of India and which properly relate to the office or position held by me in or in relation to the said Exim Bank.</p>
                <p>I further declare that I will not communicate or allow to be communicated to any person not legally entitled thereto any information relating to the affairs of the Export-Import Bank of India or to the affairs of any person having any dealing with the said Exim Bank, nor will I allow any such person to inspect or have access to any books or documents belonging to or in the possession of the said Exim Bank and relating to the business of the said Exim Bank or the business of any person having any dealing with the said Exim Bank.</p>
                <blockList id="thefirstschedule.paragraph-0.list5">
                  <listIntroduction>Signed before me.</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="thefirstschedule.paragraph-0.list5.Signature">
                    <num>(Signature)</num>
                    <p>Schedule - THE SECOND SCHEDULE</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <p>Amendment of certain enactments.—</p>
                <p>Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1988 (19 of 1988), Sec. 2 and Sch. I (w.e.f. 31-3-1988).</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
