<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1956/48/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1956/48"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The National Highways Act, 1956"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1956/48/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1956/48/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1956/48/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1956/48/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-06-30" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The National Highways Act, 1956</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 48 OF 1956</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[11th September, 1956]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the declaration of certain highways to be national highways and for matters connected therewith.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Seventh Year of the Republic of India as follows:--</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the National Highways Act, 1956.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Declaration of certain highways to be national highways.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Each of the highways specified in the Schedule is hereby declared to be a national highway.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare any other highway to be a national highway and on the publication of such notification such highway shall be deemed to be specified in the Schedule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by like notification, omit any highway from the Schedule and on the publication of such notification, the highway so omitted shall cease to be a national highway.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“competent authority” means any person or authority authorised by the Central Government, by notification in the Official Gazette, to perform the functions of the competent authority for such area as may be specified in the notification;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“land” includes benefits to arise out of land and things attached to the earth or permanently fastened to anything attached to the earth.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3A">
        <num>3A.</num>
        <heading>Power to acquire land, etc.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the Central Government is satisfied that for a public purpose any land is required for the building, maintenance, management or operation of a national highway or part thereof, it may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare its intention to acquire such land.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every notification under sub-section (1) shall give a brief description of the land.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The competent authority shall cause the substance of the notification to be published in two local newspapers, one of which will be in a vernacular language.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3B">
        <num>3B.</num>
        <heading>Power to enter for survey, etc.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3B.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>On the issue of a notification under sub-section</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-3B.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3B.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>of section 3A, it shall be lawful for any person, authorised by the Central Government in this behalf, to—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3B.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>make any inspection, survey, measurement, valuation or enquiry;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3B.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>take levels;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3B.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>dig or bore into sub-soil;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3B.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>set out boundaries and intended lines of work;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3B.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>mark such levels, boundaries and lines placing marks and cutting trenches; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3B.1.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>do such other acts or things as may be laid down by rules made in this behalf by that Government.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3C">
        <num>3C.</num>
        <heading>Hearing of objections.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3C.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person interested in the land may, within twenty-one days from the date of publication of the notification under sub-section (1) of section 3A, object to the use of the land for the purpose or purposes mentioned in that sub-section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3C.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every objection under sub-section (1) shall be made to the competent authority in writing and shall set out the grounds thereof and the competent authority shall give the objector an opportunity of being heard, either in person or by a legal practitioner, and may, after hearing all such objections and after making such further enquiry, if any, as the competent authority thinks necessary, by order, either allow or disallow the objections.</p>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <p>For the purposes of this sub-section, “legal practitioner” has the same meaning as in clause (i) of sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Advocates Act, 1961 (25 of 1961).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3C.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any order made by the competent authority under sub-section (2) shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3D">
        <num>3D.</num>
        <heading>Declaration of acquisition.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3D.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where no objection under sub-section (1) of section 3C has been made to the competent authority within the period specified therein or where the competent authority has disallowed the objection under sub-section (2) of that section, the competent authority shall, as soon as may be, submit a report accordingly to the Central Government and on receipt of such report, the Central Government shall declare, by notification in the Official Gazette, that the land should be acquired for the purpose or purposes mentioned in sub-section (1) of section 3A.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3D.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On the publication of the declaration under sub-section (1), the land shall vest absolutely in the Central Government free from all encumbrances.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3D.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where in respect of any land, a notification has been published under sub-section (1) of section 3A for its acquisition but no declaration under sub-section (1) has been published within a period of one year from the date of publication of that notification, the said notification shall cease to have any effect:</p>
            <p>Provided that in computing the said period of one year, the period or periods during which any action or proceedings to be taken in pursuance of the notification issued under sub-section (1) of section 3A is stayed by an order of a court shall be excluded.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3D.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A declaration made by the Central Government under sub-section (1) shall not be called in question in any court or by any other authority.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3E">
        <num>3E.</num>
        <heading>Power to take possession.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3E.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any land has vested in the Central Government under sub-section (2) of section 3D, and the amount determined by the competent authority under section 3G with respect to such land has been deposited under sub-section (1) of section 3H, with the competent authority by the Central Government, the competent authority may by notice in writing direct the owner as well as any other person who may be in possession of such land to surrender or deliver possession thereof to the competent authority or any person duly authorised by it in this behalf within sixty days of the service of the notice.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3E.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3E.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If any person refuses or fails to comply with any direction made under sub-section (1), the competent authority shall apply—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3E.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in the case of any land situated in any area falling within the metropolitan area, to the Commissioner of Police;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3E.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in case of any land situated in any area other than the area referred to in clause (a), to the Collector of a District,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>and such Commissioner or Collector, as the case may be, shall enforce the surrender of the land, to the competent authority or to the person duly authorised by it.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3F">
        <num>3F.</num>
        <heading>Right to enter into the land where land has vested in the Central Government.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3F.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where the land has vested in the Central Government under section 3D, it shall be lawful for any person authorised by the Central Government in this behalf, to enter and do other act necessary upon the land for carrying out the building, maintenance, management or operation of a national highway or a part thereof, or any other work connected therewith.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3G">
        <num>3G.</num>
        <heading>Determination of amount payable as compensation.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3G.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any land is acquired under this Act, there shall be paid an amount which shall be determined by an order of the competent authority.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3G.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the right of user or any right in the nature of an easement on, any land is acquired under this Act, there shall be paid an amount to the owner and any other person whose right of enjoyment in that land has been affected in any manner whatsoever by reason of such acquisition an amount calculated at ten per cent. of the amount determined under sub-section (1), for that land.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3G.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Before proceeding to determine the amount under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2), the competent authority shall give a public notice published in two local newspapers, one of which will be in a vernacular language inviting claims from all persons interested in the land to be acquired.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3G.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Such notice shall state the particulars of the land and shall require all persons interested in such land to appear in person or by an agent or by a legal practitioner referred to in sub-section (2) of section 3C, before the competent authority, at a time and place and to state the nature of their respective interest in such land.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3G.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the amount determined by the competent authority under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) is not acceptable to either of the parties, the amount shall, on an application by either of the parties, be determined by the arbitrator to be appointed by the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3G.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the provisions of the Arbitration and Conciliation Act, 1996 (26 of 1996) shall apply to every arbitration under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3G.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3G.7.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The competent authority or the arbitrator while determining the amount under sub-section (1) or sub-section (5), as the case may be, shall take into consideration—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3G.7.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the market value of the land on the date of publication of the notification under section 3A;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3G.7.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the damage, if any, sustained by the person interested at the time of taking possession of the land, by reason of the severing of such land from other land;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3G.7.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the damage, if any, sustained by the person interested at the time of taking possession of the land, by reason of the acquisition injuriously affecting his other immovable property in any manner, or his earnings;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3G.7.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>if, in consequences of the acquisition of the land, the person interested is compelled to change his residence or place of business, the reasonable expenses, if any, incidental to such change.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3H">
        <num>3H.</num>
        <heading>Deposit and payment of amount.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3H.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The amount determined under section 3G shall be deposited by the Central Government in such manner as may be laid down by rules made in this behalf by that Government, with the competent authority before taking possession of the land.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3H.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>As soon as may be after the amount has been deposited under sub-section (1), the competent authority shall on behalf of the Central Government pay the amount to the person or persons entitled thereto.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3H.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where several persons claim to be interested in the amount deposited under sub-section (1), the competent authority shall determine the persons who in its opinion are entitled to receive the amount payable to each of them.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3H.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any dispute arises as to the apportionment of the amount or any part thereof or to any person to whom the same or any part thereof is payable, the competent authority shall refer the dispute to the decision of the principal civil court of original jurisdiction within the limits of whose jurisdiction the land is situated.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3H.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the amount determined under section 3G by the arbitrator is in excess of the amount determined by the competent authority, the arbitrator may award interest at nine per cent. per annum on such excess amount from the date of taking possession under section 3D till the date of the actual deposit thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3H.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the amount determined by the arbitrator is in excess of the amount determined by the competent authority, the excess amount together with interest, if any, awarded under sub-section (5) shall be deposited by the Central Government in such manner as may be laid down by rules made in this behalf by that Government, with the competent authority and the provisions of sub-sections (2) to (4) shall apply to such deposit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3I">
        <num>3I.</num>
        <heading>Competent authority to have certain powers of civil court.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3I.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The competent authority shall have, for the purposes of this Act, all the powers of a civil court while trying a suit under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), in respect of the following matters, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3I.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person and examining him on oath;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3I.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>requiring the discovery and production of any document;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3I.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>reception of evidence on affidavits;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3I.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>requisitioning any public record from any court or office;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3I.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>issuing commission for examination of witnesses.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3J">
        <num>3J.</num>
        <heading>Land Acquisition Act 1 of 1894 not to apply.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3J.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in the Land Acquisition Act, 1894 shall apply to an acquisition under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>National highways to vest in the Union.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>All national highways shall vest in the Union, and for the purposes of this Act “highways” include—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>all lands appurtenant thereto, whether demarcated or not;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>all bridges, culverts, tunnels, causeways, carriageways and other structures constructed on or across such highways; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>all fences, trees, posts and boundary, furlong and milestones of such highways or any land appurtenant to such highways.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Responsibility for development and maintenance of national highways.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>It shall be the responsibility of the Central Government to develop and maintain in proper repair all national highways; but the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that any function in relation to the development or maintenance of any national highway shall, subject to such conditions, if any, as may be specified in the notification, also be exercisable by the Government of the State within which the national highway is situated or by any officer or authority subordinate to the Central Government or to the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Power to issue directions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may give directions to the Government of any State as to the carrying out in the State of any of the provisions of this Act or of any rule, notification or order made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Fees for services or benefits rendered on national highways.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, levy fees at such rates as may be laid down by rules made in this behalf for services or benefits rendered in relation to the use of ferries,</p>
            <p>permanent bridges the cost of construction of each of which is more than rupees twenty-five lakhs and which are opened to traffic on or after the 1st day of April, 1976, temporary bridges and tunnels on national highways and the use of sections of national highways.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Such fees when so levied shall be collected in accordance with the rules made under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any fee leviable immediately before the commencement of this Act for services or benefits rendered in relation to the use of ferries, temporary bridges and tunnels on any highway specified in the Schedule shall continue to be leviable under this Act unless and until it is altered in exercise of the powers conferred by sub-section (1):</p>
            <p>Provided that if the Central Government is of opinion that it is necessary in the public interest so to do, it may, by like notification, specify any bridge in relation to the use of which fees shall not be leviable under this sub-section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8A">
        <num>8A.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to enter into agreements for development and maintenance of national highways.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, the Central Government may enter into an agreement with any person in relation to the development and maintenance of the whole or any part of a national highway.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in section 7, the person referred to in sub-section (1) is entitled to collect and retain fees at such rate, for services or benefits rendered by him as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify having regard to the expenditure involved in building, maintenance, management and operation of the whole or part of such national highway, interest on the capital invested, reasonable return, the volume of traffic and the period of such agreement.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A person referred to in sub-section (1) shall have powers to regulate and control the traffic in accordance with the provisions contained in Chapter VIII of the Motor Vehicles Act, 1988 (59 of 1988) on the national highway forming subject-matter of such agreement, for proper management thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8B">
        <num>8B.</num>
        <heading>Punishment for mischief by injury to national highway.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8B.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever commits mischief by doing any act which renders or which he knows to be likely to render any national highway referred to in sub-section</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-8B.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of section 8A impassable or less safe for travelling or conveying property, shall be punished with imprisonment of either description for a term which may extend to five years, or with a fine, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the manner in which, and the conditions subject to which, any function in relation to the development or maintenance of a national highway or any part thereof may be exercised by the State Government or any officer or authority subordinate to the Central Government or the State Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.aa">
                <num>(aa)</num>
                <p>the manner in which the amount shall be deposited with the competent authority under sub-sections (1) and (6) of section 3H;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the rates at which fees for services rendered in relation to the use of ferries, permanent bridges, temporary bridges and tunnels on any national highway and the use of sections of any national highway may be levied, and the manner in which such fees shall be collected, under section 7;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the periodical inspection of national highways and the submission of inspection reports to the Central Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the reports on works carried out on national highways;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>any other matter for which provision should be made under this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Laying of notifications, rules, etc., before Parliament.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>All notifications or agreements issued or entered into under this Act shall be laid before both Houses of Parliament as soon as may be after they are issued or entered into.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-theschedule">
      <doc name="theschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1956/48/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1956/48"/>
              <FRBRalias value="The Schedule"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1956/48/eng@1980-01-01/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1956/48/eng@1980-01-01"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1956/48/eng@1980-01-01/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1956/48/eng@1980-01-01"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-06-30" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="theschedule">
            <heading>[See Section 2]</heading>
            <paragraph id="theschedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>National Highways</p>
                <table id="theschedule.paragraph-0.table1">
                  <tr>
                    <th>
                      <p>Serial No.</p>
                    </th>
                    <td>
                      <p>National Highway No.</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Description of National Highways</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>1</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>2</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>3</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>1</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>1</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Delhi, Ambala, Jullundur and Amritsar and proceeding to the border between India and Pakistan.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>2</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>1A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Jullundur, Madhopur, Jammu, Banihal, Srinagar, Baramula and Uri.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>2-A.</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>1B</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction at Botole on National Highway No. 1A and connecting Doda with kishtwar to be a national highway.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>2AA</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Extension of NH No. 1B</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 1B near Kishtwar and connecting Chhatree, Symthan Maidan and terminating at Symthan pass in Jammu and Kashmir.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>2AAA</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>C</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 1A near Domel and terminating at Katra in Jammu and Kashmir.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>3</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>2</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Delhi, Mathura, Agra, Kanpur, Allahabad, Banaras, Mohania, Barhi Palsit, Baidyabati, Bara, Calcutta.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>2A</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Sikandra - Bhognipur</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>4</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>3</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Agra, Gwalior, Shivpuri, Indore, Dhulia, Nasik, Thana and Bombay.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>5</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>302</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-2 near Theriat connecting Lunglei, Lungseni, Tuiehong and terminating at Demagiri in the State of Mizoram.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>5A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>4A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Belgaum, Anmod, Panda and Panaji.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>5B</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>4B</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with Panvel- Uran State Highway near Nhava-Sheva Port Complex and proceeding further with one arm terminating of Kalamboli on National Highway No. 4 and another arm crossing National Highway No. 17 near Palaspe and proceeding further to terminate on National Highway No. 4.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>6</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>5</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Baharagora with the highway specified in serial No. 7 and connecting Cuttack, Bhubaneswar, Visakhapatnam, Vijayawada and Madras.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>6 A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>5A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Haridaspur with National Highway No. 5 and terminating at the Paradip Port.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>7</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>6</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Dhulia with the highway specified in serial No. 4 and connecting Nagpur, Raipur, Sambalpur, Baharagora and Calcutta.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>7AA</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Extension of NH No. 6</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Surat on National Highway No. 6 and terminating at Hajira in Gujarat.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>8</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>7</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Banaras with the highway specified in serial No. 3 and connecting Mangawan, Rewa, Jabalpur, Lakhnadon, Nagpur, Hyderabad, Kurnool, Bangalore, Krishnagiri, Salem, Dindigul, Madurai and Cape Comorin.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>8A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>7A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Palayankottai on National Highway No. 7 with the Tuticorin Port.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>9</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>8</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Delhi, Jaipur, Ajmer, Udaipur, Ahmedabad, Baroda and Bombay.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>10</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>8A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Ahmedabad, Limbdi, Morvi and Kandla.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>10A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Extension of NH No. 8A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Kandla on National Highway No. 8A connecting Mundra and terminating at Mandvi in Gujarat.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>11</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>8B</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Bamanbhore with the highway specified in serial No. 10 and connecting Rajkot and Porbandar.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>11A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>8C</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Chiloda on National Highway No. 8, in Gujarat, Gandhinagar and terminating at Sarkej on National Highway No. 8A.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>11AA</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>8D</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Jetpur on National Highway No. 8B and connecting Junagarh, Keshod and terminating at Somnath in Gujarat.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>8E</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Somnath - Bhavnagar</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>12</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>9</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Poona, Sholapur, Hyderabad and Vijayawada.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>12A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Extension of NH No. 9</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Vijayawada on National Highway No. 5 connecting Vuyyuru, Pammari and terminating at Machilipatnam in Andhra Pradesh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>13</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>10</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Delhi and Fazilka and proceeding to the border between India and Pakistan.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>13A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>11</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Agra, Jaipur and Bikaner.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>11A</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Dausa - Manoharpur</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>13B</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>12</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Jabalpur, Bhopal and Biaora.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>12A</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Jabalpur - Mandla - Chilpi -- Simga</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>13C</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>13</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Sholapur and Chitradurga.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>13CC</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Extension of NH No. 13</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Mangalore on National Highway No. 48 and connecting Tirthahalli, Shimoga and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 4 near Chitradurga in Karnataka.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>14</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Beawar - Sirohi - Radhapur</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>13D</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>21</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Chandigarh with National Highway No. 22 and connecting Ropar, Bilaspur, Mandi, Kulu and Manali.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>13DD</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>21A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Pinjore on National Highway No. 22 in Haryana connecting Baddi, Nalagarh and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 21 near Swarghat in Himachal Pradesh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>13E</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>15</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Pathankot-Amritsar, Bhatinda, Ganganagar, Bikaner, Jaisalmer, Barmer to its junction with National Highway No. 8A near Samakhiali (near Kandla).</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>16</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Nizamabad - Mancheral - Jagdalpur</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>13F</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>17</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Panvel on National Highway No. 4 Mahad, Panaji, Karwar, Mangalore, Cannanore, Calicut (Kozhikode), Feroke, Kuttipuram, Pudu Ponnani, Chowghat Cranganpur to junction with National Highway No. 47 near Edapally.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>13G</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>17A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Cortalim with National Highway No. 17 and terminating at the Marmugao Port.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>17B</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Ponda - Verna - Vasco</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>18</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Junction with National Highway No. 7 near Kurnool - Nandyal - Cuddapah Junction with National Highway No. 4 Near Chittoor</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>19</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Gazipur - Ballia - Patna</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>20</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Pathankot - Mandi</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>14</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>22</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Ambala, Kalka, Simla, Narkanda, Rampur and Chini and proceeding to the border between India and Tibet near Shipki-La.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>14A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>23</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Chas, Ranchi, Rourkela, Talcher and terminating at National Highway No. 42.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>15</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>24</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Delhi, Bareilly and Lucknow.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>16</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>6</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-27 near Jorabat in the State of Assam connecting Shillong, Dhaleshwar, Kanpui, Aizawal, Selling, Lumtui, Khawthlir, Tuisen, Neihdawn and terminating at Champai in the State of Mizoram.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>16A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>25A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 25 at Km 19 and terminating at Bakshi ka Talab in National Highway No. 24 in Uttar Pradesh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>17</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>26</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Jhansi and Lakhnadon.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>18</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>27</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Allahabad with the highway specified in serial No. 8 near Mangawan.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>19</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>28</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Barauni with the highway specified in serial No. 23 and connecting Muzaffarpur, Pipra, Gorakhpur and Lucknow.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>20</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>28A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Pipra with the highway specified in serial No. 19 and connecting Sagauli and Raxaul and proceeding to the border between India and Nepal.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>21</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>29</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Gorakhpur, Ghazipur and Banaras.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>22</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>30</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Mohania with the highway specified in serial No. 3 and connecting Patna and Bakhtiyarpur.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>22A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>30A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Phatuha on National Highway No. 30 and connecting Chandi Harnaut National Highway No. 31, Saksohara and terminating in its junction on National Highway No. 31 near Barh in Bihar.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>23</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>31</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Barhi with the highway specified in serial No. 3 and connecting Bakhtiyarpur, Mokameh, Purnea, Dalkhola, Siliguri, Sivok, and Cooch-Behar, North Salmara and proceeding generally via Nalbari, Charali and Amingaon to its junction with the highway specified in serial No. 28 near Pandu.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>24</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>31A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Sivok and Gangtok.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>24A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>32</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Govindpur with National Highway No. 2 and connecting Dhanbad with Jamshedpur.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>24AA</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>31B</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from near North Salmara to its junction with National Highway No. 37 near Goalpara.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>24AAA</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>31C</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from near Galgalia, connecting Baghdogra, Chalsa, Nagrakata, Goyerkata.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>25</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>33</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Barhi with the highway specified in serial No. 3 and connecting Ranchi and Tatanagar and proceeding to its junction with the highway specified in serial No. 7 near Baharagora.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>26</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>34</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Dalkhola with the highway specified in serial No. 23 and connecting Berhampore, Barasat and Calcutta.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>27</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>35</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Barasat and Bangaon and proceeding to the border between India and Pakistan.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>27A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>36</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Nowgong, Dabaka, and Dimapur (Manipur Road).</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>28</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>37</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Goalpara with the highway specified in serial No. 23 and connecting Gauhati, Jorabat, Kamargaon, Makum and Saikhoa Ghat.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>37A</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Kuarital - Junction with National Highway No. 52 Near Tezpur</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>29</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>38</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Makum, Ledo and Lekhapani.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>30</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>39</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Kamargaon, Imphal and Palel and proceeding to the border between India and Burma.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>31</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>40</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Jorabat and Shillong and proceeding to the border between India and Pakistannear Dawki.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>31A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Extension of NH No. 40</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 44 near Jowai connecting Amlarem and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 40 near Dawki in Meghalaya.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>32</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>42</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Sambalpur with the highway specified in serial No. 7 and proceeding via Angul to its junction with the highway specified in serial No. 6 near Cuttack.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>33</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>43</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Rajpur and Vizianagaram and proceeding to its junction with the highway specified in serial No. 6 near Vizianagaram.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>33A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>44</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Shillong, Passi, Baderpur and Agartala.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>33AA</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>44A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 54 near Aizawl in Mizoram and connecting Sairang, Lengpui, Mamit and terminating at Manu in Tripura.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>34</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>45</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Madras, Tiruchirappalli and Dindigul.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>34AA</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Extension of NH No. 45A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 45A near Pondy in Pondicherry and connecting Cuddalore-Chidambaram and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 67 near Nagapattinam in Tamil Nadu.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>34AAA</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>45B</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 45 near Trichy and connecting Viralimalai, Tovarankuruchchi, Melur, Madurai (National Highway No. 7), Aruppakottai and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 7A near Tuticorin in Tamil Nadu.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>35</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>46</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Krishnagiri and Ranipet.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>36</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>47</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Salem, Coimbatore, Trichur, Ernakulam, Trivandrum and Cape Comorin.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>47A</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Junction with National Highway No. 47 Willington Island.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>36A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>41</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway between its junction (near Kolaghat) with National Highway No. 6 and the point where it touches Haldia port.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>37A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>48</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Bangalore, Hassan and Mangalore.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>38</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>49</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Madurai and Dhanushkodi.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>39</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>50</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway connecting Nasik with the highway specified in serial No. 5 near Poona.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>40</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>51</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction at Baihata Charali on National Highway No. 37, in Assam, connecting Tura and terminating at Dalu in Meghalaya.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>41</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>52</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction at Baihata Charali on National Highway No. 31, in Assam, connecting Tejpur, Bander Dewa, Northlakhimpur, Pasighat, Tezu, Sitapani and terminating near Saikhoaghat on National Highway No. 37.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>42</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>52A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction at Bander Dewa on National Highway No. 52 in Assam and terminating at Hanagar in Arunachal Pradesh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>42A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Extension of NH 52 A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junctions near Itanagar on National Highway No. 52A in Arunchal Pradesh and terminating at its junction with. National Highway No. 52 near Gohpur in Assam.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>43</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>53</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Badarpur on National Highway No. 44, in Assam connecting Silchar, Jirighat and terminating near Imphal on National Highway No. 39.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>44</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>54</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction at Sikhar in Assam or National Highway No. 53 connecting Aizawl and terminating at Taipang in Mizoram.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>44A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>54A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction at Theriat in Mizoram on National Highway No. 54 and terminating at Lungli in Mizoram.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>44AA</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Extension of NH No. 54</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Daboka on National Highway No. 36 and connecting Lumding, Langdin, Haflong and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 54 near Sikhar in Assam.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>44B</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>54B</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction at "Venas Saddle" in Mizoram on National Highway No. 54 and terminating at Saiha in Mizoram.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>44D</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>55</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from Siliguri on National Highway No. 31 passing through Kurseong and terminating at Darjeeling.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>45</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>56</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from Lucknow and connecting Jagdishpur, Sultanpur and Jaunpur and terminating near Varanasi.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>56A</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Chenhat (NH 28) - KM 16 (NH 56).</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>45AA</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>56B</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 56 near Km 16 and terminating at Km 19 of National Highway No. 25 in Uttar Pradesh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>NEI</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Ahmedabad - Vadodara Expressway (under construction)</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>57</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Muzaffarpur - Darbhanga - Fobesganj - Purnea</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>58</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Ghaziabad - Meerut - Haridwar - Badrinath - Manna Pass</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>59</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Ahmedabad - Godhre - Dhar - Indore.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>59A</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Indore - Betul</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>60</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Balasore - Kharagpur - Asansol</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>47</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>61</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Kohima on National Highway No. 39 in Nagaland and connecting Workha-Moko-Kchung-Amguri and terminating at its junctions with National Highway No. 37 near Jhanji in Assam.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>48</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>52B</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junctions on National Highway 52 near Kuljan and terminating at its junction with National Highway 37 in Assam.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>49</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>62</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction on National Highway 37 near Damra in Assam and terminating at Bhaghmara in Meghalaya.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>49A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Extension of NH No. 62</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 62 near Baghmara and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 51 near Dalu in Meghalaya.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>50</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>63</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 17 near Ankola-Hospet and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 7 near Gooty in Andhra Pradesh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>51</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>64</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction on National Highway No. 22 near Chandigarh and connecting Rajpura-Patiala-Sangrur and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 15 near Bhatinda in Punjab.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>51A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Extension of NH No. 64</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 15 near Bhatinda in Punjab and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 10 near Dabwali in Haryana.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>52</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>65</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 1 near Ambala in Haryana and connecting Kaithal-Hisar and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 1 near Fatehpur in Rajasthan.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>52A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Extension of NH No. 65</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 11 near Fatehpur and connecting Nagaur, Jodhpur and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 14 near Pali in Rajasthan.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>53</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>66</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 45A in Pondicherry and connecting Tindivanam-Gingee-Thiruvannamalai and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 7 near Krishnagiri in Tamil Nadu.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>54</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>716</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-16 near Chennai connecting Tiruttanni in the State of Tamilnadu Renigunta Mamanduru, Settigunta, Koduru, Pullampeta, Rajampet, Nandalur, Madhavaram, Vonimitta, Bhakarapet and terminating at its junction with NH40 near Kadapa in the state of Andhra Pradesh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>54A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Extension of NHNo. 67</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 7 near Karur and connecting Palladam and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 47 near Coimbatore in Tamil Nadu.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>55</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>68</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction on National Highway No. 45 near Ulundrupet and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 7 near Salem in Tamil Nadu.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>56</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>69</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting form its junction with National Highway No. 6 near Nagpur in Maharashtra and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 12 near Obaidullaganj in Madhya Pradesh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>57</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>70</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Jalandhar on National Highway No. 1 in Punjab and connecting Hoshiarpur, Hamirpur, Toni Devi, Ahwa Devi, Dharampur and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 21 near Mandi in Himachal Pradesh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>58</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>71</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Jalandhar on National Highway No. 1 in Punjab and connecting, Moga, Barnala, Sangrur, Narwana, Rohtak, Jhajjar and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 8 near Bawal in Haryana.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>59</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>71A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Rohtak on National Highway No. 10 and connecting Gohana and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 1 near Panipat in Haryana.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>59A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>24A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 24 near Bakshi Ka Talab and terminating near Chenhat on National Highway No. 28 in Uttar Pradesh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>60</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>72</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Ambala on National Highway No. 1 and connecting Nahan, Paonta Sahib, Dehradun and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 58 near Rishikesh (Haridwar) in Uttar Pradesh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>61</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>73</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Roorkee on National Highway No. 58 in Uttar Pradesh and connecting Saharanpur, Yamunanagar, Saha and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 22 near Panchkula in Haryana.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>62</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>74</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 58 near Haridwar and connecting Najibabad, Nagina, Afzalgarh, Kashipur, Kichha, Jehanabad, Pilibhit and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 24 near Bareilly in Uttar Pradesh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>63</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>75</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 3 near Gwalior in Madhya Pradesh and connecting Jhansi (Uttar Pradesh), Khajuraho,Chhatarpur, Panna, Satna and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 7 near Rewa in Madhya Pradesh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>64</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>76</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 14 near Pindwara in Rajasthan and connecting Udaipur, Mangarwar, Chittaurgarh, Kota (National Highway No. 12), Shivpuri (National Highway No. 3), Jhansi (National Highway No. 25), Mahoba, Banda, Karwi, Mau and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 27 near Allahabad in Uttar Pradesh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>65</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>77</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Hajipur on National Highway No. 19 and connecting Muzaffarpur (National Highway No. 28), Sitamarhi and Sonbarsa in Bihar.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>66</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>78</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Katni on National Highway No. 7 in Madhya Pradesh connecting, Shahdol, Nagar, Ambikapur-Jashpurnagar and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 23 near Gumla in Bihar.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>67</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>79</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 8 near Ajmer in Rajasthan and connecting Nasirabad, Bhilwara, Chittaurgarh, Nayagaon, Nimach, Ratlam and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 59 near Ghatbilod (Indore) in Madhya Pradesh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>68</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>80</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Mokama on National Highway No. 31 in Bihar and connecting Munger, Bhagalpur, Sahebganj, Rajmahal and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 34 near Farakka in West Bengal.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>68A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>81</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 31 near Kora in Bihar and connecting Katihar and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 34 near Maldah in West Bengal</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>68B</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>0.82</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Gaya on National Highway No. 83 and connecting Rajgir, Bihar Sharif and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 31 near Mokama in Bihar.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>68C</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>83</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 30 near Patna and connecting Punpun, Gaya, Bodh Gaya and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 2 near Dobhi in Bihar.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>68D</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>84</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 30 near Arrah and connecting Bhojpur and terminating on National Highway No. 19 near Buxar in Bihar.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>68E</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>85</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 19 near Chhapra and connecting Siwan and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 28 near Gopalganj in Bihar.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>68F</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>86</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 2 near Kanpur in Uttar Pradesh and connecting Chhatarpur and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 26 near Sagar in Madhya Pradesh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>68G</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>87</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 24 near Rampur and connecting Bilaspur, Pantnagar, Haldwani and terminating at Nainital in Uttar Pradesh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>68H</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>88</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 22 near Simla and connecting Bilaspur, Hamirpur, Nadaun, Ranital, Kangra and terminating near Bhawan on National Highway No. 20 in Himachal Pradesh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>68-1</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>89</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 8 near Ajmer and connecting Nagaur, and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 11 near Bikaner in Rajasthan.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>90</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Baran - Aklera</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>91</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Ghaziabad - Aligarh - Eta - Kannauj - Kanpur</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>92</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Bhongaon - Etawah - Gwaiior</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>93</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Agra - Aligarh - Babrala - Chandausi - Moradabad</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>94</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rishikesh - Ampata - Tehri - Dharasu - Kuthnaur - Yamnotr</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>95</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Kharar (Chandigarh) - Ludhiana - Jagaron - Ferozepu</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>96</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Faizabad - Sultanpur - Pratapgarh - Allahabad</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>97</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Ghazipur - Zamania - Saiyedraja</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>98</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Patna - Aurangabad - Rajhara</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>99</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Dobhi - Chatra - Chandwa</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>100</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Chatra - Hazaribagh - Bogoda</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>101</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Chhapra - Baniapur - Maharajganj - Barauli</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>102</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Chhapra - Rewaghat - Muzaffarpur</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>103</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Hazipur - Musahrigharar</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>104</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Chakia on National Highway No. 28 connecting Narhar-Pakri Bridge-Madhuban-Shivhar-Sitamarhi-Harlakhi-</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Umagaon-Jayanagar-Lakoush-Laukahi and terminat- ing at its junction near Narahia on National Highway No. 57 in the State of Bihar.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>105</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Darbhanga - Aunsi - Jaynagar</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>106</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Birpur - Madhepura - Bihpur</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>107</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Maheshkhunt - Sonbar Saraj - Simri Bakhtiarpur - Bariahi - Saharsa - Madhepura - Purnea</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>69</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>150</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 54 near Aizawl in Mizoram and connecting Ipaimukh, Churachandpur, Imphal, Ukhrul, Jessami and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 39 near Kohima in Nagaland.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>151</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Karimganj - Bangladesh Border</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>69 A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Extension of NH No. 60</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 6 near Kharagpur and connecting Bishnupur, Bankura and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 2 near Asansol in West Bengal</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>69B</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>152</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Patacharkuchi on National Highway No. 31C, connecting Hajua and terminating at Indo-Bhutan border.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>15</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Ledo - Lekhapani - Indo/Mynamar Border</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>154</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Dhaleshwar - Bhairabi - Kanpu</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>70</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>200</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 6 near Raipur in Madhya Pradesh and connecting Bilaspur, Sarangarh, Raigarh, Kanaktura, Jharsuguda, Kochinda, Pravasuni, Deogarh. Talcher, and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 5 near Chandikhol in Orissa.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>71</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>201</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 43 near Boriguma and connecting Bhawanipatna, Bolangir, Barapali and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 6 near Bargarh in Orissa.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>72</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>202</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Hyderabad on National Highway No. 7 in Andhra Pradesh and connecting Warangal, Venkatpuram and terminating at its junction near Bhopalpatnam on National Highway No. 16 in Madhya Pradesh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>73</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>203</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 5 near Bhubaneshwar and terminating at Puri in Orissa.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>74</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>204</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from Ratnagiri and connecting Hathkamba (National Highway No. 17), Pali (National Highway No. 17), Sakharpa, Malkapur, and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 4 near Kolhapur in Maharashtra.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>75</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>205</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Ananthapur on National Highway No. 7 in Andhra Pradesh and connecting Kadiri, Tirupati, Renigunta, Tiruttani and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 5 near Chennai in Tamil Nadu.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>76</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>206</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Tumkur on National Highway No. 4 and connecting Shimoga and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 17 near Honnavar in Karnataka.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>77</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>207</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Hosur on National Highway No. 7 in Tamil Nadu connecting Sarjapur, Devenhalli (on National Highway No. 7), Doda Ballapur and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 4 near Nelamangala in Karnataka.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>78</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>208</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Kollam on National Highway No. 47 in Kerala and connecting Punalur, Tenkasi, Rajapalaiyam, Srivilliputtur and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 7 near Tirumangalam in Tamil Nadu.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>79</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>209</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction near Dindigul on National Highway No. 7 in Tamil Nadu and connecting Pollachi, Coimbatore, Annur, Satyamanglam, Chamrajnagar, Kollegal and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 7 near Bangalore in Karnataka.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>80</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>210</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 45 near Trichy and connecting Pudukottai, Devakottai and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 49 near Ramanathpuram in Tamil Nadu.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>81</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>211</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 9 near Solapur and connecting Osmanabad, Aurangabad and terminating at is junction with National Highway No. 3 near Dhule in Maharashtra.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>82</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>212</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 17 near Kozhikode in Kerala connecting Mysore, and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 209 near Kollegal in Karnataka.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>83</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>213</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 47 near Palghat and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 17 near Kozhikode in Kerala.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>84</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>214</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 5 near Kathipudi and connecting Kakinada, and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 9 near Pamarru in Andhra Pradesh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>85</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>215</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with National Highway No. 5 near Panikoli and connecting Keonjhar, and terminating at its junction with National Highway No. 23 near Rajamunda in Orissa.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>216</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Raigarh - Sarangarh - Saraipalli</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>217</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Raipur - Gopalpur</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>218</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Bijapur - Hubli</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>219</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Madnapalli - Kuppam - Krishnagiri</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p/>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>
                        <ul>
                          <li>220</li>
                        </ul>
                      </p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Kollam (Quilon) - Teni.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>225</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>563</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-63 near Mancheral connecting Karimnangar and terminating at NH-163 near Warangal in the State of Andhra Pradesh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>226</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>365A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-65 near Kodad connecting Khammam and terminating at NH-365 near Mahboobabad in the State of Andhra Pradesh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>227</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>334B</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with new NH-34 near Meerut in the State of Uttar Pradesh connecting Sonipat, Kharkhauda, Sampla, Jhajjar, Charkhi Dadri and terminating at its junction with NH-709 near Loharu in the State of Haryana.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>228</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>150 Extn.</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with new NH-50 near Gulbarga connecting Chowdapur, Afzalpur in the State of Karnataka, Dudhani, Akkalkote and terminating at its junction with new NH-52 near Sholapur in the State of Maharashtra.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>229</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>848B</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-48 near Karembali Phatak connecting Bamanpunja, Dholar Road in the State of Gujarat, Ambawadi, Patalia Costal Highway in the Union Territory of Daman and Diu and terminating at NH-48 near Udvada in the State of Gujarat.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>230</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>251</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-51 near Una in the State of Gujarat connecting Ghoghla in the Union Territory of Daman and Diu and terminating at NH-51 near Kesaria in the State of Gujarat.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>231</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>248A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-48 near Sahpura connecting Alwar, Ramgarh, Haryana/Rajasthan border in the State of Rajasthan, Nuh and terminating at its junction with new NH No. 48 near Gurgaon in the State of Haryana.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>232</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>107A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with new NH No. 7 near Chamoli connecting Gopeshwar, Okhimath and terminating at its junction on new NH No. 107 near Baramwari in the State of Uttrakhand.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>233</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>309A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with new NH No. 9 near Rameshwar connecting Gangolihat, Berinag, Chaukori, Kanda, Bagheshwar, Takula and terminating at its junction with new NH No. 109 near Almora in the State of Uttrakhand.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>234</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>325</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-25 near Balotra connecting Siwana, Jalore, Ahor and terminating at its junction with new NH No. 62 near Sandera in the State of Rajasthan.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>235</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>25 Extn.</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from Barmer connecting Ramsar and terminating at Munabao Road in the State of Rajasthan.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>236</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>102C</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-2 near Maram in the State of Manipur connecting Peren, Jaluki, Pimla, Junction, Razaphe Junction and terminating at NH-29 Near Dimapur in the State of Nagaland.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>237</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>381</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-544 near Avinashi connecting Tirupur and terminating at its junction with new NH No. 81 near Avinashipalaiym in the State of Tamilnadu.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>238</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>367</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-67 near Bhanapur connecting Kukunur, Yelburga, Gajendragad, Badami, Guledaguda, Bagalkote, Bagalkot and terminating at its junction with new NH No. 52 near Gaddankeri in the State of Karnataka.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>239</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>173</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-73 near Mudigere connecting Chikkamagaluru and terminating at its junction with new NH No. 69 near Kadur in the State of Karnataka.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>240</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>275</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-75 near Bantwala connecting Puttur, Sulya, Madikeri, Priyapatna Mysuru, Srirangapattana, Mandya, Channapatnam, Ramanagaram and terminating at its junction with new NH No. 75 on Bengaluru in the State of Karnataka.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>241</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>150A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-50 at Jevargi connecting Siriguppa, Bellary, Hiriyur, Huliyur, Chikkanayakanahalli, Nagamangala Srirangapatna-Mysore-Nanjangud and terminating at its junction with NH-948 at Chamarajanagar in the State of Karnataka.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>242</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>154A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-154 near Chakki, Dhar in the State of Punjab connecting Banikhet, Chamba and terminating at Bharmour in the State of Himachal Pradesh</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>243</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>505</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-5 near Khab Sangam connecting Chango, Sumdo, Tabo, Attargo, Kaza, Morang, Hanse, Losar, Lachu, Chhota Dhara and terminating at Gramphoo in the State of Himachal Pradesh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>243</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>503 Extn</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-3 near Mubarakpur connecting Amb, Una, Dehlan in the State of Himachal Pradesh, Anandpur Sahib, Kiratpur and terminating at its junction with new NH No. 205 in the State of Punjab.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>245</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>444</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-44 near Srinagar connecting Badgam, Pulwama, Shupiyan, Kulgam and terminating at its junction with new NH No. 44 near Quazigund in the State of Jammu and Kashmir.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>246</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>144A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-44 near Jammu connecting Akhnur, Naoshera, Rajauri and terminating at Punch in the State of Jammu and Kashmir.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>247</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>627</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with new NH-27 near Nelle (Amsoi Gate) connecting Rajagaon, Doyangmukh, Umrangso, Khobak and terminating at NH-27 near Harangajao in the State of Assam</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>248</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>310A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-10 near Tashiview point connecting Phodang and terminating at Mangan in the State of Sikkim</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>249</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>710</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-10 near Melli connecting Manpur, Namchi and terminating at Damthang in the State of Sikkim</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>250</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>510</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-10 near Singtham connecting Damthang, Legship and terminating at Geyzing in the State of Sikkim.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>251</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>427</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-27 near Howli connecting Barpeta, Hajo and terminating at its junction with new NH No. 27 near Jalukbari in the State of Assam</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>252</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>329</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-29 near Manja connecting Diphu and terminating at its junction with new NH No. 27 near Lumding in the State of Assam</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>253</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>117A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-17 near Bilasipara connecting Kokrajhar and terminating at its junction with New NH-27 near Garubhasa in the State of Assam</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>254</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>715A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-27 near Nakhola connecting Jagiroad, Marigaon, Kaupati, Rowta, Udalguri, Khoirabari and terminating at Indo/Bhutan border in the State of Assam</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>255</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>127E</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-27 near Barama connecting Baska, Subankhata and terminating at Indo/Bhutan border in the State of Assam</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>256</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>326A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with new NH No. 326 near Mohana connecting Chandiput, Chheligada, Ramagiri Udayagiri, Raygarh, Parlakimidi, Kotabommali and terminating at its junction with NH-16 near Narasannapeta in the State of Odisha.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>257</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>702</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-2 near Chantongia connecting Longling, Lonhching, Mon, Lapa, Tizit in the State of Nagaland, Sonari and terminating at its junction with new NH No. 215 near Sapekhati in the State of Assam.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>258</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>702A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with new NH No 2 near Mokokchung connecting Zunheboto, Phek in the State of Nagaland and terminating at Jessam near new NH No. 29 in the State of Manipur.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>259</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>208</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-8 near Kumarghat connecting Kailashahar, Khowai and terminating at its junction with new NH-8 near Teliamura in the State of Tripura.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>260</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>108A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with new NH No. 8 near Jolaibari connecting Belonia and terminating at Indo/Bangladesh border.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>261</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>102C</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with new NH No. 102 near Palel and terminating at Chandel in the State of Manipur.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>262</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>103A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with new NH-3 near Hoshiarpur connecting Mahalpur, Gurhshankar, Nawanshahr, Balachur and terminating at its junction with new NH No. 205 near Rupnagar in the State of Punjab.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>263</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>703A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with new NH-3 near Jalandhar connecting Kapurthala, Sultanpur Lodhi, Pindi and terminating at its junction with new NH No. 54 near Makhu in the State of Punjab.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>264</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>512</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-12 near Gajol connecting Daulatpur, Bansihari, Gangarampur, Harsura, Balurghat and terminating at Hilli in the State of West Bengal near Indo/Bangladesh Border.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>265</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>754</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with new NH-54 near Kot Kapurthala connecting Khara, Muktsar, Saidoke and terminating at Jalalabad in the State of Punjab.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>266</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>185</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with new NH No. 85 near Adimali connecting Cheruthoni, Painavu and terminating at its junction with new NH No. 183 near Kumily in the State of Kerala.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>267</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>183A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with new NH No. 183 near Adur connecting Pathanamthitta, Vadserikkara, Lahai, and terminating at its junction with new NH No. 183 near Vandiperiyar in the State of Kerala.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>268</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>333A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-33 near Bar Bigha connecting Shekhpura, Sikandra, Jamui, Jha-Jha, Banka in the State of Bihar and terminating at its junction with NH-133 near Godda in the State of Jharkhand.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>269</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>527A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with new NH No. 527 B near Pokhrauni Chowk connecting Madhubani, Rampatti and terminating at its junction with new NH No. 27 near Jhanjharpur in the State of Bihar.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>270</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>219</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with new NH No. 19 near Mohania connecting Bhabhua, Chainpur, Chand in the State of Bihar and terminating at its junction with NH-19 near Chandauli in the state of Uttar Pradesh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>271</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>753</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-53 near Duggipar connecting Goregaon, and terminating at Gondia in the State of Maharashtra.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>272</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>753A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-53 near Malkapur connecting Buldhana, Chikhli, Deulgaon Raja, Jalna and terminating near Aurangabad on NH-52 in the State of Maharashtra.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>273</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>753B</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-53 near Shevali connecting Nizampur, Chhadvel, Nundurbar, Taloda, Akkalkura in the State of Maharashtra, Dediapada and terminating at Netrang on NH-56 in the State of Gujarat.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>274</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>166A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from Vadkhal on NH-66 and terminating at Alibag inthe State of Maharashtra.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>275</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>130D</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-30 on Kondagaon and terminating at Narainpur in the State of Chhattisgarh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>276</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>163A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from Geedam(Gidam) on NH-63 and terminating at Dantewara in the State of Chhattisgarh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>277</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>149B</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-49 near Champa connecting Korba, Chhuri and terminating at its junction with new NH No. 130 near Katghora in the State of Chhattisgarh</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>278</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>130C</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-30 near Abhanpur connecting Rajim, Gariaband, Bardula, Deobhog in the State of Chhattisgarh and terminating at its junction with new NH No. 201 near Baldhimal in the State of Odisha.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>279</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>930</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-30 near Purur connecting Balod, Kusumkasa, Kumhari, Manpur in the State of Chhattisgarh, Muramgaon, Dhanora, Gadchiroli, Mul, Chandrapur, Warora, Wani and terminating near Karanji on NH-44 in the State of Maharashtra.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>280</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>130A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-30 near Pondi connecting Pandaria, Mungeli, and terminating at NH-130 on Bilaspur in the State of Chhattisgarh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>281</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>130B</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from Raipur on NH-30 connecting Palari, Baloda Bazar, Kasdol and terminating at its junction with NH No. 153 near Sarangarh in the State of Chhattisgarh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>282</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>133A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-33 near Baharwa connecting Pakur in the State of Jharkhand and terminating with NH-12 near Nimtala in the State of West Bengal.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>283</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>419</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-19 near Kulti in the State of West Bengal connecting Chittaranjan, Jamtara and terminating at Gobindpur in the State of Jharkhand.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>284</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>143A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-43 near Gumla connecting Ghaghra, Lohardaga and terminating at its junction with NH-39 near Kuru in the State of Jharkhand.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>288</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>713</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The Highway starting from its junction with NH-13 near Joram connecting Palin, Sangram and terminating at Koloriang in the State of Arunachal Pradesh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>289</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>513</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The Highway starting from its junction with NH-13 near Passighat connecting Mariyang and terminating at Yingkiong in the State of Arunachal Pradesh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>290</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>313</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The Highway starting from its junction with NH-13 near Meka and terminating near Anini in the State of Arunachal Pradesh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>291</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>113</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The Highway starting from its junction with NH-13 near Hawacamp connecting Hayuliang and terminating near Hawai in the State of Arunachal Pradesh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>292</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>713A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The Highway starting from its junction with NH-13 near Hoj connecting Yupia and terminating at its junction with NH-415 near Pappu (near Nahurlagun) in the State of Arunachal Pradesh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>293</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>341</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-41 near Bhimasar connecting Anjar, Bhuj, Khavda and terminating at Dharmshala in the State of Gujarat.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>294</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>147A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-47 near Limbdi connecting Surendranagar, Dhrangadhra and terminating at Kuda in the State of Gujarat.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>295</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>351</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-51 near Mahuva connecting Saverkundla, Amreli, Bagasara and terminating at Jetpur on NH-27 in the State of Gujarat.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>296</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>953</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-53 near Songudh connecting Ahwa in the State of Gujarat, Sarad, Vani and terminating at its junction with NH-60 near Pimpalgaon Baswant in the State of Maharashtra.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>297</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>927D</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-27 near Dhoraji connecting Jamkandorna, Kalavad and terminating at Jamnagar in the State of Gujarat.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>298</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>348 A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with NH-348 near Jawahar Lal Nehru Port Trust connecting Gavanphata section of SH-54 (Km. 5.300 to km. 14.550), Amara Marg (km. 0.000 to km. 6.500) and terminating at its junction with Palm Beach Road in the State of Maharashtra.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>313</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>709A</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>The highway starting from its junction with new NH No. 709 at Bhiwani connecting Mundal, Jind, Karnal in the State of Haryana, Shamli, Budhana and terminating at its junction with new NH No. 34 at Meerut in the State of Uttar Pradesh.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </table>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
