<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1985/16/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1985/16"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Maharashtra Abolition Of Subsisting Proprietary Rights To Mines And Minerals In Certain Lands Act, 1985"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1985/16/eng@2017-02-10/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1985/16/eng@2017-02-10"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-02-10" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1985/16/eng@2017-02-10/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1985/16/eng@2017-02-10"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-02-10" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Maharashtra Abolition Of Subsisting Proprietary Rights To Mines And Minerals In Certain Lands Act, 1985</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>(Act No. 16 of 1985)</p>
      </longTitle>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[06th August 1985]</docDate>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>An Act to abolish subsisting proprictary rights to mines and minerals in any lands under the Land Torture Abolition Laws or such other laws for the lime being in force by acquisition thereof and to provide for matters connected therewith.</p>
      <p>WHEREAS, pursuant to the national policy of bringing the actual cultivator into direct relation with the Government, series of land tenure abolition laws for abolition of the intermediary rights, Jagirs and inam tenures have had been enacted, the rights of Inamdars and Jagirdars to mines and minerals have had been specifically saved, thereby allowing such existing rights to survive particularly where the inams are grants of soil;</p>
      <p>AND WHEREAS, the mines and minerals available in these inam Jahds are being exploited in the State by such Inamdars for individual gains without being liable to pay any royalty to the State Government and in a manner highly detrimental and prejudicial to public interest;</p>
      <p>AND WHEREAS, with a view to prevent such exloitation of mines and minerals for individual pains by a few Inamdars and also to prevent the huge loss of royalty by the State Government and to give effect to the policy of the State Government towards securing that the ownership and control of the material resources of the community are so distributed as best to subserve the common good and that the operation of the economic system docs not result in the concentration of wealth and means of production to the common detriment;</p>
      <p>AND WHEREAS, for the aforesaid purposes it is considered necessary to abolish subsisting proprietary rights to mines and minerals in any lands under the Land Tenure Abolition Laws or such other laws for the time being in force by acquisition thereof and to provide for matters connected therewith; It is hereby enacted in the Thiry-sixth Year of the Republic of India as follows:-</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, and extent.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Maharashtra Abolition of Subsisting Proprietary Rights to Mines and Minerals in certain Lands Act, 1985.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Maharashtra.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Declaration.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>It is hereby declared that this Act is for giving effect to the policy of the State towards securing the principles specified in clauses (A) and (c) of Article 39 of the Constitution of India and the acquisition therefor of the subsisting proprietary rights to mines and minerals referred to in section 4.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"alienee" means an Inamdar, Jagirdar or Estate Holder as defined in the Land Tenure Abolition Laws or such other laws for the time being in force, or a person who holds any subsisting right in any sub-soil in any land under any settlement, kaul, grant, sanad of order, any judgement, order or decree of a Court or Tribunal or any law or instrument for the time being in force, but shall not include any lawful lessee holding lease-hold rights in respect of any mines or minerals on the date of commencement of this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"Code" means the Maharashtra Land Revenue Code, 1966 (Man. XLI of 1966.);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>"Competent Authority" means the Collector of the District, and includes any officer, not below the rank of Deputy Collector, to whom; the powers find functions of the Competent Authority may be entrusted by the Collector;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>"Land Tenure Abolition Laws" means the Salsette Estate (Land Revenue Exemption Abolition) Act, 1951(Bom.XLVII of 1951), the Bombay Personal Inams Abolition Act, 1952(Bom. XXX-IX of'1952.), the Bombay Merged Territories and Areas (Jagirs Abolition) Act, 1953(Bom. XXII of'1953.), the Bombay Merged Territories Miscllaneous Alienation Abolition Act, 1955(Bom. XXX-IX of 1954.), and the Bombay City (Inami and Special Tenures) Abolition and Maharashtra Land Revenue Code (Amendment) Act, 1969(Mah. XLIV of 1959.);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>"prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>"sub-soil rights" means any rights to mines and minerals found or likely to be found, whether on surface or underground of any land;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>words and expressions used but not defined in this Act, shall have the meanings assigned to them in the Code.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Vesting of rights of aliences to mines and minerals in the State and consequences thereof.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Save as otherwise provided in this Act, notwithstanding anything contained in any settlement, kaul, grant, sanad or order, any judgement, order or decree of a Court or Tribunal or in any law or instrument for the time being in force, on the date of commencement of this Act, all subsisting rights to mines and minerals vesting in any alienee in any land shall pass from such person to and vest in the State Government, free of any encumbrances:</p>
            <p>Provided that, the rights of any lessee, holding on lease the sub-soil rights on the date of commencement of this Act, either from alienee or from Government, shall not be affected by this section except that on and from the said date if he is a (seek)lesses holding from alienee he shall be deemed to be a lessee holding from Government, and all the obligations to the alienee shall be deemed to have passed on to Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Payment of amount for Requisition of rights to mines and minerals.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any alienee having any subsisting sub-soil right in respect of any land immediately before the date of commencement of this Act, shall, subject to this following provisions of this section, be, entitled--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to receive an amount equivalent to three times the assessment fixed for the land, in which there is a mine or there are minerals, but the mine is not worked during a period of three years immediately preceding the date of commencement of this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>where any mine was worked at any time during a period of three years immediately preceding the date of commencement of this Act, to receive an-amount equivalent to twenty times the assessment fixed for the land.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every alienee entitled to the amount under sub-section (1) shall apply in writing to the Competent Authority, on or before the 31st December 1985 or such extended date (if any) as the Competent Authority may fix, for determining the amount payable to him under this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Procedure for determining the amount to be paid.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>On receipt of an application for determination of the amount payable under section 5, the Competent Authority shall make such inquiry as he deems fit. After giving a reasonable opportunity of being heard to the claimant and to prove his claim, the Competent Authority shall make an award determining the amount payable to the claimant, after recording his findings on the following points --</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>whether the claimant alienee proved that any rights to mines and minerals in any land had accrued to him and were subsisting at the date of commencement of this Act, notwithstanding the provisions of any law for the time being in force;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the area of the lend under which there is a mine and what mineral sare found therein;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the area of the land under which, there is a working mine end what minerals are found therein;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the amount, if any, payable to the claimant in accordance with the provisions of this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>where there is a co-sharer, how the amount may be apportioned between the claimant and the co-sharer.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time being in force, the onus of proving before the Competent Authority--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>that the sub-soil rights in any land had accrued to the claimant under any sanad, etc., and the rights continued to subsist at the commencement of this Act, notwithstanding the provisions of any law for the time being in force; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>that any mines of minerals are found or are being worked in any land or part thereof;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall be on the claimant.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Appeal against Competent Authority's award.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>An appeal shall lie against the award of the Competent Authority to the Maharashtra Revenue Tribunal established under Chapter XV of the Maharashtra Land Revenue Code, 1966 (Mah. XLI of 1966.); not withstanding anything contained in that Code.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Procedure before Maharashtra Revenue Tribunal.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Maharashtra Revenue Tribunal shall, after giving notice to the appellant and the State Government, decide the appeal and record its decision.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In deciding an apneal under this Act, the Maharashtra Revenue Tribunal shall exercise all the powers which a Court has and shall follow the same procedure which a Court follows, in deciding an appeal from a decree or order of an original Court under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908(V of 1908.).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Limitation.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every appeal made under this Act to the Maharashtra Revenue Tribunal shall be filed within a period of sixty days from the date of the award of the Competent Authority The provisions of sections 4, 5, 12 and 14 or the Limitation Act, 1963 (XXX-VI of 1963.), shall apply to the filing of such appeal.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Court-fees.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Bombay Court-fees Act, 1959 (Bom. XXXVI of 1959.), every appeal under this Act to the Maharashtra Revenue Tribunal shall bear a court-fee stamp of such value as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Finality of award and decision of Revenue Tribunal.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>An award made by the Competent Authority, subject to an appeal to the Maharashtra Revenue Tribunal, and the decision of the Maharashtra Revenue Tribunal on the appeal, shall be final and conclusive and shall not to questioned in any suit or proceedings in any Court.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Inquiries and proceedings to be judicial proceedings.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>All inquiries and proceedings before the Competent Authority and the Maharashtra Revenue Tribunal under this Act shall be deemed to be judicial proceeding within the meaning of section 193, 219 and 228 of the Indian Penal code (XLV of 1860.)</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rule for the purposes of giving effect to the provisions of this Act, including provisions for imposition of fees for the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All rules made under this section shall be subject to the condition of previous publication.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as" soon as may be after it is made before each House of the State legislature while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days, which may be comprised in one session or in two successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session if which it is-so laid or the session immediately following, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, and notify such decision in the Official Gazette, the rule shall, from the date of publication of such notification; have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done or omitted to be done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of section 48 of Mali. XLI of 1966.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In the Maharashtra Land Revenue Code, 1966, in section 48; in sub-section (1),-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for the words "Unless it is otherwise expressly provided by the terms of the grant made by the State Government, the right to all minerals" the words "The right to all minerals" shall be substituted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the proviso shall be deleted.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Repeal of certain enactments.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>On and from the date of commencement of this Act, section 9 of the Bombay Personal lnams Abolition Act, 1952(Bom. XLII of 1952), section 10 of the Bombay Merged Territories and Areas (Jagirs Abolition) Act, 1953(Bom. XXXIX of 1953) , section 13 of the Bombay Merged Territories Miscellaneous Alienations Abolition Act, 1955 (Bom. XXII of 1955) and section 9 of the Bombay City (Inami and Special Tenures) Abolition and Maharashtra Land Revenue Code (Amendment) Act, 1969 (Mah. XLIV of 1969), and corresponding provision in any such law for the time being in force, shall stand repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Power to remove difficulty.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the State Government may, as occasion arises, by order do anything, not inconsistent with such provisions which appears to it to be necessary or expedient for the purpose of removing the difficulty:</p>
            <p>Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a period of two years from the date of commencement of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
