<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1972/20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1972/20"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Architects Act, 1972"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1972/20/eng@1972-05-31/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1972/20/eng@1972-05-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1972-05-31" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1972/20/eng@1972-05-31/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1972/20/eng@1972-05-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-11-18" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Architects Act, 1972</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[Act, No. 20 OF 1972]</p>
      </longTitle>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[31st May, 1972]</docDate>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>An Act to provide for the registration of architects and for matters connected therewith.</p>
      <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty-third Year of the Republic of India as follows:-</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement .-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Architects Act, 1972.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India .</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this, Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"architect" means a person whose name is for the time being entered in the register;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"Council" means the Council of Architecture constituted under section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>"Indian Institute of Architects" means the Indian Institute of Architects registered under the Societies Registration Act, 1860 (21 of 1860);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>"recognized qualification" means any qualification in architecture for the time being included in the Schedule or notified under section 15;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>"register" means the register of architects maintained under section 23;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>"regulation" means a regulation made under this Act by the Council;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>"rule" means a rule made under this Act by the Central Government.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of Council of Architecture.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute, with effect from such date as may be specified in the notification, a Council to be known as the Council of Architecture, which shall be a body corporate, having perpetual succession and a common seal, with power to acquire, hold and dispose of property, both movable and immovable, and to contract, and may by that name sue or be sued.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Head Officer of the Council shall be at Delhi or at such other place as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Council shall consist of the following members, namely :-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>five architects possessing recognized qualifications elected by the Indian Institute of Architects from among its members :</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>two persons nominated by the All India Council for Technical Education established by the Resolution of the Government of India in the late Ministry of Education No.F.16-10/44-E.III, dated the 30th November, 1945;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.3.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>five person selected from among themselves by heads of architectural institutions in India imparting full-time instruction for recognized qualifications;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.3.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the Chief Architects in the Ministries of the Central Government to which the Government business relating to defense and railways has been allotted and the head of the Architectural Organization in the Central Public Works Department, ex officio;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.3.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>one person nominated by the Central Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.3.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>an architect from each State nominated by the Government of that State</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.3.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>two person nominated by the Institution of Engineers (India) from among its members; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.3.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>one person nominated by the Institution of Surveyors of India from among its members.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.3.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation.- For the purposes of this sub-section,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.3.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" Institution of Engineers (India)" means the Institution of Engineers (India first registered in 1920 under the India Companies Act, 1913 (7 of 1913) and subsequently incorporated by a Royal Charter in 1935.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.3.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"Institution of Surveyors of India" means the Institution of Surveyors registered under the Societies Registration Act, 1860 (21 of 1860).</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in clause (a) of sub-section (3), the Central Government may, pending the preparation of the register, nominate to the first Council, in consultation with the Indian Institution of Architects, persons referred to in the said clause (a) who are qualified for registration under section 25, and the persons so nominated shall hold officer for such period as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in clause (f) of sub-section (3), the Central Government may, pending the preparation of the register, nominate to the first Council, in consultation with the State Governments concerned, persons referred to in the said clause (f), who are qualified for registration under section 25, and the person so nominated shall hold officer for such period as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>President and Vice-President of Council.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The President and the Vice-President of the Council shall be elected by the members of the Council from among themselves :</p>
            <p>Provided that on the first constitution of the Council and until the President is elected, a member of the Council nominated by the Central Government in this behalf shall discharge the functions of the President.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An elected President or Vice-President of the Council shall hold officer for a term of three years or till he ceases to be a member of the Council, whichever is earlier, but subject to his being a member of the Council, he shall be eligible for re-election :</p>
            <blockList id="section-4.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.2.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the President or the Vice-President may, by writing under his hand addressed to the Vice-president or the President, as the case may be resign his office;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.2.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the President or the Vice-President shall, notwithstanding the expiry of this term of three years, continue to hold officer until his successor enters upon office.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The President and the Vice-president of the Council shall exercise such powers and discharge such duties as may be prescribed by regulations.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Mode of elections.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Elections under this Chapter shall be conducted in such manner as may be prescribed by rules.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any dispute arises regarding any such election, the matter shall be referred by the Council to a Tribunal appointed by the Central Government by notification in the Official Gazette in this behalf, and the decision of the Tribunal shall be final :</p>
            <p>Provided that no such reference shall be made except on an application made to the Council by an aggrieved party within thirty days from the date of the declaration of the result of the election.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The expenses of the Tribunal shall be borne by the Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Terms of office and casual vacancies.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provision s of this section, an elected or nominated member shall hold officer for a term of three years from the date of his election or nomination or until his successor has been duly elected or nominated, whichever is later.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An elected or nominated member may, at any time, resign his membership by writing under his hand addressed to the President, or in his absence, to the Vice-President, and the seat of such member shall thereupon become vacant.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A member shall be deemed to have vacated his seat-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.3.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>if he is absent without excuse, sufficient in the opinion of the Council, from three consecutive ordinary meetings of the Council; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.3.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>if he ceases to be a member of the body referred to in clause (a), clause (g) or clause (h) of sub-section (3) of section 3 by which he was elected or nominated, as the case may be; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.3.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>in the case where he has been elected under clause (c) of sub-section (3) of section 3, if the ceases to hold his appointment as the head of an institution referred to in the said clause.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>casual vacancy in the Council shall be filled by fresh election or nomination, as the case may be, and the person so elected or nominated to fill the vacancy shall hold office only for the remainder of the term for which the member whose place he takes was elected or nominated.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Members of the Council shall be eligible for re-election or re-nomination, but not exceeding three consecutive terms.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Validity of act or proceeding of Council, Executive Committee or other committees not to be invalidated by reason of vacancy, etc.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>No act or proceeding of the Council or the Executive Committee or any other committee shall be invalid merely by reason of-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any vacancy in, or defect in the constitution of, the Council, the Executive committee or any other committee, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any defect in the election or nomination of a person acting as a member there of, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any irregularity in procedure not affecting the merits of the case.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Disabilities.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A person shall not be eligible for election or nomination as a member of the Council, if he-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>is an undischarged insolvent; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>has been convicted by a court in India for any offence and sentenced to imprisonment for not less than two years, and shall continue to be ineligible for a further period of five years since his release.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Meetings of Council.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Council shall meet at least once in every six months at such time and place and shall observe such rules of procedure in regard to the transaction of business at its meetings as may be prescribed by regulations.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Unless otherwise prescribed by regulations, nine members of the Council shall form a quorum, and all the acts of the Council shall be decided by a majority of the members present and voting.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the case of an equal division of votes, the President, or in his absence, the Vice-President or, in the absence of both , the member presiding over the meeting, shall have and exercise a second or casting vote.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Executive Committee and other committees.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Council shall constitute from among its members an Executive Committee, and may also constitute other committees for such general or special purposes as the Council deems necessary to carry out its functions under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Executive Committee shall consist of the President and the Vice-President of the Council who shall be member ex-officio and five other members who shall be elected by the Council from among its members.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The President and the Vice-president of the Council shall be the Chairman and Vice-Chairman respectively of the Executive Committee.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A member of the Executive Committee shall hold office as such until the expiry of his term as a member of the Council but subject to his being a member of the Council, he shall be eligible for re-election.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In addition to the powers and duties conferred and imposed on it by this Act, the Executive committee shall exercise such powers and discharge such duties as may be prescribed by regulations.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Fees and allowances to President, Vice President and members.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The President, the Vice-President and other members of the Council shall be entitled to such fees and allowances as the Council may, with the previous sanction of the Central Government fix, in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Officers and other employees.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-12.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Council shall-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>appoint a Registrar who shall act as its Secretary and who may also act, if so decided by the Council, as its treasurer;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>appoint such other officers and employees as the Council deems necessary to enable it to carry out its functions under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>with the previous sanction of the Central Government, fix the pay and allowances and other conditions of service of officers and other employees of the Council.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in clause (a) of sub-section (1), for the first three years from the first constitution of the Council, the Registrar of the Council shall be a person appointed by the Central Government, who shall hold office during the pleasure of the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All the persons appointed under this section shall be the employees of the Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Finances of Council.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be established a Fund under the management and control of the Council in to which shall be paid all moneys received by the Council and out of which shall be met all expenses and liabilities properly incurred by the Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Council may invest any money for the time being standing to the credit of the Fund in any Government security or in any other security approved by the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Council shall keep proper accounts of the Fund distinguishing capital from revenue.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The annual accounts of the Council shall be subject to audit by an auditor to be appointed annually by the Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>As soon as may be practicable at the end of each year, but no later than the thirtieth day of September of the year next following, the Council shall cause to be published in the Official Gazette a copy of the audited accounts and the report of the Council for that year and copies of the said accounts and report shall be forwarded to the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13.6.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Fund shall consist of-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.6.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>all moneys received from the Central Government by way of grant, gift or deposit;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.6.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any sums received under this Act whether by way of fee or otherwise.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All moneys standing at the credit of the Council which cannot immediately be applied shall be deposited in the State Bank of India or in any other bank specified in column 2 of the First Schedule to the Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings) Act, 1970 (5 of 1970)</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Recognition qualifications granted by authorities in India.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The qualifications included in the Schedule or notified under section 15 shall be recognized qualifications for the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any authority in India which grants an architectural qualification not included in the Schedule may apply to the Central Government to have such qualification recognized, and the Central Government, after consultation with the Council, may, by notification in the Official Gazette. Amend the Schedule so as to include such qualification therein, and any such notification may also direct that an entry shall be made in the Schedule against such architectural qualification declaring that it shall be a recognized qualification only when granted after a specified date :</p>
            <p>Provided that until the first Council is constituted, the Central Government shall, before issuing any notification as aforesaid, consult an expert committee consisting of three members to be appointed by the Central Government by notification in the Official Gazette.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Recognition of architectural qualifications granted by authorities in foreign countries.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, after consultation with the Council, direct, by notification in the Official Gazette, that an architectural qualification granted by any university or other institution in any country outside India in respect of which a scheme of reciprocity for the recognition of architectural qualification is not in force, shall be a recognized qualification for the purposes of this Act or, shall be so only when granted after a specified date or before a specified date :</p>
            <p>Provided that until the first Council is constituted the Central Government shall, before issuing any notification as aforesaid, consult the expert committee set up under the proviso to sub-section (2) of section 14.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Council may enter into negotiations with the authority in any State or country outside India, which by the law of such State or country is entrusted with the maintenance of a register of architects, for settling of a scheme of reciprocity for the recognition of architectural qualifications, and in pursuance of any such scheme, the central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that such architectural qualification as the Council has decided should be recognized, shall be deemed to be a recognized qualification for the purposes of this Act, any such notification may also direct that such architectural qualification shall be so recognized only when granted after a specified date or before a specified date.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to amend Schedule.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (2) of section 14, the Central Government, after consultation with the Council, may, by notification in the Official Gazette, amend the Schedule by directing that an entry be made therein in respect of any architectural qualification.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Effect of recognition.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law, but subject to the provisions of this Act, any recognized qualification shall be a sufficient qualification for enrolment in the register.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Power require information as to courses of study and examinations.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every authority in India which grants a recognized qualification shall furnish such information as the Council may, from time to time, require as to the courses of study and examinations to be undergone in order to obtain such qualification, as to the ages at which such courses of study and examinations are required to be undergone and such qualification is conferred and generally as to the requisites for obtaining such qualification.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Inspections of examinations.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-19.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Executive Committee shall, subject to regulations, if any, made by the Council, appoint such number of inspectors as it may deem requisite to inspect any college or institution where architectural education is given or to attend any examination held by any college or institution for the purpose of recommending to the Central Government recognition of architectural qualifications granted by that college or institution.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The inspector shall not interfere with the conduct of any training or examination, but shall report to the Executive Committee on the adequacy of the standards of architectural education including staff, equipment, accommodation, training and such other facilities as may be prescribed by regulations for giving such education or on the sufficiency of every examination which they attend.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Executive committee shall forward a copy of such report to the College or institution and shall also forward copies with remarks, if any, of the college or institution thereon, to the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Withdrawal of recognition.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-20.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-20.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>When upon report by the Executive Committee it appears to the Council-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-20.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>that the courses of study and examination to be undergone in, or the proficiency required from the candidates at any examination held by, any college or institution, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-20.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>that the staff, equipment, accommodation, training and other facilities for staff and training provided in such college or institution, do not conform to the standards prescribed by regulations, the council shall make a representation to that effect to the appropriate Government.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>After considering such representation the appropriate Government shall forward it along with such remarks as it may choose to make to the college or institution concerned, with an intimation of the period within which the college or institution, as the case may be, may submit its explanation to the appropriate Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On receipt of the explanation or where no explanation is submitted within the period fixed, then on the expiry of that period, the State Government, in respect of the college or institution referred to in clause (b) of sub-section (5), shall make its recommendations to the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-20.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-20.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>after making such further enquiry, if any, as it may think fit, in respect of the college or institution referred to in sub-section (3), or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-20.4.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>on receipt of the explanation from a college or institution referred to in clause (a) of sub-section (5), or where no explanation is submitted within the period fixed, then on the expiry of that period, may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that an entry shall be made in the Schedule against the architectural qualification awarded by such college or institution, as the case may be, l declaring that it shall be a recognized qualification only when granted before a specified date and the Schedule shall be deemed to be amended accordingly.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-20.5.list1">
              <listIntroduction>For the purposes of this section, "appropriate government" means-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-20.5.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in relation to any college or institution established by an Act of Parliament or managed , controlled or financed by the Central Government, the Central Government, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-20.5.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in any other case the State Government.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Minimum standard of architectural education.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Council may prescribe the minimum standards of architectural education required for granting recognized qualifications by colleges or institutions in India.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Professional conduct.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-22.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Council may by regulations prescribe standards of professional conduct and etiquette and a code of ethics for architects.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-22.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Regulations made by the Council under sub-section (1) may specify which violations thereof shall constitute infamous conduct in any professional respect, that is to say, professional misconduct, and such provision shall have effect notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Preparation and maintenance of register.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-23.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government shall, as soon as may be, cause to be prepared in the manner hereinafter provided a register of architects for India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Council shall upon its constitution assume the duty of maintaining the register in accordance with the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-23.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The register shall include the following particulars, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-23.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the full name with date of birth, nationality and residential address of the architect;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-23.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>his qualification for registration, and the date on which he obtained that qualification and the authority which conferred it;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-23.3.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the date of this first admission to the register;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-23.3.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>his professional address; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-23.3.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>such further particulars as may be prescribed by rules.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>First preparation of register.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-24.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purposes of preparing the register of architects for the first time, the Central Government shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute a Registration Tribunal consisting of three persons who have, in the opinion of the Central Government, the knowledge of, or experience in, architecture; and the Registrar appointed under section 12 shall act as Secretary of the Tribunal.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government shall, by the same or a like notification, appoint a date on or before which application for registration, which shall be accompanied by such fee as may be prescribe by rules, shall be made to the Registration Tribunal.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Registration Tribunal shall examine every application received on or before the appointed day and if it is satisfied that the applicant is qualified for registration under section 25, shall direct the entry of the name of the applicant in the register.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The first register so prepared shall thereafter be published in such manner as the Central Government may direct and any person aggrieved by a decision of the Registration Tribunal expressed or implied in the register so published may, within thirty days from the date of such publication, appeal against such decision to an authority appointed by the Central Government in this behalf by notification in the Official Gazette.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The authority appointed under sub-section (4) shall, after giving the person affected an opportunity of being heard and after calling for relevant records, make such order as it may deem fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Registrar shall amend, where necessary, the register in accordance with the decisions of the authority appointed under sub-section (4).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every person whose name is entered in the register shall be issued a certificate of registration in such form as may be prescribed by rules.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon the constitution of the Council, the register shall be given into its custody, and the Central Government may direct that the whole or any specified part of the application fees for registration in the first register shall be paid to the credit of the Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Qualification for entry in register.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-25.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A person shall be entitled on payment of such fee as may be prescribed by rules to have his name entered in the register, if he resides or carries on the profession of architect in India and-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>holds a recognized qualification, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>does not hold such a qualification but, being a citizen of India, has been engaged in practice as an architect for a period of not less than five years prior to the date appointed under sub-section (2) of section 24, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>possesses such other qualifications as may be prescribed by rules :</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-25.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that no person other than a citizen of India shall be entitled to registration by virtue of a qualification-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>recognized under sub-section (1) of section 15 unless by the law and practice of a country outside India to which such person belongs, citizens of India holding architectural qualification registrable in that country are permitted to enter and practice the profession of architect in such country, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>unless the Central Government has, in pursuance of a scheme of reciprocity or otherwise, declared that qualification to be a recognized qualification under sub-section (2) of section 15.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Procedure for subsequent registration.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-26.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>After the date appointed for the receipt of applications for registration in the first register of architects, all applications of registration shall be addressed to the Registrar of the Council and shall be accompanied by such fees as may be prescribed by rules.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If upon such application the Register is of opinion that the applicant is entitled to have his name entered in the register he shall enter thereon the name of the applicant :</p>
            <p>Provided that no person, whose name has under the provisions of this Act been removed from the register, shall be entitled to have his name re-entered in the register except with the approval of the Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person whose application for registration is rejected by the Registrar may, within three months of the date of such rejection, appeal to the Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon entry in the register of a name under this section, the Registrar shall issue a certificate of registration in such form as may be prescribed by rules.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Renewal fees.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-27.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that for the retention of a name in the register after the 31st day of December of the year following the year in which the name is first entered in the register, there shall be paid annually to the Council such renewal fee as may be prescribed by rules and where such direction has been made, such renewal fee shall be due to be paid before the first day of April of the year to which it relates.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the renewal fee is not paid before the due date, the Registrar shall remove the name of the defaulter from the register :</p>
            <p>Provided that a name so removed may be restored to the register on, such conditions as may be prescribed by rules.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On payment of the renewal fee the Registrar shall, in such manner as may be prescribed by rules, endorse the certificate of registration accordingly.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28">
        <num>28.</num>
        <heading>Entry of additional qualification.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>An architect shall, on payment of such fee as may be prescribed by rules, be entitled to have entered in the register any further recognized qualification which he may obtain.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29">
        <num>29.</num>
        <heading>Removal from register.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-29.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-29.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Council may, by order, removing from the register the name of any architect-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-29.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>from whom a request has been received to that effect, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-29.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>who has died since the last publication of the register.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-29.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Subject to the provisions of this section, the Council may order that the name of any architect shall be removed from the register where it is satisfied, after giving him a reasonable opportunity of being heard and after such further inquiry, if any, as it may think fit to make,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-29.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>that his name has been entered in the register by error or on account of misrepresentation or suppression of a material fact; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-29.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>that he has been convicted of any offence which, in the opinion of the Council, involves moral turpitude; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-29.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>that he is an undischarged insolvent; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-29.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>that he has been adjudged by a competent court to be of unsound mind.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An order under sub-section (2) may direct that any architect whose name is ordered to be removed from a register shall be ineligible for registration under this Act for such period as may be specified.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An order under sub-section 92) shall not take effect until the expiry of three months from the date thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-30">
        <num>30.</num>
        <heading>Procedure in inquiries relating to misconduct.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-30.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When on receipt of a complain made to it, the Council is of opinion that any architect has been guilty of professional misconduct which, if proved, will render him unfit to practice as an architect, the Council may hold an inquiry in such manner as may be prescribed by rules.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-30.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>After holding the inquiry under sub-section (1) and after hearing the architect, the Council may, by order, reprimand the said architect or suspend him from practice as an architect or remove his name from the register or pass such other order as it thinks fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-31">
        <num>31.</num>
        <heading>Surrender of certificates.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-31.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A person whose name has been removed from the register under sub-section (2) of section 27, sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) of section 29 of sub-section (2) of section 30, or where such person is dead, his legal representative, as defined in clause (11) of section 2 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908, (5 of 1908) shall forthwith surrender his certificate of registration to the Registrar, and the name so removed shall be published in the Official Gazette.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-32">
        <num>32.</num>
        <heading>Restoration to register .-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-32.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Council may, at any time, for reasons appearing to it to be sufficient and subject to the approval of the Central Government, order that upon payment of such fee as may be prescribed by rules, the name of the person removed from the register shall be restored thereto.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-33">
        <num>33.</num>
        <heading>Issue of duplicate certificates.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-33.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where it is shown to the satisfaction of the Registrar that a certificate of registration has been lost or destroyed, the Registrar may, on payment of such fee as may be prescribed by rules, issue a duplicate certificate in the form prescribed by rules.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-34">
        <num>34.</num>
        <heading>Printing of register.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-34.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>As soon as may be after the 1st day of April in each year, the Registrar shall cause to be printed copies of the register as it stood on the said date and such copies shall be made available to person applying therefor on payment of such fees as may be prescribed by rules and shall be evidence that on the said date the person whose names are entered therein were architects.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-35">
        <num>35.</num>
        <heading>Effect of registration.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-35.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any reference in any law for the time being in force to an architect shall be deemed to be a reference to an architect registered under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-35.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>After the expiry of two years from the date appointed under sub-section (2) of section 24, a person who is registered in the register shall get preference for appointment as an architect under the Central or State Government or in any other local body or institution which is supported or aided from the public or local funds or in any institution recognized by the Central of State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-36">
        <num>36.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for falsely claiming to be registered.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-36.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any person whose name is not for the time being entered in the register falsely represents that it so entered, or uses in connection with his name or title any words or letters reasonably calculated to suggest that his name is so entered, he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-37">
        <num>37.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition against use of title.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-37.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>After the expiry of one year from the date appointed under sub-section (2) of section 24, no person other than a registered architect, or a firm of architects shall use the title and style of architect:</p>
            <blockList id="section-37.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that the provisions of this section shall not apply to-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-37.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>practice of the profession of an architect by a person designated as a "landscape architect" or "naval architect";</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-37.1.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-37.1.list2.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>a person who, carrying on the profession of an architect in any country outside India, undertakes the function as a consultant or designer in India for a specific project with the prior permission of the Central Government.</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-37.1.list2.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>"landscape architect" means a person who deals with the design of open spaces relating to plants trees and landscape;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-37.1.list2.b.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>"naval architect" means an architect who deals with design and construction of ships.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-37.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person contravenes the provision s of sub-section (1), he shall be punishable on first conviction with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees and on any subsequent conviction with imprisonment which may extend to six months or with fine not exceeding one thousand rupees or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-38">
        <num>38.</num>
        <heading>Failure to surrender certificate of registration.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-38.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any person whose name has been removed from the register fails without sufficient cause forthwith to surrender his certificate of registration, he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to one hundred rupees, and, in the case of a continuing failure, with an additional fine which may extend to ten rupees for each day after the first during which he has persisted in the failure.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-39">
        <num>39.</num>
        <heading>Cognizance of offences.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-39.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No Court shall take cognizance of any offence punishable under this Act, except upon complaint made by order of the Council or a person authorized in this behalf by the Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-39.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No Magistrate other than a Presidency Magistrate or a Magistrate of the first class shall try and offence punishable under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-40">
        <num>40.</num>
        <heading>Information to furnished by Council and publication thereof.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-40.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Council shall furnish such reports, copies of its minutes, and other information to the Central Government as that Government may require.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-40.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may publish, in such manner as it may think fit, any report, copy or other information furnished to it under this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-41">
        <num>41.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-41.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central Government, the Council or any member of the Council, the Executive Committee or any other committee or officers and other employees of the Council for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or any rule or regulation made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-42">
        <num>42.</num>
        <heading>Members of Council and officers and employees to be public servants.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-42.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The members of the Council and officers and other employees of the Council shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of section 21(45 of 1860) of the Indian Penal Code.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-43">
        <num>43.</num>
        <heading>Power to remove difficulties.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-43.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government may, by order published in the Official to Gazette, make such provisions not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as appear to it to be necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty:</p>
            <p>Provided that no such order shall be made under this section after the expiry of two years from the date of commencement of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-43.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every order made under this section shall, as soon as may be after it is made, be laid before each House of Parliament and the provisions of sub-section (3) of section 44 shall apply in respect of such order as it applies in respect of a rule made under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-44">
        <num>44.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to make rules.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-44.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-44.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-44.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following maters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-44.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the manner in which elections under Chapter II shall be conducted, the terms and conditions of service of the member of the Tribunal appointed under sub-section (2) of section 5 and the procedure to be followed by the Tribunal;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the procedure to be followed by the expert committee constituted under the proviso to sub-section (2) of section 14 in the transaction of its business and the powers and duties of the expert committee and the traveling and daily allowances payable to the members thereof;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the particulars to be included in the register of architects under sub-section (3) of section 23;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the form in which a certificate of registration is to be issued under sub-section (7) of Section 24, sub-section (4) of section 26 and section 33;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the fee to be paid under section 24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 32 and 33;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the conditions on which name may be restored to the register under the proviso to sub-section (2) of section 27;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the manner of endorsement under sub-section (3) of section 27;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the manner in which the Council shall hold an enquiry under section 30;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-44.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification to the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-45">
        <num>45.</num>
        <heading>Power of Council to make regulations.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-45.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Council may, with the approval of the Central Government, by notification in the Official Gazette make regulations not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, or the rules made thereunder to carry out the purpose of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-45.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-45.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such regulations may provide for-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-45.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the management of the property of the Council;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-45.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the power and duties of the President and the Vice-President of the Council;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-45.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the summoning and holding of meetings of the Council and the Executive Committee or any other committee constituted under section 10, the time and places at which such meetings shall be held, the conduct of business thereat and the number of person necessary to constitute a quorum;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-45.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the functions of the Executive Committee or of any other committee constituted under section 10;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-45.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the courses and periods of study and of practical training, if any, to be undertaken, the subjects of examinations and standards of proficiency therein to be obtained in any college or institution for grant of recognized qualifications;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-45.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the appointment, powers and duties of inspector;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-45.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the standards of staff, equipment, accommodation, training and other facilities for architectural education;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-45.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the conduct of professional examinations, qualifications of examiners and the conditions of admission to such examinations;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-45.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the standards of professional conduct and etiquette and code of ethics to be observed by architects;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-45.2.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>any other mater which is to be or may be provided by regulations under this Act and in respect of which no rules have been made.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-45.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every regulation made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the regulation or both Houses agree that the regulation should not be made, the regulation shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that regulation.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-theschedule">
      <doc name="theschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1972/20/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1972/20"/>
              <FRBRalias value="THE SCHEDULE"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1972/20/eng@1972-05-31/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1972/20/eng@1972-05-31"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1972/20/eng@1972-05-31/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1972/20/eng@1972-05-31"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-11-18" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="theschedule">
            <heading>(See section 14)</heading>
            <paragraph id="theschedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>QUALIFICATIONS</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <subsection id="theschedule.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Bachelor Degree in Architecture awarded by Indian Universities established by an Act of the Central or State Legislature.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>National Diploma (formerly All Indian Diploma) in Architecture awarded by the All India Council for Technical Education.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Degree of Bachelor of Architecture (B.Arch.) awarded by the Indian Institute of Technology, Kharagpur.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.4">
              <num>(4)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Five-Year full-time diploma in Architecture of the Sir J. J. School of Art, Bombay, awarded after 1941.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.5">
              <num>(5)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Diploma in Architecture awarded by the State Board of Technical Education and Training of the Government of Andhra Pradesh with effect from 1960 (for the students trained at the Government College of Arts and Architecture, Hyderabad).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.6">
              <num>(6)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Diploma in Architecture awarded by the Government College of Arts and Architecture, Hyderabad till 1959, subject to the condition that the candidates concerned have subsequently passed a special final examination in architecture held by the State Board of Technical Education, Andhra Pradesh and obtained a special certificate.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.7">
              <num>(7)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Diploma in Architecture awarded by the University of Nagpur with effect from 1965 to the students trained at the Government Polytechnic, Nagpur .</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.8">
              <num>(8)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Government Diploma in Architecture awarded by the Government of Maharashtra (or the former Government of Bombay).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.9">
              <num>(9)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Diploma in Architecture of Kalabhavan Technical Institute, Baroda.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.10">
              <num>(10)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Diploma in Architecture awarded by the School of Architecture, Ahmedabad.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.11">
              <num>(11)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Membership of the Indian Institute of Architects.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.13">
              <num>(13)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Bachelor Degree in Architecture awarded by the School of Planning and Architecture, New Delhi (an institution deemed to be a University) with effect from 3-12-1979.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.14">
              <num>(14)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Diploma in Architecture awarded by the Center for Environmental Planning and Technology (CEPT), Ahmedabad, with effect from 16-10-1980.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
