<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1961/28/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1961/28"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Dowry Prohibition Act, 1961"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1961/28/eng@1961-05-20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1961/28/eng@1961-05-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1961-05-20" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1961/28/eng@1961-05-20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1961/28/eng@1961-05-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-10-28" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Dowry Prohibition Act, 1961</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 28 OF 1961.</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[20th May, 1961]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to prohibit the giving or taking of dowry.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twelfth Year of the Republic of India as follows:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Dowry Prohibition Act, 1961.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definition of 'dowry'.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, “dowry” means any property or valuable security given or agreed to be given either directly or indirectly—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>by one party to a marriage to the other party to the marriage; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>by the parent of either party to a marriage or by any other person, to either party to the marriage or to any other person,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>at or before or any time after the marriage in connection with the marriage of the said parties, but does not include dower or mahr in the case of persons to whom the Muslim Personal Law (Shariat) applies.</p>
            <p>***</p>
            <p>Explanation II.— The expression “valuable security” has the same meaning as in section 30 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for giving or taking dowry.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person, after the commencement of this Act, gives or takes or abets the giving or taking of dowry, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than five years, and with fine which shall not be less than fifteen thousand rupees or the amount of the value of such dowry, whichever is more:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Court may, for adequate and special reasons to be recorded in the judgment, impose a sentence of imprisonment for a term of less than five years.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Nothing in sub-section (1) shall apply to, or in relation to,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>presents which are given at the time of a marriage to the bride (without any demand having been made in that behalf):</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that such presents are entered in a list maintained in accordance with the rules made under this Act;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>presents which are given at the time of a marriage to the bridegroom (without any demand having been made in that behalf):</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that such presents are entered in a list maintained in accordance with the rules made under this Act:</p>
            <p>Provided further that where such presents are made by or on behalf of the bride or any person related to the bride, such presents are of a customary nature and the value thereof is not excessive having regard to the financial status of the person by whom, or on whose behalf, such presents are given.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for demanding dowry.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any person demands, directly or indirectly, from the parents or other relatives or guardian of a bride or bridegroom, as the case may be, any dowry, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than six months, but which may extend to two years and with fine which may extend to ten thousand rupees:</p>
            <p>Provided that the court may, for adequate and special reasons to be mentioned in the judgment, impose a sentence of imprisonment for a term of less than six months.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4A">
        <num>4A.</num>
        <heading>Ban on advertisement.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4A.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If any person,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4A.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>offers, through any advertisement in any newspaper, periodical, journal or through any other media, any share in his property or of any money or both as a share in any business or other interest as consideration for the marriage of his son or daughter or any other relative;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4A.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>prints or publishes or circulates any advertisement referred to in clause (a),</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than six months, but which may extend to five years, or with fine which may extend to fifteen thousand rupees:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Court may, for adequate and special reasons to be recorded in the judgment, impose a sentence of imprisonment for a term of less than six months.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Agreement for giving or taking dowry to be void.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any agreement for the giving or taking of dowry shall be void.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Dowry to be for the benefit of the wife or her heirs.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where any dowry is received by any person other than the woman in connection with whose marriage it is given, that person shall transfer it to the woman—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>if the dowry was received before marriage, within three months after the date of marriage; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>if the dowry was received at the time of or after the marriage, within three months after the date of its receipt; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>if the dowry was received when the woman was a minor, within three months after she has attained the age of eighteen years,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>and pending such transfer, shall hold it in trust for the benefit of the woman.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person fails to transfer any property as required by sub-section (1) within the time limit specified therefor, or as required by sub-section (3), he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than six months, but which may extend to two years or with fine which shall not be less than five thousand rupees, but which may extend to ten thousand rupees or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the woman entitled to any property under sub-section (1) dies before receiving it, the heirs of the woman shall be entitled to claim it from the person holding it for the time being:</p>
            <blockList id="section-6.3.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that where such woman dies within seven years of her marriage, otherwise than due to natural causes, such property shall,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.3.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>if she has no children, be transferred to her parents; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.3.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>if she has children, be transferred to such children and pending such transfer, be held in trust for such children.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3A">
          <num>(3A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a person convicted under sub-section (2) for failure to transfer any property as required by sub-section (1) or sub-section (3) has not, before his conviction under that sub-section, transferred such property to the woman entitled thereto or, as the case may be, her heirs, parents or children the Court shall, in addition to awarding punishment under that sub-section, direct, by order in writing, that such person shall transfer the property to such woman or, as the case may be,her heirs, parents or children within such period as may be specified in the order, and if such person fails to comply with the direction within the period so specified, an amount equal to the value of the property may be recovered from him as if it were a fine imposed by such Court and paid to such woman or, as the case may be, her heirs, parents or children.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing contained in this section shall affect the provisions of section 3 or section 4.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Cognizance of offences.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974),—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>no Court inferior to that of a Metropolitan Magistrate or a Judicial Magistrate of the first class shall try any offence under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-7.1.list1.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>no Court shall take cognizance of an offence under this Act except upon—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-7.1.list1.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>its own knowledge or a police report of the facts which constitute such offence, or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-7.1.list1.b.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>a complaint by the person aggrieved by the offence or a parent or other relative of such person, or by any recognized welfare institution or organisation;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>it shall be lawful for a Metropolitan Magistrate or a Judicial Magistrate of the first class to pass any sentence authorised by this Act on any person convicted of an offence under this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Explanation.— For the purposes of this sub-section, “recognized welfare institution or organisation” means a social welfare institution or organisation recognized in this behalf by the Central or State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in Chapter XXXVI of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) shall apply to any offence punishable under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time being in force a statement made by the person aggrieved by the offence shall not subject such person to a prosecution under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Offences to be cognizable for certain purposes and to be non-bailable and non-compoundable.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), shall apply to offences under this Act as if they were cognizable offences—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for the purposes of investigation of such offences; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-8.1.list1.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>for the purposes of matters other than—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-8.1.list1.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>matters referred to in section 42 of that Code; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-8.1.list1.b.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>the arrest of a person without a warrant or without an order of a Magistrate.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every offence under this Act shall be non-bailable and non-compoundable.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8A">
        <num>8A.</num>
        <heading>Burden of proof in certain cases.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where any person is prosecuted for taking or abetting the taking of any dowry under section 3, or the demanding of dowry under section 4, the burden of proving that he had not committed an offence under these sections shall be on him.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8B">
        <num>8B.</num>
        <heading>Dowry Prohibition Officers.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8B.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may appoint as many Dowry Prohibition Officers as it thinks fit and specify the areas in respect of which they shall exercise their jurisdiction and powers under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8B.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8B.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Every Dowry Prohibition Officer shall exercise and perform the following powers and functions, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8B.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to see that the provisions of this Act are complied with;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8B.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to prevent, as far as possible, the taking or abetting the taking of, or the demanding of, dowry;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8B.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to collect such evidence as may be necessary for the prosecution of persons committing offences under the Act; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8B.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>to perform such additional functions as may be assigned to him by the State Government, or as may be specified in the rules made under this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8B.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, confer such powers of a police officer as may be specified in the notification on the Dowry Prohibition Officer who shall exercise such powers subject to such limitations and conditions as may be specified by rules made under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8B.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, for the purpose of advising and assisting Dowry Prohibition Officers in the efficient performance of their functions under this Act, appoint an Advisory Board consisting of not more than five social welfare workers (out of whom at least two shall be women) from the area in respect of which such Dowry Prohibition Officer exercises jurisdiction under sub-section (1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the form and manner in which, and the persons by whom, any list of presents referred to in sub-section (2) of section 3 shall be maintained and all other matters connected therewith; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the better co-ordination of policy and action with respect to the administration of this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Power of State Government to make rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the additional functions to be performed by the Dowry Prohibition Officers under sub-section (2) of section 8B;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>limitations and conditions subject to which a Dowry Prohibition Officer may exercise his functions under sub-section (3) of section 8B.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made by the State Government under this section shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made before the State Legislature.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
