<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/2010/11/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/2010/11"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Maharashtra Medicare Service Persons And Medicare Service Institutions (Prevention Of Violence And Damage Or Loss To Property) Act, 2010."/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/2010/11/eng@2017-01-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/2010/11/eng@2017-01-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/2010/11/eng@2017-01-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/2010/11/eng@2017-01-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-12-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Maharashtra Medicare Service Persons And Medicare Service Institutions (Prevention Of Violence And Damage Or Loss To Property) Act, 2010.</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>No. XI of 2010</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the prevention of violence against Medicare Service Persons and prevention of damage or loss of property of Medicare Service Institutions in the State of Maharashtra and for matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS acts of violence of causing injury or danger to life of Medicare Service Persons and damage or loss to the property of Medicare Service Institutions were on increase in the State creating unrest in Medicare Service Persons and professionals resulting in total hindrance of such services in the State</p>
        <p>AND WHEREAS it had become necessary to provide for the prevention of violence against Medicare Service Persons and prevention of damage or loss of property of Medicare Service Institutions from such violent activities;</p>
        <p>AND WHEREAS both Houses of the State Legislature were not in session;</p>
        <p>AND WHEREAS the Governor of Maharashtra was satisfied that circumstances existed which rendered it necessary for him to take immediate act ion to make necessary provisions, for the purposes aforesaid; and, therefore, promulgated the "Maharashtra Medicare Service Persons and Medicare Service Institution (Prevention of Violence and Damage or Loss to Property) Ordinance, 2010, on the 17th February 2010 (Mah. Ord. 1 of 2010)";</p>
        <p>AND WHEREAS it is expedient to replace the said Ordinance by an Act of the State Legislature; it is hereby enacted in the Sixty-first Year of the Republic of India as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Maharashtra Medicare Service Persons and Medicare Service Institutions (Prevention of Violence and Damage or Loss to Property) Act, 2010.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Maharashtra.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 17th February 2010.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act , unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"Medicare Service Institution" means an institution, providing medicare service to people either in Medicare Service Institution or through Mobile Medicare Unit or by arranging medical check up camps, under the control of the State Government or the Central Government, or a local body including any private hospital having facilities for treatment of the sick and used for their reception or stay in any private maternity home, where women are usually received and accommodated for the purpose of confinement and ante-natal and post-natal care in connection with the child birth or anything connected therewith and any private nursing home used or intended to be used for the reception and accommodation of person suffering from any sickness, injury or infirmity, whether of body or mind, and providing of treatment or nursing or both of them and includes convalescent home;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>"Medicare Service Person", in relation to Medicare Service Institution, shall include,—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>Registered Medical Practitioner, Practitioner or Registered Practitioner (including a person having provisional registration) working in a Medicare Service Institution other than the public servant within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code 45 of 1860;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>Registered Nurse, registered under the " Maharashtra Nurses Act, 1966 (Mah. XL of 1966)", other than the public servant within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code 45 of 1860;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>Medical Student;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>Nursing Student; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.v">
                    <num>(v)</num>
                    <p>Para-Medical Worker and other member staff or worker directly or indirectly employed by a Medicare Service Institution for providing required services other than the public servant within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code 45 of 1860.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation.—For the purpose of this Act , the expression Registered Medical Practitioner, Practitioner or Registered Practitioner, Nurse, shall have the same meanings, as assigned to them in the "Maharashtra Medical Practitioners’ Act, 1961 (Mah. XXVIII of 1961)", the " Maharashtra Medical Council Act, 1965 (Mah. XLVI of 1965)", the "Bombay Homoeopathic Practitioners’ Act, 1959 and the " Maharashtra Nurses Act, 1966 (Mah. XL of 1966)"; Bom. XII of 1960.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>"Medical Student" means a student, who is undergoing training or studies in medical profession;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>"Mobile Medical Unit" means an ambulance equipped with medical equipment, used for providing medicare services;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>"Nursing Student" means a student, who is undergoing training or studies in nursing profession;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>"Offender" means any person, who either by himself or as a member or leader of a group of persons or organization commits or attempts to commit or abets or incites the commission of violence under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>"Para-Medical Worker" means a person, who assists the Medicare Service Person providing medicare services;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>"Property" means any property, movable or immovable or medical equipment or medical machinery owned by or in possession of, or under the control of any Medicare Service Person or Medicare Service Institution;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>"Violence" means an act, which causes or may cause any harm, injury or endangering the life of, or intimidation, obstruction or hindrance to, any Medicare Service Person in discharging his duty in a Medicare Service Institution or causing damage or loss to the property in a Medicare Service Institution.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition of violence.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any act of violence against a Medicare Service Person or damage or loss to the property in a Medicare Service Institution, shall be prohibited.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Penalty.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any offender, who commits or attempts to commit or abets or incites the commission of any act of violence in contravention of the provisions of section 3, shall be punished with imprisonment which may extend to three years and with fine, which may extend to fifty thousand rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Cognizance of offence.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any offence committed under this Act , shall be cognizable and non-bailable and triable by the Court of Judicial Magistrate of the First Class.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Liability to pay compensation for loss or damage caused to property.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In addition to the punishment specified in section 4, the offender shall be liable to pay compensation of twice the amount of damage or loss caused to the property, as may be determined by the Court referred to in section 5.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the offender has not paid the compensation imposed under sub-section (1), the same sum shall be recovered as if it were an arrear of land revenue.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Authority to aid and advise victims of medical negligence.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, establish the Authority for the area as may be specified in such notification, to hear grievances of victims of medical negligence or mismanagement and to aid and advise such victims for taking recourse to an appropriate forum for suitable relief.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Authority shall consist of experts one each from the field of medical, law, consumer movement and health management.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The conditions of service of the experts mentioned in sub-section (2), and the procedure to be followed by the Authority shall be such as may be specified by the State Government by an order in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Act not in derogation of any other law.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of this Act shall be in addition to and not in derogation of, the provisions of any other law for the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Repeal of Mah. Ord. 1 of 2010 and saving.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The "Maharashtra Medicare Service Persons and Medicare Service Institutions (Prevention of Violence and Damage or Loss to Property) Ordinance, 2010 (Mah. Ord. 1 of 2010)", is hereby repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any act ion taken (including any notification or order issued) under the said Ordinance, shall be deemed to have been done, taken or issued, as the case may be, under the corresponding provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
