<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1974/24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1974/24"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Andhra Pradesh Village Police Act, 1974"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1974/24/eng@2017-01-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1974/24/eng@2017-01-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-24" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1974/24/eng@2017-01-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1974/24/eng@2017-01-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-12-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Andhra Pradesh Village Police Act, 1974</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[29th August, 1974]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>No. 31 of 1974</p>
        <p>An Act to consolidate and amend the law relating to the establishment of the system of village police in the State of Andhra Pradesh.</p>
        <p>Be it enacted by the Legislature of the State of Andhra Pradesh in the Twenty-fifty Year of the Republic of India, as follows.—</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Andhra Pradesh Village Police Act, 1974.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Andhra Pradesh.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the State Government may, by notification in the Andhra Pradesh Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In this Act , unless the context otherwise requires—</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“cattle” includes all horned cattle, elephants, camels, horses, asses, mules, sheep, goats and swine;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“Government” means the State Government;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“notification” means the notification published in the Andhra Pradesh Gazette, and the words “notified” shall be construed accordingly;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“police officer” means any member of the police force appointed or deemed to be appointed under any law relating to the police force for the time being in force in the State; and includes a special police officer;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“village” means any local area which is recognised as a revenue village in the revenue accounts of the Government;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“village police officer” means the head of a village, by whatever designation locally known, who is appointed as the head of the village police and Section 3.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Appointment of village police and its head.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>For the purposes of this Act , the District Magistrate or any officer authorised by him in this behalf may appoint, one or more village servants as village police for each village, and the police patel, village headman, village munsif, triune officer or other head of the village by whatever designation locally known, as the head of the village police of that village.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Administration of village police.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The administration of the village police in each district shall vest in the District Magistrate, who may delegate any of his powers and functions relating to such administration to a subordinate Executive Magistrate within whose local jurisdiction the village is situated.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Duties of village police officer.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Every village police officer shall—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>reciprocally communicate all information regarding any offence committed or any gang of robbers or strangers of suspicious appearance having entered or taken refuge in the village;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>report promptly to the nearest Executive Magistrate having jurisdiction over the village and to the police officer in charge of the nearest police station,—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>the matters specified in Clause (a),</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>all offences committed in the village, and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>all matters connected with public peace and tranquility:</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>afford such assistance and facility as may be necessary or required by an police officer in the discharge of his duty;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>obey and execute all lawful orders issued to him by the concerned Executive Magistrate or the police officer;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>prevent, to the best of his ability, the commission of any offence or public nuisance within the limits of the village; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>take measures consistent with law to bring offenders to justice.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Authority of the village police officer over other Village Officers and servants.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The village police officer shall have authority to require the Karnam and any village servant to aid him in the discharge of his duties under this Act .</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Action as to stolen property.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where the village police officer is informed that stolen property is being concealed and where he has reason to apprehend that the stolen property may be made away with unless prompt measures are taken to secure it, he shall cause search to be made in the prescribed manner and secure and forward the property, if found, along with the offender to the police officer in charge of the nearest police station.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Preservation in tact of scene of offence.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The village police officer shall Endeavour to the best of his ability to preserve intact scene of offence and finger and foot prints in case of murder, house-breaking, robbery, dacoity, rioting, accidental death or suicide until the police officer concerned arrives on the scene for investigation.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Village police officer to take charge of unclaimed property.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The village police officer shall take charge of all the unclaimed property found within the limits of the village or delivered to him lawfully and shall forthwith forward all such property to the police officer incharge of the nearest police station for disposal in accordance with law.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Accident to aircraft.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>On the occurrence of an accident to an aircraft, the village police officer shall at once report the matter to the Executive Magistrate having jurisdiction over the area and to the police officer incharge of the nearest police station and if any person is injured as a result of such accident, the village police officer shall forthwith report the matter to the nearest medical officer. He shall also take such further act ion as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for neglect of duty, etc..—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any village police officer, village police, or other village officer or servant liable to be requisitioned for the purpose of police duties under this Act , who shall be guilty of neglect or violation of duty imposed by or under this Act or wilful breach of any rule or order made by a competent authority under this Act , shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three months, or with fine which may extend to one hundred rupees, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification, make rules for carrying out all or any of the purposes of this Act .</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this Act, shall, immediately after it if made, be laid before each Housing of the State Legislature if it is in session and if it is not in session, in the session immediately following, for a total period of fourteen days which may be comprised in one session, or in two successive sessions, and if, before the expiration of the session in which it is so laid or the session immediately following, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or in the annulment of the rule, the rule shall from the date on which the modification or annulment is notified, have effect only in such modified form, or shall stand annulled, as the case may be, so however that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Repeal.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Andhra Pradesh (Andhra Area) Village Police Regulation, 1816, and the Andhra Pradesh (Andhra Area) Village Police Regulation, 1821 are hereby repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
