<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1952/37/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1952/37"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Cinematograph Act, 1952"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1952/37/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1952/37/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1952/37/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1952/37/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-11-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Cinematograph Act, 1952</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Cinematograph Act, 1952.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Parts I, II and IV extends to the whole of India and Part III extends to the Union Territories only.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act shall come into force on such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint:</p>
            <p>Provided that Parts I and II shall come into force in the State of Jammu and Kashmir only on such date after the commencement of the Cinematograph (Amendment) Act, 1973 (26 of 1973), as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“adult” means a person who has completed his eighteenth year;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“Board” means the Board of Film Certification constituted by the Central Government under section 3;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>( bb) “certificate” means the certificate granted by the Board under section 5A;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“cinematograph” includes any apparatus for the representation of moving pictures or series of pictures;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>“district magistrate”, in relation to a presidency-town, means the Commissioner of police;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5">
              <listIntroduction>( dd) “film” means a cinematograph film;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>“place” includes a house, building, tent and any description of transport, whether by sea, land or air;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>“regional officer” means a regional officer appointed by the Central Government under section 5 and includes an additional regional officer and an assistant regional officer;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>“Tribunal” means the Appellate Tribunal constituted under section 5D.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2A">
        <num>2A.</num>
        <heading>Construction of references to any law not in force or any functionary not in existence in the State of Jammu and Kashmir.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any reference in this Act to any law which is not in force, or any functionary not in existence, in the State of Jammu and Kashmir, shall, in relation to that State, be construed as a reference to the corresponding law in force, or to the corresponding functionary in existence, in that State.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Board of film Certification.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of sanctioning films for public exhibition, the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute a Board to be called the Board of Film Certification which shall consist of a Chairman and not less than twelve and not more than twenty-five other members appointed by the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chairman of the Board shall receive such salary and allowances as may be determined by the Central Government, and the other members shall receive such allowances or fees for attending the meetings of the Board as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The other terms and conditions of service of the members of the Board shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Examination of films.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any person desiring to exhibit any film shall in the prescribed manner make an application to the Board for a certificate in respect thereof, and the Board may, after examining or having the film examined in the prescribed manner,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>sanction the film for unrestricted public exhibition:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that, having regard to any material in the film, if the Board is of the opinion that it is necessary to caution that the question as to whether any child below the age of twelve years may be allowed to see such a film should be considered by the parents or guardian of such child, the Board may sanction the film for unrestricted public exhibition with an endorsement to that effect; or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list3.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>sanction the film for public exhibition restricted to adults; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list3.iia">
                <num>(iia)</num>
                <p>sanction the film for public exhibition restricted to members of any profession or any class of persons, having regard to the nature, content and theme of the film; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list3.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>direct the applicant to carry out such excisions or modifications in the film as it thinks necessary before sanctioning the film for public exhibition under any of the foregoing clauses; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list3.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>refuse to sanction the film for public exhibition.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No action under the proviso to clause (i), clause (ii), clause (iia), clause (iii) or clause (iv) of sub-section (1) shall be taken by the Board except after giving an opportunity to the applicant for representing his views in the matter.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Advisory panels.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of enabling the Board to efficiently discharge its functions under this Act, the Central Government may establish at such regional centres as it thinks fit, advisory panels each of which shall consist of such number of persons, being persons qualified in the opinion of the Central Government to judge the effect of films on the public, as the Central Government may think fit to appoint thereto.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>At each regional centre there shall be as many regional officers as the Central Government may think fit to appoint, and rules made in this behalf may provide for the association of regional officers in the examination of films.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board may consult in such manner as may be prescribed, any advisory panel in respect of any film for which an application for a certificate has been made.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be the duty of every such advisory panel whether acting as a body or in committees as may be provided in the rules made in this behalf to examine the film and to make such recommendations to the Board as it thinks fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The members of the advisory panel shall not be entitled to any salary but shall receive such fees or allowances as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5A">
        <num>5A.</num>
        <heading>Certification of films.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5A.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If, after examining a film or having it examined in the prescribed manner, the Board considers that—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5A.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the film is suitable for unrestricted public exhibition, or, as the case may be, for unrestricted public exhibition with an endorsement of the nature mentioned in the proviso to clause (i) of sub-section (1) of section 4, it shall grant to the person applying for a certificate in respect of the film a “U” certificate or, as the case may be, a “UA” certificate; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5A.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the film is not suitable for unrestricted public exhibition, but is suitable for public exhibition restricted to adults or, as the case may be, is suitable for public exhibition restricted to members of any profession or any class of persons, it shall grant to the person applying for a certificate in respect of the film an “A” certificate or, as the case may be, a “S” certificate.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>and cause the film to be so marked in the prescribed manner:</p>
            <p>Provided that the applicant for the certificate, any distributor or exhibitor or any other person to whom the rights in the film have passed shall not be liable for punishment under any law relating to obscenity in respect of any matter contained in the film for which certificate has been granted under clause (a) or clause (b).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A certificate granted or an order refusing to grant a certificate in respect of any film shall be published in the Gazette of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the other provisions contained in this Act, a certificate granted by the Board under this section shall be valid throughout India for a period of ten years.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5B">
        <num>5B.</num>
        <heading>Principles for guidance in certifying films.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5B.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A film shall not be certified for public exhibition if, in the opinion of the authority competent to grant the certificate, the film or any part of it is against the interests of the sovereignty and integrity of India the security of the State, friendly relations with foreign States, public order, decency or morality, or involves defamation or contempt of court or is likely to incite the commission of any offence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5B.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions contained in sub-section (1), the Central Government may issue such directions as it may think fit setting out the principles which shall guide the authority competent to grant certificates under this Act in sanctioning films for public exhibition.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5C">
        <num>5C.</num>
        <heading>Appeals.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5C.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5C.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any person applying for a certificate in respect of a film who is aggrieved by any order of the Board—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5C.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>refusing to grant a certificate; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5C.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>granting only an “A” certificate; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5C.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>granting only a “S” certificate; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5C.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>granting only a “UA” certificate; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5C.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>directing the applicant to carry out any excisions or modifications,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>may, within thirty days from the date of such order, prefer an appeal to the Tribunal:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Tribunal may, if it is satisfied that the appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from filing the appeal within the aforesaid period of thirty days, allow such appeal to be admitted within a further period of thirty days.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5C.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every appeal under this section shall be made by a petition in writing and shall be accompanied by a brief statement of the reasons for the order appealed against where such statement has been furnished to the appellant and by such fees, not exceeding rupees one thousand, as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5D">
        <num>5D.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of Appellate Tribunal.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5D.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of hearing appeals against any order of the Board under section 5C, the Central Government shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute an Appellate Tribunal.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5D.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The head office of the Tribunal shall be at New Delhi or at such other place as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5D.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Such Tribunal shall consist of a Chairman and not more than four other members appointed by the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5D.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A person shall not be qualified for appointment as the Chairman of the Tribunal unless he is a retired Judge of a High Court, or is a person who is qualified to be a Judge of a High Court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5D.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may appoint such persons who, in its opinion, are qualified to judge the effect of films on the public, to be members of the Tribunal.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5D.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chairman of the Tribunal shall receive such salary and allowances as may be determined by the Central Government and the members shall receive such allowances or fees as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5D.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to such rules as may be made in this behalf, the Central Government may appoint a Secretary and such other employees as it may think necessary for the efficient performance of the functions of the Tribunal under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5D.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Secretary to, and other employees of, the Tribunal shall exercise such powers and perform such duties as may be prescribed after consultation with the Chairman of the Tribunal.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5D.9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The other terms and conditions of service of the Chairman and members of, and the Secretary to, and other employees of, the Tribunal shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5D.10">
          <num>(10)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Tribunal may regulate its own procedure.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5D.11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Tribunal may, after making such inquiry into the matter as it considers necessary, and after giving the appellant and the Board an opportunity of being heard in the matter, make such order in relation to a film as it thinks fit and the Board shall dispose of the matter in conformity with such order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5E">
        <num>5E.</num>
        <heading>Suspension and revocation of certificate.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5E.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5E.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (2) of section 6, the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette suspend a certificate granted under this Part, for such period as it thinks fit or may revoke such certificate if it is satisfied that—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5E.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the film in respect of which the certificate was granted, was being exhibited in a form other than the one in which it was certified; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5E.1.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>the film or any part thereof is being exhibited in contravention of the provisions of this Part or the rules made thereunder.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5E.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a notification under sub-section (1) has been published, the Central Government may require the applicant for certificate or any other person to whom the rights in the film have passed, or both, to deliver up the certificate and all duplicate certificates, if any, granted in respect of the film to the Board or to any person or authority specified in the said notification.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5E.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No action under this section shall be taken except after giving an opportunity to the person concerned for representing his views in the matter.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5E.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>During the period in which a certificate remains suspended under this section, the film shall be deemed to be an uncertified film.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5F">
        <num>5F.</num>
        <heading>Review of orders by Central Government.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5F.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an applicant for a certificate or any other person to whom the rights in the film have passed, is aggrieved by any order of the Central Government under section 5E, he may, within sixty days of the date of publication of the notification in the Official Gazette, make an application to the Central Government for review of the order, setting out in such application the grounds on which he considers such review to be necessary:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Central Government may, if it is satisfied that the applicant for a certificate or that other person was prevented by sufficient cause from filing an application for review within the aforesaid period of sixty days, allow such application to be filed within a further period of sixty days.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5F.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On receipt of the application under sub-section (1), the Central Government may, after giving the aggrieved person a reasonable opportunity of being heard, and after making such further inquiry, as it may consider necessary, pass such order as it thinks fit, confirming, modifying or reversing its decision and the Board shall dispose of the matter in conformity with such order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Revisional powers of the Central Government.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Part, the Central Government may, of its own motion, at any stage, call for the record of any proceeding in relation to any film which is pending before, or has been decided by, the Board, or, as the case may be, decided by the Tribunal (but not including any proceeding in respect of any matter which is pending before the Tribunal) and after such inquiry, into the matter as it considers necessary, make such order in relation thereto as it thinks fit, and the Board shall dispose of the matter in conformity with such order:</p>
            <p>Provided that no such order shall be made prejudicially affecting any person applying for a certificate or to whom a certificate has been granted, as the case may be, except after giving him an opportunity for representing his views in the matter:</p>
            <p>Provided further that nothing in this sub-section shall require the Central Government to disclose any fact which it considers to be against public interest to disclose.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Without prejudice to the powers conferred on it under sub-section (1), the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>a film which has been granted a certificate shall be deemed to be an uncertified film in the whole or any part of India; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>a film which has been granted a “U” certificate or a “UA” certificate or a “S” certificate shall be deemed to be a film in respect of which an “A” certificate has been granted; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the exhibition of any film be suspended for such period as may be specified in the direction:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that no direction issued under clause (c) shall remain in force for more than two months from the date of the notification.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No action shall be taken under clause (a) or clause (b) of sub-section (2) except after giving an opportunity to the person concerned for representing his views in the matter.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>During the period in which a film remains suspended under clause (c) of sub-section (2), the film shall be deemed to be an uncertified film.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6A">
        <num>6A.</num>
        <heading>Information and documents to be given to distributors and exhibitors with respect to certified films.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any person who delivers any certified film to any distributor or exhibitor shall, in such manner as may be prescribed, notify to the distributor or exhibitor, as the case may be, the title, the length of the film, the number and the nature of the certificate granted in respect thereof and the conditions, if any, subject to which it has been so granted, and any other particulars respecting the film which may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Penalties for contraventions of this Part.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If any person—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-7.1.list1.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>exhibits or permits to be exhibited in any place—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-7.1.list1.a.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>any film other than a film which has been certified by the board as suitable for unrestricted public exhibition or for public exhibition restricted to adults or to members of any profession or any class of persons and which, when exhibited, displays the prescribed mark of the Board and has not been altered or tampered with in any way since such mark was affixed thereto,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-7.1.list1.a.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>any film, which has been certified by the Board as suitable for public exhibition restricted to adults, to any person who is not an adult, ***.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-7.1.list1.a.list0.iia">
                    <num>(iia)</num>
                    <p>any film which has been certified by the Board as suitable for public exhibition restricted to any profession or class of persons, to a person who is not a member of such profession or who is not a member of such class, or</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>without lawful authority (the burden of proving which shall be on him), alters or tampers with in any way any film after it has been certified, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>fails to comply with the provision contained in section 6A or with any order made by the Central Government or by the Board in the exercise of any of the powers or functions conferred on it by this Act or the rules made thereunder,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years, or with fine which may extend to one lakh rupees, or with both, and in the case of a continuing offence with a further fine which may extend to twenty thousand rupees for each day during which the offence continues:</p>
            <p>Provided that a person who exhibits or permits to be exhibited in any place a video film in contravention of the provisions of sub-clause (i) of clause (a) shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than three months, but which may extend to three years and with fine which shall not be less than twenty thousand rupees, but which may extend to one lakh rupees, and in the case of a continuing offence with a further fine which may extend to twenty thousand rupees for each day during which the offence continues:</p>
            <p>Provided further that a court may, for adequate and special reasons to be mentioned in the judgment, impose a sentence of imprisonment for a term of less than three months, or a fine of less than twenty thousand rupees:</p>
            <p>Provided further that notwithstanding anything contained in section 29 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), it shall be lawful for any Metropolitan Magistrate, or any Judicial Magistrate of the first class specially empowered by the State Government in this behalf, to pass a sentence of fine exceeding five thousand rupees on any person convicted of any offence punishable under this Part:</p>
            <p>Provided also that no distributor or exhibitor or owner or employee of a cinema house shall be liable to punishment for contravention of any condition of endorsement of caution on a film certified as “UA” under this Part.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person is convicted of an offence punishable under this section committed by him in respect of any film, the convicting court may further direct that the film shall be forfeited to the Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The exhibition of a film, in respect of which an “A” certificate or a “S” certificate or a “UA” certificate has been granted, to children below the age of three years accompanying their parents or guardians shall not be deemed to be an offence within the meaning of this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7A">
        <num>7A.</num>
        <heading>Power of seizure.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a film in respect of which no certificate has been granted under this Act is exhibited, or a film certified as suitable for public exhibition restricted to adults is exhibited to any person who is not an adult or a film is exhibited in contravention of any of the other provisions contained in this Act or of any order made by the Central Government ,the Tribunal or the Board in the exercise of any of the powers conferred on it, any police officer may, enter any place in which he has reason to believe that the film has been or is being or is likely to be exhibited, search it and seize the film.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All searches under this Act shall be carried out in accordance with the provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), relating to searches.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7B">
        <num>7B.</num>
        <heading>Delegation of powers by Board.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7B.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by general or special order, direct that any power, authority or jurisdiction exercisable by the Board under this Act shall, in relation to the certification of the films under this Part and subject to such condition, if any, as may be specified in the order, be exercisable also by the Chairman or any other member of the Board, and anything done or action taken by the Chairman or other member specified in the order shall be deemed to be a thing done or action taken by the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7B.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by order and subject to such conditions and restrictions as may be prescribed, authorise the regional officer to issue provisional certificates.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7C">
        <num>7C.</num>
        <heading>Power to direct exhibition of films for examination.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7C.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of exercising any of the powers conferred on it by this Act, the Central Government , the Tribunal or the Board may require any film to be exhibited before it or, before any person or authority specified by it in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7D">
        <num>7D.</num>
        <heading>Vacancies, etc., not to invalidate proceeding.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7D.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No act or proceeding of the Tribunal, the Board or of any advisory panel shall be deemed to be invalid by reason only of a vacancy in, or any defect in, the constitution of the Tribunal, the Board or panel, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7E">
        <num>7E.</num>
        <heading>Members of the Board and advisory panels, to be public servants.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7E.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>All members of the Tribunal, the Board and of any advisory panel shall, when acting or purporting to act in pursuance of any of the provisions of this Act, be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1960).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7F">
        <num>7F.</num>
        <heading>Bar of legal proceedings.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7F.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central Government, the Tribunal, the Board, advisory panel or any officer or member of the Central Government, the Tribunal, the Board or advisory panel, as the case may be, in respect of anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for the purpose of carrying into effect the provisions of this Part.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, rules made under this section may provide for—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the allowances or fees payable to the members of the Board;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the terms and conditions of service of the members of the Board;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the manner of making an application to the Board for a certificate and the manner in which a film has to be examined by the Board and the fees to be levied therefor;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the association of regional officers in the examination of films, the conditions and restrictions subject to which regional officers may be authorised under section 7B to issue provisional certificates and the period of validity of such certificates;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the manner in which the Board may consult any advisory panel in respect of any film;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the allowances or fees payable to the members of advisory panel;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the marking of the films;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the allowances or fees payable to the members of the Tribunal;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the powers and duties of the Secretary to, and other employees of, the Tribunal;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>the other terms and conditions of service of the Chairman and members of, and the Secretary to, and other employees of, the Tribunal;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>the fees payable by the appellant to the Tribunal in respect of an appeal;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>the conditions (including conditions relating to the length of films in general or any class of films, in particular) subject to which any certificate may be granted, or the circumstances in which any certificate shall be refused;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>any other matter which is required to be or may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Part shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall, thereafter, have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Power to exempt.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by order in writing exempt, subject to such conditions and restrictions, if any, as it may impose, the exhibition of any film or class of films from any of the provisions of this Part or of any rules made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Cinematograph exhibitions to be licensed.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Save as otherwise provided in this Part, no person shall give an exhibition by means of a cinematograph elsewhere than in a place licensed under this Part or otherwise than in compliance with any conditions and restrictions imposed by such licence.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Licensing authority.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The authority having power to grant licences under this Part (hereinafter referred to as the licensing authority) shall be the district magistrate:</p>
            <p>Provided that the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute, for the whole or any part of a</p>
            <p>Union territory, such other authority as it may specify in the notification to be the licensing authority for the purposes of this Part.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Restrictions on powers of licensing authority.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-12.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The licensing authority shall not grant a licence under this Part, unless it is satisfied that—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the rules made under this Part have been substantially complied with, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>adequate precautions have been taken in the place, in respect of which the licence is to be given, to provide for the safety of persons attending exhibitions therein.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the foregoing provisions of this section and to the control of the State Government, the licensing authority may grant licences under this Part to such persons as that authority thinks fit and on such terms and conditions and subject to such restrictions as it may determine.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person aggrieved by the decision of a licensing authority refusing to grant a licence under this Part may, within such time as may be prescribed, appeal to the State Government or to such officer as the State Government may specify in this behalf and the State Government or the officer, as the case may be, may make such order in the case as it or he thinks fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, from time to time, issue directions to licensees generally or to any licensee in particular for the purpose of regulating the exhibition of any film or class of films, so that scientific films, films intended for educational purposes, films dealing with news and current events, documentary films or indigenous films secure an adequate opportunity of being exhibited, and where any such directions have been issued those directions shall be deemed to be additional conditions and restrictions subject to which the licence has been granted.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government or local authority to suspend exhibition of films in certain cases.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Lieutenant-Governor or, as the case may be, the Chief Commissioner, in respect of the</p>
            <p>whole or any part of a Union territory and the District Magistrate in respect of the district within his jurisdiction, may, if he is of opinion that any film which is being publicly exhibited is likely to cause a breach of the peace, by order, suspend the exhibition of the film and during such suspension the film shall be deemed to be an uncertified film in the State, part or district, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an order under sub-section (1) has been issued by the Chief Commissioner or a District Magistrate, as the case may be, a copy thereof, together with a statement of reasons therefor, shall forthwith be forwarded by the person making the same to the Central Government, and the Central Government may either confirm or discharge the order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An order made under this section shall remain in force for a period of two months from the date thereof, but the Central Government may, if it is of opinion that the order should continue in force, direct that the period of suspension shall be extended by such further period as it thinks fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Penalties for contravention of this Part.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If the owner or person in charge of a cinematograph uses the same or allows it to be used, or if the owner or occupier of any place permits that place to be used in contravention of the provisions of this Part or of the rule made thereunder, or of the conditions and restrictions upon or subject to which any licence has been granted under this Part, he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees and, in the case of a continuing offence, with a further fine which may extend to one hundred rupees for each day during which the offence continues.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Power to revoke licence.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where the holder of a licence has been convicted of an offence under section 7 or section 14, the licence may be revoked by the licensing authority.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-16.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-16.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-16.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>prescribing the terms, conditions and restrictions, if any, subject to which licences may be granted under this Part;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>providing for the regulation of cinematograph exhibitions for securing the public safety;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>prescribing the time within which and the conditions subject to which an appeal under sub-section (3) of section 12 may be preferred.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Part shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Power to exempt.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by order in writing exempt, subject to such conditions and restrictions as it may impose, any cinematograph exhibition or class of cinematograph exhibitions from any of the provisions of this Part or of any rules made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Repeal.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Cinematograph Act, 1918 (2 of 1918) is hereby repealed:</p>
            <p>Provided that in relation to Part A States and Part B States the repeal shall have effect only in so far as the said Act relates to the sanctioning of cinematograph films for exhibition.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
