<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1976/33/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1976/33"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Maharashtra Dog Race-Courses Licensing Act, 1976"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1976/33/eng@2017-01-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1976/33/eng@2017-01-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1976/33/eng@2017-01-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1976/33/eng@2017-01-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-12-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Maharashtra Dog Race-Courses Licensing Act, 1976</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>No. XXXIII of 1976</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the regulation, control and management of dog racing in the State of Maharashtra and for matters connected therewith.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the regulation, control and management of dog racing in the State of Maharashtra and for matters connected therewith;</p>
        <p>It is hereby enacted in the Twenty-seventh Year of the Republic of India as follows</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Maharashtra Dog Race-courses Licensing Act, 1976.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Maharashtra.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force2 on such date as the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context requires otherwise,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"dog-race" means a race in which an object propelled by mechanical means is pursued by dogs</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"race-course" means any ground on which a dog-race can be held</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>"Schedule" means the Schedule appended to this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition against dog-racing on unlicensed dog racecourses</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No dog-race shall be held save on a race-course for which a licence for dog-racing granted in accordance with the provisions of this Act, is in force.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The terms of such licence shall be published in the Official Gazette.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Licence for dog-racing</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The owner, lessee or occupier of any race-course may apply to the State Government for a licence for dog-racing on such race-course.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The State Government may withhold such licence or grant it subject to such conditions and for such period as it may think fit. Such conditions may provide for—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the payment of a licence fee;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the amount of stakes which may be allotted for different kinds of dogs;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>such other matters, whether directly or indirectly connected with dog-racing, for which, in the opinion of the State Government, it is necessary or expedient to make provision in the licence.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may by such licence authorize the licensee to grant, subject to such conditions as shall be specified by the State Government in such licence, a permit to any book-maker to carry on his business or vocation or to act as a book-maker or turf commission agent in respect of dog-races held on a dog racecourse, being a race-course which is situated in this State or outside it. The permit may be granted for such period not exceeding the period of the licence granted to the licensee as the licensee may think fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may at any time cancel any licence granted under this section in the event of any breach of the conditions subject to which it is granted.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for taking part in dog-race on unlicensed race course</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever takes part in any dog-race on any race-course for which a licence granted in accordance with the provisions of section 4 of this Act is not in force shall, on conviction, be punished with fine which may extend to two hundred rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for owner, etc. allowing dog-racing in unlicensed place</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any dog-race is held on any race-course for which a licence granted in accordance with the provisions of section 4 of this Act is not in force, any person being the owner, lessee or occupier of such race-course shall, on conviction, be punished with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for contravening conditions of licence</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person to whom a licence has been granted in accordance with the provisions of section 4 of this Act contravenes any of the conditions subject to which such licence is granted, such person shall, on conviction, be punished with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person to whom a permit has been granted by a license in pursuance of the provisions of sub-section (3) of section 4 of this Act, contravenes any of the conditions subject to which such permit is granted he shall, on conviction, be punished with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Cognizance of offences under this Act</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No Court inferior to that of a Metropolitan Magistrate or of a Magistrate of the First Class shall try any offence punishable under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Exemption</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may from time to time by general or special order published in the Official Gazette exempt any dog-race from the operation of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Rules</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, subject to the condition of previous publication, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this Act shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made before each House of the State Legislature while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, and notify such decision in the Official Gazette, the rule shall from the date of publication of such notification have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done or omitted to be done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of certain Acts</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Acts mentioned in column 1 of the Schedule shall be amended in the manner and to the extent specified in column 2 Of the Schedule.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-theschedule">
      <doc name="theschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1976/33/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1976/33"/>
              <FRBRalias value="The Schedule"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1976/33/eng@2017-01-19/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1976/33/eng@2017-01-19"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1976/33/eng@2017-01-19/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1976/33/eng@2017-01-19"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-12-26" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="theschedule">
            <heading>(See section 11)</heading>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
