<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1993/15/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1993/15"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Maharashtra State Commission For, Women Act, 1993"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1993/15/eng@2017-03-10/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1993/15/eng@2017-03-10"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-10" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1993/15/eng@2017-03-10/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1993/15/eng@2017-03-10"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-10" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Maharashtra State Commission For, Women Act, 1993</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>(ACT NO. 15 of 1993)</p>
      </longTitle>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[25th April 1993]</docDate>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>An Act to provide for constitution of a State Level Commission for women in the State of Maharashtra</p>
      <p>WHEREAS it was expedient to provide for the Constitution of a commission with the aim of furthering the fundamental rights guaranteed by Articles, 14, 15 and 16 of the Constitution of India with respect to women and, to give effect to the Directive Principle of State Policy and in particular those enshrined in Articles 38, 39, 39A and 42 of the Constitution to improve the status and dignity of women in the society, to investigate into and take or suggest suitable remedial measures against practices derogatory to women, to effectively monitor and implement laws affecting women and to advise the Government on all matters related to the improvement and upliftment of status and dignity of women in the society and for matters connected therewith or incidental thereto;</p>
      <p>AND WHEREAS it was considered necessary to immediately make a law for the same;</p>
      <p>AND WHEREAS both Houses of the State Legislature were not in session;</p>
      <p>AND WHEREAS the Governor of Maharashtra was satisfied that circumstances existed which rendered it necessary for him to take immediate action to make a law for the purposes aforesaid; and, therefore, promulgated the Maharashtra State Commission for Women Ordinance, 1993, on the 25th January 1993.</p>
      <p>AND WHEREAS it is expedient to replace the said Ordinance by an Act of the State Legislature, It is hereby enacted in the Forty-fourth Year of the Republic of India as follows:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short Title, Extent and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Maharashtra State Commission for Women Act, 1993.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Maharashtra.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 25th January 1993.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definition.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"Commission" means the Maharashtra State Commission for Women Constituted under section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"Director General of Police" means the Director General of Police, Maharashtra State;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>"member" means a member of the Commission and includes the Chairperson and the Member-Secretary;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>"National Commission for Women" means the National Commission for Women constituted under section 3 of the National Commission for Women Act, 1990 (20 of 1990)</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>"prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act; "Women" includes female-child or adolescent girl.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of Commission.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government shall, by notification in the Official Gazette constitute a body to be known as "the Maharashtra State Commission for Women to exercise the powers conferred on and to perform the functions assigned to it, under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Commission shall consist of-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>A Chairperson, who shall be an eminent woman committed to the cause of women;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>not more than six non-official members preferably women, to be nominated by the State Government from amongst the persons of ability, integrity and standing who have served the cause of women or have had sufficient knowledge and experience in law or legislation, administration of matters concerning the advancement of women or leadership of any trade union or voluntary organisation for women for protection, upliftment and promotion of common interests of women:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that, at least one member each shall be from amongst persons belonging to the scheduled castes and the scheduled Tribes, respectively:</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Provided further that, before nominating the Chairperson the State Government shall consult the women organisations within the State of Maharashtra;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>The Director General of Police shall be the ex-officio member of the Commission;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list4.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>One Member Secretary, to be nominated by the State Government, shall be a woman officer, who is a member of the Civil Services of the State or of an All India Service or holds a civil post under the State with appropriate experience, of the rank of Joint secretary or above.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Term of Office and Conditions of Service of Chairperson and Member.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>The chairperson and every non-official member shall hold office for a period of three years.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The chairperson or a non-official member may, at any time, by writing and addressed to the State Government, resign from the office of the Chairperson or of the office of the member.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), the State Government may remove a person from the office of the Chairperson or member if, that person</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>becomes an un-discharged insolvent;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>is convicted and sentenced to imprisonment for an offence which, in the opinion of the State Government, involves moral turpitude;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>becomes of unsound mind and stands so declared by a competent Court;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>refuses to act or becomes incapable of acting;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>is, without obtaining leave of absence from the Commission, absent from three consecutive meetings of the Commission; in the opinion of the State Government, has so abused the position of the Chairperson or member as to render that person's continuance in office detrimental to the public interest or is otherwise unfit or unsuitable to continue as such Chairperson or member:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that, no person shall be removed under this clause until that person has been given a reasonable opportunity of being heard in the matter.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A vacancy caused under sub-section (2) or (3) or in any other manner, shall be filled in, as soon as may be, by a fresh nomination by the State Government, and the person so nominated shall hold office for the remainder of the term of office of the person in whose vacancy such person has been nominated would have held office, if the vacancy had not occurred;</p>
            <p>Provided that, if the vacancy of a member other than that of the Chairperson occurs within six months preceding the date on which the term of office of the member expires, the vacancy shall not be filled in.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The honorarium, if any, and allowances payable to, and the other Terms and Conditions of holding the office of the chairperson and the members shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Officers and Other Employees of Commission.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government shall provide the Commission with such officers and-employee's as, in the opinion of the State Government, may be necessary for the efficient performance of the functions of the Commission under this Act,</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The salaries and allowances "payable" to, and the other Terms and Conditions of service of the officers and other employee appointed for the purpose of the Commission shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Salaries and Allowances to be out of Grants.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The honorarium and allowances payable to the Chairperson and members and the administrative expenses, including salaries, allowances and pensions payable to the officers and other employees referred to in section 5, shall be paid out of the grants referred to in section 16.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Vacancies etc. not to Invalidate Proceedings of Commission.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No act or proceeding of the Commission shall be questioned or shall be invalid on the ground merely of the existence of any vacancy in, or defect in the constitution of, the Commission or any defect in the nomination of a person acting as the Chairperson or a member or any irregularity in the procedure of the Commission, including in issuing of notice for holding of a meeting, not affecting merits of the matter.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Committee of Commission.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commission may appoint such committees as may be necessary for the efficient performance, exercise and discharge of its functions, powers and duties and also for dealing with such special issues as may be taken up by the Commission, from time to time.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commission shall have the power to appoint one or more persons, as it may think fit, on any committee appointed under subsection (1), and such person or persons, who are not members of the Commission, shall have the right to attend the meeting of the committee and take part in its proceedings, but shall not have the right to vote.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The person so appointed shall be entitled to receive such allowances, towards expenses for attending the meetings and any other task of the Committee, as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commission may invite any representative of the National Commission for Women to any of its meetings, or may associate with itself, in such manner and for such purposes as it may deem necessary, any person whose assistance or advice it may need in complying with any of the provisions of this Act or in carrying out any of its functions under this Act; and a person so invited or associated shall have the right to take part in the discussions of the Commission relevant to the purposes for which such representative or person has been invited or associated, but shall not have the right to vote.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Procedure to be regulated by Commission.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commission or a committee thereof shall meet as and when necessary and shall at such time and place, as the Chairperson may deem fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commission shall regulate its own procedure and the procedure of the committees thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All order and decisions of the Commission shall be authenticated by the Member- Secretary or any other officer of the Commission duly authorised by the Member- Secretary in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Functions of Commission.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Commission shall perform all or any of the following functions namely:</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>Investigate and examine all matters relating to the safeguards provided, for women under the Constitution and other laws;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>present to the State Government, annually and at such other times, as the Commission may deem fit, reports upon the working of those safeguards;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>make in. such reports recommendations for the effective implementation of those safeguards for improving the condition of women by the State;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>review, from time to time, the existing provisions of the Constitution and other laws affecting women and recommend amendment thereto so as to suggest remedial legislative measures to meet any lacunae, inadequacies or shortcomings in such legislations;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <blockList id="section-10.1.list1.e.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>take up the cases of violation of the provisions of the Constitution and of other laws relating to women with the State Government or appropriate authorities; entertain complaints and take suo motu notice of matters relating to,</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-10.1.list1.e.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>deprivation of women's rights;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-10.1.list1.e.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>non-implementation of laws enacted to provide protection to women and also to achieve the objective of equality and development;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-10.1.list1.e.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>non-compliance of policy decisions, guidelines or instructions aimed at mitigating hardships and ensuring welfare and providing relief to women and to take up the issues arising out of such matters with the State Government or appropriate authorities;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>render guidance and advice to needy women in instituting proceedings in any judicial forum or tribunal for violation of Constitutional provisions or any other laws relating to women;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>call for special studies or investigations into specific problems or situations arising out of discrimination and atrocities against women and identify the constraints so as to recommend strategies for their removal;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>undertake promotional and educational research so as to suggest ways of ensuring due representation of women in all spheres and identify factors responsible for impeding their advancement, such as, lack of access to housing and basic services, inadequate support services and technologies for reducing drudgery and occupational health hazards; participate and advice on the planning process of socio-economic development of women;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>evaluate the progress of the development of women in the State;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.1.list0">
              <item id="section-10.1.list0.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>inspect or cause to be inspected a jail, remand home, women's institution or other places of custody where women are kept as prisoners or otherwise, and take up with the concerned authorities such matters for remedial action as found necessary;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list0.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>may attend and with the permission of the concerned Court or Lok Nyayalaya may also have a right of audience before such Court or Lok Nyayalaya in any case or any question involving the protection of rights of women including in camera trials by any Court, within the State;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list0.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>fund litigation including police complaint involving issues affecting a large body of women or the interpretation of any provision of the Constitution or any other laws affecting women, and present to the State Government, every six months, report relating to such matters;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list0.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>make periodical reports to the State Government on any matter pertaining to women and, in particular, various difficulties under which women toil;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list0.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>co-operate with and assist and seek co-operation and assistance of the National Commission for Women and other Commissions for Women set up by different State Governments and also the Commission for Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes and the minorities Commission;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list0.p">
                <num>(p)</num>
                <p>frame schemes for the consideration of the State Government or any other appropriate authority for more effective implementation of this Act and, in particular, frame schemes for more effective implementation of laws relating to payment of maintenance to deserted women, payment of minimum wages, ensuring equal pay for equal work, housing and shelter for women, prevention of domestic violence, prevention of sexual harassment at work, prevention of illegal traffic in women, improvement of the health and safety in women and legal aid for women;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list0.q">
                <num>(q)</num>
                <p>any other matter which may be referred to it by the State Government or by the National Commission for Women.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The commission shall, while investigating any matter referred to in clause (a) or sub-clauses (i) and (ii) of Clause (f) of sub-section (1), have all the powers of a Civil Court trying a suit, and in particular, in respect of the following matters, namely:,</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person from any part in the State and examining him on oath;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>requiring the discovery and production of any document;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>receiving evidence on affidavits;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>requisitioning any public record or copy thereof from any Court or office;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>issuing commissions for the examination of witness and documents; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>any other matter which may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.3.list0">
              <item id="section-10.3.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>On any investigation mentioned in Clause (a) or sub-clauses (i) and (ii) o Clause (f) of sub-section (1) being completed, the Commission on taking up the matter with the State Government or the appropriate authority under Clause (e) or (f) of sub-section (1) may, recommend to the State Government or the appropriate authority, as the case may be, to institute legal proceedings or prosecution in the matter and may also recommend to the State Government or the appropriate authority, as the case may be, to appoint a counsel or a special prosecutor for the conduct of any such legal proceedings or prosecution; and the State Government may, having regard to the nature of the case and on being satisfied that it is necessary, in its opinion, to appoint a counsel or special prosecutor, do so.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.3.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the State Government or the appropriate authority, as the case may be, shall communicate in writing to the Commission, from time to time, the progress of any such legal proceeding or prosecution filed on the recommendation of the Commission.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government or the appropriate authority shall not apply for withdrawal of any such case or proceedings instituted under subsection (3), without the prior consultation, in writing, with the Commission.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Government to Consult Commission.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government shall consult the Commission on all major policy matters affecting women.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Power of Commission to Utilise the Services of certain Officers and Investigation Agencies for Conducting Investigation.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-12.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Commission may, for the purpose of conducting investigations under this Act utilise the services of,</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any officer or investigation agency of the State or the Central Government with the concurrence of that Government; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any other person.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-12.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>For the purpose of conducting an investigation, any officer or agency referred to in Clause (a) of sub-section (1) may, subject to the direction and control of the Commission,</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>summon and enforce the attendance of any person and examine him;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>require the discovery and production of any document ; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>requisition any public record or copy thereof from any office.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Such officer or agency or the person shall investigate into the matter as directed by the Commission and submit a report thereon (hereinafter, in this section, referred to as "the investigation report"), to the Commission within such period or extended period as may be specified or extended by the Commission in this behalf</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commission shall satisfy itself about the correctness of the facts stated and the conclusions, if any, arrived at in the investigation report submitted to it under sub-section (3), and for this purpose the Commission may make such inquiry (including the examination of the person or persons who conducted or assisted in the investigation) as it thinks fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Statement made by persons to Commission.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No statement made by a person in the course of giving evidence before the Commission or an officer or agency, referred to in Clause (a), or the person appointed under Clause (b), of sub-section (1) of section 12, shall subject him to, or be used against him in, any civil or criminal proceeding except a prosecution for giving false evidence by such statement:</p>
            <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that the statement,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>is made in reply to a question which is required by the Commission or such officer or agency or such person to answer, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>is relevant to the subject matter under investigation</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Registration of voluntary Organisations and seeking their assistance.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list0.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>Any voluntary organisation for women within the State may seek registration with the Commission for the purposes of the Act. The Commission may, after satisfying itself in the manner deemed fit by the Commission about the value and role of such organisation in the society, include the name of such organisation in its register.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commission may maintain a register of voluntary organisations within the State and more particularly women’s organisations whose assistance it may seek for the discharge of its functions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In discharge of its functions, the Commission may seek the assistance of any voluntary organisations within the State, more particularly, the women’s organisations</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A list of such organisations registered with the Commission shall be made available to any Court of authority or, on request, to the members of -general public.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If, for any reasons to be recorded in writing, the Commission deems it fit to cancel the name of any organisation from its register, it may do so, after giving such organisation a reasonable opportunity to be heard.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The decision of the Commission about such cancellation shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Protection of Act done in Good Faith.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against any member of the Commission or any officer or other employee of the Commission or any person acting under the direction either of the State Government or of the Commission, in respect of anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any rules or orders made there under.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Grants by State Government.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-16.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list0.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>The State Government shall, after due appropriation made by the State Legislature by law in this behalf, pay to the Commission by way of grants from the Consolidated Fund of the State, such sums of money as the State Government may think fit for being utilised for the purposes of this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-16.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commission may spend such sums as it thinks fit for performing the functions under this Act, and such sums of money shall be treated as expenditure payable out of the grants referred to in sub-section (1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Accounts and Audit.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commission shall maintain proper accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual statement of accounts in such form as may be prescribed by the State Government in consultation with the Accountant General of the State of Maharashtra.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The annual accounts of the Commission shall be audited by the Accountant General of the State at such intervals as may be specified by him and any expenditure incurred in connection with such audit shall be payable by the Commission to the Accountant General.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Accountant General and any person appointed by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the Commission under this Act, shall have the same rights and privileges and the authority in connection with such audit as the Accountant General generally has in connection with the audit of Government accounts and, in particular, shall have the right to demand the production of books, accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and to inspect any of the offices of the Commission.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The accounts of the Commission, as certified by the Accountant General or any other person duly appointed or authorised by him in this behalf, together with the audit report, thereon shall be forwarded annually to the State Government, by the Commission.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Annual report.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Commission shall prepare, in such form and at such time for each financial year as may be prescribed, its annual report, giving a full account of its activities during the previous financial year and forward a copy thereof to the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Annual and other reports and Audit report to be laid before State legislature.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government shall cause the annual report and all the reports under Clauses (b), (m) and (n) of sub-section (1) of section 10 together with the memorandum of action taken or proposed to be taken on the recommendation contained therein, in so far as they relate to the State Government and the reasons for the non-acceptance, if any, of such recommendations, and the audit report, to be laid as soon as may be after the reports are received, before each House of the State Legislature.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Chairperson, member, etc. to be Public Servants.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Chairperson, the members, officers and other employees of the Commission shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code, (45 of 1860).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Power to make Rules.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-21.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list0.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, and subject to the condition of previous publication, make rules for carrying out the provisions of this Act. Such rules may provide for charging of fees for any of the purpose of this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-21.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this Act, shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of the State Legislature while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done or omitted to be done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Power to remove difficulties.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-22.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-22.paragraph-0.list0.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the State Government may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such, provisions, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as appear to it to be necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that, no such order shall be made after the expiry of a period of two years from the date of commencement of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Repeal of Mah. Ord. VII of 1993 and Saving.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-23.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-23.paragraph-0.list0.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>The Maharashtra State Commission for Women Ordinance, 1993 (Mah. Ord. VII of 1993), is, hereby repealed,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-23.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken (including any notification issued or nomination, appointment, rules or order made) under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done, taken, issued or made, as the case may be, under the corresponding provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
