<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1957/4/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1957/4"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Karnataka Legislature (Prevention Of Disqualification) Act, 1956."/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1957/4/eng@2017-07-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1957/4/eng@2017-07-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-07-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1957/4/eng@2017-07-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1957/4/eng@2017-07-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-07-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Karnataka Legislature (Prevention Of Disqualification) Act, 1956.</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[24th January 1957]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No. 4 of 1957</p>
        <p>An Act to declare certain offices of profit not to disqualify their holders for being chosen as, or for being members of the Karnataka Legislative Assembly and the Karnataka Legislative Council.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to declare that certain offices should not, under certain conditions, disqualify or be deemed to have disqualified, the holders thereof for being chosen as, or for being, members of the Karnataka Legislative Assembly and the Karnataka Legislative Council;</p>
      </longTitle>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by the Karnataka State Legislature in the Seventh Year of the Republic of India as follows:—</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Karnataka Legislature (Prevention of Disqualification) Act, 1956.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“Committee” means any Committee, Commission, Council, Board or any other body of one or more persons whether statutory or not, set up by the Government of India or the Government of any State;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“Compensatory allowance” means such sum of money as the Central Government, or the Government of any State, as the case may be, may determine as being payable to the Chairman or any other member of a Committee by way of travelling allowance, daily allowance, sitting fee, conveyance allowance or house rent allowance for the purpose of enabling the Chairman or other member to recoup any expenditure incurred by him in attending any meeting of a Committee or performing any other function as a member of a Committee.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“Statutory body” means any corporation, board, company, society or any other body of one or more persons, whether incorporated or not, established, registered or formed by or under any Central Law or the law of any State for the time being in force or exercising powers and functions under any such law.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Removal of certain disqualifications.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>It is hereby declared that the following offices shall not disqualify and shall be deemed never to have disqualified, the holders thereof for being chosen as, or for being members of the Karnataka Legislative Assembly or the Karnataka Legislative Council</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the offices of the Chairman, the Speaker, the Deputy Chairman, the Deputy Speaker, the Minister of State, the Deputy Minister, the Parliamentary Secretary, the leaders of the Opposition or the Government Chief Whip in the Legislative Assembly or in the Legislative Council.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the offices held in the National Cadet Corps raised and maintained under the National Cadet Corps Act, 1948 (Central Act XXXI of 1948), in the Territorial Army raised and maintained under the Territorial Army Act, 1948 (Central Act LVI of 1948), and in the Auxiliary Air Forces Act, 1952 (Central Act LXII of 1952);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.bb">
                <num>(bb)</num>
                <p>the office of a member of the Home Guards constituted under the Karnataka Home Guards Act, 1962;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>Omitted</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c1">
                <num>(c1)</num>
                <p>the offices of the President and the Vice-President of a Municipal Council under the Karnataka Municipalities Act, 1964.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c2">
                <num>(c2)</num>
                <p>the Mayor or the Deputy Mayor of a Municipal Corporation constituted under the Karnataka Municipal Corporations Act, 1976.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c3">
                <num>(c3)</num>
                <p>the offices of Adhyaksha and Upadhyaksha of the Zilla Panchayats, Taluk Panchayats and Grama Panchayats constituted under the Karnataka Panchayat Raj Act, 1993.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the offices of the Chairman, Vice-Chairman, President, Vice President, Director, of the Governing body or a Member by whatever name any of the aforesaid office is called, of any Committee (by whatever name called) or of any Society registered under any other law relating to registration of societies.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
