<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1982/3/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1982/3"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Sugar Cess Act, 1982"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1982/3/eng@1982-03-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1982/3/eng@1982-03-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1982-03-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1982/3/eng@1982-03-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1982/3/eng@1982-03-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Sugar Cess Act, 1982</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 3 OF 1982</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 19th March, 1982.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty- third Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the imposition of a cess on sugar for the  development of sugar industry and for matters connected therewith.</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:--</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be  called the Sugar Cess Act, 1982.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date  as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" occupier", in relation to any sugar factory, means the  person who has ultimate control over the affairs of the sugar  factory or the owner of the sugar factory in case he is not the  occupier;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" sugar factory" means any premises (including the   precincts thereof) in any part of which sugar is manufactured by  vacuum pan process;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>" sugar" means any form of sugar including crushed sugar  or sugar in crystalised or powder form, containing ninety per  cent, or more of sucrose and produced by the vacuum pan process  and includes raw sugar produced by the said process.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Imposition of cess.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be levied and collected as  a cess, for the purposes of the Sugar Development Fund Act, 1982, a  duty of excise on all sugar produced by any sugar factory in India, at  such rate not exceeding  fifteen rupees] per quintal of sugar, as  the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette,</p>
            <p>specify from time to time:</p>
            <p>Provided that until such rate is specified by the Central</p>
            <p>Government, the duty of excise shall be levied and collected at the  rate of  fourteen rupees] per quintal of sugar.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The duty of excise levied under sub- section (1) shall be in  addition to the duty of excise leviable on sugar under the Central</p>
            <p>Excises and Salt Act, 1944, (1 of 1944.) or any other law for the time  being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The duty of excise levied under sub- section (1) shall be  payable by the occupier of the sugar factory in which sugar is  produced.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of the Central Excises and Salt Act, 1944, (1   of 1944.) and the rules made thereunder, including those relating to  refunds and exemptions from duty, shall, so far as may be, apply in  relation to the levy and collection of the said duty of excise as they  apply in relation to the levy and collection of the duty of excise on  sugar under that Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Crediting proceeds of duty to Consolidated Fund of India. The  proceeds of the duty of excise levied under section 3 shall be  credited to the Consolidated Fund of India.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Power to call for reports and returns. The Central Government  may require an occupier of a sugar factory to furnish, for the  purposes of this Act, such statistical and other information in such  form and within such period as may be prescribed.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the  provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for the form in which and the  period within which statistical and other information may be furnished  under section 5.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as  may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is  in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised  in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before  the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the  successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not  be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified  form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any  such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the  validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
