<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2010/31/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2010/31"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Land Ports Authority of India Act, 2010"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2010/31/eng@2016-11-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2010/31/eng@2016-11-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-11-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2010/31/eng@2016-11-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2010/31/eng@2016-11-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-11-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Land Ports Authority Of India Act, 2010</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 31 OF 2010</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[31st August, 2010.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the establishment of the Land Ports Authority of India to put in place systems which address security imperatives and for the development and management of facilities for cross border movement of passengers and goods at designated points along the international borders of India and for matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.</p>
      </longTitle>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Sixty-first Year of the Republic of India as follows:—</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <heading>Preliminary</heading>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title and commencement.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the Land Ports Authority of India Act, 2010.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint, and different dates may be appointed for different provisions of this Act, and any reference in any such provision to the commencement of this Act shall be construed as a reference to the coming into force of that provision.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>“Authority” means the Land Ports Authority of India constituted under section 3;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>“Chairperson” means the Chairperson of the Authority appointed under clause (a) of sub-section (3) of section 3;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>“immigration check post” means any port or place of departure on the land as notified under the Foreigners' Act, 1946 (31 of 1946);</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>“integrated check post” means any land port, as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>“land customs station” means any place notified as such by the Central Government under clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 7 of the Customs Act, 1962 (52 of 1962) for the clearance of goods imported or to be exported by land or inland water;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>“land port” means an area on the international borders of India including portions of national highways, State highways and other roads, notified as land customs station or immigration check post under the Customs Act, 1962 (52 of 1962) or the Foreigners' Act, 1946 (31 of 1946), and includes railways, with facilities for clearance and transport of passengers and goods across the borders of India;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>“notification” means a notification published in the Official Gazette;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>“regulations” means regulations made by the Authority under this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <heading>The land ports authority of india</heading>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Constitution of Authority.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>With effect from such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint, there shall be constituted an Authority to be known as the Land Ports Authority of India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Authority shall be a body corporate by the name aforesaid, having perpetual succession and a common seal, with power, subject to the provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of property both movable and immovable, and to contract and shall by the said name sue and be sued.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Authority shall consist of—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>a Chairperson;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.3.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>two Members, out of whom one shall be Member (Planning and Development) and other shall be Member (Finance);</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.3.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>not more than nine members, ex officio, to be appointed by the Central Government from amongst the officers, not below the rank of the Joint Secretary to the Government of India, representing the ministries or departments of the Government of India dealing with Home Affairs, External Affairs, Revenue, Commerce, Road Transport and Highways, Railways, Defence, Agriculture and Cooperation, Law and Justice;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.3.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the Chief Secretary or his nominee not below the rank of the Secretary to the Government of the respective State where the integrated check posts are located;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.3.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>two representatives, one of whom shall be from recognised bodies of workers and the other shall be from traders, to be appointed by the Central Government; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.3.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>such other representatives as the Central Government may co-opt for functional purposes.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chairperson and the members referred to in clause (b) shall be appointed by the Central Government and shall be whole-time members.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chairperson shall be chosen from among persons who have special knowledge and experience in the field of security, transport, industry, commerce, law, finance or public administration.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Disqualification for office of member.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>A person shall be disqualified for being appointed as a member if, he—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>has been convicted and sentenced to imprisonment for an offence, which, in the opinion of the Central Government, involves moral turpitude; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>is an undischarged insolvent; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>is of unsound mind and stands so declared by a competent court; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>has been removed or dismissed from the service of the Government or a body corporate owned or controlled by the Government; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>has in the opinion of the Central Government such financial or other interest in the Authority as is likely to affect prejudicially the discharge by him of his functions as a member.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Term of office and conditions of service of members.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of section 6, every whole-time member shall hold office for a period of five years from the date on which he assumes office or till he attains the age of sixty years, whichever is earlier:</p>
              <blockList id="section-5.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that the Central Government may—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.1.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>terminate the appointment of any whole-time member, after giving him notice of a period of not less than three months or, in lieu thereof, on payment of an amount equal to his salary and allowances, if any, for a period of three months;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-5.1.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>terminate at any time the appointment of any member who is a servant of the Government.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The other conditions of service of the members shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any member may resign his office by giving notice in writing for such period as may be prescribed, to the Central Government and, on such resignation being notified in the Official Gazette by that Government, such member shall be deemed to have vacated his office.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Vacation of office of members.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Central Government shall remove a member if, he—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>becomes subject to any of the disqualifications mentioned in section 4:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that no member shall be removed on the ground that he has become subject to the disqualification mentioned in clause (e) of that section, unless he has been given a reasonable opportunity of being heard in the matter; or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>refuses to act or becomes incapable of acting; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>is, without obtaining leave of absence from the Authority, absent from three consecutive meetings of the Authority; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>in the opinion of the Central Government, has so abused his position as to render his continuance in office detrimental to the public interest:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that no member shall be removed under this clause unless he has been given a reasonable opportunity of being heard in the matter.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Eligibility of member for re-appointment.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Any person ceasing to be a member shall, unless disqualified under section 4, be eligible for re-appointment.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Meetings.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Authority shall meet at such times and places, and shall observe such rules of procedure in regard to the transaction of business at its meetings (including the quorum at such meetings) as may be provided by regulations.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chairperson, or, if for any reason, he is unable to attend any meeting of the Authority, any other member chosen by the members present at the meeting shall preside at the meeting.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All questions which come up before any meeting of the Authority shall be decided by a majority of the votes of the members present and voting, and in the event of an equality of votes, the Chairperson, or in his absence the person presiding, shall have and exercise a second or casting vote.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Vacancies, etc., not to invalidate proceedings of Authority.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>No act or proceeding of the Authority shall be invalid merely by reason of—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>any vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution of, the Authority; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>any defect in the appointment of a person acting as a member of the Authority; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>any irregularity in the procedure of the Authority not affecting the merits of the case.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Officers and other employees of Authority.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purpose of enabling it to efficiently discharge its functions under this Act, the Authority shall appoint such number of officers and other employees as it may consider necessary:</p>
              <p>Provided that the appointment of such category of officers, as may be specified, shall be subject to the approval of the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every officer or other employee appointed by the Authority shall be subject to such conditions of service and shall be entitled to such remuneration as may be determined by regulations.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <heading>Functions of authority</heading>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Functions of Authority.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Authority shall have powers to develop, sanitize and manage the facilities for cross border movement of passengers and goods at designated points along the international borders of India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-11.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Without prejudice to the generality of the provisions contained in sub-section (1), the Authority may—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>put in place systems, which address security imperatives at the integrated check posts on the border;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>plan, construct and maintain roads, terminals and ancillary buildings other than national highways, State highways and railways, at an integrated check post;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>plan, procure, install and maintain communication, security, goods handling and scanning equipment at an integrated check post;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>provide appropriate space and facilities for immigration, customs, security, taxation authorities, animal and plant quarantine, warehouses, cargo and baggage examination yards, parking zones, banks, post offices, communication facilities, tourist information centres, waiting halls, canteen, refreshment stalls, public conveniences, health services and such other services, as may be deemed necessary;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>construct residential buildings for its employees as well as residential accommodation for staff deployed at integrated check posts;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>establish and maintain hotels, restaurants and restrooms;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>establish and maintain warehouses, container depots and cargo complexes for the storage or processing of goods;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>arrange for postal, money exchange, insurance and telephone facilities for the use of passengers and other persons at integrated check posts;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>make appropriate arrangements for the security of integrated check posts and provide for regulation and control of movement of vehicles, entry and exit of passengers and goods in accordance with the respective law concerning them;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>ensure prevention and control of fire and other hazards and other facilities as deemed necessary;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>regulate and control the movement of vehicles, and the entry and exit of passengers, transportation workers, handling agents, clearing and forwarding agents and goods at the integrated check post with due regard to the law, security and protocol of the Government of India;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>co-ordinate and facilitate the working of agencies who have been engaged to undertake various activities at the integrated check posts, in accordance with the respective law, for the time being in force;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.m">
                  <num>(m)</num>
                  <p>develop and provide consultancy, construction or management services, and undertake operations in India and abroad in relation to an integrated check post;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.n">
                  <num>(n)</num>
                  <p>form one or more companies under the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) or under any other law relating to companies for efficient discharge of the functions imposed on it by this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.o">
                  <num>(o)</num>
                  <p>take all such steps as may be necessary or expedient for, or may be incidental to, the exercise of any power or the discharge of any function conferred or imposed on it by this Act:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-11.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that sovereign functions of the Authority shall not be assigned to any private entity;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.2.list3.p">
                  <num>(p)</num>
                  <p>set up joint ventures for the discharge of any of the functions assigned to the Authority; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list3.q">
                  <num>(q)</num>
                  <p>undertake any other activity at the integrated check post in the best commercial interests of the Authority.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the discharge of its functions under this section, the Authority may consult such ministry or department of the Government of India or of the State Government as it deems necessary, and shall have due regard to the development of land port services and to the efficiency, economy and safety of such service.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-11.4.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Nothing contained in this section shall be construed as—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.4.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>authorising the disregard by the Authority of any law for the time being in force; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.4.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>authorising any person to institute any proceeding in respect of duty or liability to which the Authority or its officers or other employees would not otherwise be subject to.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Responsibilities and powers of other agencies.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-12.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The respective border guarding forces deployed at the borders of India shall be responsible for security around an integrated check post.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Authority may, whenever considered necessary so to do for ensuring the peace and security at an integrated check post, seek the assistance of armed force, Central para military force or State police as per the provisions of the law for the time being in force.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Customs, immigration, quarantine and other officials shall co-ordinate with the Authority for the effective discharge of its functions.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any provisions of this Act, the Customs, immigration, quarantine officials, the border guarding forces and the police shall discharge their functions in accordance with the law for the time being in force.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <heading>Property and contract</heading>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Assets and liabilities to vest in Authority.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-13.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On the date of notification issued under clause (d) of section 2, all such assets, rights, powers, authorities and privileges and such property movable and immovable, real or personal, corporeal or incorporeal, present or contingent, of whatever nature, including lands, buildings, machinery, equipments, works, workshops, cash balances, capital, reserves, reserve funds, investments, tenancies, losses and book debts and all other rights and interests arising out of such property, as immediately before the issue of that notification, were in the ownership or possession of the Government of India in any of the land port, as the Central Government may, in such notification, specify, shall vest in the Authority and such vesting shall also be deemed to include all borrowings, liabilities and obligations of whatever kind then subsisting.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The notification under sub-section (1) shall be issued only after the concurrence of the concerned ministries or departments of the Government of India, in case where such properties are owned or controlled by such ministries or departments.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>General effect of vesting of undertakings in Authority.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>All contracts, agreements and working arrangements subsisting immediately before the date of notification issued under clause (d) of section 2, and affecting the land ports shall be of full force and effect as regards the Authority.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Guarantee to be operative.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Any guarantee given for or in favour of land customs stations or immigration check posts with respect to a loan, lease or finance shall continue to be operative in relation to such stations or check posts which have been vested in the Authority by virtue of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Compulsory acquisition of land for Authority.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Any land required by the Authority for the discharge of its functions under this Act shall be deemed to be needed for a public purpose and such land may be acquired for the Authority under the provisions of the National Highways Act, 1956 (48 of 1956) or any other law for the time being in force.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Contracts by Authority.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of section 18, the Authority shall be competent to enter into and perform any contract necessary for the discharge of its functions under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Mode of executing contracts on behalf of Authority.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-18.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every contract on behalf of the Authority, shall be made by the Chairperson or such officer of the Authority as may be generally or specially empowered in this behalf by the Authority and such contracts as may be specified, in the regulations, shall be sealed with the common seal of the Authority:</p>
              <p>Provided that no contract exceeding such value or amount as the Central Government may, by order fix in this behalf, shall be made unless it has been previously approved by the Central Government:</p>
              <p>Provided further that no contract for the acquisition or sale of immovable property or for the lease of any such property for a term exceeding thirty years and no other contract exceeding such value or amount as the Central Government may, by order fix in this behalf, shall be made unless it has been previously approved by the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of sub-section (1), the form and manner in which any contract shall be made under this Act shall be such as may be provided by regulations.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any contract which is not in accordance with the provisions of this Act and the rules and regulations made thereunder shall not be binding on the Authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <heading>Finance, accounts and audit</heading>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Power of Authority to charge fees, rent, etc.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-19.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Authority may, determine and charge such fees or rent, not being a statutory levy under any other Act, as may be provided by regulations, separately for each integrated check post,—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>for the cargo handling, warehousing, parking of trucks or for any other service or facility offered in connection with transport operations;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>for the parking of passenger vehicles and other amenities given to the passengers and visitors; and;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>for the availing of facilities and other services provided by the Authority.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Additional capital and grant to Authority by Central Government.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-20.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Central Government may, after the appropriation made by Parliament by law in this behalf,—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>provide any capital that may be required by the Authority for the discharge of its functions under this Act or for any purpose connected therewith on such terms and conditions as that Government may determine;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>pay to the Authority, on such terms and conditions as the Central Government may determine, by way of loans or grants such sums of money as that Government may consider necessary for the efficient discharge of its functions under this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Fund of Authority and its investment.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-21.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Authority shall establish its own fund and all receipts of the Authority shall be credited thereto and all payments by the Authority shall be made there from.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-21.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Authority shall have the power, subject to the provisions of this Act, to spend such sums as it thinks fit to cover all administrative expenses of the Authority or for purposes authorised by this Act and such sums shall be treated as expenditure out of the fund of the Authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-21.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-21.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>All moneys standing at the credit of the Authority which cannot immediately be applied as provided in sub-section (2), shall be—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-21.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>deposited in the State Bank of India or any such scheduled bank or banks or other public financial institutions subject to such conditions as may, from time to time, be specified by the Central Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.3.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>invested in the securities of the Central Government or in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Explanation.—</p>
              <p>In this sub-section, “scheduled bank” has the same meaning as in clause (e) of section 2 of the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Allocation of surplus funds.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-22.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Authority may, from time to time, set apart such amounts as it thinks fit, as a reserve fund or funds for the purpose of expanding existing facilities or services or creating new facilities or services at any integrated check post or increase of expenditure from transient causes or for purposes of replacement or meeting expenditure arising from loss or damage due to any natural calamity or accident or meeting any liability arising out of any act of omission or commission in the discharge of its functions under this Act:</p>
              <p>Provided that the Authority shall also have the power to establish specific reserves for specific purposes:</p>
              <p>Provided further that the sums set apart annually in respect of each or any of the specific and general reserves and the aggregate at any time of such sums shall not exceed such limits as may, from time to time, be fixed in that behalf by the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>After making provision for such reserve fund or funds and for bad and doubtful debts, depreciation in assets and all other matters which are usually provided for by companies registered and incorporated under the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), the Authority shall pay the balance of its annual net profits to the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Submission of programme of activities and financial estimates.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Authority shall, before the commencement of each financial year prepare a statement of the programme of its activities during the forthcoming financial year as well as financial estimate in respect thereof and submit it for the approval of the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Borrowing powers of Authority.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-24.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Authority may, with the consent of the Central Government or in accordance with the terms of any general or special authority given to it by the Central Government, borrow money from any source by the issue of bonds, debentures or such other instruments as it may deem fit for discharging all or any of its functions under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-24.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may guarantee in such manner as it thinks fit, the repayment of the principal and the payment of interest thereon with respect to the loans taken by the Authority under sub-section (1).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-24.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to such limits as the Central Government may, from time to time, lay down, the Authority may borrow temporarily by way of overdraft or otherwise, such amount as it may require for discharging its functions under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Accounts and audit.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-25.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Authority shall maintain proper accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual statement of accounts including the profit and loss account and the balance sheet in such form as may be prescribed by the Central Government in consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The accounts of the Authority shall be audited annually by the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India and any expenditure incurred by him in connection with such audit shall be reimbursed to him by the Authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Comptroller and Auditor-General of India and any person appointed by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the Authority shall have the same rights and privileges and authority in connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor-General has in connection with the audit of Government accounts and, in particular shall have the right to demand the production of books, accounts, connected vouchers, documents and papers and inspect any of the offices of the Authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The accounts of the Authority as certified by the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India or any other person appointed by him in this behalf together with the audit report thereon shall be forwarded annually to the Central Government and that Government shall cause the same to be laid before both Houses of Parliament.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VI">
        <num>VI</num>
        <heading>Miscellaneous</heading>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Submission of annual report.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-26.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Authority shall, as soon as may be, after the end of each financial year, prepare and submit to the Central Government in such form as may be prescribed, a report giving an account of its activities during that financial year and the report shall also give an account of the activities which are likely to be undertaken by the Authority during the next financial year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-26.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government shall cause such report to be laid before both Houses of Parliament, as soon as may be, after it is submitted.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Delegation.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Authority may, by general or special order in writing, delegate to the Chairperson or any other member or to any officer of the Authority, subject to such conditions and limitations, if any, as may be specified in the order, such of its powers and functions under this Act (except the powers under section 35), as it may deem necessary.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Authentication of orders and other instruments of Authority.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>All orders and decisions of the Authority shall be authenticated by the signature of the Chairperson or any other member authorised by</p>
              <p>the Authority in this behalf and all other instruments executed by the Authority shall be authenticated by the signature of an officer of the Authority authorised by it in this behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Officers and employees of Authority to be public servants.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-29.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>All officers and employees of Authority shall, while acting or purporting to act in pursuance of the provisions of this Act or of any rule or regulation made thereunder, be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-30.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Authority or any member or any officer or other employee of the Authority for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or of any rule or regulation made thereunder.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading>Custody and disposal of lost property.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-31.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Subject to such regulations as the Authority may make in this behalf, the Authority shall provide for securing the safe custody and restoration of any property which, while not in proper custody, is found on any premises belonging to the Authority or under its overall control.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>Power of Central Government to supersede Authority.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-32.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-32.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>If, at any time, the Central Government is of opinion—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>that on account of a grave emergency, the Authority is unable to discharge the functions and duties imposed on it by or under the provisions of this Act; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>that the Authority has persistently defaulted in complying with any direction issued by the Central Government under this Act or in the discharge of the functions and duties imposed on it by or under the provisions of this Act and as a result of default the financial position of the Authority or the administration of an integrated check post has deteriorated; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>that circumstances exist which render it necessary in the public interest so to do,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, supersede the Authority for such period, not exceeding six months, as may be specified in the notification:</p>
              <p>Provided that before issuing a notification under this sub-section for the reasons mentioned in clause (b), the Central Government shall give a reasonable opportunity to the Authority to show cause why it should not be superseded and shall consider the explanations and objections, if any, of the Authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-32.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Upon the publication of a notification under sub-section (1) superseding the Authority,—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>all the members shall, as from the date of supersession, vacate their offices as such;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>all the powers, functions and duties which may, by or under the provisions of this Act, be exercised or discharged by or on behalf of the Authority, shall until the Authority is reconstituted under sub-section (3), be exercised and discharged by such person or persons as the Central Government may direct; and;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>all property owned or controlled by the Authority shall, until the Authority is reconstituted under sub-section (3), vest in the Central Government.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-32.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>On the expiration of the period of supersession specified in the notification issued under sub-section (1), the Central Government may,—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>extend the period of supersession for such further term not exceeding six months, as it may consider necessary, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.3.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>reconstitute the Authority by fresh appointment and in such case the members who vacated their offices under clause (a) of sub-section (2) shall not be deemed disqualified for appointment:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that the Central Government may, at any time before the expiration of the period of supersession, whether as originally specified under sub-section (1) or as extended under this sub-section, take action under clause (b) of this sub-section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government shall cause a notification issued under sub-section (1) and a full report of any action taken under this section and the circumstances leading to such action to be laid before both Houses of Parliament in the immediate subsequent session of Parliament.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading>Power of Central Government to issue directions.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-33.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Without prejudice to the foregoing provisions of this Act, the Authority shall, in the discharge of its functions and duties under this Act, be bound by such directions on questions of policy as the Central Government may give in writing to it from time to time:</p>
              <p>Provided that the Authority shall, as far as practicable, be given opportunity to express its views before any direction is given under this sub-section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-33.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The decision of the Central Government whether a question is one of policy or not shall be final.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-33.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, from time to time, issue directions to the Authority regarding the discharge of any functions by it under the clauses of sub-section (2) of section 11 and the Authority shall be bound to comply with such directions.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-34">
          <num>34.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-34.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-34.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-34.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-34.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the other conditions of service of members of the Authority under sub-section (2) of section 5;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-34.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the period of notice as may be given by any member to resign his office under sub-section (3) of section 5;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-34.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which the Authority may invest the funds under clause (b) of sub-section (3) of section 21;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-34.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the form in which the annual statement of accounts shall be prepared by the Authority under sub-section (1) of section 25;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-34.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the form in which a report giving an account of its activities shall be prepared and submitted by the Authority to the Central Government under sub-section (1) of section 26; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-34.2.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>any other matter which is to be, or may be, prescribed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading>Power to make regulations.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-35.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Authority may, with the previous approval of the Central Government, make regulations not inconsistent with this Act and the rules made thereunder for the purpose of giving effect to the provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-35.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-35.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such regulations may provide for—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-35.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the time and places of meetings of the Authority and the procedure to be followed for transaction of business including the quorum at such meetings under sub-section (1) of section 8;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-35.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the conditions of service and the remuneration of officers and other employees to be appointed by the Authority under sub-section (2) of section 10;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-35.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the contracts which are to be sealed with the common seal of the Authority under sub-section (1), and the form and manner in which a contract may be made by the Authority under sub-section (2) of section 18;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-35.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the fees and rent to be charged by the Authority under sub-section (1) of section 19;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-35.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the custody and restoration of lost property and the terms and conditions under which lost property may be restored to the persons entitled thereto under section 31.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-36">
          <num>36.</num>
          <heading>Rules, regulations and notifications to be laid before Parliament.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-36.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every rule and every regulation made or notification issued under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule, regulation or notification, as the case may be, or both Houses agree that the rule, regulation or notification, as the case may be, should not be made or issued, the rule, regulation or notification shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be;</p>
              <p>so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule, regulation or notification.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-37">
          <num>37.</num>
          <heading>Power to remove difficulties.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-37.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government may, by general or special order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act as appear to it to be necessary or expedient for the removal of the difficulty:</p>
              <p>Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a period of two years from the date of the commencement of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-37.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every order made under this section shall as soon as may be after it is made, be laid before each House of Parliament.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
