<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-wbg/act/1994/51/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-wbg/act/1994/51"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The West Bengal Prohibition Of Unlawful Possession Of Property Of Electrical Undertakings Act, 1994"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-wbg/act/1994/51/eng@2017-01-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-wbg/act/1994/51/eng@2017-01-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-wbg/act/1994/51/eng@2017-01-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-wbg/act/1994/51/eng@2017-01-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-12-07" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The West Bengal Prohibition Of Unlawful Possession Of Property Of Electrical Undertakings Act, 1994</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[Act No. 51 of 1994]</p>
      </longTitle>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[8th May, 1995]</docDate>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>An Act to prohibit unlawful possession of property of electrical undertaking in West Bengal.</p>
      <p>Whereas it is expedient to prohibit unlawful possession of property of electrical undertakings in West Bengal;</p>
      <p>It is hereby enacted as follows:-</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the West Bengal Prohibition of Unlawful Possession of Property of Electrical Undertakings Act, 1994.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of West Bengal.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>"electrical undertaking" means-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>a Generating Company, by whatever name called, formed by the State Government and registered under the Companies Act, 1956, or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>the West Bengal State Electricity Board constituted under section 5 of the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1948,</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>and includes a licensee as defined in clause (h) of section 2 of the Indian Electricity Act, 1910;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>"property" includes-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>distributing main, electric supply-line, main overhead line, public lamp, service-line, or works, as defined in section 2 of the Indian Electricity Act. 1910, or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.b.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>main transmission lines, or tie-line, as defined in section 2 of the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1948.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for unlawful possession of property of electrical undertakings</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Whoever is found, or is proved to have been, in possession of any property of any electrical undertaking reasonably suspected of having been stolen or unlawfully obtained shall, unless he proves that such property came into his possession lawfully, be punishable-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for the first offence, with imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years, and shall also be liable to tine and in the absence of special and adequate reasons to be mentioned in the judgement of the court, such imprisonment shall not be less than two years and such fine shall not be less than two thousand rupees;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>for the second or a subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term which may extend to seven years and also with fine and in the absence of special and adequate reasons to be mentioned in the judgement of the court, such imprisonment shall not be less than three years and such fine shall not be less than three thousand rupees.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Punishment for connivance at offences</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any owner or occupier of land or building or any agent of such owner or occupier in-charge of the management of that land or building, who wilfully connives at an offence against the provisions of this Act, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years, or with fine, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Power to arrest without warrant</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any police officer not below the rank of Inspector may, without an order from a Magistrate and without a warrant, arrest any person who has been concerned in an offence punishable under this Act or against whom a reasonable suspicion exists of his having been so concerned.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Issue of search warrant</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If a police officer has reason to believe that any place is used for the deposit or sale of any property of any electrical undertaking which had been stolen or unlawfully obtained, he shall make an application to the Magistrate having jurisdiction over the area in which that place is situate, for issue of a search warrant.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Magistrate to whom an application is made under sub-section (1), may, after such inquiry as he thinks necessary, by his warrant authorise any police officer-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to enter, with such assistance as may be required, such place;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to search the same in the manner specified in the warrant;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to take possession of any property of the electrical undertaking therein found which he reasonably suspects to be stolen or unlawfully obtained; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>to convey such property of the electrical undertaking before a Magistrate, or to guard the same on the spot until the offender is taken before a Magistrate, or otherwise to dispose thereof in some place of safety.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Searches and arrests how to be made</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>All searches and arrests made under this Act shall be carried out in accordance with the provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973, relating respectively to searches and arrests made under that Code.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Assistance to police officer</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>All officers of the State Government and all members of Gram Panchayats, Panchayat Samitis and Zilla Parishads and also of Mahakuma Parishad, constituted under the West Bengal Panchayat Act, 1973, are hereby empowered and required to assist the police officers in the enforcement of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Power to try offences</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No Court inferior to that of a Judicial Magistrate of the first class or, in any metropolitan area, a Metropolitan Magistrate shall try any offence punishable under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Power of Court to order forfeiture of property etc.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any court trying an offence punishable under this Act may order the forfeiture to the State Government of any property of any electrical undertaking in respect of which the court is satisfied that an offence under this Act has been committed and may also order the forfeiture of any receptacles, packages or coverings in which such property is contained, and the animals, vehicles, or other conveyances used in carrying the property.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon the forfeiture of any property of any electrical undertaking to the State Government under sub-section (1) the State Government shall, after consultation with such electrical undertaking, dispose of such property in such manner as it deems fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Act to override other laws</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained in any other law for the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
