<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-meg/act/2012/13/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-meg/act/2012/13"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Meghalaya Compulsory Registration Of Marriage Act, 2012"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-meg/act/2012/13/eng@2017-03-16/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-meg/act/2012/13/eng@2017-03-16"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-16" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-meg/act/2012/13/eng@2017-03-16/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-meg/act/2012/13/eng@2017-03-16"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-16" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Meghalaya Compulsory Registration Of Marriage Act, 2012</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 13 OF 2012</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[14th September, 2012]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for compulsory registration of marriage in the State of Meghalaya and for matters connected therewith;</p>
        <p>Whereas, it is expedient to provide for compulsory registration of marriages in the State of Meghalaya;</p>
        <p>Whereas further it is mandatory for married man and married women to compulsorily furnish a marriage certificate for all official purposes;</p>
        <p>Be it enacted by the Legislature of the State of Meghalaya in the Sixty-third Year of the Republic of India as follows:</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Meghalaya Compulsory Registration of Marriages Act, 2012.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of Meghalaya.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the state Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“Act” means the Meghalaya Compulsory Registration of Marriage Act, 2012;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"marriage" includes all marriages contracted by persons belonging to any caste, tribe or religion, and the marriages contracted in accordance with customary, practices or traditions and also includes re-marriages and marriages contracted under any existing law.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.bb">
                <num>(bb)</num>
                <p>"Marriage Officer" or "License Holder" means such officer or license holder notified or authorized under the Indian Christian Marriage Act,1872 (Central Act No. 15 of 1872), the Special Marriage Act, 1954 (Central Act No. 43 of 1954), the Hindu Marriage Act, 1955 (Central Act 25 of 1955)the Meghalaya Moslem Marriages and Divorces Registration Act (Assam Act IX of 1935) (as adopted by the State of Meghalaya) or any other Act for the time being in force in the State.-</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“memorandum” means a memorandum of marriage mentioned in Section 5 of this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>“prescribed” means a prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>“register” means a register of marriages maintained under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>"Registrar" means a Registrar of marriages appointed under section 4 of the Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>"Registrar General of Marriages" means the Secretary to the Government of Meghalaya in the Excise, Registration, Taxation and Stamps Department, ex-officio;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>“State Government” means the Government of the State of Meghalaya; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>"to contract a marriage" means to solemnize or enter into a marriage in any form or manner, in accordance with any religion, custom, practices or traditions in force and includes marriages solemnized by a Marriage Officer or an authorized License holder under any existing law.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Every Marriage in the State to be registered.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>After the date on which the provisions of this Act have been brought into force under sub-section (3) of Section 1, every marriage contracted in the State shall be compulsorily registered in the manner provided in Section 5 and such marriage registration shall be required for all official purposes.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Appointment of Registrars of Marriages.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may appoint, one or more officer of the Government as it thinks necessary, to be Registrars of Marriages for such local areas as it may specify.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Memorandum of Marriage.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The parties to a marriage to which Section 3 applies, shall prepare and sign a memorandum in the form as may be prescribed and shall deliver or send by registered post the said memorandum in duplicate to the Registrar of the area within a period of sixty days from the date of the marriage.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The memorandum shall also be signed by the bride and the bridegroom and two witnesses from each side.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The memorandum shall be accompanied with a fee as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Registrar shall maintain a register of such marriages in such form as may be prescribed and on receipt of the memorandum, he shall file the same in the register and shall also send the duplicate copy thereof to the Registrar General of marriages.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Memorandum of Marriage submitted after 30 days</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A memorandum regarding any particular marriage may be submitted to the Registrar even after the expiry of the sixty days as specified in sub- section (1) of Section 5. However, such memorandum shall be in the form, and shall be signed, as provided for in Section 5 and shall be accompanied with such fee, as may be prescribed. On receipt of such memorandum, the Registrar shall file the same in the Register and shall also send the duplicate copy thereof to the Registrar General as provided in Section 5.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing contained in sub- section (1) shall effect or absolve the liability of any person who has willfully omitted or neglected to deliver or send the memorandum within the period specified in sub-section (1) of Section 5 to any penalty under Section 14.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Marriage Certification to be given to the couple.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Registrar shall , as soon as the registration of marriage has been completed, give free of cost, to the couple a certificate of registration of the marriage in the form as may be prescribed under his hand and seal.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Such certificate issued by the Registrar shall be the conclusive proof of registration of the said marriage.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Registrar to keep registers in the prescribed form.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Registrar shall keep in the prescribed form a Register of Marriage made in the area under his jurisdiction.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Registrar-General shall from time to time cause to be printed and supplied to the Registrars sufficient number of registers in the prescribed form.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Search of Register.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Subject to any rules made in this behalf by the State Government including the rules relating to payment of fees any person may-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>cause a search to be made for any entry in the Register of Marriage; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>obtain an extract from such Register.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All extracts given under sub-section (1) shall be signed by the Registrar concerned and shall be admissible as evidence in any court of law for the purposes of establishing the fact of marriage to which the entry relates.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Register to be open for public inspection.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The register maintained under this Act shall, at all reasonable times, be open to inspection and certified extracts there from shall on application be given by the Registrar on payment by the applicant of a fee as may be prescribed for each such extract.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Registrar to send periodical returns to the Registrar General for compilation.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every Registrar shall send to .the Registrar-General or to any officer specified by him at such intervals and in such form as may be prescribed, a return regarding entries of marriage registration in the Register kept by such Registrar.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Non-registration not to invalidate marriage.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No marriage contracted in the State of Meghalaya prior to this Act shall be deemed to be invalid solely by reason of the fact that it was not registered under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for failing to Register a Marriage.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any Registrar who fails to register a marriage pursuant to section 5 or section 6 shall on conviction be punished with simple imprisonment for a term which may extend to three months or fine which may extend to five hundred rupees or both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for neglecting to comply with the provisions of section 4, 5 and 6 or for making false statement in Memorandum.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any person who -</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>willfully omits or neglects to get his or her marriage registered under this Act as required under section 3; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>willfully omits or neglects to deliver or send the memorandum as required by section 5 or 6; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>makes any statement in such memorandum which is false in any material particulars and which he knows or has reason to believe to be false.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall, on conviction be punished with simple imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees or both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for secreting, destroying or altering Register.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any person, destroying or dishonesty or fraudulently altering the register or any part thereof shall, on conviction, be punished with simple imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months and shall also be liable to fine.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Offences under this Act summarily triable by a Magistrate.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>An offence under this Act shall be tried summarily by the Judicial Magistrate of the First Class, in accordance with the procedure as laid down in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Cognizance of offence under the Act.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No court shall take cognizance of any offence punishable under this Act, except upon a complaint in writing made by the Registrar of the area concerned or by an officer authorized by the Registrar-General of Marriages as the Case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Registrar to be public servant</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every Registrar shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code 186G (No. XLV of 1860).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Protection for action taken in good faith.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against the State Government, the Registrar General of Marriages, any Registrar or any person exercising any power or performing any duty under this Act, for anything which is done or intended to be done in good faith in pursuance of this Act or any rules or orders made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-20.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Meghalaya Gazette, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-20.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing powers, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely :-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-20.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the duties and powers of the Registrar General of Marriages and the Registrars;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-20.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the forms and the manner in which memorandum under sections 5 and 6 shall be filed and registers or records required to be kept by or under this Act shall be maintained.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-20.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the custody in whom the registers and records are to be kept and preservation of such registers and records;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-20.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the fees to be paid under the Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before the Legislative Assembly of Meghalaya.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Application of other laws not barred.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Save as otherwise provided the provisions of this Act shall be in addition to and not in derogation of any existing law in force.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
