<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1976/19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1976/19"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Bonded Labour System (Abolition) Act, 1976"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1976/19/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1976/19/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1976/19/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1976/19/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-11-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Bonded Labour System (Abolition) Act, 1976</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[9th February, 1976]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>(19 of 1976)</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the abolition of bonded labour system with a view to preventing the economic and physical exploitation of the weaker sections of the people and for matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.</p>
      </longTitle>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty-seventh Year of the Republic of India as follows:-</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Bonded Labour System (Abolition) Act, 1976.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 25th day of October, 1975.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“advance” means an advance, whether in cash or in kind, or partly in cash or partly in kind, made by one person (hereinafter referred to as the creditor) to another person (hereinafter referred to as the debtor);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“agreement” means as agreement (whether written or oral, or partly written and partly oral) between a debtor and creditor, and includes an agreement providing for forced labour, the existence of which is presumed under any social custom prevailing in the concerned locality.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation.— The existence of an agreement between the debtor and creditor is ordinarily presumed, under the social custom, in relation to the following forms of forced labour, namely:— Adiyamar, Baramasia, Basahya, Bethu, Bhagela, Cherumar, Garru-Galu, Hali, Hari, Harwai, Holya, Jana, Jeetha, Kamiya, Khundit-Mundit, Kuthia, Lakhari, Munjhi, Mat, Munish system, Nit-Majoor, Paleru, Padiyal, Pannayilal, Sagri, Sanji, Sanjawat, Sewak, Sewakia, Seri, Vetti;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“ascendant” or “descendant”, in relation to a person belong­ing to a matriarchal society, means the person who corresponds to such expression in accordance with the law of succession in force in such society;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>“bonded debt” means an advance obtained, or presumed to have been obtained, by a bonded labourer under, or in pursuance of the bonded labour system;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>“bonded labour” means any labour or service rendered under</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>“bonded labour” means any labour or service rendered under the bonded labour system;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>“bonded labourer” means a labourer who incurs, or has, or is presumed to have, incurred, a bonded debt;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.g.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>“bonded labour system” means the system of forced, or partly forced, labour under which a debtor enters, or has, or is pre­sumed to have, entered, into an agreement with the creditor to the effect than,—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.g.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>in consideration of an advance obtained by him or by any of his lineal ascendants or descendants (whether or not such advance is evidenced by any document) and in consideration of the inter­est, if any, due on such advance, or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.g.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>in pursuance of any customary or social obligation, or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.g.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>in pursuance of an obligation devolving on him by succes­sion, or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.g.list0.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>for any economic consideration received by him or by any of his lineal ascendants or descendants, or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.g.list0.v">
                    <num>(v)</num>
                    <p>by reason of his birth in any particular caste or community,—</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>he would—</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>render, by himself or through any member of his family, or any person dependent on him, labour or service to the creditor, or for the benefit of the creditor, for a specified period or for an unspecified period, either without wages or for nominal wages, or</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>forfeit the freedom of employment or other means of livelihood for a specified period or for an unspecified period, or</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>forfeit the right to move freely throughout the territory of India, or</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>forfeit the right to appropriate or sell at market value any of his property or product of his labour or the labour of a member of his family or any person dependent on him,</p>
            <p>and includes the system of forced, or partly forced, labour under which a surety for a debtor enters, or has, or is presumed to have, entered, into an agreement with the creditor to the effect that in the event of the failure of the debtor to repay the debt, he would render the bonded labour on behalf of the debtor;</p>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.4.list4">
              <listIntroduction>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that any system of forced or partly forced labour under which any workman being contract labour as defined in clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Contract Labour (Regulation and Abolition) Act, 1970 (37 of 1970), or an Inter-State migrant workman as defined in clause (e) of sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Inter-State Migrant Workmen (Regulation of Employment and Conditions of Service) Act, 1979 (30 of 1979), is required to render labour or service in circumstances of the nature mentioned in sub-clause (1) of this clause or is subjected to all or any of the disabilities referred to in sub-clauses (2) to (4), is “bonded labour system” within the meaning of this clause.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.4.list4.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>“family” in relation to a person, includes the ascendant and descendant of such person;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.4.list4.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>“nominal wages”, in relation to any labour, means a wage which is less than,—</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.4.list4.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the minimum wages fixed by the Government, in relation to the same or similar labour, under any law for the time being in force, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.4.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>where no such minimum wage has been fixed in relation to any form of labour, the wages that are normally paid, for the same or similar labour, to the labourers working in the same locality.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.4.list4.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Act to have over-riding effect.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained in any enactment other than this Act, or in any instrument having effect by virtue of any enactment other than this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Abolition of bonded labour system.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On the commencement of this Act, the bonded labour system shall stand abolished and every bonded labourer shall, on such commencement, stand freed and discharged from any obligation to render any bonded labour.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>After the commencement of this Act, no person shall—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>make any advance under, or in pursuance of, the bonded labour system, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>compel any person to render any bonded labour or other form of forced labour.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Agreement, custom, etc., to be void.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>On the commencement of this Act, any custom or tradition or any contract, agreement or other instrument (whether entered into or executed before or after the commencement of this Act), by virtue of which any per­son, or any member of the family or dependent of such person, is required to do any work or render any service as a bonded labour­er, shall be void and inoperative.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Liability to repay bonded debt to stand extinguished.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On the commencement of this Act, every obligation of a bonded labour­er to repay any bonded debt, or such part of any bonded debt as remains unsatisfied immediately before such commencement, shall be deemed to have been extinguished.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>After the commencement of this Act, no suit or other proceed­ing shall lie in any civil court or before any other authority for the recovery of any bonded debt or any part thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every decree or order for the recovery of bonded debt, passed before the commencement of this Act and not fully satisfied before such commencement, shall be deemed, on such commencement, to have been fully satisfied.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every attachment made before the commencement of this Act, for the recovery of any bonded debt, shall, on such commencement, stand vacated; and, where, in pursuance of such attachment, any movable property of the bonded labourer was seized and removed from his custody and kept in the custody of any court or other authority pending sale thereof, such movable property shall be restored, as soon as may be practicable after such commencement, to the possession of the bonded labourer.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where, before the commencement of this Act, possession of any property belonging to a bonded labourer or a member of his family or other dependent was forcibly taken over by any creditor for the recovery of any bonded debt, such property shall be restored, as soon as may be practicable after such commencement, to the possession of the person from whom it was seized.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If restoration of the possession of any property referred to in sub-section (4) or sub-section (5) is not made within thirty days from the commencement of this Act, the aggrieved person may, within such time as may be prescribed, apply to the prescribed authority for the restoration of the possession of such property and the prescribed authority may, after giving the creditor a reasonable opportunity of being heard, direct the creditor to restore to the applicant the possession of the concerned property within such time as may be specified in the order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An order made by any prescribed authority, under sub-section (6), shall be deemed to be an order made by a civil court and may be executed by the court of the lowest pecuniary jurisdiction within the local limits of whose jurisdiction the creditor volun­tarily resides or carries on business or personally works for gain.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the avoidance of doubts, it is hereby declared that, where any attached property was sold before the commencement of this Act, in execution of a decree or order for the recovery of a bonded debt, such sale shall not be affected by any provision of this Act:</p>
            <p>Provided that the bonded labour, or an agent authorised by him in this behalf, may, at any time within five years from such com­mencement, apply to have the sale set aside on his depositing in court, for payment to the decree-holder, the amount specified in the proclamation of sale, for the recovery of which the sale was ordered, less any amount, as well as mesne profits, which may, since the date of such proclamation of sale, have been received by the decree-holder.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any suit or proceeding, for the enforcement of any obligation under the bonded labour system, including a suit or proceeding for the recovery of any advance made to a bonded labourer, is pending at the commencement of this Act, such suit or other proceeding shall, on such commencement, stand dismissed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.10">
          <num>(10)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On the commencement of this Act, every bonded labourer who has been detained in civil prison, whether before or after judg­ment, shall be released from detention forthwith.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Property of bonded labourer to be freed from mortgage, etc.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All property vested in a bonded labourer which was, immedi­ately before the commencement of this Act under any mortgage, charge , lien or other incumbrances in connection with any bonded debt shall, in so far as it is relatable to the bonded debt, stand freed and discharged from such mortgage, charge, lien or other incumbrances, and where any such property was, immediately before the commencement of this Act, in the possession of the mortgagee or the holder of the charge, lien or incumbrance, such property shall (except where it was subject to any other charge), on such commencement, be restored to the possession of the bonded labourer.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any delay is made in restoring any property referred to in sub-section (1) to the possession of the bonded labourer, such labourer shall be entitled, on and from the date of such com­mencement, to recover from the mortgagee or holder of the lien, charge or incumbrance, such mesne profits as may be determined by the civil court of the lowest pecuniary jurisdiction within the local limits of whose jurisdiction such property is situated.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Freed bonded labourer not to be evicted from homestead, etc.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No person who has been freed and discharged under this Act from any obligation to render any bonded labour, shall be evicted from any homestead or other residential premises which he was occupying immediately before the commencement of this Act as part of the consideration for the bonded labour.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If, after the commencement of this Act, any such person is evicted by the creditor from any homestead or other residential premises, referred to in sub-section (1), the Executive Magis­trate in charge of the Sub-Division within which such homestead or residential premises is situated shall, as early as practica­ble, restore the bonded labourer to the possession of such home­stead or other residential premises.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Creditor not to accept payment against extinguished debt.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No creditor shall accept any payment against any bonded debt which has been extinguished or deemed to have been extinguished or fully satisfied by virtue of the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever contravenes the provisions of sub-section (1), shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years and also with fine.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The court, convicting any person under sub-section (2) may, in addition to the penalties which may be imposed under that sub-section, direct the person to deposit, in court, the amount accepted in contravention of the provisions of sub-section (1), within such period as may be specified in the order for being refunded to the bonded labourer.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Authorities who may be specified for implementing the provi­sions of this Act.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may confer such powers and impose such duties on a District Magistrate as may be necessary to ensure that the provisions of this Act are properly carried out and the District Magistrate may specify the officer, subordinate to him, who shall exercise all or any of the powers, and perform all or any of the duties, so conferred or imposed and the local limits within which such powers or duties shall be carried out by the officer so specified.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Duty of District Magistrate and other officers to ensure credit.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The District Magistrate authrorised by the State Gov­ernment under section 10 and the officer specified by the Dis­trict Magistrate under that section shall, as far as practicable, try to promote the welfare of the freed bonded labourer by secur­ing and protecting the economic interests of such bonded labourer so that he may not have any occasion or reason to contract and further bonded debt.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Duty of District Magistrate and officers authorised by him.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>It shall be the duty of every District Magistrate and every officer specified by him under section 10 to inquire whether, after the commencement of this Act, any bonded labour system or any other form of forced labour is being enforced by, or on behalf of, any person resident within the local limits of his jurisdiction and if, as a result of such inquiry, any person is found to be enforcing the bonded labour system or any other system of forced labour, he shall forthwith take such action as may be necessary to eradicate the enforcement of such forced labour.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Vigilance Committees.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every State Government shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute such number of Vigilance Committees in each district and each Sub-Division as it may think fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Each Vigilance Committee, constituted for a district, shall consist of the following members namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the District Magistrate, or a person nominated by him, who shall be the Chairman;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>three persons belonging to the Scheduled Castes or Scheduled Tribes and residing in the district, to be nominated by the District Magistrate;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>two social workers, resident in the district, to be nominated by the District Magistrate;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>not more than three persons to represent the official or non-official agencies in the district connected with rural develop­ment, to be nominated by the State Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>one person to represent the financial and credit institutions in the district, to be nominated by the District Magistrate.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Each Vigilance Committee, constituted for a Sub-Division, shall consist of the following members, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the Sub-Divisional Magistrate, or person nominated by him, who shall be the Chairman;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>three persons belonging to the Scheduled Castes or Scheduled Tribes and residing in the Sub-Division, to be nominated by the Sub-Divisional Magistrate;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.3.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>two social workers, resident in the Sub-Division, to be nominated by the Sub-Divisional Magistrate;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.3.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>not more than three persons to represent the official or non-official agencies in the Sub-Division connected with rural devel­opment to be nominated by the District Magistrate;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.3.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>one person to represent the financial and credit institutions in the Sub-Division, to be nominated by the Sub-Divisional Magis­trate;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.3.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>one officer specified under section 10 functioning in the Sub-Division.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Each Vigilance Committee shall regulate its own procedure and secretarial-assistance, as may be necessary, shall be provided by—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the District Magistrate, in the case of a Vigilance Committee constituted for the district;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.4.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the Sub-Divisional Magistrate, in the case of a Vigilance Committee constituted for the Sub-Division.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No proceeding of a Vigilance Committee shall be invalid merely by reason of any defect in the constitution, or in the pro­ceedings, of the Vigilance Committee.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Fuctions of Vigilance Committees.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The functions of each Vigilance Committee shall be,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to advise the District Magistrate or any officer authorised by him as to the efforts made, and action taken, to ensure that the provisions of this Act or of any rule made thereunder are properly implemented;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to provide for the economic and social rehabilitation of the freed bonded labourers;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to co-ordinate the functions of rural banks and co-operative societies with a view to canalising adequate credit to the freed bonded labourer;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>to keep an eye on the number of offences of which cognizance has been taken under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>to make a survey as to whether there is any offence of which cognizance ought to be taken under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.1.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>to defend any suit instituted against a freed bonded labourer or a number of his family or any other person dependent on him for the recovery of the whole or part of any bonded debt or any other debt which is claimed by such person to be bonded debt.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A Vigilance Committee may authorise one of its members to defend a suit against a freed bonded labourer and the member so authorised shall be deemed, for the purpose of such suit, to be the authorised agent of the freed bonded labourer.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Burden of proof.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whenever any debt is claimed by a bonded labourer, or a Vigilance Committee, to be a bonded debt, the burden of proof that such debt is not a bonded debt shall lie on the creditor.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Punishment for enforcement of bonded labour.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever, after the commencement of this Act, compels any person to render any bonded labour shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years and also with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Punishment for advancement of bonded debt.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever ad­vances, after the commencement of this Act, any bonded debt shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years and also with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Punishment for extracting bonded labour under the bonded labour system.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever enforces, after the commencement of this Act, any custom, tradition, contract, agreement or other instrument, by virtue of which any person or any member of the family of such person or any dependent of such person is required to render any service under the bonded labour system, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years and also with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees; and, out of the fine, if recovered, payment shall be made to the bonded labourer at the rate of rupees five for each day for which the bonded labour was extracted from him.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Punishment for omission or failure to restore possession of property to bonded labourers.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever, being required by this Act to restore any property to the possession of any bonded labourer, omits or fails to do so, within a period of thirty days from the commencement of this Act, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both; and, out of the fine, if recovered, payment shall be made to the bonded labourer at the rate of rupees five for each day during which possession of the property was not restored to him.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Abetment to be an offence.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever abets any offence punish­able under this Act shall, whether or not the offence abetted is committed, be punishable with the same punishment as is provided for the offence which has been abetted.</p>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <p>For the purpose of this Act, “abetment” has the meaning assigned to it in the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Offences to be tried by Executive Magistrates.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-21.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may confer, on an Executive Magistrate, the powers of a Judicial Magistrate of the first class or of the second class for the trial of offences under this Act; and, on such conferment of powers, the Executive Magistrate on whom the powers are so conferred, shall be deemed, for the purposes of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), to be a Judicial Magistrate of the first class, or of the second class, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-21.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An offence under this Act may be tried summarily by a Magis­trate.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Cognizance of offences.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every offence under this Act shall be cognizable and bailable.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Offences by companies.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-23.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an offence under this Act has been committed by a company, every person who, at the time the offence was committed, was in charge of, and was responsible to, the company for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where any offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is attributable to, any neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary or other officer shall be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.</p>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <blockList id="section-23.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>For the purposes of this section,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-23.2.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“company” means any body corporate and includes a firm or other association of individuals; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-23.2.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“director”, in relation to a firm, means a partner in the firm.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any State Government or any officer of the State Government or any member of the Vigilance Committee for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Jurisdiction of civil courts barred.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No civil court shall have jurisdiction in respect of any matter to which any provi­sions of this Act applies and no injuction shall be granted by any civil court in respect of anything which is done or intended to be done by or under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-26.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-26.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-26.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the authority to which application for the restoration of possession of property referred to in sub-section (4), or sub-section (5), of section 6 is to be submitted in pursuance of sub-section (6) of that section;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-26.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the time within which application for restoration of posses­sion of property is to be made under sub-section (6) of section 6, to the prescribed authority;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-26.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>steps to be taken by Vigilance Committees under clause (a) of sub-section (1) of section 14, to ensure the implementation of the provisions of this Act or of any rule made thereunder;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-26.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>any other matter which is required to be, or may be, pre­scribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the ses­sion immediately following the session or successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Repeal and saving.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-27.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Bonded Labour System (Abolition) Ordinance, 1975 (17 of 1975) is hereby repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken under the Ordinance (including any notification published, direction or nomination made, power conferred, duty imposed or officer specified) shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
