<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-jnk/act/1978/06/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-jnk/act/1978/06"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Jammu And Kashmir Public Safety Act, 1978"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-jnk/act/1978/06/eng@2017-03-03/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-jnk/act/1978/06/eng@2017-03-03"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-03" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-jnk/act/1978/06/eng@2017-03-03/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-jnk/act/1978/06/eng@2017-03-03"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-03" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Jammu And Kashmir Public Safety Act, 1978</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[8th April, 1978]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No. VI of 1978</p>
        <p>Whereas it is necessary in the interest of the security of the State and public order to make law providing for the measures hereinafter appearing.</p>
        <p>Now, therefore, it is enacted by the Jammu and Kashmir State Legislature in the Twenty-ninth Year of the Republic of India as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <heading>Preliminary</heading>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title and extent.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the Jammu and Kashmir Public Safety Act, 1978.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It extends to the whole of Jammu and Kashmir State</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context, -</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-2.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>"the Code"' means the Code of Criminal Procedure, Samvat 1989;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>"notified" and "notification"' mean notified and notification respectively in the Government Gazette.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <heading>ACCESS TO CERTAIN PREMlSES AND AREAS</heading>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Prohibited places.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If as respects any place the Government considers it necessary or expedient that special precautions should be taken to prevent the entry of unauthorised persons, the Government may, by notified order, declare that place to be a prohibited place.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No person shall, without the permission of the Government or the authority specified by the Government, enter, or be on or in, or pass over, or loiter in the vicinity of, any prohibited place.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where in pursuance of sub-section (2) any person is granted permission to enter, or to be on or in, or to pass over, a prohibited place, that person shall, while acting under such permission comply with such orders for regulating his conduct.as may he given by the Government or the authority specified by the Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any Police Officer, or any other person authorised in this behalf by the Government, may search any person entering or seeking to enter or being on or in, or leaving a prohibited place, and any vehicle, aircraft or article brought in by such person, and may, for the purpose of the search, detain such person, vehicle, aircraft and article.</p>
              <p>Provided that no female shall be searched in pursuance of this sub-section except by a female.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any person is in a prohibited place in contravention of this section, then, without prejudice to any other proceedings which may be taken against him, he may be removed therefrom by any Police Officer not below the rank of a Sub Inspector or by any other person authorised in this behalf by the Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any person is in a prohibited place in contravention of any of the provisions of this section he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one month, or with fine, or with both.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Protected areas.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the Government considers it necessary or expedient in the interests of the defence or security of the State to regulate the entry of person into any area, it may, by a notified order declare the area to be a protected area, and thereupon, for so long as the order is in force, such area shall be protected area for the purpose of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Government or the authority specified by the Government may regulate the entry of any person into a protected area.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any person is in a protected area in contravention of the provisions of any order passed under thin section then, without prejudice to any other proceedings which may be taken against him, he may be removed therefrom by or under the direction of any police officer not below the rank of a sub-inspector.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any person is in a protected area in contravention of any of provisions of this section, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to two months, or with fine, or with both.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Forcing or evading a guard.- Any person who effects or attempts to effect entry into a prohibited place or a protected area after taking precautions to conceal his entry or attempted entry from any person posted for the purpose of protecting or of preventing or controlling access to such place or area shall be punishable with imprisonment for term which may extend to three months, or with fine, or with both.</heading>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <heading>Maintenance of communal and regional harmony</heading>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Power to prohibit circulation within the State or entry into the State of certain documents.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Government, or any authority authorized by it in this behalf, if satisfied that such action is necessary for the purposes of preventing or combating any activity prejudicial to the maintenance of communal or sectarian, or regional harmony effecting or likely to affect public order, may, by notified order, regulate or restrict the circulation within the State, or prohibit or restrict the importation into the State, of any document:</p>
              <p>Provided that no such order shall remain in force for more than three months from the making thereof unless before the expiry of such period, and in case the High Court does not otherwise direct, the Government, by an order made in the like manner, extend it by any period not exceeding three months at a time as it thinks fit, so however, that the total period of the original order does not exceed one year:</p>
              <p>Provided further that a person aggrieved by such order may, within ten days of the passing thereof, make a representation to the Government which may, on consideration, confirm, modify or rescind the order within 21 days of the making of the representations, after giving the aggrieved party an opportunity of being heard.</p>
              <p>Provided also that in case the representation is rejected by the Government, the aggrieved person may within a period of two months from the date of the order rejecting the representation, apply to the High Court to set aside the order. Every such application shall be heard and determined by a Special Bench of the High Court composed of three Judges.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person who contravenes an order made under this section shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three months or with fine or with both.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the event of disobedience of an order made under sub-section (1), the Government or the authority issuing the order, may without prejudice to the penalty to which the person guilty of the disobedience is liable under sub-section (2), order the seizure of all copies of, any such document.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Removal of doubts.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>For the removal of doubts it is hereby declared that the restrictions imposed by section 6 on the rights conferred by clause (1) of Article 19 of the Constitution of India shall he deemed to be reasonable restrictions.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <heading>Power to make orders detaining certain persons</heading>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Detention of certain persons.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-8.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Government may-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-8.1.list1.a.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>if satisfied with respect to any person that with a view to preventing him from acting in any manner prejudicial to</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-8.1.list1.a.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>the security of the State or the maintenance of the public order, or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-8.1.list1.a.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>***</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.1.list1.a1">
                  <num>(a1)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-8.1.list1.a1.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>if satisfied with respect to any person that with a view to preventing him from-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-8.1.list1.a1.list1.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>smuggling timber or liquor; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-8.1.list1.a1.list1.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>abetting the smuggling of timber or liquor; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-8.1.list1.a1.list1.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>engaging in transporting or concealing or keeping smuggled timber; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-8.1.list1.a1.list1.iv">
                      <num>(iv)</num>
                      <p>dealing the smuggled timber otherwise than by engaging in transporting or concealing or keeping in smuggled timber or liquor; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-8.1.list1.a1.list1.v">
                      <num>(v)</num>
                      <p>harbouring persons engaged in smuggling of timber or liquor, or abetting the smuggling of timber or liquor; or</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-8.1.list1.b.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>if satisfied with respect to any person who is -</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-8.1.list1.b.list2.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>a foreigner within the meaning of the Foreigners Act, or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-8.1.list1.b.list2.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>a person residing in the area of the State under the occupation of Pakistan,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>that with a view to regulating his continued presence in the state or with a view to making arrangements for his expulsion from the State,</p>
              <p>it is necessary so to do, make an order directing that such person be detained.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-8.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>any of the following officers, namely -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.2.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>Divisional Commissioners,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.2.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>District Magistrates,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>may, if satisfied as provided in sub-clauses (i) and (ii) of clause (a) of sub-section (1), exercise the powers conferred by the said sub-section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-8.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>For the purposes of sub-section (1), -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>***</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.3.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-8.3.list1.b.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>"acting in any manner prejudicial to the maintenance of public order" means -</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-8.3.list1.b.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>promoting, propagating, or attempting to create, feelings of enmity or hatred or disharmony on grounds of religion, race, caste, community, or region;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-8.3.list1.b.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>making preparations for using, or attempting its use, or using, or instigating, inciting, or otherwise abetting the use of force where such preparation, using, attempting, instigating, inciting. provoking or abetting, disturbs or is likely to disturb public order;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-8.3.list1.b.list0.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>attempting to commit, or committing, or instigating, inciting, provoking or otherwise abetting the commission of mischief within the meaning of section 425 of the Ranbir Penal Code where the commission of such mischief disturbs, or is likely to disturb public order;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-8.3.list1.b.list0.iv">
                      <num>(iv)</num>
                      <p>attempting to commit, or committing, or instigating, inciting, provoking or otherwise abetting the commission of an offence punishable with death or imprisonment for life or imprisonment for a term extending to seven years or more, where the commission of such offence disturbs, or is likely to disturb public order.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.3.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>"smuggling" in relation to timber or liquor means possessing or carrying of illicit timber or liquor and includes any act which will render the timber or liquor liable to confiscation under the Jammu and Kashmir Forest Act, Samvat 1987 or under the Jammu and Kashmir Excise Act, 1958, as the case may be;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.3.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>"timber" means timber of Fir, Kail, Chir or Deodar tree whether in logs or cut up in pieces but does not include firewood;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.3.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>"Liquor" includes all alcoholic beverages including beer;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.3.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>"person" shall not include a citizen of India who has not attained the age of eighteen years for being detained under clauses (a) and (a1) thereof.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When any order is made under this section by an officer mentioned in sub-section (2), he shall forthwith report the fact to the Government together with the grounds on which the order has been made and such other particulars as in his opinion have a bearing on the matter, and no such order shall remain in force for more than twelve days after the making thereof unless in the meantime it has been approved by the Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Execution of detention orders.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>A detention order may be executed at any place in the manner provided for the execution of warrants of arrest under the Code.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Power to regulate place and conditions of detention.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Any person in respect of whom a detention order has been made under section 8 shall be liable-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to be detained in such place and under such conditions including conditions as to the maintenance of discipline and punishment for breaches of discipline as the Government may, by general or, special order, specify and,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>to be removed from one place of detention to another place of detention by order of the Government.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that the detenues who are permanent residents of the State shall not be lodged in jails outside the State.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10A">
          <num>10A.</num>
          <heading>Grounds of detention severable.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10A.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-10A.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Where a person has been detained in pursuance of an order of detention under section 8 which has been made on two or more grounds, such order of detention shall be deemed to have been made separately on each of such grounds and accordingly-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10A.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-10A.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>such order shall not be deemed to be in valid or inoperative merely because one or some of the grounds is or are-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-10A.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>vague,</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-10A.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>non-existent,</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-10A.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>not relevant,</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-10A.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.iv">
                      <num>(iv)</num>
                      <p>not connected or not proximately connected with such person, or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-10A.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.v">
                      <num>(v)</num>
                      <p>invalid for any other reasons whatsoever, and it is not, therefore, possible to hold that the Government or officer making such order would have been satisfied as provided in section 8 with reference to the remaining ground or grounds and made the order of detention;</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10A.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the Government or officer making the order of detention shall be deemed to have made the order of detention under the said section after being satisfied as provided in that section with reference to the remaining ground or grounds.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Detention orders not to be invalid or inoperative, on certain grounds.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>No detention order shall be invalid or inoperative merely on the ground -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>that the person to be detained thereunder is outside the limits of the territorial jurisdiction of the officer making the order; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>that the place of detention of such person is outside the said limits.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Powers in relation to absconding persons.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>If the Government, or an officer specified in sub-section (2) of section 8, as the case may be, has reason to believe that a person in respect of whom a detention order has been made has absconded or is concealing himself so that order cannot be executed, the Government or the officer may -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>make a report in writing of the fact to a Magistrate of the first class having jurisdiction in the place where the said person ordinarily resides, and thereupon the provisions of sections 87, 88 and 89 of the Code shall apply in respect of the said person and his property as if the order directing that be be detained were a warrant issued by the Magistrate</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>by notified order direct the said person to appear before such officer, at such place and within such period as may be specified in the order, and if the person fails to comply with such direction, he shall, unless he proves that it was not possible for him to comply therewith and that he had within the period specified in the order, informed the officer mentioned in the order of the reason which rendered compliance therewith impossible and of his whereabouts, be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year or with fine or with both.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Grounds of order of detention to be disclosed to persons affected by the order.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-13.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When a person is detained in pursuance of a detention order, the authority making the order shall, as soon as may be, but ordinarily not later than five days and in exceptional circumstances and for reasons to be recorded in writing, not later than ten days from the date of detention communicate to him, in the language which is understandable to him the grounds on which the order has been made, and shall afford him the earliest opportunity of making a representation, against the order to the Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in sub-section (1) shall require the authority to disclose facts which it considers to be against the public interest to disclose.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Constitution of Advisory Board.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Government shall whenever necessary, constitute an Advisory Board for the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Such Board shall consist of a Chairman, who is or has been a Judge of the High Court, and two other members who are, or have been, or are qualified to be appointed as Judges of the High Court.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chairman and the other members of the Board shall be appointed by the Government in consultation with the Chief Justice of the High Court.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chairman and the other members of the Board shall hold the office for a period of three years which will be extendable for a further period of two years.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Reference to Advisory Board.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>In every case where a detention order has been made under this Act, the Government shall, within four weeks from the date of detention under the order, place before the Advisory Board constituted by it under section 14, the grounds on which the order has been made, the representation, if any, made by the person affected by the order and in case where the order as been made by an officer, also the report by such officer under sub-section (4) of section 8.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Procedure of Advisory Board.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-16.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Advisory Board shall, after considering the material placed before it and, after calling for such further information as it may deem necessary from the Government or from the person concerned and if in any particular case it considers it essential to do so or, if the person concerned desires to be heard, after hearing him in person, submit its report to the Government within eight weeks from the date of detention.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), the Board may, if the person detained so demands, at any time before submitting its report, after affording an opportunity to the person detained and the Government or the officer, as the case may be, of being heard, determine whether the disclosure of facts, not disclosed under sub-section (2) of section 13 to the person detained, is or is not against public interest. Such finding of the Board shall be binding on the Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The report of the Advisory Board shall specify in a separate part thereof the opinion of the Advisory Board as to whether or not there is sufficient cause for the detention of the person concerned.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When there is a difference of opinion among the members forming the Advisory Board, the opinion of the majority of such members shall be deemed to be the opinion of the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in this section shall entitle any person against whom a detention order has been made to appear by any legal practitioner in any matter connected with the reference to the Advisory Board and the proceedings of the Advisory Board and its report, excepting that part of the report in which the opinion of the Advisory Board is specified, shall be confidential.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Action upon the report of Advisory Board.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In any case where the Advisory Board has reported that there is in its opinion sufficient cause for the detention of a person, the Government may confirm the detention order and continue the detention of the person concerned for such period as it thinks fit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In any case where the Advisory Board has reported that there is, in its opinion, no sufficient cause for the detention of the person concerned, the Government shall revoke the detention order and cause the person to be released forthwith.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Maximum period of detention.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-18.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-18.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The maximum period for which any person may be detained in pursuance of any detention order which has been confirmed under section 17, shall be -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-18.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>three months in the first instance which may be extended up to twelve months from the date of detention in the case of persons acting in any manner prejudicial to the maintenance of public order;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.1.list1.a1">
                  <num>(a1)</num>
                  <p>twelve months from the date of detention in the case of the persons indulging in smuggling of timber; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>six months in the first instance which may be extneded up to two years from the date of detention in the case of persons acting in any manner prejudicial to the security of the State.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing contained in this section shall affect the powers of the Government to revoke or modify the detention order at any earlier time, or extend the period of detention of a foreigner in case his expulsion from the State has not been made possible.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Revocation of detention orders.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-19.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Without prejudice to the provisions of section 21 of the General Clauses Act, Smvat 1977, a detention order may, at any time, be revoked or modified by the Government, notwithstanding that the order has been made by any officer mentioned in sub- section (2) of section 8.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-19.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>There shall he no bar to making of a fresh order of detention against a person on the same facts as an earlier order of detention made against such person in any case where -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-19.2.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the earlier order of detention or its continuance is not legal on account of any technical defect or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.2.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>the earlier order of detention has been revoked by reason of any apprehension, or for avoiding any challenge that such order or its continuance is not legal on account of any technical defect:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that in computing the maximum period for which a person against whom such fresh order of detention has been issued may be detained, the period during which such person was under detention under the earlier order of detention shall be excluded.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Temporary release of persons detained.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-20.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Government may, at any time, order that a person detained in pursuance of detention order may be released for any specified period either without conditions or upon such conditions specified in the direction as that person accepts and may, at any time, cancel his release.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In directing the release of any person under sub-section (1), the Government may require him to enter into a bond with or without sureties for the due observance of the conditions specified in the direction.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person released under sub-section (1), shall surrender himself at the time and place and to the authority, specified in the order directing his release or cancelling his release as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any person fails without sufficient cause to surrender himself in the manner specified in sub-section (3) be shall be punishable with imprison- ment for a term which may extend to two years or with fine, or with both.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any person released under subsection (1) fails to fulfil any of the conditions imposed upon him under the said sub-section or in. the bond entered into by him, the bond shall be declared to be forfeited and any person bound thereby shall be liable to the penalty thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The period of release shall not count towards the total period of detention undergone by the person released under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <heading>Miscellaneous</heading>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Cognizance of offences under this Act.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-21.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No Court shall take cognizance of any offence under this Act except on a report in writing made by a public servant.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-21.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Second Schedule to the Code, offences under this Act shall be cognizable and non-bailable.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Protection of action taken under this Act.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No suit, prosecution or any other legal proceeding shall lie against any person for anything done or intended to be done in good faith in pursuance of the provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Government may, by notification, make such rules consistent with the provisions of this Act, as may be necessary for carrying out the objects of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Repeal and Saving.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-24.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Jammu and Kashmir Public Safety Ordinance, 1977 is hereby repealed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-24.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken (including any rule or order made) under the said Ordinance shall, so far as consistent with the provisions of this Act, be deemed to have been done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
