<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-raj/act/1960/1/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-raj/act/1960/1"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Rajasthan Prevention Of Mrityu Bhoj Act, 1960"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-raj/act/1960/1/eng@2017-01-20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-raj/act/1960/1/eng@2017-01-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-20" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-raj/act/1960/1/eng@2017-01-20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-raj/act/1960/1/eng@2017-01-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-12-06" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Rajasthan Prevention Of Mrityu Bhoj Act, 1960</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[03rd February, 1960]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[Act No. 01 of 1960]</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the prevention of Mrityu Bhoj.</p>
        <p>Whereas it is expedient in the interest of the general public to provide for the prevention of the holding of Mrityu Bhoj in the State of Rajasthan;</p>
        <p>Be it enacted by the Rajasthan State Legislature in the Tenth Year of the Republic of India as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Rajasthan Prevention of Mrityu Bhoj Act, 1960.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Rajasthan.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force at once.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the subject or context otherwise requires,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"Mrityu Bhoj" means a feast held or given on the occasion of, or in connection with, the demise of a person after any time or at any intervals, and includes a Nukta, a Mosar and a Chahallum, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"holding or giving Mrityu Bhoj" includes the distribution of articles of food, prepared or unprepared, but does not include the feeding of the family people or persons of the priestly order or faqirs in pursuance of the performance of religious or secular rites, not exceeding in the aggregate one hundred persons in number.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition of Mrityu Bhoj</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No person shall hold or give or join or take part in a Mrityu Bhoj in the State.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Punishment for contravention of section 3</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever commits a contravention of the provisions of section 3 or instigates, abets or assists the commission of any such contravention shall be punishable with imprisonment of either description for a term which may extend to one year, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Power to issue injunction</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If a court competent to take cognizance of an offence punishable under section 4 is satisfied that a Mrityu Bhoj in contravention of the provisions of this Act has been arranged or is about to be held or given such court may issue an injunction prohibiting the holding or giving of such Mrityu Bhoj.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Punishment for disobedience of injunction under section 5</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever, knowing that an injunction has been issued under section 5, disobeys such injunction shall be punishable with imprisonment of either description for a term which may extend to one year, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Sarpanchas etc. bound to give information</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Sarpanch and every Panch of a Gram Panchayat established under the Rajasthan Panchayat Act, 1953 (Rajasthan Act 21 of 1953) and every patwari and lambardar shall be bound to communicate forthwith to the nearest magistrate competent to take cognizance of an offence punishable under section 4 or section 6 any information which he may possess respecting the commission of, or intention to commit, such offence, within the local limits of his jurisdiction.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any such Sarpanch, Panch, patwari or lambardar failing to give the information required by sub-section (1) to communicate shall be punishable with imprisonment of either description for a term which may extend to three months, or with line, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition of borrowing or lending money</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No person shall borrow from, or lend to, any other person money or materials for the purpose of holding or giving a Mrityu Bhoj.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every agreement for the repayment of a loan advanced with the knowledge or having reason to believe that the loan so advanced will be utilised for the purpose of the holding or giving of a Mrityu Bhoj shall be void and not enforceable in a court of law.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Jurisdiction and cognizance of offence</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No court other than that of a magistrate of the first class shall take cognizance of, or try, any offence punishable under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Limitation for prosecution</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No court shall take cognizance of any offence under this Act after the expiry of one year from the date on which the offence is alleged to have been committed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may make rules for the purpose of carrying into effect the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All rules made under this section shall, as soon as may be after they are made, be laid for not less than fourteen days before the House of the State Legislature and shall be subject to such modifications, whether by way of repeal or amendment, as the House may make during the session in which they are so laid.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Repeal</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Jaipur Prevention of Funeral Feasts Act 1947 (Jaipur Act LI of 1947) and other corresponding laws in force in any part of the State are hereby repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of section 11, Rajasthan Act 21 of 1953</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>After clause (1) of section 11 of the Rajasthan Panchayat Act, 1953 (Rajasthan Act 21 of 1953), the following new clause shall be inserted, namely:-</p>
            <p>"(m) has been convicted of an offence punishable under the Rajasthan Prevention of Mrityu Bhoj Act, 1960".</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In clause (ii) of the proviso to the said section of the said Act,</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the word 'and' occurring between the brackets and letters '(g)' and '(i)' shall be deleted, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>after the brackets and letter '(i)', the word, brackets and letter "and (m)" shall be inserted.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
