<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/2013/2/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/2013/2"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Karnataka State Commission For Safai Karmacharis Act, 2012"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/2013/2/eng@2017-07-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/2013/2/eng@2017-07-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-07-24" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/2013/2/eng@2017-07-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/2013/2/eng@2017-07-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-07-24" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Karnataka State Commission For Safai Karmacharis Act, 2012</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[4th January 2013]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No. 2 of 2013</p>
        <p>Preamble—</p>
        <p>An Act to constitute the Karnataka State Commission for Safai Karmacharis.</p>
        <p>Whereas it is expedient to constitute a Commission for the Safai Karmacharis and for matters connected therewith or incidental thereto;</p>
        <p>Be it enacted by Karnataka State Legislature in the Sixty third year of the Republic of India as fol-lows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <heading>Preliminary</heading>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title and commencement.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the Karnataka State Commission for Safai Karmacharis Act, 2012.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on such date as the State Government may, by notification, appoint.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,.—</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-2.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>"Chairperson" means the Chairperson of the Karnataka State Commission for SafaiKarma-charis;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>"Commission" means the Karnataka State Commission for SafaiKarmacharis constituted under section 3;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>"Member" means a Member of the Commission;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>"prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>"Safai Karmachari" means a person engaged in, or employed for, manually carrying human excreta or any sanitation work.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <heading>State Commission for Safai Karmacharis</heading>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Constitution of Commission:-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The State Government shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute a Commission to be known as the Karnataka State Commission for SafaiKarmacharis to exercise the powers conferred on, and to perform the functions assigned to it under this Act consisting of the following, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.1.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>A Chairperson to be nominated by State Government who in its opinion is a person having knowledge and associated with the socio-economic development and welfare of SafaiKarmacharis;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.1.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>Two members out of whom one shall be a women to be nominated by the State Gov-ernment who in its opinion is a person having knowledge and associated with the so-cio-economic development and welfare of SafaiKarmacharis.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Head quarters of the Commission shall be at Bangalore.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Term of office and conditions of service of the Chairperson and Member.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the pleasure of the State Government, the Chairperson and every Member shall hold office for such period not exceeding three years as may be specified by the State Govern-ment in this behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chairperson or a Member may, at any time by giving notice in writing under his signa-ture, addressed to the State Government, resign from the office of the Chairperson or the Mem-ber, as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-4.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The State Government may by order, remove from office, the Chairperson or any Member if the chairperson or such member, as the case may be,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>becomes an un discharged insolvent; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.3.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>is convicted and sentenced to imprisonment for an offence which, in the opinion of the State Government, involves moral turpitude; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.3.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>is of unsound mind and stands so declared by a competent court of law; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.3.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>refuses to act or becomes incapable of so acting; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.3.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>without obtaining leave, absents himself from the commission or absents from three consecutive meetings of the commission; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.3.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>in the opinion of the State Government has so abused the position of Chairperson or Member so as to render that person's continuance in office detrimental to the interest of SafaiKarmacharis in the public interest:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that no person shall be so removed under this clause unless that person has been given a reasonable opportunity of being heard in the matter.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A vacancy caused under sub-section (2) or otherwise, shall be filled by fresh nomination, by the State Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The salaries and allowances payable to and other terms and conditions of service of the Chairperson, and Members shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Staff of the Commission.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Government shall provide the Commission with such officers and employees who are Government Servants as may be required for the proper functioning of the Commission under this Act. The strength and terms and conditions of the Officers and the employees of the Com-mission shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Vacancy, etc., not to invalidate the proceedings of the Commission.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No act or proceeding of the Commission shall be questioned or shall be invalid merely on the ground of the existence of any vacancy or defect in the constitution of the commission.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Procedure to be regulated by the Commission.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Commission shall meet at such time and place as the Chairperson may think fit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder, the commission shall have the power to regulate its own procedure.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All orders and decisions of the Commission shall be authenticated by the Chairperson or any other officer of the Commission duly authorised by the Chairperson in this behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <heading>Functions and Powers of the Commissioner</heading>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Functions of the Commission.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-8.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Commission shall perform all or any of the following functions, namely: -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>recommend to the State Government specific programs of action towards elimination of inequalities in status, facilities and opportunities for Safai Karmacharis under a time-bound action plan;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>to study and evaluate the implementation of the programs and schemes relating to the social and economic rehabilitation of SafaiKarmacharis and make recommendations to the State Government for Co-ordination and implementation of such programs and schemes;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-8.1.list1.c.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>to enquire in to specific grievances and take notice of matters relating to nonimplemen-tation of,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-8.1.list1.c.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>programs or schemes in respect of any group of Safai Karmacharis;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-8.1.list1.c.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>decisions, guidelines or instructions, aimed at mitigating the hardship of Safai-Karmacharis;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-8.1.list1.c.list0.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>measures for the social and economic upliftment of Safai Karmacharis;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-8.1.list1.c.list0.iv">
                      <num>(iv)</num>
                      <p>the provisions of any law in its application to Safai Karmacharis and take up such matters with the concerned authorities. (d)</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>to make periodical reports to the State Government on any matter relating to Safai-Karmacharis, taking into account any difficulties or disabilities being encountered by Safai Karamcharis;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.1.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>any other matter which may be referred to it by the State Government. (2) In the dis-charge of its functions under sub-section (1), the Commission shall have power to call for information with respect to any matter specified in that sub-section from State Gov-ernment departments and its agencies/Corporations and local bodies.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the discharge of its functions under sub-section (1), the Commission shall have power to call for information with respect to any matter specified in that sub-section from State Gov-ernment departments and its agencies/Corporations and local bodies</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Powers of Commission:-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Commission shall while investigating /enquiring any matter under section 8, have all the powers of civil court trying a suit under the code of civil procedure 1908, and in particular in respect of the following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person from any part of the state and ex-amining him on oath.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>discovery and production of any documents and witness.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>receiving any evidence on affidavits.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>requisitioning for any public record or copy there of from any court or office,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>any other matter which may be prescribed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <heading>Finance, Accounts and Audit</heading>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Grants by the State Government.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government shall after due appropriation made by the State Legislature by law in this behalf, pay to the Commission by way of grants such sums of money as the State Govern-ment may think fit, for being utilized for the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Commission may spend such sums out of the grants as it thinks fit for performing the functions under this Act, and such sums shall be treated as expenditure payable out of the grants referred to in sub-section (1).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Accounts and audit.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Accounts of income and expenditure of the Commission shall be kept in accordance with such rules, as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Commission shall prepare an annual statement of accounts in such form as may be pre-scribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The accounts of the Commission shall be audited annually by such auditor as the State Gov-ernment may appoint.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The auditor shall, for the purposes of audit have access to all the accounts and other records of the Commission.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Commission shall pay out of the grant such charges for the audit, as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As soon as after the receipt of the report from the auditor, the Commission shall send a copy of the annual statement of accounts, together with a copy of the report of the auditor to the State Government and shall cause to be published the annual statement of accounts in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>After receipt of the audit report the State Government shall take necessary steps to lay the report before both houses of state Legislature.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, after perusal of the auditor report give such directions as it thinks fit to the Commission and the Commission shall comply with such directions.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <heading>Miscellaneous</heading>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Chairperson and Members and staff of the Commission to be the public servants.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Chairperson, every Members, of the Commission and every officers appointed or autho-rized by the commission to exercise functions under this Act, shall be deemed to be public ser-vants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (Central Act 45 of 1860).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Annual Report.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Commission shall prepare in such form and at such time for each financial year as may be prescribed its annual report giving a full account of its activities during the previous financial year and forward a copy thereof to the State Government.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Annual report to be laid before State Legislature.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Government shall cause the annual report to be laid before each House of State Legis-lature along with the memorandum explaining the action taken or proposed to be taken on the recommendations of the Commission and the reasons for non-acceptance of the recommenda-tions, if any.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Delegation of powers. -</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Commission may, by general or special order, delegate to the Chairperson or any Member or to any officer of the Commission subject to such conditions and limitations, if any as may be specified therein, such of its powers and duties under this Act as it may deem fit.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the State Government, Commis-sion, Chairperson, Members or any officer or other employee of the Commission for anything which is done in good faith or intended to be done under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-17.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing powers, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.2.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>salaries and allowances payable to, and the other terms and conditions of service of, the Chairperson, and Members under sub-section (5) of section 4 and the officers and other employees of the Commission under section 5;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.2.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>the form in and the time at which the annual report shall be prepared under section 13.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.2.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>any other matter which is required to be, or as the case may be, to be made or pre-scribed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before both the House of State Legislature while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Power to remove difficulties.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-18.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the State Government, may by order published in the official gazette make such provisions not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act as appear to it to be necessary or expedient for removing difficulty: Pro-vided that no such order shall be made after expiry of the period of two years from the date of commencement of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every order made under this section shall as soon as may be after it is made, be laid before both the houses of State Legislature.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
