<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1959/61/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1959/61"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Married Women's Property (Extension) Act, 1959"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1959/61/eng@1959-12-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1959/61/eng@1959-12-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1959-12-24" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1959/61/eng@1959-12-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1959/61/eng@1959-12-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-11-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Married Women's Property (Extension) Act, 1959</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>NO. 61 OF 1959</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 24th December, 1959.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the extension of the Married Women' s Property Act, 1874, to parts of India in which it is not now in force.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the TenthYear of the Republic of India as follows:-</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Married Women' s Property (Extension) Act, 1959.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date, as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of section 2.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In section 2 of the Married Women's Property Act, 1874 (3 of 1874) (hereinafter referred to as the principal Act), for the sentence "It extends to the whole of India except the territories which, immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised in Part B States", the sentence "It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir" shall be substituted.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of section 6.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>For sub-section (2) of section 6 of the principal Act, the following sub- section shall be substituted, namely:-</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>"(2) Notwithstanding anything contained in section 2, the provisions of sub-section (1) shall apply in the case of any policy of insurance such as is referred to therein which is effected-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>by any Hindu, Muhammadan, Sikh or Jain-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2.a.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>in Madras, after the thirty- first day of December, 1913, or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2.a.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>in any other territory to which this Act extended immediately before the commencement of the Married Women' s Property (Extension) Act, 1959, after the first day of April, 1923, or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2.a.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>in any territory to which this Act extends on and from the commencement of the Married Women's Property (Extension) Act, 1959, on or after such commencement;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>by a Buddhist in any territory to which this Act extends, on or after the commencement of the Married Women's Property (Extension) Act, 1959:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that nothing herein contained shall affect any right or liability which has accrued or been incurred under any decree of a competent court passed-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list4.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>before the first day of April, 1923, in any case to which sub- clause (i) or sub- clause (ii) of clause (a) applies; or 1. Ist March, 1960, vide Notification No. S. O. 528, dated 29- 2- 1960, see Gazette of India, Extraordinary, Part II, Section 3 (ii), page 77.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list4.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>before the commencement of the Married Women's Property (Extension) Act, 1959, in any case to which sub- clause (iii) of clause (a) or clause (b) applies."</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of Act 30 of 1950.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In Part A of the Schedule to the Union Territories (Laws) Act, 1950, the entry relating to the Married Women's Property Act, 1874, shall be omitted.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Repeal and savings.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If immediately before the commencement of this Act, there is in force in any territory to which the principal Act is now extended any law corresponding to the principal Act, that law shall, save as otherwise expressly provided in his Act, stand repealed on such commencement:</p>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that the repeal shall not affect-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the previous operation of any law so repealed or anything duly done or suffered thereunder,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any right, privilege, obligation or liability acquired, accrued or incurred under any law so repealed,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any penalty, forfeiture or punishment incurred in respect of any offence committed against any law so repealed, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>any investigation, legal proceeding or remedy in respect of any such right, privilege, obligation, liability, penalty, forfeiture or punishment as aforesaid, and any such investigation, legal proceeding or remedy may be instituted, continued or enforced, and any such penalty, forfeiture or punishment may be imposed as if this Act had not been passed:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided further that, subject to the preceding proviso, anything done or any action taken under any such law shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the corresponding provision of the principal Act, and shall continue to be in force accordingly unless and until superseded by anything done or any action taken under the principal Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
