<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-hmp/act/1974/5/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-hmp/act/1974/5"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Himachal Pradesh Suppression of Indecent Advertisements Act, 1973"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1974-02-02" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-hmp/act/1974/5/eng@1974-02-02/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-hmp/act/1974/5/eng@1974-02-02"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1974-02-02" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-hmp/act/1974/5/eng@1974-02-02/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-hmp/act/1974/5/eng@1974-02-02"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="1974-02-02" name="R.H.P. Extra" showAs="R.H.P. Extra" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preamble>
      <p>The Himachal Pradesh Suppression of Indecent Advertisements Act, 1973</p>
      <p>Act No. 05 of 1974</p>
      <p>An Act to suppress indecent advertisements.</p>
      <p>BE it enacted by the Legislative Assembly of Himachal Pradesh in the Twenty-fourth Year of the Republic of India as follows,-</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Himachal Pradesh Suppression of Indecent Advertisements Act, 1973.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Himachal Pradesh.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force at once.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Interpretation.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>For the purposes of this Act any advertisement relating syphilis, gonorrhoea, nervous, debility or other complaint or infirmity arising from or relating to sexual intercourse shall be deemed to be printed or written matter of an indecent nature.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Proceedings against persons affixing etc. indecent pictures, or printed or written matter.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whosoever affixes to, inscribes or stencils on any house, building, wall, boarding, gate, fence, pillar, post, board, tree, or any other thing whatsoever so as to be visible to a person being or in passing along any street, public highway or foot-path, and whoever affixes to, inscribes or stencils on any public latrine or urinal, or exhibits to public view on the cinema screen or in the window of any house or shop, any picture or printed or written matter which is: of indecent nature, shall, on conviction, be punished with imporisonment of either description for a term which may extend to 6 months or with fine which may extend to 500 rupees, or with both such imprisonment and fine.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whenever any printed or written matter of an indecent nature has been displayed in the manner prohibited by subsection (1), any person being in possesion or control of the land, building, structure or premises tc which such printed or written matter has been affixed who knowingly allows the same to be continued to be displayed, shall, on conviction, be punished with imprisonment which may extend to six months or with fine which may extend to 500 rupees, or with both such imprisonment and fine.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Proceedings against persons sending other to do the acts punishable under section 3.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever gives or delivers to any other person any such pictures, or printed or written matter mentioned in section 3 with the intent that the same, some one or more thereof, should be affixed, inscribed, stencilled, or exhibited as therein mentioned, shall, on conviction, be punished with imprisonment of either description which may extend to one year or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both such imprisonment and fine.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Power to seize, remove, deface or destroy pictures or printed or written matter of an indecent nature.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If a District Magistrate, Sub-Divisional Magistrate or Magistrate of the First Class has reason to believe that any picture or printed or written matter of an indecent nature which has been affixed, inscribed or stencilled as mentioned in section 3, continues to be exhibited to public view after the commencement of this Act, he may by order in writing authorise any police officer to enter, with such assistance as may be required, any place and seize, remove, deface or destroy any such picture or printed or written matter.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Police officer may arrest on view of offence.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any police officer may arrest without warrant any persons whom he shall find committing any offence against this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Exemption.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in this Act shall apply to any advertisement published by any municipal corporation or by any municipal, small town or notified area committee or published with the sanction of the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Repeal and savings.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Punjab Suppression of Indecent Advertisements Act, 1941 (7 of 1941) as in force in the areas added to Himachal Pradesh under section 5 of the Punjab Reorganisation Act, 1966, (31 of 1966) is hereby repealed.</p>
            <p>Provided that anything done or any action taken (including any notification issued, permission granted or proceedings commenced or continued) under the provisions of the said Act, shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
