<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2004/26/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2004/26"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Prevention of Terrorism (Repeal) Act, 2004"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2004/26/eng@2004-12-21/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2004/26/eng@2004-12-21"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2004-12-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2004/26/eng@2004-12-21/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2004/26/eng@2004-12-21"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-23" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Prevention Of Terrorism (Repeal) Act, 2004</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 26 OF 2004</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[21st December, 2004.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to repeal the Prevention of Terrorism Act, 2002.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty-fifth Year of the Republic of India as follows:—</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Prevention of Terrorism (Repeal) Act, 2004.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 21st day of September, 2004.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Repeal of Act 15 of 2002 and saving.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Prevention of Terrorism Act, 2002 (hereinafter referred to as the principal Act) is hereby repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The repeal of the principal Act shall not affect—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the previous operation of, or anything duly done or suffered under the principal Act, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any right, privilege or obligation or liability acquired, accrued or incurred under the principal Act, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any penalty, forfeiture or punishment incurred in respect of any offence under the principal Act, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>any investigation, legal proceeding or remedy in respect of any such right, privilege, obligation, liability, penalty, forfeiture or punishment as aforesaid,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>and, any such investigation, legal proceeding or remedy may be instituted, continued or enforced and any such penalty, forfeiture or punishment may be imposed as if the principal Act had not been repealed:</p>
            <p>Provided that notwithstanding anything contained in this sub-section or in any other law for the time being in force, no court shall take cognizance of an offence under the principal Act after the expiry of the period of one year from the commencement of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding the repeal of section 60 of the principal Act, the Review Committee constituted by the Central Government under sub-section (1) of that section, whether or not an application under sub-section (4) of that section has been made, shall review all cases registered under the principal Act as to whether there is a prima facie case for proceeding against the accused thereunder and such review shall be completed within a period of one year from the commencement of this Act and where the Review Committee is of the opinion that there is no prima facie case for proceeding against the accused, then,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in cases in which cognizance has been taken by the Court, the cases shall be deemed to have been withdrawn; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in cases in which investigations are pending, the investigations shall be closed forthwith,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>with effect from the date of issuance of the direction by such Review Committee in this regard.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Review Committee constituted by the Central Government under sub-section (1) of section 60 of the principal Act shall, while reviewing cases, have powers of a civil court under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) in respect of the following matters, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>discovery and production of any document;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.4.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>requisitioning any public record or copy thereof from any court or office.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may constitute more Review Committees, as it may consider necessary, for completing the review within the period specified in sub-section (3).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Repeal and saving.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Prevention of Terrorism (Repeal) Ordinance, 2004 (Ord. 1 of 2004) is hereby repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
