<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1957/46/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1957/46"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Cantonments (Extension Of Rent Control Laws) Act, 1957"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1957/46/eng@1957-12-18/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1957/46/eng@1957-12-18"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1957-12-18" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1957/46/eng@1957-12-18/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1957/46/eng@1957-12-18"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-02-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Cantonments (Extension Of Rent Control Laws) Act, 1957</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 46 OF 1957</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[18th December, 1957]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the extension to cantonments of laws relating to the control of rent and regulation of house accommodation.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Cantonments (Extension of Rent Control Laws) Act, 1957.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 26th day of January, 1950.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definition.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In this Act," cantonment" means any place declared to be cantonment under section 3 of the Cantonments Act, 1924 (2 of 1924).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Power to extend to cantonments laws relating to control of rents and regulation of house accommodation.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, extend to any cantonment with such restrictions and modifications as it thinks fit, any enactment relating to the control of rent and regulation of house accommodation which is in force in the State in which the cantonment is situated:</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that nothing contained in any enactment so extended shall apply to--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any premises within the cantonment belonging to the Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any tenancy or other line relationship created by a group the Government in respect of premises within the cantonment taken on lease or requisitioned by the Government; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any house within the cantonment which is, or may be, appropriated by the Central Government on lease under the Cantonment (House Accommodation) Act, 1923 (6 of 1923)</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The extension of any enactment under sub- section (1) may be made from such earlier or future date as the Central Government may think fit:</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that no such extension shall be made from a date earlier than--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the commencement of such enactment, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the establishment of the cantonment, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the commencement of this Act, whichever is later.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any enactment in force in any State relating to the control of rent and regulation of house accommodation is extended to a cantonment from a date earlier than the date on which such extension is made (hereafter referred to as the" earlier date"), such enactment, as in force on such earlier date, shall apply to such cantonment, and, where any such enactment has been amended at any time after the earlier date but before the commencement of the Cantonments (Extension of Rent Control Laws) Amendment Act, 1972 (22 of 1972), such enactment, as amended, shall apply to the cantonment on and from the date on which the enactment by which such amendment was made came into force.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where, before the extension to a cantonment of any enactment relating to the control of rent and regulation of house accommodation therein (hereafter referred to as the "Rent Control Act")--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.4.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>any decree or order for the regulation of, or for eviction from, any house accommodation in that cantonment, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.4.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>any order in the proceedings for the execution of such decree or order, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.4.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>any order relating to the control of rent or other incident of such house accommodation,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>was made by any court, tribunal or other authority in accordance with any law for the control of rent and regulation of house accommodation for the time being in force in the State in which such cantonment is situated, such decree or order shall, on and from the date on which the Rent Control Act is extended to that cantonment, be deemed to have been made under the corresponding provisions of the Rent Control Act, as extended to that cantonment, as if the said Rent Control Act, as so extended were in force in that cantonment, on the date on which such decree or order was made.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Extension of the Madhya Bharat Accomodation Control Act, 1955 to the cantonment of Mhow.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Madhya Bharat Accommodation Control Act, 1955 (M. B. Act 23 of 1955), as in force in that part of the State of Madhya Pradesh which immediately before the 1st day of November, 1956, formed the State of Madhya Bharat is hereby extended to, and brought into force in the Cantonment of Mhow with the following modifications, namely:--</p>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>In the said Act,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for the words "commencement of this Act" wherever they occur, the words "extension of this Act to the cantonment" shall be substituted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in section 1, for sub- sections (2), (3) and (4), the following sub-sections shall be substituted, namely:--</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>"(2) It extends to the Cantonment of Mhow.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>It shall remain in force up to the 31st day of December, 1957; but the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct from time to time that it shall remain in force for such further period as may be specified in the notification so, however, that the total period for which it may remain in force shall not exceed two years from the 31st day of December, 1957";</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>in section 2, in clause (b) of sub- section (1), for the words "a Municipality", the words "the Cantonment Board" shall be substituted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>in section 3, in clause (e), for the word "Municipal", the words" Cantonment Board" shall be substituted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <blockList id="section-4.3.list1.e.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>in section 4,--</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-4.3.list1.e.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>in clause (g), for the words "city or town concerned", the word "cantonment" shall be substituted;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-4.3.list1.e.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>in clause (h), for the words "city or town for that purpose and if he was in occupation, has for sufficient reasons vacated it after the Act has been extended to that city or town", the words" cantonment for that purpose or if he was in occupation, has for sufficient reasons vacated it after the extension of this Act thereto" shall be substituted;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <blockList id="section-4.3.list1.f.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>in section 6,--</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-4.3.list1.f.list1.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>in sub- section (1), the words and brackets "situated in the city of Lashkar (including Gwalior and Morar), Indore, Ujjain or Ratlam" shall be omitted;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-4.3.list1.f.list1.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>sub-section (2) shall be omitted;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>in section 14, the words "the provisions of this Act cease to be applicable to any town, or" shall be omitted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>in section 15, after the word "instituted", the words "or if instituted, continued," shall be inserted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>in section 18, sub-section (4) shall be omitted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>in section 21, the words "or deemed to have been passed" shall be omitted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>in section 22, the words "or deemed to have been made" shall be omitted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>section 23, section 27 and the Schedule shall be omitted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>in sections 24 and 25, the words "or deemed to have been made" shall be omitted.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any law relating to the control of rent and regulation of house accommodation in force in the cantonment of Mhow immediately before the commencement therein of the Madhya Bharat Accommodation Control Act, 1955 (Madhya Bharat Act 23 of 1955), shall be, and shall be deemed always to have been, extended to that cantonment under section 3 of this Act with effect from the commencement of such law in that cantonment or from the commencement of this Act, whichever is later:</p>
            <p>Provided that no such law shall continue, and shall be deemed to have continued, in force in the cantonment of Mhow on and from the commencement therein of the Madhya Bharat Accommodation Control Act, 1955. (Madhya Bharat Act 23 of 1955).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where, before the extension under sub-section (2) of any law to the cantonment of Mhow,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>any decree or order for the regulation of, or for eviction from, any house accommodation in that cantonment, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>any order in the proceedings for the execution of such decree or order, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>any order relating to the control of rent or other incident of such house accommodation,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>was made by any court, tribunal or other authority in accordance with any law for the control of rent and regulation of house accommodation for the time being in force in that cantonment, such decree or order shall, on and from the commencement of such law in that cantonment, be deemed to have been made under the corresponding provisions of the first- mentioned Act as if the said Act were in force in that cantonment on the date on which such decree or order was made.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
