<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1967/15/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1967/15"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Karnataka (Abolition Of Cash Grants) Act, 1967"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1967/15/eng@2017-07-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1967/15/eng@2017-07-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-07-24" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1967/15/eng@2017-07-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1967/15/eng@2017-07-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-07-24" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Karnataka (Abolition Of Cash Grants) Act, 1967</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[21st December, 1967]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No. 15 of 1967</p>
        <p>An act to discontinue certain classes of cash grants in the Gulburga Area of the State of Karnataka.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to discontinue certain classes of cash grants in the Gulburga Area of the State of Karnataka;</p>
      </longTitle>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by the Karnataka State Legislature in the Eighteenth Year of the Republicof India as follows :-</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement .-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Karnataka (Abolition of Cash Grants) Act, 1967.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the Gulburga Area of the State of Karnataka.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force at once.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"Government" means the State Government ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"charitable institution" means any charitable establishment, with a specific locationand known address which is dedicated to, or for the benefit of, or used as of right by, the public generally or any community or section thereof, for any pious, charitable orphilanthropic purpose ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>"prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>"religious institution" means any religious establishment (such as temple, shrine,mosque or the like) with a specific location and known address which is dedicated to, orused as of right by, the public generally or any community or section thereof, as a place ofpublic religious worship.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Application of Act .-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act shall apply to any cash grant specified in theSchedule other than those mentioned in sub-section (2).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing contained in this Act shall apply to any such cash grant given in the name, orfor the support, of any religious or charitable institution or given to any person for theperformance of any service or charity, such service or charity being of a public natureconnected with any religious or charitable institution:</p>
            <p>Provided that the payment of cash grant mentioned in this sub-section shall be made tothe institution or to the person concerned only so long as the institution exists.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that the provisions of section 5 of theHyderabad Atiyat Enquiries Act, 1952 (Hyderabad Act X of 1952), as in force in theHyderabad Area, shall apply to the cash grants continued by this Act as they apply to Atiyatgrants under that Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification in the official Gazette, alter, add to or omit anyof the entries in the Schedule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Abolition of certain grants and payment of compensation therefor.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in any law, custom, usage, sanad or decree or order ofa court or other authority and subject to the provisions of sub-section (2) all cash grantsspecified in Part A of the Schedule which were payable or enforceable during the yearcommencing on the 1st April, 1952 or any subsequent financial year, and all cash grantsspecified in part B and Part C of the Schedule which were payable or enforceable during theyear commencing on the 1st day of April, 1954 or any subsequent financial year, shall bediscontinued and cease to have effect,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in the case of cash grants specified in Part A of the Schedule - with effect fromthe 30th day of July, 1952 ; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in the case of cash grants specified in Part B and Part C of the Schedule-with effect from the 1st day of July, 1954.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The grantee whose cash grant is abolished under sub-section (1) shall be paidcompensation as follows :-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>in the case of a cash grant specified in Part A of the Schedule, a sum equivalentto four times the annual amount payable to the grantee;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>in the case of a cash grant specified in Part B of the Schedule, a sum equivalentto six times the annual amount payable to the grantee; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>in the case of a cash grant specified in Part C of the Schedule, a sum equivalentto four times the annual amount payable to the grantee:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that in respect of each of the cases specified in column (1) of the Table below,the cash grant specified in Part C shall be continued subject to the conditions specified ineach case during the period mentioned in column (2), namely:-</p>
            <table id="section-4.2.table3">
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p>1</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>2</p>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p>(1) Where the age of the grantee, whether male or female, was not less than 60 years on the 1st day of April, 1964</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>Till the date of the death of the grantee</p>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p>(2) Where the age of the grantee was less than 60 years on the 1st day of April, 1954,-</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p>(i) in the case of a male or an unmarried woman, if the grantee is incapable of earning a livelihood on account of being blind, deaf, dumb and mute, mentally deranged, crippled or paralytic;</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>From the date of abolition till the date of the death of the grantee.</p>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p>(ii) in the case of a widow.</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>So long as she remains a widow.</p>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p>(3) Where the grantee is a minor,-</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p>(i) in the case of a male if such cash grant is his only source date of income</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>From the date of abolition till the attainment of 18 years.</p>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p>(ii) in the case of a female.</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>From the date of abolition till the date of marriage or the date of attainment of 18 years whichever is earlier.</p>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </table>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the amount of cash grant received by a male minor before attainment of 18 years of age, or by a female minor before such attainment or marriage, falls short of fourtimes the annual amount of cash grant, the deficiency shall be made good to the male minoron his attaining 18 years of age, and to the female minor on her attaining 18 years of age orher marriage, whichever is earlier.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a cash grant to which this Act applies is subject to the rendering of anyservice, the grantee shall, with effect from the date of discontinuation of the grant, standrelieved of the liability to render that service.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The compensation payable under sub-section (2) for the cash grants specified in Part A and Part C of the Schedule shall be paid to the grantee in such manner and in suchinstallments as may be prescribed ; and the compensation payable for the cash grantspecified in Part B of the Schedule shall be paid to him either in full or in annual instalments not exceeding twelve.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules .-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification in the official Gazette, make rules to carry out all or any of the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of the State Legislature while it is in session for a total period of thirtydays which may be comprised in one session or in two successive sessions and if before theexpiry of the session in which it is so laid or the session immediately following, both Housesagree in making any modification in the rule or both houses agree that the rule should not bemade, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, asthe case may be ; so however that any such modification or annulment shall be withoutprejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Disposal of pending matters .-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>All claims and all proceedings relating to cash grantspending on the date of commencement of this Act, before any authority shall,notwithstanding anything in any law, contract, decision or order of a court, be dealt with anddisposed of in accordance with the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Repeal .-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Hyderabad (Abolition of Cash Grants) Act, 1952 (Hyderabad Act XXXIII of 1952), is hereby repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-schedule">
      <doc name="schedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1967/15/schedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1967/15"/>
              <FRBRalias value="Schedule"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1967/15/eng@2017-07-24/schedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1967/15/eng@2017-07-24"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1967/15/eng@2017-07-24/schedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1967/15/eng@2017-07-24"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-07-24" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="schedule">
            <heading>(Part A)</heading>
            <paragraph id="schedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>Rusums payable to,-</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <subsection id="schedule.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Sardesmukhs,</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedule.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Sardeshpandyas,</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedule.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Deshmuks,</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedule.4">
              <num>(4)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Deshapandyas,</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedule.5">
              <num>(5)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Dastbandars (including mirasi-dastbandars),</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedule.6">
              <num>(6)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Choudhari,</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedule.7">
              <num>(7)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Shettigiri</p>
                <p>(Part B)</p>
                <p>Mansab Maviza Jagir including Jagir Pension,</p>
                <p>Mansab Maviza (Qarza),</p>
                <p>Mansab Maviza Arasi,</p>
                <p>Mansab Maviza Abkari,</p>
                <p>Mansab Maviza Sair,</p>
                <p>Mansab Maviza Aslaha, Kutub, Dookan, Safai,</p>
                <p>Mansab Imtiassi,</p>
                <p>Mansab Nazam Mahwars,</p>
                <p>Mahwarat Walajahi issued in lieu of Jagirs.</p>
                <p>(Part C)</p>
                <p>Ordinary Mansaba, Riayeti, Khas and MutaferiqaMuhwars, Mash, Youmia, Mamool, Saliyans,Customs Mukasas and Agrahara, MahwaratWalajahi (other than those issued in lieu of Jagirs) TahirSarishtadari, Wiquai Nigari.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
