<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1971/70/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1971/70"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Contempt Of Courts Act, 1971"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1971/70/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1971/70/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1971/70/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1971/70/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-11-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Contempt Of Courts Act, 1971</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and extent.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Contempt of Courts Act, 1971.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India:</p>
            <p>Provided that it shall not apply to the State of Jammu and Kashmir except to the extent to which the provisions of this Act relate to contempt of the Supreme Court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“contempt of court” means civil contempt or criminal contempt;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“civil contempt” means wilful disobedience to any judgment, decree, direction, order, writ or other process of a court or wilful breach of an undertaking given to a court;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>“criminal contempt” means the publication (whether by words, spoken or written, or by signs, or by visible representation, or otherwise) of any matter or the doing of any other act whatsoever which—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>scandalises or tends to scandalise, or lowers or tends to lower the authority of, any court; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>prejudices, or interferes or tends to interfere with, the due course of any judicial proceeding; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>interferes or tends to interfere with, or obstructs or tends to obstruct, the administration of justice in any other manner;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>“High Court” means the High Court for a State or a Union territory, and includes the court of the Judicial Commissioner in any Union territory.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Innocent publication and distribution of matter not contempt.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A person shall not be guilty of contempt of court on the ground that he has published (whether by words, spoken or written, or by signs, or by visible representations, or otherwise) any matter which interferes or tends to interfere with, or obstructs or tends to obstruct, the course of justice in connection with any civil or criminal proceeding pending at that time of publication, if at that time he had no reasonable grounds for believing that the proceeding was pending.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in this Act or any other law for the time being in force, the publication of any such matter as is mentioned in sub-section (1) in connection with any civil or criminal proceeding which is not pending at the time of publication shall not be deemed to constitute contempt of court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A person shall not be guilty of contempt of court on the ground that he has distributed a publication containing any such matter as is mentioned in sub-section (1), if at the time of distribution he had no reasonable grounds for believing that it contained or was likely to contain any such matter as aforesaid:</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.3.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that this sub-section shall not apply in respect of the distribution of—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.3.list2.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>any publication which is a book or paper printed or published otherwise than in conformity with the rules contained in section 3 of the Press and Registration of Books Act, 1867 (25 of 1867);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.3.list2.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>any publication which is a newspaper published otherwise than in conformity with the rules contained in section 5 of the said Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.3.list5">
              <listIntroduction>For the purposes of this section, a judicial proceeding—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.3.list5.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-3.3.list5.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>is said to be pending—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-3.3.list5.a.list0.A">
                    <num>(A)</num>
                    <p>in the case of a civil proceeding, when it is instituted by the filing of a plaint or otherwise,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.3.list5.a.list0.B">
                    <num>(B)</num>
                    <blockList id="section-3.3.list5.a.list0.B.list0">
                      <listIntroduction>in the case of a criminal proceeding under the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898), or any other law—</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-3.3.list5.a.list0.B.list0.i">
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <p>where it relates to the commission of an offence, when the charge-sheet or challan is filed, or when the court issues summons or warrant, as the case may be, against the accused, and</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-3.3.list5.a.list0.B.list0.ii">
                        <num>(ii)</num>
                        <p>in any other case, when the court takes cognizance of the matter to which the proceeding relates, and</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.3.list7">
              <listIntroduction>in the case of a civil or criminal proceeding, shall be deemed to continue to be pending until it is heard and finally decided, that is to say, in a case where an appeal or revision is competent, until the appeal or revision is heard and finally decided or, where no appeal or revision is preferred, until the period of limitation prescribed for such appeal or revision has expired;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.3.list7.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>which has been heard and finally decided shall not be deemed to be pending merely by reason of the fact that proceedings for the execution of the decree, order or sentence passed therein are pending.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Fair and accurate report of judicial proceeding not contempt.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions contained in section 7, a person shall not be guilty of contempt of court for publishing a fair and accurate report of a judicial proceeding or any stage thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Fair criticism of judicial act not contempt.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A person shall not be guilty of contempt of court for publishing any fair comment on the merits of any case which has been heard and finally decided.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Complaint against presiding officers of subordinate courts when not contempt.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A person shall not be guilty of contempt of court in respect of any statement made by him in good faith concerning the presiding officer of any subordinate court to—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any other subordinate court, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the High Court,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>to which it is subordinate.</p>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <p>In this section, “subordinate court” means any court subordinate to a High Court.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Publication of information relating to proceedings in chambers or in camera not contempt except in certain cases.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, a person shall not be guilty of contempt of court for publishing a fair and accurate report of a judicial proceeding before any court sitting in chambers or in camera except in the following cases, that is to say,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>where the publication is contrary to the provisions of any enactment for the time being in force;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>where the court, on grounds of public policy or in exercise of any power vested in it, expressly prohibits the publication of all information relating to the proceeding or of information of the description which is published;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>where the court sits in chambers or in camera for reasons connected with public order or the security of the State, the publication of information relating to those proceedings;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>where the information relates to a secret process, discovery or invention which is an issue in the proceedings.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Without prejudice to the provisions contained in sub-section (1), a person shall not be guilty of contempt of court for publishing the text or a fair and accurate summary of the whole, or any part, of an order made by a court sitting in chambers or in camera, unless the court has expressly prohibited the publication thereof on grounds of public policy, or for reasons connected with public order or the security of the State, or on the ground that it contains information relating to a secret process, discovery or invention, or in exercise of any power vested in it.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Other defences not affected.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Nothing contained in this Act shall be construed as implying that any other defence which would have been a valid defence in any proceedings for contempt of court has ceased to be available merely by reason of the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Act not to imply enlargement of scope of contempt.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Nothing contained in this Act shall be construed as implying that any disobedience, breach, publication or other act is punishable as contempt of court which would not be so punishable a part from this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Power of High Court to punish contempts of subordinate courts.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every High Court shall have and exercise the same jurisdiction, powers and authority, in accordance with the same procedure and practice, in respect of contempts of courts subordinate to it as it has and exercises in respect of contempts of itself:</p>
            <p>Provided that no High Court shall take cognizance of a contempt alleged to have been committed in respect of a court subordinate to it where such contempt is an offence punishable under the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Power of High Court to try offences committed or offenders found outside jurisdiction.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A High Court shall have jurisdiction to inquire into or try a contempt of itself or of any court subordinate to it, whether the contempt is alleged to have been committed within or outside the local limits of its jurisdiction, and whether the person alleged to be guilty of contempt is within or outside such limits.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Punishment for contempt of court.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Save as otherwise expressly provided in this Act or in any other law, a contempt of court may be punished with simple imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees, or with both:</p>
            <p>Provided that the accused may be discharged or the punishment awarded may be remitted on apology being made to the satisfaction of the court.</p>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <p>An apology shall not be rejected merely on the ground that it is qualified or conditional if the accused makes it bona fide.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being in force, no court shall impose a sentence in excess of that specified in sub-section (1) for any contempt either in respect of itself or of a court subordinate to it.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, where a person is found guilty of a civil contempt, the court, if it considers that a fine will not meet the ends of justice and that a sentence of imprisonment is necessary shall, instead of sentencing him to simple imprisonment, direct that he be detained in a civil prison for such period not exceeding six months as it may think fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the person found guilty of contempt of court in respect of any undertaking given to a court is a company, every person who, at the time the contempt was committed, was in charge of, and was responsible to, the company for the conduct of business of the company, as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the contempt and the punishment may be enforced, with the leave of the court, by the detention in civil prison of each such person:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to such punishment if he proves that the contempt was committed without his knowledge or that he exercised all due diligence to prevent its commission.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (4), where the contempt of court referred to therein has been committed by a company and it is proved that the contempt has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of the contempt and the punishment may be enforced, with the leave of the court, by the detention in civil prison of such director, manager, secretary or other officer.</p>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <blockList id="section-12.5.list3">
              <listIntroduction>For the purposes of sub-sections (4) and (5),—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.5.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“company” means any body corporate and includes a firm or other association of individuals; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.5.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“director”, in relation to a firm, means a partner in the firm.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Contempts not punishable in certain cases.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time being in force,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>no court shall impose a sentence under this Act for a contempt of court unless it is satisfied that the contempt is of such a nature that it substantially interferes, or tends substantially to interfere with the due course of justice;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the court may permit, in any proceeding for contempt of court, justification by truth as a valid defence if it is satisfied that it is in public interest and the request for invoking the said defence is bona fide.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Procedure where contempt is in the face of the Supreme Court or a High Court.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>When it is alleged, or appears to the Supreme Court or the High Court upon its own view, that a person has been guilty of contempt committed in its presence or hearing, the Court may cause such person to be detained in custody, and, at any time before the rising of the Court, on the same day, or as early as possible thereafter, shall—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>cause him to be informed in writing of the contempt with which he is charged;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>afford him an opportunity to make his defence to the charge;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>after taking such evidence as may be necessary or as may be offered by such person and after hearing him, proceed, either forthwith or after adjournment, to determine the matter of the charge; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>make such order for the punishment or discharge of such person as may be just.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where a person charged with contempt under that sub-section applies, whether orally or in writing, to have the charge against him tried by some Judge other than the Judge or Judges in whose presence or hearing the offence is alleged to have been committed, and the Court is of opinion that it is practicable to do so and that in the interests of proper administration of justice the application should be allowed, it shall cause the matter to be placed, together with a statement of the facts of the case, before the Chief Justice for such directions as he may think fit to issue as respects the trial thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law, in any trial of a person charged with contempt under sub-section (1) which is held, in pursuance of a direction given under sub-section (2), by a Judge other than the Judge or Judges in whose presence or hearing the offence is alleged to have been committed, it shall not be necessary for the Judge or Judges in whose presence or hearing the offence is alleged to have been committed to appear as a witness and the statement placed before the Chief Justice under sub-section (2) shall be treated as evidence in the case.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Pending the determination of the charge, the Court may direct that a person charged with contempt under this section shall be detained in such custody as it may specify:</p>
            <p>Provided that he shall be released on bail, if a bond for such sum of money as the Court thinks sufficient is executed with or without sureties conditioned that the person charged shall attend at the time and place mentioned in the bond and shall continue to so attend until otherwise directed by the Court:</p>
            <p>Provided further that the Court may, if it thinks fit, instead of taking bail from such person, discharge him on his executing a bond without sureties for his attendance as aforesaid.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Cognizance of criminal contempt in other cases.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-15.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In the case of a criminal contempt, other than a contempt referred to in section 14, the Supreme Court or the High Court may take action on its own motion or on a motion made by—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the Advocate-General, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any other person, with the consent in writing to the Advocate-General, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>in relation to the High Court for the Union territory of Delhi, such Law Officer as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf, or any other person, with the consent in writing of such Law Officer.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the case of any criminal contempt of a subordinate court, the High Court may take action on a reference made to it by the subordinate court or on a motion made by the Advocate-General or, in relation to a Union territory, by such Law Officer as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every motion or reference made under this section shall specify the contempt of which the person charged is alleged to be guilty.</p>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <blockList id="section-15.3.list3">
              <listIntroduction>In this section, the expression “Advocate-General” means—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.3.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in relation to the Supreme Court, the Attorney-General or the Solicitor-General;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.3.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in relation to the High Court, the Advocate-General of the State or any of the States for which the High Court has been established;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.3.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>in relation to the Court of a Judicial Commissioner, such Law Officer as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Contempt by Judge, Magistrate or other person acting judicially.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-16.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of any law for the time being in force, a Judge, Magistrate or other person acting judicially shall also be liable for contempt of his own court or of any other court in the same manner as any other individual is liable and the provisions of this Act shall, so far as may be, apply accordingly.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in this section shall apply to any observations or remarks made by a Judge, Magistrate or other person acting judicially, regarding a subordinate court in an appeal or revision pending before such Judge, Magistrate or other person against the order or judgment of the subordinate court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Procedure after cognizance.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notice of every proceeding under section 15 shall be served personally on the person charged, unless the court for reasons to be recorded directs otherwise.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-17.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The notice shall be accompanied—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in the case of proceedings commenced on a motion, by a copy of the motion as also copies of the affidavits, if any, on which such motion is founded; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in case of proceedings commenced on a reference by a subordinate court, by a copy of the reference.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Court may, if it is satisfied that a person charged under section 15 is likely to abscond or keep out of the way to avoid service of the notice, order the attachment of his property of such value or amount as it may deem reasonable.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every attachment under sub-section (3) shall be effected in the manner provided in the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), for the attachment of property in execution of a decree for payment of money, and if, after such attachment, the person charged appears and shows to the satisfaction of the court that he did not abscond or keep out of the way to avoid service of the notice, the Court shall order the release of his property from attachment upon such terms as to costs or otherwise as it may think fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person charged with contempt under section 15 may file an affidavit in support of his defence, and the court may determine the matter of the charge either on the affidavits filed or after taking such further evidence as may be necessary, and pass such order as the justice of the case requires.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Hearing of cases of criminal contempt to be by Benches.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every case of criminal contempt under section 15 shall be heard and determined by a Bench of not less than two Judges.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Sub-section (1) shall not apply to the Court of a Judicial Commissioner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Appeals.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-19.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-19.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>An appeal shall lie as of right from any order or decision of High Court in the exercise of its jurisdiction to punish for contempt—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-19.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>where the order or decision is that of a single Judge, to a Bench of not less than two Judges of the Court;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>where the order or decision is that of a Bench, to the Supreme Court:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that where the order or decision is that of the Court of the Judicial Commissioner in any Union territory, such appeal shall lie to the Supreme Court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-19.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Pending any appeal, the appellate Court may order that—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the execution of the punishment or order appealed against be suspended;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>if the appellant is in confinement, he be released on bail; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the appeal be heard notwithstanding that the appellant has not purged his contempt.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any person aggrieved by any order against which an appeal may be filed satisfies the High Court that he intends to prefer an appeal, the High Court may also exercise all or any of the powers conferred by sub-section (2).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-19.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>An appeal under sub-section (1) shall be filed—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-19.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in the case of an appeal to a Bench of the High Court, within thirty days;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.4.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in the case of an appeal to the Supreme Court, within sixty days,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>from the date of the order appealed against.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Limitation for actions for contempt.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No court shall initiate any proceedings of contempt, either on its own motion or otherwise, after the expiry of a period of one year from the date on which the contempt is alleged to have been committed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Act not to apply to Nyaya Panchayats or other village courts.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Nothing contained in this Act shall apply in relation to contempt of Nyaya Panchayats or other village courts, by whatever name known, for the administration of justice, established under any law.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Act to be in addition to, and not in derogation of, other laws relating to contempt.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of this Act shall be in addition to, and not in derogation of the provisions of any other law relating to contempt of courts.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Power of Supreme Court and High Courts to make rules.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Supreme Court or, as the case may be, any High Court, may make rules, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, providing for any matter relating to its procedure.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Repeal.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Contempt of Courts Act, 1952 (32 of 1952), is hereby repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
