<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2009/6/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2009/6"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Limited Liability Partnership Act, 2008"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2009/6/eng@2009-01-07/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2009/6/eng@2009-01-07"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2009-01-07" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2009/6/eng@2009-01-07/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2009/6/eng@2009-01-07"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-11-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Limited Liability Partnership Act, 2008</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Limited Liability Partnership Act, 2008.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India .</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint:</p>
            <p>Provided that different dates may be appointed for different provisions of this Act and any reference in any such provision to the commencement of this Act shall be construed as a reference to the coming into force of that provision.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.1.list1.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>"address", in relation to a partner of a limited liability partnership, means-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.1.list1.a.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>if an individual, his usual residential address; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.1.list1.a.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>if a body corporate, the address of its registered office;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"advocate" means an advocate as defined in clause (a) of sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Advocates Act, 1961 (25 of 1961);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>"Appellate Tribunal" means the National Company Law Appellate Tribunal constituted under sub-section (1) of section 10FR of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.1.list1.d.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>"body corporate" means a company as defined in section 3 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) and includes-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.1.list1.d.list1.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>a limited liability partnership registered under this Act;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.1.list1.d.list1.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>a limited liability partnership incorporated outside India ; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.1.list1.d.list1.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>a company incorporated outside India ,</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>but does not include-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list3.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>a corporation sole;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list3.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>a co-operative society registered under any law for the time being in force; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list3.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>any other body corporate (not being a company as defined in section 3 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) or a limited liability partnership as defined in this Act), which the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>"business" includes every trade, profession, service and occupation;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list3.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>"chartered accountant" means a chartered accountant as defined in clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Chartered Accountants Act, 1949 (38 of 1949) and who has obtained a certificate of practice under sub-section (1) of section 6 of that Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list3.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>"company secretary" means a company secretary as defined in clause (c) of sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Company Secretaries Act, 1980 (56 of 1980) and who has obtained a certificate of practice under sub-section (1) of section 6 of that Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list3.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>"cost accountant" means a cost accountant as defined in clause (b) of sub­-section (1) of section 2 of the Cost and Works Accountants Act, 1959 (23 of 1959) and who has obtained a certificate of practice under sub-section (1) of section 6 of that Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list3.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>"Court", with respect to any offence under this Act, means the Court having jurisdiction as per the provisions of section 77;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list3.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>"designated partner" means any partner designated as such pursuant to section 7;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list3.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>"entity" means any body corporate and includes, for the purposes of sections 18, 46, 47, 48, 49, 50, 52 and 53, a firm set-up under the Indian Partnership Act, 1932 (9 of 1932);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list3.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>"financial year", in relation to a limited liability partnerships, means the period from the 1st day of April of a year to the 31st day of March of the following year:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that in the case of a limited liability partnership incorporated after the 30th day of September of a year, the financial year may end on the 31st day of March of the year next following that year;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list5.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>"foreign limited liability partnership" means a limited liability partnership formed, incorporated or registered outside India which establishes a place of business within India ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list5.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>"limited liability partnership" means a partnership formed and registered under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list5.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>"limited liability partnership agreement" means any written agreement between the partners of the limited liability partnership or between the limited liability partnership and its partners which determines the mutual rights and duties of the partners and their rights and duties in relation to that limited liability partnership;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list5.p">
                <num>(p)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.1.list5.p.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>"name", in relation to a partner of a limited liability partnership, means-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.1.list5.p.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>if an individual, his forename, middle name and surname; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.1.list5.p.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>if a body corporate, its registered name;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list5.q">
                <num>(q)</num>
                <p>"partner", in relation to a limited liability partnership, means any person who becomes a partner in the limited liability partnership in accordance with the limited liability partnership agreement;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list5.r">
                <num>(r)</num>
                <p>prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list5.s">
                <num>(s)</num>
                <p>"Registrar" means a Registrar, or an Additional, a Joint, a Deputy or an Assistant Registrar, having the duty of registering companies under the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list5.t">
                <num>(t)</num>
                <p>"Schedule" means a Schedule to this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list5.u">
                <num>(u)</num>
                <p>"Tribunal" means the National Company Law Tribunal constituted under sub-section (1) of section 10FB of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956).</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Words and expressions used and not defined in this Act but defined in the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in that Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Limited liability partnership to be body corporate. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A limited liability partnership is a body corporate formed and incorporated under this Act and is a legal entity separate from that of its partners.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A limited liability partnership shall have perpetual succession.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any change in the partners of a limited liability partnership shall not affect the existence, rights or liabilities of the limited liability partnership.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Non-applicability of the Indian Partnership Act, 1932.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Save as otherwise provided, the provisions of the Indian Partnership Act, 1932 (9 of 1932) shall not apply to a limited liability partnership.</p>
            <p>This section provides that the provisions of the Indian Partnership Act, 1932 shall not apply to an LLP.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Partners. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any individual or body corporate may be a partner in a limited liability partnership:</p>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that an individual shall not be capable of becoming a partner of a limited liability partnership, if-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>he has been found to be of unsound mind by a Court of competent jurisdiction and the finding is in force;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>he is an undischarged insolvent; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>he has applied to be adjudicated as an insolvent and his application is pending.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Minimum number of partners. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every limited liability partnership shall have at least two partners.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If at any time the number of partners of a limited liability partnership is reduced below two and the limited liability partnership carries on business for more than six months while the number is so reduced, the person, who is the only partner of the limited liability partnership during the time that it so carries on business after those six months and has the knowledge of the fact that it is carrying on business with him alone, shall be liable personally for the obligations of the limited liability partnership incurred during that period.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Designated partners. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every limited liability partnership shall have at least two designated partners who are individuals and at least one of them shall be a resident in India :</p>
            <p>Provided that in case of a limited liability partnership in which all the partners are bodies corporate or in which one or more partners are individuals and bodies corporate, at least two individuals who are partners of such limited liability partnership or nominees of such bodies corporate shall act as designated partners.</p>
            <p>Explanation .-For the purposes of this section, the term "resident in India " means a person who has stayed in India for a period of not less than one hundred and eighty-two days during the immediately preceding one year.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Subject to the provisions of sub-section (1),-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>if the incorporation document-</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>specifies who are to be designated partners, such persons shall be designated partners on incorporation; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>states that each of the partners from time to time of limited liability partnership is to be designated partner, every partner shall be a designated partner;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>any partner may become a designated partner by and in accordance with the limited liability partnership agreement and a partner may cease to be a designated partner in accordance with limited liability partnership agreement.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An individual shall not become a designated partner in any limited liability partnership unless he has given his prior consent to act as such to the limited liability partnership in such form and manner as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every limited liability partnership shall file with the registrar the particulars of every individual who has given his consent to act as designated partner in such form and manner as may be prescribed within thirty days of his appointment.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An individual eligible to be a designated partner shall satisfy such conditions and requirements as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every designated partner of a limited liability partnership shall obtain a Designated Partner Identification Number (DPIN) from the Central Government and the provisions of sections 266A to 266G (both inclusive) of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) shall apply mutatis mutandis for the said purpose.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Liabilities of designated partners. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Unless expressly provided otherwise in this Act, a designated partner shall be-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>responsible for the doing of all acts, matters and things as are required to be done by the limited liability partnership in respect of compliance of the provisions of this Act including filing of any document, return, statement and the like report pursuant to the provisions of this Act and as may be specified in the limited liability partnership agreement; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>liable to all penalties imposed on the limited liability partnership for any contravention of those provisions.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Changes in designated partners. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A limited liability partnership may appoint a designated partner within thirty days of a vacancy arising for any reason and provisions of sub-section (4) and sub-section (5) of section 7 shall apply in respect of such new designated partner:</p>
            <p>Provided that if no designated partner is appointed, or if at any time there is only one designated partner, each partner shall be deemed to be a designated partner.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Punishment for contravention of sections 7, 8 and 9. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the limited liability partnership contravenes the provisions of sub-section (1) of section 7, the limited liability partnership and its every partner shall be punishable with fine which shall not be less than ten thousand rupees but which may extend to five lakh rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the limited liability partnership contravenes the provisions of sub-section (4) and sub-section (5) of section 7, section 8 or section 9, the limited liability partnership and its every partner shall be punishable with fine which shall not be less than ten thousand rupees but which may extend to one lakh rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Incorporation document. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>For a limited liability partnership to be incorporated,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>two or more persons associated for carrying on a lawful business with a view to profit shall subscribe their names to an incorporation document;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the incorporation document shall be filed in such manner and with such fees, as may be prescribed with the Registrar of the State in which the registered office of the limited liability partnership is to be situated; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>there shall be filed along with the incorporation document, a statement in the prescribed form, made by either an advocate, or a Company Secretary or a Chartered Accountant or a Cost Accountant, who is engaged in the formation of the limited liability partnership and by any one who subscribed his name to the incorporation document, that all the requirements of this Act and the rules made thereunder have been complied with, in respect of incorporation and matters precedent and incidental thereto.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The incorporation document shall-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>be in a form as may be prescribed;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>state the name of the limited liability partnership;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>state the proposed business of the limited liability partnership;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>state the address of the registered office of the limited liability partnership;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>state the name and address of each of the persons who are to be partners of the limited liability partnership on incorporation;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>state the name and address of the persons who are to be designated partners of the limited liability partnership on incorporation;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>contain such other information concerning the proposed limited liability partnership as may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If a person makes a statement under clause (c) of sub-section (1) which he-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>knows to be false; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>does not believe to be true, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years and with fine which shall not be less than ten thousand rupees but which may extend to five lakh rupees.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Incorporation by registration. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-12.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>When the requirements imposed by clauses (b) and (c) of sub-section (1) of section 11 have been complied with, the Registrar shall retain the incorporation document and, unless the requirement imposed by clause</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>of that sub-section has not been complied with, he shall, within a period of fourteen days-</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>register the incorporation document; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>give a certificate that the limited liability partnership is incorporated by the name specified therein.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Registrar may accept the statement delivered under clause (c) of sub-section (1) of section 11 as sufficient evidence that the requirement imposed by clause (a) of that sub-section has been complied with.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The certificate issued under clause (b) of sub-section (1) shall be signed by the Registrar and authenticated by his official seal.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The certificate shall be conclusive evidence that the limited liability partnership is incorporated by the name specified therein.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Registered office of limited liability partnership and change therein. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every limited liability partnership shall have a registered office to which all communications and notices may be addressed and where they shall be received.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A document may be served on a limited liability partnership or a partner or designated partner thereof by sending it by post under a certificate of posting or by registered post or by any other manner, as may be prescribed, at the registered office and any other address specifically declared by the limited liability partnership for the purpose in such form and manner as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A limited liability partnership may change the place of its registered office and file the notice of such change with the Registrar in such form and manner and subject to such conditions as may be prescribed and any such change shall take effect only upon such filing.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the limited liability partnership contravenes any provisions of this section, the limited liability partnership and its every partner shall be punishable with fine which shall not be less than two thousand rupees but which may extend to twenty-five thousand rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Effect of registration. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>On registration, a limited liability partnership shall, by its name, be capable of-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>suing and being sued;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>acquiring, owning, holding and developing or disposing of property, whether movable or immovable, tangible or intangible;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>having a common seal, if it decides to have one; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>doing and suffering such other acts and things as bodies corporate may lawfully do and suffer.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Name. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every limited liability partnership shall have either the words "limited liability partnership" or the acronym "LLP" as the last words of its name.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-15.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>No limited liability partnership shall be registered by a name which, in the opinion of the Central Government is-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>undesirable; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>identical or too nearly resembles to that of any other partnership firm or limited liability partnership or body corporate or a registered trade mark, or a trade mark which is subject of an application for registration, of any other person under the Trade Marks Act, 1999 (47 of 1999).</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Reservation of name. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-16.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-16.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A person may apply in such form and manner and accompanied by such fee as may be prescribed to the Registrar for the reservation of a name set out in the application as-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-16.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the name of a proposed limited liability partnership; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the name to which a limited liability partnership proposes to change its name.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon receipt of an application under sub-section (1) and on payment of the prescribed fee, the Registrar may, if he is satisfied, subject to the rules prescribed by the Central Government in the matter, that the name to be reserved is not one which may be rejected on any ground referred to in sub-section (2) of section 15, reserve the name for a period of three months from the date of intimation by the Registrar.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Change of name of limited liability partnership. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-17.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in sections 15 and 16, where the Central Government is satisfied that a limited liability partnership has been registered (whether through inadvertence or otherwise and whether originally or by a change of name) under a name which-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>is a name referred to in sub-section (2) of section 15; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>is identical with or too nearly resembles the name of any other limited liability partnership or body corporate or other name as to be likely to be mistaken for it, the Central Government may direct such limited liability partnership to change its name, and the limited liability partnership shall comply with the said direction within three months after the date of the direction or such longer period as the Central Government may allow.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any limited liability partnership which fails to comply with a direction given under sub-section (1) shall be punishable with fine which shall not be less than ten thousand rupees but which may extend to five lakh rupees and the designated partner of such limited liability partnership shall be punishable with fine which shall not be less than ten thousand rupees but which may extend to one lakh rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Application for direction to change name in certain circumstances. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any entity which already has a name similar to the name of a limited liability partnership which has been incorporated subsequently, may apply, in such manner as may be prescribed, to the Registrar to give a direction to any limited liability partnership, on a ground referred to in section 17 to change its name.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Registrar shall not consider any application under sub-section (1) to give a direction to a limited liability partnership on the ground referred to in clause (b) of sub-­section (1) of section 17 unless the Registrar receives the application within twenty-four months from the date of registration of the limited liability partnership under that name.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Change of registered name. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any limited liability partnership may change its name registered with the Registrar by filing with him a notice of such change in such form and manner and on payment of such fees as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for improper use of words "limited liability partnership" or "LLP". -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any person or persons carry on business under any name or title of which the words "Limited Liability Partnership" or "LLP" or any contraction or imitation thereof is or are the last word or words, that person or each of those persons shall, unless duly incorporated as limited liability partnership, be punishable with fine which shall not be less than fifty thousand rupees but which may extend to five lakh rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Publication of name and limited liability. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-21.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-21.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Every limited liability partnership shall ensure that its invoices, official correspondence and publications bear the following, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-21.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the name, address of its registered office and registration number of the limited liability partnership; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-21.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>a statement that it is registered with limited liability.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-21.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any limited liability partnership which contravenes the provisions of sub-section (1) shall be punishable with fine which shall not be less than two thousand rupees but which may extend to twenty-five thousand rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Eligibility to be partners.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>On the incorporation of a limited liability partnership, the persons who subscribed their names to the incorporation document shall be its partners and any other person may become a partner of the limited liability partnership by and in accordance with the limited liability partnership agreement.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Relationship of partners.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-23.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Save as otherwise provided by this Act, the mutual rights and duties of the partners of a limited liability partnership, and the mutual rights and duties of a limited liability partnership and its partners, shall be governed by the limited liability partnership agreement between the partners, or between the limited liability partnership and its partners.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The limited liability partnership agreement and any changes, if any, made therein shall be filed with the Registrar in such form, manner and accompanied by such fees as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An agreement in writing made before the incorporation of a limited liability partnership between the persons who subscribe their names to the incorporation document may impose obligations on the limited liability partnership, provided such agreement is ratified by all the partners after the incorporation of the limited liability partnership.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the absence of agreement as to any matter, the mutual rights and duties of the partners and the mutual rights and duties of the limited liability partnership and the partners shall be determined by the provisions relating to that matter as are set out in the First Schedule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Cessation of partnership interest .-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-24.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A person may cease to be a partner of a limited liability partnership in accordance with an agreement with the other partners or, in the absence of agreement with the other partners as to cessation of being a partner, by giving a notice in writing of not less than thirty days to the other partners of his intention to resign as partner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-24.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A person shall cease to be a partner of a limited liability partnership-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-24.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>on his death or dissolution of the limited liability partnership; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>if he is declared to be of unsound mind by a competent court; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>if he has applied to be adjudged as an insolvent or declared as an insolvent.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-24.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where a person has ceased to be a partner of a limited liability partnership (hereinafter referred to as "former partner"), the former partner is to be regarded (in relation to any person dealing with the limited liability partnership) as still being a partner of the limited liability partnership unless-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-24.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the person has notice that the former partner has ceased to be a partner of the limited liability partnership; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>notice that the former partner has ceased to be a partner of the limited liability partnership has been delivered to the Registrar.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The cessation of a partner from the limited liability partnership does not by itself discharge the partner from any obligation to the limited liability partnership or to the other partners or to any other person which he incurred while being a partner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-24.5.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where a partner of a limited liability partnership ceases to be a partner, unless otherwise provided in the limited liability partnership agreement, the former partner or a person entitled to his share in consequence of the death or insolvency of the former partner, shall be entitled to receive from the limited liability partnership-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-24.5.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>an amount equal to the capital contribution of the former partner actually made to the limited liability partnership; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.5.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>his right to share in the accumulated profits of the limited liability partnership, after the deduction of accumulated losses of the limited liability partnership, determined as at the date the former partner ceased to be a partner.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A former partner or a person entitled to his share in consequence of the death or insolvency of the former partner shall not have any right to interfere in the management of the limited liability partnership.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Registration of changes in partners .-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-25.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every partner shall inform the limited liability partnership of any change in his name or address within a period of fifteen days of such change.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-25.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A limited liability partnership shall-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-25.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>where a person becomes or ceases to be a partner, file a notice with the Registrar within thirty days from the date he becomes or ceases to be a partner; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-25.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>where there is any change in the name or address of a partner, file a notice with the Registrar within thirty days of such change.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-25.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A notice filed with the Registrar under sub-section (2)-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-25.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>shall be in such form and accompanied by such fees as may be prescribed;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-25.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>shall be signed by the designated partner of the limited liability partnership and authenticated in a manner as may be prescribed; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-25.3.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>if it relates to an incoming partner, shall contain a statement by such partner that he consents to becoming a partner, signed by him and authenticated in the manner as may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the limited liability partnership contravenes the provisions of sub-section (2), the limited liability partnership and every designated partner of the limited liability partnership shall be punishable with fine which shall not be less than two thousand rupees but which may extend to twenty-five thousand rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any partner contravenes the provisions of sub-section (1), such partner shall be punishable with fine which shall not be less than two thousand rupees but which may extend to twenty-five thousand rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person who ceases to be a partner of a limited liability partnership may himself file with the Registrar the notice referred to in sub-section (3) if he has reasonable cause to believe that the limited liability partnership may not file the notice with the Registrar and in case of any such notice filed by a partner, the Registrar shall obtain a confirmation to this effect from the limited liability partnership unless the limited liability partnership has also filed such notice:</p>
            <p>Provided that where no confirmation is given by the limited liability partnership within fifteen days, the registrar shall register the notice made by a person ceasing to be a partner under this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Partner as agent.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every partner of a limited liability partnership is, for the purpose of the business of the limited liability partnership, the agent of the limited liability partnership, but not of other partners.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Extent of liability of limited liability partnership .-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-27.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-27.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A limited liability partnership is not bound by anything done by a partner in dealing with a person if-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-27.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the partner in fact has no authority to act for the limited liability partnership in doing a particular act; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-27.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the person knows that he has no authority or does not know or believe him to be a partner of the limited liability partnership.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The limited liability partnership is liable if a partner of a limited liability partnership is liable to any person as a result of a wrongful act or omission on his part in the course of the business of the limited liability partnership or with its authority.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An obligation of the limited liability partnership whether arising in contract or otherwise, shall be solely the obligation of the limited liability partnership.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The liabilities of the limited liability partnership shall be met out of the property of the limited liability partnership.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28">
        <num>28.</num>
        <heading>Extent of liability of partner .-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-28.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A partner is not personally liable, directly or indirectly for an obligation referred to in sub-section (3) of section 27 solely by reason of being a partner of the limited liability partnership.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-28.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of sub-section (3) of section 27 and sub-section (1) of this section shall not affect the personal liability of a partner for his own wrongful act or omission, but a partner shall not be personally liable for the wrongful act or omission of any other partner of the limited liability partnership.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29">
        <num>29.</num>
        <heading>Holding out .-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-29.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person, who by words spoken or written or by conduct, represents himself, or knowingly permits himself to be represented to be a partner in a limited liability partnership is liable to any person who has on the faith of any such representation given credit to the limited liability partnership, whether the person representing himself or represented to be a partner does or does not know that the representation has reached the person so giving credit:</p>
            <p>Provided that where any credit is received by the limited liability partnership as a result of such representation, the limited liability partnership shall, without prejudice to the liability of the person so representing himself or represented to be a partner, be liable to the extent of credit received by it or any financial benefit derived thereon.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where after a partner's death the business is continued in the same limited liability partnership name, the continued use of that name or of the deceased partner's name as a part thereof shall not of itself make his legal representative or his estate liable for any act of the limited liability partnership done after his death.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-30">
        <num>30.</num>
        <heading>Unlimited liability in case of fraud .-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-30.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the event of an act carried out by a limited liability partnership, or any of its partners, with intent to defraud creditors of the limited liability partnership or any other person, or for any fraudulent purpose, the liability of the limited liability partnership and partners who acted with intent to defraud creditors or for any fraudulent purpose shall be unlimited for all or any of the debts or other liabilities of the limited liability partnership:</p>
            <p>Provided that in case any such act is carried out by a partner, the limited liability partnership is liable to the same extent as the partner unless it is established by the limited liability partnership that such act was without the knowledge or the authority of the limited liability partnership.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-30.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any business is carried on with such intent or for such purpose as mentioned in sub-section (1), every person who was knowingly a party to the carrying on of the business in the manner aforesaid shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years and with fine which shall not be less than fifty thousand rupees but which may extend to five lakh rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-30.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a limited liability partnership or any partner or designated partner or employee of such limited liability partnership has conducted the affairs of the limited liability partnership in a fraudulent manner, then without prejudice to any criminal proceedings which may arise under any law for the time being in force, the limited liability partnership and any such partner or designated partner or employee shall be liable to pay compensation to any person who has suffered any loss or damage by reason of such conduct:</p>
            <p>Provided that such limited liability partnership shall not be liable if any such partner or designated partner or employee has acted fraudulently without knowledge of the limited liability partnership.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-31">
        <num>31.</num>
        <heading>Whistle blowing .-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-31.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-31.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Court or Tribunal may reduce or waive any penalty leviable against any partner or employee of a limited liability partnership, if it is satisfied that-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-31.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>such partner or employee of a limited liability partnership has provided useful information during investigation of such limited liability partnership; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-31.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>when any information given by any partner or employee (whether or not during investigation) leads to limited liability partnership or any partner or employee of such limited liability partnership being convicted under this Act or any other Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-31.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No partner or employee of any limited liability partnership may be discharged, demoted, suspended, threatened, harassed or in any other manner discriminated against the terms and conditions of his limited liability partnership or employment merely because of his providing information or causing information to be provided pursuant to sub-section (1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-32">
        <num>32.</num>
        <heading>Form of contribution .-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-32.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A contribution of a partner may consist of tangible, movable or immovable or intangible property or other benefit to the limited liability partnership, including money, promissory notes, other agreements to contribute cash or property, and contracts for services performed or to be performed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-32.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The monetary value of contribution of each partner shall be accounted for and disclosed in the accounts of the limited liability partnership in the manner as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-33">
        <num>33.</num>
        <heading>Obligation to contribute .-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-33.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The obligation of a partner to contribute money or other property or other benefit or to perform services for a limited liability partnership shall be as per the limited liability partnership agreement.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-33.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A creditor of a limited liability partnership, which extends credit or otherwise acts in reliance on an obligation described in that agreement, without notice of any compromise between partners, may enforce the original obligation against such partner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-34">
        <num>34.</num>
        <heading>Maintenance of books of account, other records and audit, etc .-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-34.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The limited liability partnership shall maintain such proper books of account as may be prescribed relating to its affairs for each year of its existence on cash basis or accrual basis and according to double entry system of accounting and shall maintain the same at its registered office for such period as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-34.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every limited liability partnership shall, within a period of six months from the end of each financial year, prepare a Statement of Account and Solvency for the said financial year as at the last day of the said financial year in such form as may be prescribed, and such statement shall be signed by the designated partners of the limited liability partnership.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-34.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every limited liability partnership shall file within the prescribed time, the Statement of Account and Solvency prepared pursuant to sub-section (2) with the Registrar every year in such form and manner and accompanied by such fees as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-34.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The accounts of limited liability partnerships shall be audited in accordance with such rules as may be prescribed:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, exempt any class or classes of limited liability partnerships from the requirements of this sub-section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-34.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any limited liability partnership which fails to comply with the provisions of this section shall be punishable with fine which shall not be less than twenty-five thousand rupees but which may extend to five lakh rupees and every designated partner of such limited liability partnership shall be punishable with fine which shall not be less than ten thousand rupees but which may extend to one lakh rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-35">
        <num>35.</num>
        <heading>Annual return.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-35.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every limited liability partnership shall file an annual return duly authenticated with the Registrar within sixty days of closure of its financial year in such form and manner and accompanied by such fee as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-35.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any limited liability partnership which fails to comply with the provisions of this section shall be punishable with fine which shall not be less than twenty-five thousand rupees but which may extend to five lakh rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-35.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the limited liability partnership contravenes the provisions of this section, the designated partner of such limited liability partnership shall be punishable with fine which shall not be less than ten thousand rupees but which may extend to one lakh rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-36">
        <num>36.</num>
        <heading>Inspection of documents kept by Registrar.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-36.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The incorporation document, names of partners and changes, if any, made therein, Statement of Account and Solvency and annual return filed by each limited liability partnership with the Registrar shall be available for inspection by any person in such manner and on payment of such fee as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-37">
        <num>37.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for false statement.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-37.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-37.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If in any return, statement or other document required by or for the purposes of any of the provisions of this Act, any person makes a statement-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-37.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>which is false in any material particular, knowing it to be false; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-37.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>which omits any material fact knowing it to be material,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>he shall, save as otherwise expressly provided in this Act, be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years, and shall also be liable to fine which may extend to five lakh rupees but which shall not be less than one lakh rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-38">
        <num>38.</num>
        <heading>Power of Registrar to obtain information.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-38.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In order to obtain such information as the Registrar may consider necessary for the purposes of carrying out the provisions of this Act, the Registrar may require any person including any present or former partner or designated partner or employee of a limited liability partnership to answer any question or make any declaration or supply any details or particulars in writing to him within a reasonable period.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-38.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In case any person referred to in sub-section (1) does not answer such question or make such declaration or supply such details or particulars asked for by the Registrar within a reasonable time or time given by the Registrar or when the Registrar is not satisfied with the reply or declaration or details or particulars provided by such person, the Registrar shall have power to summon that person to appear before him or an inspector or any other public officer whom the Registrar may designate, to answer any such question or make such declaration or supply such details, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-38.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person who, without lawful excuse, fails to comply with any summons or requisition of the Registrar under this section shall be punishable with fine which shall not be less than two thousand rupees but which may extend to twenty-five thousand rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-39">
        <num>39.</num>
        <heading>Compounding of offences.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-39.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may compound any offence under this Act which is punishable with fine only, by collecting from a person reasonably suspected of having committed the offence, a sum which may extend to the amount of the maximum fine prescribed for the offence.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-40">
        <num>40.</num>
        <heading>Destruction of old records.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-40.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Registrar may destroy any document filed or registered with him in physical form or in electronic form in accordance with such rules as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-41">
        <num>41.</num>
        <heading>Enforcement of duty to make returns, etc.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-41.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-41.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If any limited liability partnership is in default in complying with-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-41.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any provisions of this Act or of any other law which requires the filing in any manner with the Registrar of any return, account or other document or the giving of notice to him of any matter; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-41.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any request of the Registrar to amend or complete and resubmit any document or to submit a fresh document, and fails to make good the default within fourteen days after the service on the limited liability partnership of a notice requiring it to be done, the Tribunal may, on application by the Registrar, make an order directing that limited liability partnership or its designated partners or its partners to make good the default within such time as specified in the order.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-41.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any such order may provide that all the costs of and incidental to the application shall be borne by that limited liability partnership.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-41.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in this section shall limit the operation of any other provision of this Act or any other law imposing penalties in respect of any default referred to in this section on that limited liability partnership.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-42">
        <num>42.</num>
        <heading>Partner's transferable interest .-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-42.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The rights of a partner to a share of the profits and losses of the limited liability partnership and to receive distributions in accordance with the limited liability partnership agreement are transferable either wholly or in part.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-42.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The transfer of any right by any partner pursuant to sub-section (1) does not by itself cause the disassociation of the partner or a dissolution and winding up of the limited liability partnership.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-42.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The transfer of right pursuant to this section does not, by itself, entitle the transferee or assignee to participate in the management or conduct of the activities of the limited liability partnership, or access information concerning the transactions of the limited liability partnership.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-43">
        <num>43.</num>
        <heading>Investigation of the affairs of limited liability partnership .-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-43.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-43.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government shall appoint one or more competent persons as inspectors to investigate the affairs of a limited liability partnership and to report thereon in such manner as it may direct if-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-43.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the Tribunal, either suo motu , or on an application received from not less than one-fifth of the total number of partners of limited liability partnership, by order, declares that the affairs of the limited liability partnership ought to be investigated; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-43.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any Court, by order, declares that the affairs of a limited liability partnership ought to be investigated.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-43.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may appoint one or more competent persons as inspectors to investigate the affairs of a limited liability partnership and to report on them in such manner as it may direct.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-43.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-43.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The appointment of inspectors pursuant to sub-section (2) may be made,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-43.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>if not less than one-fifth of the total number of partners of the limited liability partnership make an application along with supporting evidence and security amount as may be prescribed; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-43.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>if the limited liability partnership makes an application that the affairs of the limited liability partnership ought to be investigated; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-43.3.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <blockList id="section-43.3.list1.c.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>if, in the opinion of the Central Government, there are circumstances suggesting-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-43.3.list1.c.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>that the business of the limited liability partnership is being or has been conducted with an intent to defraud its creditors, partners or any other person, or otherwise for a fraudulent or unlawful purpose, or in a manner oppressive or unfairly prejudicial to some or any of its partners, or that the limited liability partnership was formed for any fraudulent or unlawful purpose; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-43.3.list1.c.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>that the affairs of the limited liability partnership are not being conducted in accordance with the provisions of this Act; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-43.3.list1.c.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>that, on receipt of a report of the Registrar or any other investigating or regulatory agency, there are sufficient reasons that the affairs of the limited liability partnership ought to be investigated.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-44">
        <num>44.</num>
        <heading>Application by partners for investigation.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-44.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>An application by partners of the limited liability partnership under clause (a) of sub-section (1) of section 43 shall be supported by such evidence as the Tribunal may require for the purpose of showing that the applicants have good reason for requiring the investigation and the Central Government may, before appointing an inspector, require the applicants to give security, of such amount as may be prescribed, for payment of costs of the investigation.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-45">
        <num>45.</num>
        <heading>Firm, body corporate or association not to be appointed as inspector.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-45.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No firm, body corporate or other association shall be appointed as an inspector.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-46">
        <num>46.</num>
        <heading>Power of inspectors to carry out investigation into affairs of related entities, etc.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-46.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If an inspector appointed by the Central Government to investigate the affairs of a limited liability partnership thinks it necessary for the purposes of his investigation to investigate also the affairs of an entity which has been associated in the past or is presently associated with the limited liability partnership or any present or former partner or designated partner of the limited liability partnership, the inspector shall have the power to do so and shall report on the affairs of the other entity or partner or designated partner, so far as he thinks that the results of his investigation thereof are relevant to the investigation of the affairs of the limited liability partnership.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-46.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the case of any entity or partner or designated partner referred to in sub-section (1), the inspector shall not exercise his power of investigating into, and reporting on, its or his affairs without first having obtained the prior approval of the Central Government thereto:</p>
            <p>Provided that before according approval under this sub-section, the Central Government shall give the entity or partner or designated partner a reasonable opportunity to show cause why such approval should not be accorded.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-47">
        <num>47.</num>
        <heading>Production of documents and evidence.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-47.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-47.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>It shall be the duty of the designated partner and partners of the limited liability partnership-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-47.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to preserve and to produce before an inspector or any person authorised by him in this behalf with the previous approval of the Central Government, all books and papers of, or relating to, the limited liability partnership or, as the case may be, the other entity, which are in their custody or power; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-47.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>otherwise to give to the inspector all assistance in connection with the investigation which they are reasonably able to give.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-47.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The inspector may, with the previous approval of the Central Government, require any entity other than an entity referred to in sub-section (1) to furnish such information to, or produce such books and papers before him or any person authorised by him in this behalf, with the previous approval of that Government, as he may consider necessary, if the furnishing of such information or the production of such books and papers is relevant or necessary for the purposes of his investigation.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-47.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The inspector may keep in his custody any books and papers produced under sub­-section (1) or sub-section (2) for thirty days and thereafter shall return the same to the limited liability partnership, other entity or individual by whom or on whose behalf the books and papers are produced:</p>
            <p>Provided that the inspector may call for the books and papers if they are needed again:</p>
            <p>Provided further that if certified copies of the books and papers produced under sub­-section (2) are furnished to the inspector, he shall return those books and papers to the entity or person concerned.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-47.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-47.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>An inspector may examine on oath-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-47.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any of the persons referred to in sub-section (1);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-47.4.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>with the previous approval of the Central Government, any other person in relation to the affairs of the limited liability partnership or any other entity, as the case may be; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-47.4.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>may administer an oath accordingly and for that purpose may require any of those persons to appear before him personally.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-47.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-47.5.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If any person fails without reasonable cause or refuses-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-47.5.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to produce before an inspector or any person authorised by him in this behalf with the previous approval of the Central Government any book or paper which it is his duty under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) to produce ; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-47.5.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to furnish any information which is his duty under sub-section (2) to furnish; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-47.5.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to appear before the inspector personally when required to do so under sub­-section (4) or to answer any question which is put to him by the inspector in pursuance of that sub-section; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-47.5.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>to sign the notes of any examination,he shall be punishable with fine which shall not be less than two thousand rupees but which may extend to twenty-five thousand rupees and with a further fine which shall not be less than fifty rupees but which may extend to five hundred rupees for every day after the first day after which the default continues.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-47.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The notes of any examination under sub-section (4) shall be taken down in writing and signed by the person whose examination was made on oath and a copy of such notes shall be given to the person so examined on oath and thereafter be used as an evidence by the inspector.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-48">
        <num>48.</num>
        <heading>Seizure of documents by inspector.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-48.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where in the course of investigation, the inspector has reasonable ground to believe that the books and papers of, or relating to, the limited liability partnership or other entity or partner or designated partner of such limited liability partnership may be destroyed, mutilated, altered, falsified or secreted, the inspector may make an application to the Judicial Magistrate of the first class, or, as the case may be, the Metropolitan Magistrate, having jurisdiction, for an order for the seizure of such books and papers.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-48.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-48.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>After considering the application and hearing the inspector, if necessary, the Magistrate may, by order, authorise the inspector-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-48.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to enter, with such assistance, as may be required, the place or places where such books and papers are kept;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-48.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to search that place or those places in the manner specified in the order; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-48.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to seize books and papers which the inspector considers it necessary for the purposes of his investigation.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-48.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The inspector shall keep in his custody the books and papers seized under this section for such period not later than the conclusion of the investigation as he considers necessary and thereafter shall return the same to the concerned entity or person from whose custody or power they were seized and inform the Magistrate of such return:</p>
            <p>Provided that the books and papers shall not be kept seized for a continuous period of more than six months:</p>
            <p>Provided further that the inspector may, before returning such books and papers as aforesaid, place identification marks on them or any part thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-48.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Save as otherwise provided in this section, every search or seizure made under this section shall be carried out in accordance with the provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) relating to searches or seizures made under that Code.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-49">
        <num>49.</num>
        <heading>Inspectors' report.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-49.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The inspectors may, and if so directed by the Central Government, shall make interim reports to that Government, and on the conclusion of the investigation, shall make a final report to the Central Government and any such report shall be written or printed, as the Central Government may direct.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-49.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-49.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-49.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>shall forward a copy of any report (other than an interim report) made by the inspectors to the limited liability partnership at its registered office, and also to any other entity or person dealt with or related to the report; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-49.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>may, if it thinks fit, furnish a copy thereof, on request and on payment of the prescribed fee, to any person or entity related to or affected by the report.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-50">
        <num>50.</num>
        <heading>Prosecution.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-50.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If, from the report under section 49, it appears to the Central Government that any person in relation to the limited liability partnership or in relation to any other entity whose affairs have been investigated, has been guilty of any offence for which he is liable, the Central Government may prosecute such person for the offence; and it shall be the duty of all partners, designated partners and other employees and agents of the limited liability partnership or other entity, as the case may be, to give the Central Government all assistance in connection with the prosecution which they are reasonably able to give.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-51">
        <num>51.</num>
        <heading>Application for winding up of limited liability partnership.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-51.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any such limited liability partnership is liable to be wound up under this Act or any other law for the time being in force, and it appears to the Central Government from any such report under section 49 that it is expedient to do so by reason of any such circumstances as are referred to in sub-clause (i) or sub-clause (ii) of clause (c) of sub-section (3) of section 43, the Central Government may, unless the limited liability partnership is already being wound up by the Tribunal, cause to be presented to the Tribunal by any person authorised by the Central Government in this behalf, a petition for the winding up of the limited liability partnership on the ground that it is just and equitable that it should be wound up.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-52">
        <num>52.</num>
        <heading>Proceedings for recovery of damages or property.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-52.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-52.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If, from any report under section 49, it appears to the Central Government that proceedings ought, in the public interest, to be brought by the limited liability partnership or any entity whose affairs have been investigated,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-52.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for the recovery of damages in respect of any fraud, misfeasance or other misconduct in connection with the promotion or formation, or the management of the affairs, of such limited liability partnership or such other entity; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-52.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>for the recovery of any property of such limited liability partnership or such other entity, which has been misapplied or wrongfully retained,the Central Government may itself bring proceedings for that purpose.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-53">
        <num>53.</num>
        <heading>Expenses of investigation.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-53.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-53.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The expenses of, and incidental to, an investigation by an inspector appointed by the Central Government under this Act shall be defrayed in the first instance by the Central Government; but the following persons shall, to the extent mentioned below, be liable to reimburse the Central Government in respect of such expenses, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-53.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any person who is convicted on a prosecution, or who is ordered to pay damages or restore any property in proceedings brought by virtue of section 52, may, in the same proceedings, be ordered to pay the said expenses to such extent as may be specified by the court convicting such person, or ordering him to pay such damages or restore such property, as the case may be;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-53.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any entity in whose name proceedings are brought as aforesaid shall be liable, to the extent of the amount or value of any sums or property recovered by it as a result of the proceedings; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-53.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <blockList id="section-53.1.list1.c.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>unless, as a result of the investigation, a prosecution is instituted in pursuance of section 50,-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-53.1.list1.c.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>any entity, a partner or designated partner or any other person dealt with by the report of the inspector shall be liable to reimburse the Central Government in respect of the whole of the expenses, unless and except insofar as, the Central Government otherwise directs; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-53.1.list1.c.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>the applicants for the investigation, where the inspector was appointed in pursuance of the provisions of clause (a) of sub-section (1) of section 43, shall be liable to such extent, if any, as the Central Government may direct.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-53.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any amount for which a limited liability partnership or other entity is liable by virtue of clause (b) of sub-section (1) shall be a first charge on the sums or property mentioned in that clause.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-53.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The amount of expenses in respect of which any limited liability partnership, other entity, a partner or designated partner or any other person is liable under sub-clause (i) of clause (c) of sub-section (1) to reimburse the Central Government shall be recoverable as arrears of land revenue.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-53.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purposes of this section, any costs or expenses incurred by the Central Government or in connection with the proceedings brought by virtue of section 52 shall be treated as expenses of the investigation giving rise to the proceedings.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-54">
        <num>54.</num>
        <heading>Inspector's report to be evidence.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-54.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A copy of any report of any inspector or inspectors appointed under the provision of this Act, authenticated in such manner, if any, as may be prescribed, shall be admissible in any legal proceeding as evidence in relation to any matter contained in the report.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-55">
        <num>55.</num>
        <heading>Conversion from firm to limited liability partnership.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-55.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A firm may convert into a limited liability partnership in accordance with the provisions of this Chapter and the Second Schedule.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-56">
        <num>56.</num>
        <heading>Conversion from private company to limited liability partnership.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-56.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A private company may convert into a limited liability partnership in accordance with the provisions of this Chapter and the Third Schedule.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-57">
        <num>57.</num>
        <heading>Conversion from unlisted public company into limited liability partnership.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-57.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>An unlisted public company may convert into a limited liability partnership in accordance with the provisions of this Chapter and the Fourth Schedule.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-58">
        <num>58.</num>
        <heading>Registration and effect of conversion.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-58.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Registrar, on satisfying that a firm, private company or an unlisted public company, as the case may be, has complied with the provisions of the Second Schedule, the Third Schedule or the Fourth Schedule, as the case may be, shall, subject to the provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder, register the documents submitted under such Schedule and issue a certificate of registration in such form as the Registrar may determine stating that the limited liability partnership is, on and from the date specified in the certificate, registered under this Act:</p>
            <p>Provided that the limited liability partnership shall, within fifteen days of the date of registration, inform the concerned Registrar of Firms or Registrar of Companies, as the case may be, with which it was registered under the provisions of the Indian Partnership Act, 1932 (9 of 1932) or the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), as the case may be, about the conversion and of the particulars of the limited liability partnership in such form and manner as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-58.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon such conversion, the partners of the firm, the shareholders of private company or unlisted public company, as the case may be, the limited liability partnership to which such firm or such company has converted, and the partners of the limited liability partnership shall be bound by the provisions of the Second Schedule, the Third Schedule or the Fourth Schedule, as the case may be, applicable to them.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-58.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon such conversion, on and from the date of certificate of registration, the effects of the conversion shall be such as specified in the Second Schedule, the Third Schedule or the Fourth Schedule, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-58.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-58.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being in force, on and from the date of registration specified in the certificate of registration issued under the Second Schedule, the Third Schedule or the Fourth Schedule, as the case may be,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-58.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>there shall be a limited liability partnership by the name specified in the certificate of registration registered under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-58.4.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>all tangible (movable or immovable) and intangible property vested in the firm or the company, as the case may be, all assets, interests, rights, privileges, liabilities, obligations relating to the firm or the company, as the case may be, and the whole of the undertaking of the firm or the company, as the case may be, shall be transferred to and shall vest in the limited liability partnership without further assurance, act or deed; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-58.4.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the firm or the company, as the case may be, shall be deemed to be dissolved and removed from the records of the Registrar of Firms or Registrar of Companies, as the case may be.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-59">
        <num>59.</num>
        <heading>Foreign limited liability partnerships.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-59.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may make rules for provisions in relation to establishment of place of business by foreign limited liability partnerships within India and carrying on their business therein by applying or incorporating, with such modifications, as appear appropriate, the provisions of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) or such regulatory mechanism with such composition as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-60">
        <num>60.</num>
        <heading>Compromise or arrangement of limited liability partnerships.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-60.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-60.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where a compromise or arrangement is proposed-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-60.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>between a limited liability partnership and its creditors; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-60.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>between a limited liability partnership and its partners, the Tribunal may, on the application of the limited liability partnership or of any creditor or partner of the limited liability partnership, or, in the case of a limited liability partnership which is being wound up, of the liquidator, order a meeting of the creditors or of the partners, as the case may be, to be called, held and conducted in such manner as may be prescribed or as the Tribunal directs.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-60.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If a majority representing three-fourths in value of the creditors, or partners, as the case may be, at the meeting, agree to any compromise or arrangement, the compromise or arrangement shall, if sanctioned by the Tribunal, by order be binding on all the creditors or all the partners, as the case may be, and also on the limited liability partnership, or in the case of a limited liability partnership which is being wound up, on the liquidator and contributories of the limited liability partnership:</p>
            <p>Provided that no order sanctioning any compromise or arrangement shall be made by the Tribunal unless the Tribunal is satisfied that the limited liability partnership or any other person by whom an application has been made under sub-section (1) has disclosed to the Tribunal, by affidavit or otherwise, all material facts relating to the limited liability partnership, including the latest financial position of the limited liability partnership and the pendency of any investigation proceedings in relation to the limited liability partnership.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-60.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An order made by the Tribunal under sub-section (2) shall be filed by the limited liability partnership with the Registrar within thirty days after making such an order and shall have effect only after it is so filed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-60.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If default is made in complying with sub-section (3), the limited liability partnership, and every designated partner of the limited liability partnership shall be punishable with fine which may extend to one lakh rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-60.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Tribunal may, at any time after an application has been made to it under this section, stay the commencement or continuation of any suit or proceeding against the limited liability partnership on such terms as the Tribunal thinks fit, until the application is finally disposed of.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-61">
        <num>61.</num>
        <heading>Power of Tribunal to enforce compromise or arrangement.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-61.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-61.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where the Tribunal makes an order under section 60 sanctioning a compromise or an arrangement in respect of a limited liability partnership, it-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-61.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>shall have power to supervise the carrying out of the compromise or an arrangement; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-61.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>may, at the time of making such order or at any time thereafter, give such directions in regard to any matter or make such modifications in the compromise or arrangement as it may consider necessary for the proper working of the compromise or arrangement.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-61.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the Tribunal aforesaid is satisfied that a compromise or an arrangement sanctioned under section 60 cannot be worked satisfactorily with or without modifications, it may, either on its own motion or on the application of any person interested in the affairs of the limited liability partnership, make an order for winding up the limited liability partnership, and such an order shall be deemed to be an order made under section 64 of this Act</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-62">
        <num>62.</num>
        <heading>Provisions for facilitating reconstruction or amalgamation of limited liability partnerships.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-62.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-62.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where an application is made to the Tribunal under section 60 for sanctioning of a compromise or arrangement proposed between a limited liability partnership and any such persons as are mentioned in that section, and it is shown to the Tribunal that-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-62.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>compromise or arrangement has been proposed for the purposes of, or in connection with, a scheme for the reconstruction of any limited liability partnership or limited liability partnerships, or the amalgamation of any two or more limited liability partnerships; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-62.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>under the scheme the whole or any part of the undertaking, property or liabilities of any limited liability partnership concerned in the scheme (in this section referred to as a "transferor limited liability partnership") is to be transferred to another limited liability partnership (in this section referred to as the "transferee limited liability partnership"),</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-62.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>the Tribunal may, either by the order sanctioning the compromise or arrangement or by a subsequent order, make provisions for all or any of the following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-62.1.list3.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the transfer to the transferee limited liability partnership of the whole or any part of the undertaking, property or liabilities of any transferor limited liability partnership;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-62.1.list3.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>the continuation by or against the transferee limited liability partnership of any legal proceedings pending by or against any transferor limited liability partnership;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-62.1.list3.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>the dissolution, without winding up, of any transferor limited liability partnership;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-62.1.list3.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>the provision to be made for any person who, within such time and in such manner as the Tribunal directs, dissent from the compromise or arrangement; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-62.1.list3.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>such incidental, consequential and supplemental matters as are necessary to secure that the reconstruction or amalgamation shall be fully and effectively carried out:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that no compromise or arrangement proposed for the purposes of, or in connection with, a scheme for the amalgamation of a limited liability partnership, which is being wound up, with any other limited liability partnership or limited liability partnerships, shall be sanctioned by the Tribunal unless the Tribunal has received a report from the Registrar that the affairs of the limited liability partnership have not been conducted in a manner prejudicial to the interests of its partners or to public interest:</p>
            <p>Provided further that no order for the dissolution of any transferor limited liability partnership under clause (iii) shall be made by the Tribunal unless the Official Liquidator has, on scrutiny of the books and papers of the limited liability partnership, made a report to the Tribunal that the affairs of the limited liability partnership have not been conducted in a manner prejudicial to the interests of its partners or to public interest.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-62.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an order under this section provides for the transfer of any property or liabilities, then, by virtue of the order, that property shall be transferred to and vest in, and those liabilities shall be transferred to and become the liabilities of, the transferee limited liability partnership; and in the case of any property, if the order so directs, freed from any charge which is, by virtue of the compromise or arrangement, to cease to have effect.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-62.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Within thirty days after the making of an order under this section, every limited liability partnership in relation to which the order is made shall cause a certified copy thereof to be filed with the Registrar for registration.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-62.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If default is made in complying with the provisions of sub-section (3), the limited liability partnership, every designated partner of the limited liability partnership shall be punishable with fine which may extend to fifty thousand rupees.</p>
            <p>Explanation .-In this section "property" includes property, rights and powers of every description; and "liabilities" includes duties of every description.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-63">
        <num>63.</num>
        <heading>Winding up and dissolution.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-63.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The winding up of a limited liability partnership may be either voluntary or by the Tribunal and limited liability partnership, so wound up may be dissolved.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-64">
        <num>64.</num>
        <heading>Circumstances in which limited liability partnership may be wound up by Tribunal.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-64.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-64.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A limited liability partnership may be wound up by the Tribunal,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-64.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>if the limited liability partnership decides that limited liability partnership be wound up by the Tribunal;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-64.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>if, for a period of more than six months, the number of partners of the limited liability partnership is reduced below two;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-64.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>if the limited liability partnership is unable to pay its debts;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-64.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>if the limited liability partnership has acted against the interests of the sovereignty and integrity of India , the security of the State or public order;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-64.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>if the limited liability partnership has made a default in filing with the Registrar the Statement of Account and Solvency or annual return for any five consecutive financial years; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-64.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>if the Tribunal is of the opinion that it is just and equitable that the limited liability partnership be wound up.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-65">
        <num>65.</num>
        <heading>Rules for winding up and dissolution.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-65.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may make rules for the provisions in relation to winding up and dissolution of limited liability partnerships.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-66">
        <num>66.</num>
        <heading>Business transactions of partner with limited liability partnership.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-66.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A partner may lend money to and transact other business with the limited liability partnership and has the same rights and obligations with respect to the loan or other transactions as a person who is not a partner.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-67">
        <num>67.</num>
        <heading>Application of the provisions of the Companies Act.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-67.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-67.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that any of the provisions of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) specified in the notification-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-67.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>shall apply to any limited liability partnership; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-67.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>shall apply to any limited liability partnership with such exception, modification and adaptation, as may be specified, in the notification.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-67.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A copy of every notification proposed to be issued under sub-section (1) shall be laid in draft before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in disapproving the issue of the notification or both Houses agree in making any modification in the notification, the notification shall not be issued or, as the case may be, shall be issued only in such modified form as may be agreed upon by both the Houses.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-68">
        <num>68.</num>
        <heading>Electronic filing of documents .-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-68.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any document required to be filed, recorded or registered under this Act may be filed, recorded or registered in such manner and subject to such conditions as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-68.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A copy of or an extract from any document electronically filed with or submitted to the Registrar which is supplied or issued by the Registrar and certified through affixing digital signature as per the Information Technology Act, 2000 (21 of 2000) to be a true copy of or extract from such document shall, in any proceedings, be admissible in evidence as of equal validity with the original document.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-68.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any information supplied by the Registrar that is certified by the Registrar through affixing digital signature to be a true extract from any document filed with or submitted to the Registrar shall, in any proceedings, be admissible in evidence and be presumed, unless evidence to the contrary is adduced, to be a true extract from such document.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-69">
        <num>69.</num>
        <heading>Payment of additional fee.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-69.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any document or return required to be filed or registered under this Act with the Registrar, if, is not filed or registered in time provided therein, may be filed or registered after that time upto a period of three hundred days from the date within which it should have been filed, on payment of additional fee of one hundred rupees for every day of such delay in addition to any fee as is payable for filing of such document or return:</p>
            <p>Provided that such document or return may, without prejudice to any other action or liability under this Act, also be filed after such period of three hundred days on payment of fee and additional fee specified in this section.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-70">
        <num>70.</num>
        <heading>Enhanced punishment.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-70.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In case a limited liability partnership or any partner or designated partner of such limited liability partnership commits any offence, the limited liability partnership or any partner or designated partner shall, for the second or subsequent offence, be punishable with imprisonment as provided, but in case of offences for which fine is prescribed either along with or exclusive of imprisonment, with fine which shall be twice the amount of fine for such offence.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-71">
        <num>71.</num>
        <heading>Application of other laws not barred.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-71.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of this Act shall be in addition to, and not in derogation of, the provisions of any other law for the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-72">
        <num>72.</num>
        <heading>Jurisdiction of Tribunal and Appellate Tribunal.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-72.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Tribunal shall exercise such powers and perform such functions as are, or may be, conferred on it by or under this Act or any other law for the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-72.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person aggrieved by an order or decision of Tribunal may prefer an appeal to the Appellate Tribunal and the provisions of sections 10FQ, 10FZA, 10G 10GD, 10GE and 10GF of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) shall be applicable in respect of such appeal.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-73">
        <num>73.</num>
        <heading>Penalty on non-compliance of any order passed by Tribunal.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-73.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever fails to comply with any order made by the Tribunal under any provision of this Act shall be punishable with imprisonment which may extend to six months and shall also be liable to a fine which shall not be less than fifty thousand rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-74">
        <num>74.</num>
        <heading>General penalties.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-74.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any person guilty of an offence under this Act for which no punishment is expressly provided shall be liable to a fine which may extend to five lakh rupees but which shall not be less than five thousand rupees and with a further fine which may extend to fifty rupees for every day after the first day after which the default continues.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-75">
        <num>75.</num>
        <heading>Power of Registrar to strike defunct limited liability partnership off register.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-75.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where the Registrar has reasonable cause to believe that a limited liability partnership is not carrying on business or its operation, in accordance with the provisions of this Act, the name of limited liability partnership may be struck off the register of limited liability partnerships in such manner as may be prescribed:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Registrar shall, before striking off the name of any limited liability partnership under this section, give such limited liability partnership a reasonable opportunity of being heard.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-76">
        <num>76.</num>
        <heading>Offences by limited liability partnerships.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-76.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-76.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where an offence under this Act committed by a limited liability partnership is proved-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-76.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to have been committed with the consent or connivance of a partner or partners or designated partner or designated partners of the limited liability partnership; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-76.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to be attributable to any neglect on the part of the partner or partners or designated partner or designated partners of that limited liability partnership,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>the partner or partners or designated partner or designated partners of the limited liability partnership, as the case may be, as well as that limited liability partnership shall be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-77">
        <num>77.</num>
        <heading>Jurisdiction of Court.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-77.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding any provision to the contrary in any Act for the time being in force, the Judicial Magistrate of the first class or, as the case may be, the Metropolitan Magistrate shall have jurisdiction to try any offence under this Act and shall have power to impose punishment in respect of said offence.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-78">
        <num>78.</num>
        <heading>Power to alter Schedules.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-78.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, alter any of the provisions contained in any of the Schedules to this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-78.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any alteration notified under sub-section (1) shall have effect as if enacted in the Act and shall come into force on the date of the notification, unless the notification otherwise directs.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-78.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every alteration made by the Central Government under sub-section (1) shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the alteration, or both Houses agree that the alteration should not be made, the alteration shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done in pursuance of that alteration.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-79">
        <num>79.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-79.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-79.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-79.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>form and manner of prior consent to be given by designated partner under sub-section (3) of section 7;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the form and manner of particulars of every individual agreeing to act as designated partner of limited liability partnership under sub-section (4) of section 7;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the conditions and requirements relating to the eligibility of an individual to become a designated partner under sub-section (5) of section 7;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the manner of filing the incorporation document and payment of fees payable thereof under clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 11;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the form of statement to be filed under clause (c) of sub-section (1) of section 11;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the form of incorporation document under clause (a) of sub-section (2) of section 11;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the information to be contained in the incorporation document concerning the proposed limited liability partnership under clause (g) of sub-section (2) of section 11;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the manner of serving the documents on a limited liability partnership or a partner or a designated partner and the form and manner in which any other address may be declared by the limited liability partnership under sub-section (2) of section 13;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the form and manner of notice to the Registrar and the conditions in respect of change of registered office under sub-section (3) of section 13;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>the form and manner of application and amount of fee payable to the Registrar under sub-section (1) of section 16;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>the manner in which names will be reserved by the Registrar under sub-section (2) of section 16;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>the manner in which an application may be made by an entity under sub-section (1) of section 18;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>the form and manner of notice of change of name of limited liability partnership and the amount of fee payable under section 19;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>the form and manner of the limited liability partnership agreement and the changes made therein and the amount of fee payable under sub-section (2) of section 23;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>the form of notice, the amount of fee payable and the manner of authentication of the statement under clauses (a), (b) and (c) of sub-section (3) of section 25;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.p">
                <num>(p)</num>
                <p>the manner of accounting and disclosure of monetary value of contribution of a partner under sub-section (2) of section 32;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.q">
                <num>(q)</num>
                <p>the books of account and the period of their maintenance under sub-section (1) of section 34;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.r">
                <num>(r)</num>
                <p>the form of Statement of Account and Solvency under sub-section (2) of section 34;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.s">
                <num>(s)</num>
                <p>the form, manner, fee and time of filing of Statement of Account and Solvency under sub-section (3) of section 34;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.t">
                <num>(t)</num>
                <p>the audit of accounts of a limited liability partnership under sub-section (4) of section 34;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.u">
                <num>(u)</num>
                <p>the form and manner of annual return and fee payable under sub-section (1) of section 35;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>the manner and amount of fee payable for inspection of incorporation document, names of partners and changes made therein, Statement of Account and Solvency and annual return under section 36;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.w">
                <num>(w)</num>
                <p>the destruction of documents by Registrar in any form under section 40;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.x">
                <num>(x)</num>
                <p>the amount required as security under clause (a) of sub-section (3) of section 43;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.y">
                <num>(y)</num>
                <p>the amount of security to be given under section 44;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.z">
                <num>(z)</num>
                <p>the fee payable for furnishing a copy under clause (b) of sub-section (2) of section 49;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.za">
                <num>(za)</num>
                <p>the manner of authentication of report of inspector under section 54;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.zb">
                <num>(zb)</num>
                <p>the form and manner of particulars about conversion under the proviso to sub-section (1) of section 58;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.zc">
                <num>(zc)</num>
                <p>in relation to establishment of place of business and carrying on business in India by foreign limited liability partnerships and regulatory mechanism and composition under section 59;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.zd">
                <num>(zd)</num>
                <p>the manner of calling, holding and conducting meeting under sub-section (1) of section 60;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.ze">
                <num>(ze)</num>
                <p>in relation to winding up and dissolution of limited liability partnerships under section 65;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.zf">
                <num>(zf)</num>
                <p>the manner and conditions for filing document electronically under sub-section (1) of section 68;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.zg">
                <num>(zg)</num>
                <p>the manner for striking off the names of limited liability partnerships from the register under section 75;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.zh">
                <num>(zh)</num>
                <p>the form and manner of statement containing particulars and amount of fee payable under sub-paragraph (a) of paragraph 4 of the Second Schedule;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.zi">
                <num>(zi)</num>
                <p>he form and manner of particulars about conversion under the proviso to paragraph 5 of the Second Schedule;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.zj">
                <num>(zj)</num>
                <p>the form and manner of the statement and the amount of fee payable under sub-paragraph (a) of paragraph 3 of the Third Schedule;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.zk">
                <num>(zk)</num>
                <p>the form and manner of particulars about conversion under the proviso to paragraph 4 of the Third Schedule;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.zl">
                <num>(zl)</num>
                <p>the form and manner of the statement and amount of fee payable under sub-paragraph (a) of paragraph 4 of the Fourth Schedule; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-79.2.list1.zm">
                <num>(zm)</num>
                <p>the form and manner of particulars about conversion under the proviso to paragraph 5 of the Fourth Schedule.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-79.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this Act by the Central Government shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule, or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-80">
        <num>80.</num>
        <heading>Power to remove difficulties.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-80.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act as may appear to it to be necessary for removing the difficulty:</p>
            <p>Provided that no such order shall be made under this section after the expiry of a period of two years from the commencement of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-80.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every order made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be, after it is made, before each House of Parliament.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-81">
        <num>81.</num>
        <heading>Transitional provisions.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-81.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-81.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Until the Tribunal and the Appellate Tribunal are constituted under the provisions of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), the provisions of this Act shall have effect subject to the following modifications, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-81.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for the word "Tribunal" occurring in clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 41, clause (a) of sub-section (1) of section 43 and section 44, the words "Company Law Board" had been substituted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-81.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>for the word "Tribunal" occurring in section 51 and in sections 60 to 64, the words "High Court" had been substituted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-81.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>for the words "Appellate Tribunal" occurring in sub-section (2) of section 72, the words "High Court" had been substituted.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-thefirstschedule">
      <doc name="thefirstschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2009/6/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2009/6"/>
              <FRBRalias value="THE FIRST SCHEDULE"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2009/6/eng@2009-01-07/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2009/6/eng@2009-01-07"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2009/6/eng@2009-01-07/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2009/6/eng@2009-01-07"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-10-17" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="thefirstschedule">
            <heading>See section 23(4)</heading>
            <paragraph id="thefirstschedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>PROVISIONS REGARDING MATTERS RELATING TO MUTUAL RIGHTS AND DUTIES OF PARTNERS AND LIMITED LIABILITY PARTNERSHIP AND ITS PARTNERS APPLICABLE IN THE ABSENCE OF ANY AGREEMENT ON SUCH MATTERS</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <subsection id="thefirstschedule.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The mutual rights and duties of the partners and the mutual rights and duties of the limited liability partnership and its partners shall be determined, subject to the terms of any limited liability partnership agreement or in the absence of any such agreement on any mat­ter, by the provisions in this Schedule.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thefirstschedule.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All the partners of a limited liability partnership are entitled to share equally in the capital, profits and losses of the limited liability partnership.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thefirstschedule.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <blockList id="thefirstschedule.3.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>The limited liability partnership shall indemnify each partner in respect of pay­ments made and personal liabilities incurred by him-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="thefirstschedule.3.list1.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>in the ordinary and proper conduct of the business of the limited liability partnership; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="thefirstschedule.3.list1.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>in or about anything necessarily done for the preservation of the business or property of the limited liability partnership.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thefirstschedule.4">
              <num>(4)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Every partner shall indemnify the limited liability partnership for any loss caused to it by his fraud in the conduct of the business of the limited liability partnership.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thefirstschedule.5">
              <num>(5)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Every partner may take part in the management of the limited liability partnership.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thefirstschedule.6">
              <num>(6)</num>
              <content>
                <p>No partner shall be entitled to remuneration for acting in the business or management of the limited liability partnership.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thefirstschedule.7">
              <num>(7)</num>
              <content>
                <p>No person may be introduced as a partner without the consent of all the existing partners.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thefirstschedule.8">
              <num>(8)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any matter or issue relating to the limited liability partnership shall be decided by a resolution passed by a majority in number of the partners, and for this purpose, each partner shall have one vote. However, no change may be made in the nature of business of the limited liability partnership without the consent of all the partners.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thefirstschedule.9">
              <num>(9)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Every limited liability partnership shall ensure that decisions taken by it are recorded in the minutes within thirty days of taking such decisions and are kept and maintained at the registered office of the limited liability partnership.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thefirstschedule.10">
              <num>(10)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Each partner shall render true accounts and full information of all things affecting the limited liability partnership to any partner or his legal representatives.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thefirstschedule.11">
              <num>(11)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If a partner, without the consent of the limited liability partnership, carries on any business of the same nature as and competing with the limited liability partnership, he must account for and pay over to the limited liability partnership all profits made by him in that business.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thefirstschedule.12">
              <num>(12)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Every partner shall account to the limited liability partnership for any benefit derived by him without the consent of the limited liability partnership from any transaction concerning the limited liability partnership, or from any use by him of the property, name or any business connection of the limited liability partnership.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thefirstschedule.13">
              <num>(13)</num>
              <content>
                <p>No majority of the partners can expel any partner unless a power to do so has been conferred by express agreement between the partners.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thefirstschedule.14">
              <num>(14)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All disputes between the partners arising out of the limited liability partnership agreement which cannot be resolved in terms of such agreement shall be referred for arbitra­ tion as per the provisions of the Arbitration and Conciliation Act, 1996 (26 of 1996).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-thesecondschedule">
      <doc name="thesecondschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2009/6/thesecondschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2009/6"/>
              <FRBRalias value="THE SECOND SCHEDULE"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2009/6/eng@2009-01-07/thesecondschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2009/6/eng@2009-01-07"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2009/6/eng@2009-01-07/thesecondschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2009/6/eng@2009-01-07"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-10-23" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="thesecondschedule">
            <heading>(See section 55)</heading>
            <paragraph id="thesecondschedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>CONVERSION FROM FIRM INTO LIMITED LIABILITY PARTNERSHIP</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <blockList id="thesecondschedule.1.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>Interpretation.- In this Schedule, unless the context otherwise requires,-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="thesecondschedule.1.list1.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>"firm" means a firm as defined in section 4 of the Indian Partnership Act, 1932 (9 of 1932);</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="thesecondschedule.1.list1.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>"convert", in relation to a firm converting into a limited liability partnership, means a transfer of the property, assets, interests, rights, privileges, liabilities, obligations and the undertaking of the firm to the limited liability partnership in accordance with this Schedule.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Conversion from firm into limited liability partnership.- (1) A firm may convert into a limited liability partnership by complying with the requirements as to the conversion set out in this Schedule.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon such conversion, the partners of the firm shall be bound by the provisions of this Schedule that are applicable to them.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Eligibility for conversion.- A firm may apply to convert into a limited liability partnership in accordance with this Schedule if and only if the partners of the limited liability partnership into which the firm is to be converted, comprise, all the partners of the firm and no one else.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.4">
              <num>(4)</num>
              <content>
                <blockList id="thesecondschedule.4.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>Statements to be filed.- A firm may apply to convert into a limited liability partnership by filing with the Registrar-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="thesecondschedule.4.list1.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <blockList id="thesecondschedule.4.list1.a.list0">
                      <listIntroduction>a statement by all of its partners in such form and manner and accompanied by such fee as the Central Government may prescribe, containing the following particulars, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="thesecondschedule.4.list1.a.list0.i">
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <p>the name and registration number, if applicable, of the firm; and</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="thesecondschedule.4.list1.a.list0.ii">
                        <num>(ii)</num>
                        <p>the date on which the firm was registered under the Indian Partnership Act, 1932 (9 of 1932) or under any other law, if applicable, and</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </item>
                  <item id="thesecondschedule.4.list1.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>incorporation document and statement referred to in section 11.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.5">
              <num>(5)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Registration of conversion.- On receiving the documents referred to in paragraph 4, the Registrar shall subject to the provisions of this Act, register the documents and issue a certificate of registration in such form as the Registrar may determine stating that the limited liability partnership is, on and from the date specified in the certificate, registered under this Act:</p>
                <p>Provided that the limited liability partnership shall, within fifteen days of the date of registration, inform, the concerned Registrar of Firms with which it was registered under the provisions of the Indian Partnership Act, 1932 (9 of 1932) about the conversion and of the particulars of the limited liability partnership in such form and manner as the Central Government may prescribe.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.6">
              <num>(6)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Registrar may refuse to register.- (1) Nothing in this Schedule shall be construed as to require the Registrar to register any limited liability partnership if he is not satisfied with the particulars or other information furnished under the provisions of this Act:</p>
                <p>Provided that an appeal may be made before the Tribunal in case of refusal of registration by the Registrar:</p>
                <p>Provided further that until the Tribunal is constituted under the Companies Act, 1956, the appeal under this sub-paragraph may be made before the Company Law Board.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Registrar may, in any particular case, require the documents referred to in paragraph 4 to be verified in such manner, as he considers fit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.7">
              <num>(7)</num>
              <content>
                <blockList id="thesecondschedule.7.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>Effect of registration.- On and from the date of registration specified in the certificate of registration issued under paragraph 5,-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="thesecondschedule.7.list1.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>there shall be a limited liability partnership by the name specified in the certificate of registration registered under this Act;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="thesecondschedule.7.list1.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>all tangible (movable and immovable) property as well as intangible property vested in the firm, all assets, interests, rights, privileges, liabilities, obligations relating to the firm and the whole of the undertaking of the firm shall be transferred to and shall vest in the limited liability partnership without further assurance, act or deed; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="thesecondschedule.7.list1.c">
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <p>the firm shall be deemed to be dissolved and if earlier registered under the Indian Partnership Act, 1932 (9 of 1932) removed from the records maintained under that Act.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.8">
              <num>(8)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Registration in relation to property.- If any property to which sub-paragraph (b) of paragraph 7 applies is registered with any authority, the limited liability partnership shall, as soon as practicable after the date of registration, take all necessary steps as required by the relevant authority to notify the authority of the conversion and of the particulars of the limited liability partnership in such medium and form as the authority may specify.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.9">
              <num>(9)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Pending proceedings.- All proceedings by or against the firm which are pending in any Court or Tribunal or before any authority on the date of registration may be continued, completed and enforced by or against the limited liability partnership.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.10">
              <num>(10)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Continuance of conviction, ruling, order or judgment. -Any conviction, ruling, order or judgment of any Court, Tribunal or other authority in favour of or against the firm may be enforced by or against the limited liability partnership.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.11">
              <num>(11)</num>
              <content>
                <blockList id="thesecondschedule.11.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>Existing agreements.- Every agreement to which the firm was a party immediately before the date of registration, whether or not of such nature that the rights and liabilities thereunder could be assigned, shall have effect as from that date as if-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="thesecondschedule.11.list1.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>the limited liability partnership were a party to such an agreement instead of the firm; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="thesecondschedule.11.list1.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>for any reference to the firm, there were substituted in respect of anything to be done on or after the date of registration a reference to the limited liability partnership.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.12">
              <num>(12)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Existing contracts, etc.- All deeds, contracts, schemes, bonds, agreements, applications, instruments and arrangements subsisting immediately before the date of registration relating to the firm or to which the firm is a party, shall continue in force on and after that date as if they relate to the limited liability partnership and shall be enforceable by or against the limited liability partnership as if the limited liability partnership were named therein or were a party thereto instead of the firm.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.13">
              <num>(13)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Continuance of employment.- Every contract of employment to which paragraph 11 or paragraph 12 applies shall continue to be in force on or after the date of registration as if the limited liability partnership were the employer thereunder instead of the firm.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.14">
              <num>(14)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Existing appointment, authority or power.- (1) Every appointment of the firm in any role or capacity which is in force immediately before the date of registration shall take effect and operate from that date as if the limited liability partnership were appointed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any authority or power conferred on the firm which is in force immediately before the date of registration shall take effect and operate from that date as if it were conferred on the limited liability partnership.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.15">
              <num>(15)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Application of paragraphs 7 to 14.- The provisions of paragraphs 7 to 14 (both inclusive) shall apply to any approval, permit or licence issued to the firm under any other Act which is in force immediately before the date of registration of the limited liability partnership, subject to the provisions of such other Act under which such approval, permit or licence has been issued.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.16">
              <num>(16)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Partner liable for liabilities and obligations of firm before conversion.-</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Notwithstanding anything in paragraphs 7 to 14 (both inclusive), every partner of a firm that has converted into a limited liability partnership shall continue to be personally liable (jointly and severally with the limited liability partnership) for the liabilities and obligations of the firm which were incurred prior to the conversion or which arose from any contract entered into prior to the conversion.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If any such partner discharges any liability or obligation referred to in sub-paragraph (7), he shall be entitled (subject to any agreement with the limited liability partnership to the contrary) to be fully indemnified by the limited liability partnership in respect of such liability or obligation.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.17">
              <num>(17)</num>
              <content>
                <blockList id="thesecondschedule.17.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>Notice of conversion in correspondence.- (1) The limited liability partnership shall ensure that for a period of twelve months commencing not later than fourteen days after the date of registration, every official correspondence of the limited liability partnership bears the following:</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="thesecondschedule.17.list1.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>a statement that it was, as from the date of registration, converted from a firm into a limited liability partnership; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="thesecondschedule.17.list1.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>the name and registration number, if applicable, of the firm from which it was converted.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any limited liability partnership which contravenes the provisions of sub-paragraph (7) shall be punishable with fine which shall not be less than ten thousand rupees but which may extend to one lakh rupees and with a further fine which shall not be less than fifty rupees but which may extend to five hundred rupees for every day after the first day after which the default continues.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-thethirdschedule">
      <doc name="thethirdschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2009/6/thethirdschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2009/6"/>
              <FRBRalias value="THE THIRD SCHEDULE"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2009/6/eng@2009-01-07/thethirdschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2009/6/eng@2009-01-07"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2009/6/eng@2009-01-07/thethirdschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2009/6/eng@2009-01-07"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-10-17" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="thethirdschedule">
            <heading>(See section 56)</heading>
            <paragraph id="thethirdschedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>CONVERSION FROM PRIVATE COMPANY INTO LIMITED LIABILITY PARTNERSHIP</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <subsection id="thethirdschedule.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <blockList id="thethirdschedule.1.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>Interpretation.- In this Schedule, unless the context otherwise requires,-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="thethirdschedule.1.list1.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>"company" means a private company as defined in clause (iii) of sub-section (1) of section 3 of the Companies Act, 1956;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="thethirdschedule.1.list1.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>"convert", in relation to a private company converting into a limited liability partnership, means a transfer of the property, assets, interests, rights, privileges, liabilities, obligations and the undertaking of the private company to the limited liability partnership in accordance with this Schedule.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thethirdschedule.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Eligibility for conversion of private companies into limited liability partnership.- (1) A company may convert into a limited liability partnership by complying with the requirements as to the conversion set out in this Schedule.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thethirdschedule.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <blockList id="thethirdschedule.2.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>A company may apply to convert into a limited liability partnership in accordance with this Schedule if and only if-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="thethirdschedule.2.list1.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>there is no security interest in its assets subsisting or in force at the time of application; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="thethirdschedule.2.list1.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>the partners of the limited liability partnership to which it converts comprise all the shareholders of the company and no one else.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thethirdschedule.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon such conversion, the company, its shareholders, the limited liability partnership into which the company has converted and the partners of that limited liability partnership shall be bound by the provisions of this Schedule that are applicable to them.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thethirdschedule.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <blockList id="thethirdschedule.3.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>Statements to be filed.- A company may apply to convert into a limited liability partnership by filing with the Registrar-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="thethirdschedule.3.list1.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <blockList id="thethirdschedule.3.list1.a.list0">
                      <listIntroduction>a statement by all its shareholders in such form and manner to be accompanied by such fees as the Central Government may prescribe, containing the following particulars, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="thethirdschedule.3.list1.a.list0.i">
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <p>the name and registration number of the company;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="thethirdschedule.3.list1.a.list0.ii">
                        <num>(ii)</num>
                        <p>the date on which the company was incorporated; and</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </item>
                  <item id="thethirdschedule.3.list1.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>incorporation document and statement referred to in section 11.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thethirdschedule.4">
              <num>(4)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Registration of conversion.- On receiving the documents referred to in paragraph 3, the Registrar shall, subject to the provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder, register the documents and issue a certificate of registration in such form as the Registrar may determine stating that the limited liability partnership is, on and from the date specified in the certificate, registered under this Act:</p>
                <p>Provided that the limited liability partnership shall, within fifteen days of the date of registration, inform the concerned Registrar of Companies with which it was registered under the provisions of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) about the conversion and of the particulars of the limited liability partnership in such form and manner as the Central Government may prescribe.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thethirdschedule.5">
              <num>(5)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Registrar may refuse to register.- (1) Nothing in this Schedule shall be construed as to require the Registrar to register any limited liability partnership if he is not satisfied with the particulars or other information furnished under the provisions of this Act:</p>
                <p>Provided that an appeal may be made before the Tribunal in case of refusal of registration by the Registrar:</p>
                <p>Provided further that until the Tribunal is constituted under the Companies Act, 1956, the appeal under this sub-paragraph may be made before the Company Law Board.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thethirdschedule.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Registrar may, in any particular case, require the documents referred to in paragraph 3 to be verified in such manner, as he considers fit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thethirdschedule.6">
              <num>(6)</num>
              <content>
                <blockList id="thethirdschedule.6.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>Effect of registration.- On and from the date of registration specified in the certificate of registration issued under paragraph 4-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="thethirdschedule.6.list1.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>there shall be a limited liability partnership by the name specified in the certificate of registration registered under this Act;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="thethirdschedule.6.list1.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>all tangible (movable or immovable) and intangible property vested in the company, all assets, interests, rights, privileges, liabilities, obligations relating to the company and the whole of the undertaking of the company shall be transferred to and shall vest in the limited liability partnership without further assurance, act or deed; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="thethirdschedule.6.list1.c">
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <p>the company shall be deemed to be dissolved and removed from the records of the Registrar of Companies.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thethirdschedule.7">
              <num>(7)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Registration in relation to property.- If any property to which clause (b) of paragraph 6 applies is registered with any authority, the limited liability partnership shall, as soon as practicable, after the date of registration, take all necessary steps as required by the relevant authority to notify the authority of the conversion and of the particulars of the limited liability partnership in such form and manner as the authority may determine.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thethirdschedule.8">
              <num>(8)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Pending proceedings.- All proceedings by or against the company which are pending before any Court, Tribunal or other authority on the date of registration may be continued, completed and enforced by or against the limited liability partnership.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thethirdschedule.9">
              <num>(9)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Continuance of conviction, ruling, order or judgment.- Any conviction, ruling, order or judgment of any Court, Tribunal or other authority in favour of or against the company may be enforced by or against the limited liability partnership.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thethirdschedule.10">
              <num>(10)</num>
              <content>
                <blockList id="thethirdschedule.10.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>Existing agreements.- Every agreement to which the company was a party immediately before the date of registration, whether or not of such nature that the rights and liabilities thereunder could be assigned, shall have effect as from that date as if-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="thethirdschedule.10.list1.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>the limited liability partnership were a party to such an agreement instead of the company; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="thethirdschedule.10.list1.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>for any reference to the company, there were substituted in respect of anything to be done on or after the date of registration a reference to the limited liability partnership.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thethirdschedule.11">
              <num>(11)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Existing contracts, etc.- All deeds, contracts, schemes, bonds, agreements, applications, instruments and arrangements subsisting immediately before the date of registration relating to the company or to which the company is a party shall continue in force on and after that date as if they relate to the limited liability partnership and shall be enforceable by or against the limited liability partnership as if the limited liability partnership were named therein or were a party thereto instead of the company.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thethirdschedule.12">
              <num>(12)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Continuance of employment.- Every contract of employment to which paragraph 10 or paragraph 11 applies shall continue in force on or after the date of registration as if the limited liability partnership were the employer thereunder instead of the company.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thethirdschedule.13">
              <num>(13)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Existing appointment, authority or power.- (1) Every appointment of the company in any role or capacity which is in force immediately before the date of registration shall take effect and operate from that date as if the limited liability partnership were appointed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thethirdschedule.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any authority or power conferred on the company which is in force immediately before the date of registration shall take effect and operate from that date as if it were conferred on the limited liability partnership.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thethirdschedule.14">
              <num>(14)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Application of paragraphs 6 to 13.- The provisions of paragraphs 6 to 13 (both inclusive) shall apply to any approval, permit or licence issued to the company under any other Act which is in force immediately before the date of registration of the limited liability partnership, subject to the provisions of such other Act under which such approval, permit or licence has been issued.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thethirdschedule.15">
              <num>(15)</num>
              <content>
                <blockList id="thethirdschedule.15.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>Notice of conversion in correspondence.- (1) The limited liability partnership shall ensure that for a period of twelve months commencing not later than fourteen days after the date of registration, every official correspondence of the limited liability partnership bears the following, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="thethirdschedule.15.list1.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>a statement that it was, as from the date of registration, converted from a company into a limited liability partnership; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="thethirdschedule.15.list1.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>the name and registration number of the company from which it was converted.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thethirdschedule.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any limited liability partnership which contravenes the provisions of sub-paragraph (1) shall be punishable with fine which shall not be less than ten thousand rupees but which may extend to one lakh rupees and with a further fine which shall not be less than fifty rupees but which may extend to five hundred rupees for every day after the first day after which the default continues.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-thefourthschedule">
      <doc name="thefourthschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2009/6/thefourthschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2009/6"/>
              <FRBRalias value="THE FOURTH SCHEDULE"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2009/6/eng@2009-01-07/thefourthschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2009/6/eng@2009-01-07"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2009/6/eng@2009-01-07/thefourthschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2009/6/eng@2009-01-07"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-10-17" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="thefourthschedule">
            <heading>(See section 57)</heading>
            <paragraph id="thefourthschedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>CONVERSION FROM UNLISTED PUBLIC COMPANY INTO LIMITED LIABILITY PARTNERSHIP</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <subsection id="thefourthschedule.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <blockList id="thefourthschedule.1.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>Interpretation.- (1) In this Schedule, unless the context otherwise requires,-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="thefourthschedule.1.list1.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>"company" means an unlisted public company;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="thefourthschedule.1.list1.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>"convert", in relation to a company converting into a limited liability partnership, means a transfer of the property, assets, interests, rights, privileges, liabilities, obligations and the undertaking of the company to the limited liability partnership in accordance with the provisions of this Schedule;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="thefourthschedule.1.list1.c">
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <p>"listed company" means a listed company as defined in the Securities Exchange Board of India (Disclosure and Investor Protection) Guidelines, 2000 issued by the Securities and Exchange Board of India under section 11 of the Securities and Exchange Board of India Act, 1992 (15 of 1992);</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="thefourthschedule.1.list1.d">
                    <num>(d)</num>
                    <p>"unlisted public company" means a company which is not a listed company.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thefourthschedule.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Conversion of company into a limited liability partnership.- (1) A company may convert into a limited liability partnership by complying with the requirements as to the conversion set out in this Schedule.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thefourthschedule.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Upon such conversion, the company, its shareholders, the limited liability partnership into which the company has converted and the partners of that limited liability partnership shall be bound by the provisions of this Schedule that are applicable to them.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thefourthschedule.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <blockList id="thefourthschedule.3.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>Eligibility for conversion.- A company may apply to convert into a limited liability partnership in accordance with the provisions of this Schedule if and only if-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="thefourthschedule.3.list1.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>there is no security interest in its assets subsisting or in force at the time of application; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="thefourthschedule.3.list1.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>the partners of the limited liability partnership to which it converts comprise all the shareholders of the company and no one else.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thefourthschedule.4">
              <num>(4)</num>
              <content>
                <blockList id="thefourthschedule.4.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>Statements to be filed.- A company may apply to convert into a limited liability partnership by filing with the Registrar-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="thefourthschedule.4.list1.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <blockList id="thefourthschedule.4.list1.a.list0">
                      <listIntroduction>a statement by all its shareholders in such form and manner to be accompanied by such fee as the Central Government may prescribe containing the following particulars, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="thefourthschedule.4.list1.a.list0.i">
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <p>the name and registration number of the company;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="thefourthschedule.4.list1.a.list0.ii">
                        <num>(ii)</num>
                        <p>the date on which the company was incorporated; and</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </item>
                  <item id="thefourthschedule.4.list1.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>incorporation document and statement referred to in section 11.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thefourthschedule.5">
              <num>(5)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Registration of conversion.- On receiving the documents referred to in paragraph 4, the Registrar shall, subject to the provisions of this Act, and the rules made thereunder, register the documents and issue a certificate of registration in such form as the Registrar may determine stating that the limited liability partnership is, on and from the date specified in the certificate, registered under this Act:</p>
                <p>Provided that the limited liability partnership shall, within fifteen days of the date of registration, inform the concerned Registrar of Companies with which it was registered under the provisions of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) about the conversion and of the particulars of the limited liability partnership in such form and manner as the Central Government may prescribe.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thefourthschedule.6">
              <num>(6)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Registrar may refuse to register.- (1) Nothing in this Schedule shall be construed as to require the Registrar to register any limited liability partnership if he is not satisfied with the particulars or other information furnished under the provisions of this Act:</p>
                <p>Provided that an appeal may be made before the Tribunal in case of refusal of registration by the Registrar:</p>
                <p>Provided further that until the Tribunal is constituted under the Companies Act, 1956, the appeal under this sub-paragraph may be made before the Company Law Board.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thefourthschedule.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Registrar may, in any particular case, require the documents referred to in paragraph 4 to be verified in such manner, as he considers fit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thefourthschedule.7">
              <num>(7)</num>
              <content>
                <blockList id="thefourthschedule.7.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>Effect of registration.- On and from the date of registration specified in the certificate of registration issued under paragraph 5-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="thefourthschedule.7.list1.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>there shall be a limited liability partnership by the name specified in the certificate of registration registered under this Act;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="thefourthschedule.7.list1.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>all tangible (movable or immovable) and intangible property vested in the company, all assets, interests, rights, privileges, liabilities, obligations relating to the company and the whole of the undertaking of the company shall be transferred to and shall vest in the limited liability partnership without further assurance, act or deed; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="thefourthschedule.7.list1.c">
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <p>the company shall be deemed to be dissolved and removed from the records of the Registrar of Companies.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thefourthschedule.8">
              <num>(8)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Registration in relation to property.- If any property to which clause (b) of paragraph 7 applies is registered with any authority, the limited liability partnership shall, as soon as practicable, after the date of registration, take all necessary steps as required by the relevant authority to notify the authority of the conversion and of the particulars of the limited liability partnership in such form and manner as the authority may determine.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thefourthschedule.9">
              <num>(9)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Pending proceedings.- All proceedings by or against the company which are pending in any Court or Tribunal or before an authority on the date of registration may be continued, completed and enforced by or against the limited liability partnership.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thefourthschedule.10">
              <num>(10)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Continuance of conviction, ruling, order or judgment.- Any conviction, ruling, order or judgment of any Court, Tribunal or other authority in favour of or against the company may be enforced by or against the limited liability partnership.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thefourthschedule.11">
              <num>(11)</num>
              <content>
                <blockList id="thefourthschedule.11.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>Existing agreements.- Every agreement to which the company was a party immediately before the date of registration, whether or not of such nature that the rights and liabilities thereunder could be assigned, shall have effect as from that date as if-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="thefourthschedule.11.list1.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>the limited liability partnership were a party to such an agreement instead of the company; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="thefourthschedule.11.list1.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>for any reference to the company, there were substituted in respect of anything to be done on or after the date of registration a reference to the limited liability partnership.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thefourthschedule.12">
              <num>(12)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Existing contracts, etc.- All deeds, contracts, schemes, bonds, agreements, applications, instruments and arrangements subsisting immediately before the date of registration relating to the company or to which the company is a party shall continue in force on and after that date as if they relate to the limited liability partnership and shall be enforceable by or against the limited liability partnership as if the limited liability partnership were named therein or were a party thereto instead of the company.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thefourthschedule.13">
              <num>(13)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Continuance of employment. -Every contract of employment to which paragraph 11 or paragraph 12 applies shall continue in force on or after the date of registration as if the limited liability partnership were the employer thereunder instead of the company.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thefourthschedule.14">
              <num>(14)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Existing appointment, authority or power.- (1) Every appointment of the company in any role or capacity which is in force immediately before the date of registration shall take effect and operate from that date as if the limited liability partnership were appointed.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thefourthschedule.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any authority or power conferred on the company which is in force immediately before the date of registration shall take effect and operate from that date as if it were conferred on the limited liability partnership.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thefourthschedule.15">
              <num>(15)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Application of paragraphs 7 to 14.- The provisions of paragraphs 7 to 14 (both inclusive) shall apply to any approval, permit or licence issued to the company under any other Act which is in force immediately before the date of registration of the limited liability partnership, subject to the provisions of such other Act under which such approval, permit or licence has been issued.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thefourthschedule.16">
              <num>(16)</num>
              <content>
                <blockList id="thefourthschedule.16.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>Notice of conversion in correspondence.- (1) The limited liability partnership shall ensure that for a period of twelve months commencing not later than fourteen days after the date of registration, every official correspondence of the limited liability partnership bears the following, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="thefourthschedule.16.list1.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>a statement that it was, as from the date of registration, converted from a company into a limited liability partnership; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="thefourthschedule.16.list1.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>the name and registration number of the company from which it was converted.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thefourthschedule.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any limited liability partnership which contravenes the provisions of sub-paragraph (7) shall be punishable with fine which shall not be less than ten thousand rupees but which may extend to one lakh rupees and with a further fine which shall not be less than fifty rupees but which may extend to five hundred rupees for every day after the first day after which the default continues.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
