<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-odi/act/2014/03/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-odi/act/2014/03"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Odisha Prevention Of Witch-Hunting Act, 2013"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-odi/act/2014/03/eng@2016-12-23/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-odi/act/2014/03/eng@2016-12-23"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-12-23" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-odi/act/2014/03/eng@2016-12-23/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-odi/act/2014/03/eng@2016-12-23"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-12-23" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Odisha Prevention Of Witch-Hunting Act, 2013</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[25th February, 2014]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No. 3 of 2014</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for effective measures to tackle the menace of witch-hunting and to prevent the practices of witch craft in the state of Odisha and for matters connected therewith and incidental thereto.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>BE it enacted by the Legislature of the State of Odisha in the Sixty-fourth Year of the Republic of India as follows: —</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-1.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list0.I">
                <num>(I)</num>
                <p>This Act may be called the Odisha Prevention of Witch-hunting Act, 2013.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Odisha.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the State Government may, by notification, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires, --</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"Witch" means a woman, locally known as "Dahani", "Doyen" or otherwise, who has been identified by any person or persons believing her to be in possession of, or is having, any evil power for causing any harm to any person or his property;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"Witch craft" means use of supposed supernatural or magical power with evil intention to call up spirit or cast spell or discover the whereabouts of stolen goods and includes such other similar practices which are locally known as "Guni", "Jhada phunka", "Cot Bidya", 'Bata Bidya", "Kula Bidya", "Nakha Darpana" or by any other name;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>"Witch-doctor" means a person who claims to be a Gunia, Tantrik, Kalisi or by any other name called and, claims or is believed to be having supernatural or magical power to control or to cure a witch or by performing rituals to free a woman from evil spirit or bless a woman with a child or performs any ritual on behalf of any person with an intention to harm a person;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>"Witch- hunting" means any act of omission, commission or conduct on the part of any person,—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>identifying, accusing or defaming a woman as a witch, or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>harassing, harming or injuring such-woman whether mentally or physically or damaging her property.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition of witch-hunting and practising witch craft.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No person shall commit witch-hunting or exercise or practise witch craft with intent to cause harm or injury to another person.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for witch-hunting</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever, except in the cases provided for in sub-section (2), commits witch-hunting, or abets, or provokes for witch-hunting, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years and with fine but which shall not be less than one thousand rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever forces any woman, branding her as witch, to drink or eat any inedible substance or any other obnoxious substance or parade her with painted face or body or commits any similar acts which is derogatory to human dignity or displaced from her house, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than one year but may extend to five years and with fine.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for witch craft</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever practises witch craft or ogler similar practices with intent to cause harm or injury to any woman shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than one year but which may extend to three years or with fine which shall not be less than five thousand rupees or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for witch-doctor.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever performs any practice as witch doctor knowingly that such practices shall cause harm or injury to any woman upon whom such practices is being performed, shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than one year but may extend to three years or with fine which shall not be less than five thousand rupees or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Enhancement of the punishment.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever, having already been convicted of an offence punishable under this Act, is convicted for the second offence or any offence subsequent to second offence, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a tun) which shall not be less than three years but may extend to seven years and with fine which shall not be less than ten thousand rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Act not in derogation of any other law.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of this Act shall be in addition to, and not in derogation of, the provisions of any other kw for the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Order for compensation.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a sentence of fine is imposed under sections 4,5,6 and 7 the Court shall, in king the amount of fine, take into considaution the physical and mental damage caused to the victim including any cost of thunnent and also damage, if any, caused to the property.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When a Court imposes sentence of fine, the Court shall while passing judgment, order the whole or part efthe fine recovered to be awarded as compensation to the victim.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Offence to be cognizable and non-bailable.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every offence under this Act shall be cognizable and non-bailable.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Preventive action to be taken by the State Government.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may make one or more schemes to conduct awareness programs on blind belief and educate people about the absurd concept of evil spirit, witch craft and for such other matters as the State Government may deem proper.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
