<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1939/8/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1939/8"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Dissolution Of Muslim Marriages Act, 1939"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1939/8/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1939/8/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1939/8/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1939/8/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-10" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Dissolution Of Muslim Marriages Act, 1939</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>(ACT NO. VIII OF 1939).</p>
      </longTitle>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[17th March 1939]</docDate>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>An Act to consolidate and clarify the provisions of Muslim law relating to suits for dissolution of marriage by women married under Muslim law and to remove doubts as to the effect of the renunciation of Islam by a married Muslim woman on her marriage tie.</p>
      <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to consolidate and clarify the provisions of Muslim law relating to suits for dissolution of marriage by women married under Muslim law and to remove doubts as to the effect of the renunciation of Islam by a married Muslim woman on her marriage tie;</p>
      <p>It is hereby enacted as follows:-</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and extent.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Dissolution of Muslim Marriages Act, 1939.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Grounds for decree for dissolution of marriage.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A woman married under Muslim law shall be entitled to obtain a decree for the dissolution of her marriage on any one or more of the following grounds, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>that the whereabouts of the husband have not been known for a period of four years;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>that the husband has neglected or has failed to provide for her maintenance for a period of two years;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>that the husband has been sentenced to imprisonment for a period of seven years or upwards;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>that the husband has failed to perform, without reasonable cause, his marital obligations for a period of three years;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>that the husband was impotent at the time of the marriage and continues to be so;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.vi">
                <num>(vi)</num>
                <p>that the husband has been insane for a period of two years or is suffering from leprosy or virulent venereal disease;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.vii">
                <num>(vii)</num>
                <p>that she, having been given in marriage by her father or other guardian before she attained the age of fifteen years, repudiated the marriage before attaining the age of eighteen years:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that the marriage has not been consummated;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.viii">
                <num>(viii)</num>
                <p>that the husband treats her with cruelty, that is to say,—</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>habitually assaults her or makes her life miserable by cruelty of conduct even if such conduct does not amount to physical ill-treatment, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>associates with women of evil repute or leads an infamous life, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>attempts to force her to lead an immoral life, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>disposes of her property or prevents her exercising her legal rights over it, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>obstructs her in the observance of her religious profession or practice, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>if he has more wives than one, does not treat her equitably in accordance with the injunctions of the Quran;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.ix">
                <num>(ix)</num>
                <p>on any other ground which is recognised as valid for the dissolution of marriages under Muslim law:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>no decree shall be passed on ground (iii) until the sentence has become final;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>a decree passed on ground (i) shall not take effect for a period of six months from the date of such decree, and if the husband appears either in person or through an authorised agent within that period and satisfies the Court that he is prepared to perform his conjugal duties, the Court shall set aside the said decree; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>before passing a decree on ground (v) the Court shall, on application by the husband, make an order requiring the husband to satisfy the Court within a period of one year from the date of such order that he has ceased to be impotent, and if the husband so satisfies the Court within such period, no decree shall be passed on the said ground.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Notice to be served on heirs of the husband, when the husband’s whereabouts are not known.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In a suit to which clause (i) of section 2 applies —</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the names and addresses of the persons who would have been the heirs of the husband under Muslim law if he had died on the date of the filing of the plaint shall be stated in the plaint,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>notice of the suit shall be served on such persons, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>such persons shall have the right to be heard in the suit:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that paternal uncle and brother of the husband, if any, shall be cited as party even if he or they are not heirs.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Effect of conversion to another faith.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The renunciation of Islam by a married Muslim woman or her conversion to faith other than Islam shall not by itself operate to dissolve her marriage:</p>
            <p>Provided that after such renunciation, or conversion, the woman shall be entitled to obtain a decree for the dissolution of her marriage on any of the grounds mentioned in section 2:</p>
            <p>Provided further that the provisions of this section shall not apply to a woman converted to Islam from some other faith who re-embraces her former faith.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Rights to dower not to be affected.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Nothing contained in this Act shall affect any right which a married woman may have under Muslim law to her dower or any part thereof on the dissolution of her marriage.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
