<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1960/10/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1960/10"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Orphanages And Other Charitable Homes (Supervision And Control) Act, 1960"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1960/10/eng@1960-04-09/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1960/10/eng@1960-04-09"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1960-04-09" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1960/10/eng@1960-04-09/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1960/10/eng@1960-04-09"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-10-23" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Orphanages And Other Charitable Homes (Supervision And Control) Act, 1960</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the Orphanages and other Charitable Homes (Supervision and Control) Act, 1960.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force in a State on such date as the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>"Board" means the Board of Control established under section 5;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>"certificate" means the certificate of recognition granted under section 15;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>"child" means a boy or girl who has not completed the age of eighteen years;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>"home" means an institution, whether called an orphanage, a home for neglected women or children, a widows' home, or by any other name, maintained or intended to be maintained for the reception, care, protection and welfare of women or children;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>"manager" means a member of the managing committee appointed as such by the committee under section 20;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>"managing committee" means the committee of management referred to in section 20;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>"recognised home" means a home in respect of which a certificate has been granted;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>"prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>"woman" means a female who has completed the age of eighteen years.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Act not to apply to certain institutions.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Nothing in this Act shall apply to-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>any hostel or boarding house attached to, or controlled or recognised by, an educational institution; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>any protective home established under the Suppression of Immoral Traffic in Women and Girls Act, 1956 (104 of 1956); or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>any reformatory, certified or other school, or any home or workhouse, governed by any enactment for the time being in force.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Effect of Act on instruments governing recognised homes.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained in any instrument governing a recognised home.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>THE BOARD OF CONTROL AND ITS POWERS AND FUNCTIONS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Board of Control, its constitution, etc.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, establish a Board of Control for the supervision and control of homes in the State.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-5.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Board shall consist of the following members, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>three members of the State Legislature to be elected by the members thereof; provided that where the State Legislature consist of two Houses, two members shall be elected by the members of the Legislative Assembly from among themselves and one member shall be elected by the members of the Legislative Council from among themselves;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-5.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>five members of the managing committees in the State, to be elected by such committees from among themselves, each such committee having one vote only for this purpose;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-5.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the officer in charge of social welfare work in the State, to be nominated by the State Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-5.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>six members to be nominated by the State Government, of whom not more than one shall be a member of Parliament from the State and not less than three shall be women.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If for any reason the officer referred to in clause (c) of subsection (2) is unable to attend any meeting of the Board, he may depute any officer subordinate to him to attend such meeting.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chairman of the Board shall be elected by the members of the Board from among themselves:</p>
              <p>Provided that at the time of the first constitution of the Board, one of the members of the Board shall be nominated by the State Government to be its Chairman.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Term of office and casual vacancies.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Save as otherwise provided in this section, the term of office of a member of the Board shall be five years from the date of his election or nomination or until his successor has been duly elected or nominated, whichever is longer:</p>
              <p>Provided that the term of office of a member elected under clause (a) or clause (b) of sub- section (2) of section 5, or of a member of Parliament nominated under clause (d) of sub- section (2) of section 5, shall come to an end as soon as he ceases to be a member of the House of the State Legislature which elected him, the managing committee or Parliament, as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A member may at any time resign his office by giving notice in writing to the State Government and on such resignation being notified in the Official Gazette by that Government, the seat of such member shall become vacant.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A casual vacancy in the Board shall be filled by fresh election or nomination, as the case may be; and the term of office of a member elected or nominated to fill such vacancy shall be the remainder of the term of the member in whose place he is elected or nominated.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Members of the Board shall be eligible for re- election or re- nomination.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No act done or proceeding taken by the Board shall be questioned on the ground merely of the existence of any vacancy in, or defect in the constitution of, the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Functions of the Board.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall be the duty of the Board to supervise and control generally all matters relating to the management of homes in accordance with the provisions of this Act; and exercise such other powers and perform such other functions as may be prescribed by or under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the performance of its functions under this Act, the Board shall be bound by such directions as the State Government may give to it.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Power of the Board to give directions to manager of a recognised home.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the directions, if any given under sub-section (2) of section 7, the Board may, from time to time, give such general or special directions to the manager of a recognised home as it thinks fit for the efficient management of the home and the manager shall comply with such directions.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Power of inspection.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Any member of the Board, or any officer of the Board authorised in writing by it in this behalf, by general or special order, may enter at all reasonable times any home for the purpose of ascertaining whether the provisions of this Act or of any rules, regulations, directions or orders thereunder are being complied with and may require the production, for his inspection, of any document, book, register or record kept therein and ask for any information relating to the working of the home:</p>
              <p>Provided that no such member or officer shall enter any home or part thereof where there are females, except in the presence of two respectable women of the locality.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Funds of the Board.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The funds of the Board shall consist of--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>contributions, subscriptions, donations or bequests made to it by any person; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>grants made to it by the State Government or any local or other public body.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Staff of the Board.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Subject to such rules as may be made by the State Government in this behalf, the Board may, for the purpose of enabling it to perform efficiently its functions or exercise its powers under this Act, appoint such officers or other employees as it may think fit and determine their functions and conditions of service.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Delegation of powers.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the control of the State Government, the Board may, by general or special order in writing and subject to such conditions and limitations, if any, as may be specified therein, delegate to the Chairman or any other member or any officer thereof such of its powers and functions under this Act, as it may deem necessary, for the efficient carrying on of its administration.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>RECOGNITION OF HOMES</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Homes not to be run without certificate.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>After the commencement of this Act, no person shall maintain or conduct any home except under, and in accordance with, the conditions of a certificate of recognition granted under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Application for certificate.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every person desiring to maintain or conduct a home shall make an application for a certificate of recognition to the Board in such form and containing such particulars as may be prescribed:</p>
              <p>Provided that a person maintaining or conducting a home at the commencement of this Act shall be allowed a period of three months from such commencement to make an application for such certificate.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Grant or refusal of certificate.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-15.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On receipt of an application under section 14, the Board after making such inquiry as it considers necessary, may, by order in writing, either grant a certificate or refuse to grant it.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No order refusing to grant a certificate shall be made until an opportunity is given to the applicant to be heard in the matter and where a certificate is refused, the grounds for such refusal shall be communicated to the applicant in the prescribed manner.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No fee shall be charged for the grant of a certificate.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A certificate shall not be transferable.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Contents of certificate.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-16.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-16.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The certificate shall specify-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-16.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the name and location of the recognised home;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the name of the manager thereof;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the nature of the home, whether for women generally or for widows or for children generally or for orphans or for one or more of these classes;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the number of inmates to be taken by the home;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.1.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the minimum standards regarding boarding, lodging, clothing, sanitation, health and hygiene which, having regard to the conditions of the locality in which the recognised home is situated and its resources, should be complied with in the home;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.1.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the standard of education or training to be provided for the inmates of the home, in case the education or training of its inmates is undertaken; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.1.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>such other conditions and particulars as may be prescribed:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that there shall be deemed to be included in the certificate granted in respect of a home for females a condition to the effect that the person in charge thereof, whether called superintendent or by any other name, shall ordinarily be a woman.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall not, ordinarily, permit any recognised home to admit as inmates, persons of different sexes, but may do so for reasons to be recorded and subject to such conditions and limitations as may appear to it to be in the public interest.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-16.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Without the previous written consent of the Board, no recognised home shall-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-16.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>change its name or location as specified in the certificate in respect of it; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.3.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>alter the purpose of any service specified therein.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Revocation of certificate.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-17.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Board may, without prejudice to any other penalty to which a person to whom a certificate has been granted may be liable under this Act, revoke the certificate-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>if it is satisfied that the home is not being conducted in accordance with the conditions laid down in the certificate; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the management of the home is being persistently carried on in an unsatisfactory manner or is being carried on in a manner highly prejudicial to the moral and physical well- being of the inmates; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the home has, in the opinion of the Board, otherwise rendered itself unsuitable for that purpose:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that no order of revocation shall be made under this sub- section until an opportunity is given to the person to show cause why the certificate should not be revoked;</p>
              <p>and in every case of revocation. the grounds therefor shall be communicated to the person in the prescribed manner.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-17.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Where a certificate in respect of a home is revoked under subsection (1), such home shall cease to function-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>where an appeal has not been preferred under section 18 against the order of revocation, immediately on the expiration of the period prescribed for such appeal;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>where such appeal has been preferred, but the order of revocation is upheld, from the date of the appellate order.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-17.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>On any home ceasing to function under sub- section (2), the Board may direct that any woman or child who is an inmate of such home shall be-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>restored to the custody of her or his parent, husband or lawful guardian, as the case may be, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.3.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>transferred to another recognised home, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.3.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>entrusted to the care of any other fit person:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that no woman shall be entrusted to the care of any person other than a woman.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Appeals.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Any person aggrieved by an order of the Board refusing to grant a certificate or revoking a certificate may, in such manner land within such period as may be prescribed, prefer an appeal to the State Government or to such authority as may be specified by it against such refusal or revocation:</p>
              <p>Provided that the State Government or the authority so specified, as the case may be, may admit an appeal after the expiry of the period so prescribed, if it is satisfied that the applicant was prevented by sufficient cause from preferring the appeal in time.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Surrender of certificate and its effect.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-19.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The manager of a home, if specially authorised in this behalf by resolution of the managing committee, may, on giving six months' notice in writing to the Board of his intention so to do, apply for the withdrawal of the certificate granted in respect of that home and on the expiration of the said period from the date of notice, the certificate shall, unless before that time the notice is withdrawn, cease to have effect; and the home shall cease to function.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No woman or child shall be received into any such home after the date of such notice; but nothing in this section shall be construed to affect the obligation of the manager to comply with, all the requirements of this Act and the rules, regulations, directions and orders thereunder until the certificate ceases to take effect under sub-section (1).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MANAGEMENT OF RECOGNISED HOMES</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Managing committee.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-20.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>There shall be a managing committee in charge of the management of every recognised home and the members of the managing committee shall appoint a member thereof to be the manager of such home for the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The constitution, powers and functions of the managing committee and the term of office of the members thereof shall be such as may be provided in the constitution pertaining to such home.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Duty of manager.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>It shall be the duty of the manager to comply with all the requirements of this Act and the rules, regulations, directions and orders thereunder in respect of every woman or child admitted into the recognised home until the woman is rehabilitated or the child completes the age of eighteen years or until the certificate ceases to have effect.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Discharge of inmates of home.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-22.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the regulations, if any, made by the Board, if the managing committee of a home is satisfied that an inmate of the home has become fit to earn his or her livelihood or is otherwise fit to be discharged from the home, the manager may discharge such inmate.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), no female inmate of a home shall be discharged or given in marriage or entrusted to the care of any other person unless such female has made a declaration before the Board or an officer specified by it in this behalf that she consents to such discharge, marriage or entrustment, as the case may be, and, if the inmate to be given in marriage is a minor, unless the Board or officer, as the case may be, has, after recording the reasons in writing, given its or his approval thereto.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Reports regarding deaths of inmates.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The manager shall, immediately after the occurrence of any death among the inmates of the home, send a written report thereof to the Board explaining the cause of death to the best of his knowledge.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-V.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Penalties.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Any person who fails to comply with any of the provisions of this Act or of any rule, regulation, direction or order thereunder or any of the conditions of a certificate shall be punishable in the case of a first offence with imprisonment which may extend to three months or with fine which may extend to two hundred and fifty rupees or with both, and in the case. of a second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment which may extend to six months or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees or with both.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Sanction for prosecutions.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No prosecution under this Act shall be instituted except with the previous sanction of the District Magistrate or the Chief Presidency Magistrate, as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Persons performing functions under Act to be public servants.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The members of the Board and every person empowered by the Board to exercise any of its powers under this Act shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Protection of acts done in good faith.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any person who performs any function under this Act for anything done or intended to be done in good faith under this Act or any rule, regulation direction or order thereunder.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Power of State Government to exempt homes.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-28.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If, after consultation with the Board, the State, Government is satisfied that the circumstances in relation to any class of homes or any home are such that it is necessary or expedient so to do, it may, by notification in the Official Gazette, and for reasons to be specified therein, exempt, subject to such conditions, restrictions or limitations, if any, as it may think fit to impose, such class of homes or home, as the case may be, from the operation of all or any of the provisions of this Act or of any rule or regulation made thereunder.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-28.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every notification issued under this section granting an exemption shall be reviewed in consultation with the Board at intervals not exceeding two years, but nothing herein contained shall affect the power of the State Government to amend, vary or rescind any such notification at any time in consultation with the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Power of State Government to make rules.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-29.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-29.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-29.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>all matters relating to, or in connection with, elections, to the Board under clause (b) of sub- section (2) of section 5 and the election of the Chairman;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-29.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the disqualifications for membership of the Board and the procedure to be followed in removing a member who is or becomes subject to any disqualification;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-29.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the funds of the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-29.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the travelling and other allowances to be drawn by members of the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-29.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the appointment of staff for enabling the Board to perform its functions efficiently under this Act and their recruitment and conditions of service;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-29.2.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the calling of returns and other information by the State Government from the Board and the managing committees;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-29.2.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the form in which an application for certificate of recognition may be made, the particulars to be contained in such application and the form in which, and the conditions subject to which, such certificate may be granted;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-29.2.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>the maintenance of registers and accounts by the Board and the audit of its accounts;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-29.2.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>any other matter which is to be, or may be, prescribed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All rules made under this Act shall, as soon as may be after they are made, be laid before the State Legislature.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading>Power of the Board to make regulations.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-30.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board may, with the previous approval of the State Government, by notification in the, Official Gazette, make regulations not inconsistent with this Act and the rules made thereunder, for enabling it to perform its functions under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-30.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-30.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such regulations may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-30.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the time and place of the meetings of the Board, the procedure to be followed in regard to the transaction of business at such meetings and the quorum necessary for the transaction of business at such meetings;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the maintenance of the minutes of meetings of the Board and the transmission of copies thereof to the State Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the appointment of sub- committees and local committees and of persons by the Board for the purpose of assisting it in performing its functions under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the supervision and control of the management of recognised homes;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the inspection of homes;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.2.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the calling of returns and other information by the Board from managing committees;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.2.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the reception, care, treatment, maintenance, protection, training, welfare, instruction, control and discipline of inmates in recognised homes;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.2.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>visits to, and communication with, inmates of recognised homes and the grant of permission to such inmates to absent themselves for short periods;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.2.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the discharge of inmates from recognised homes, their transfer from one recognised home to another and the reports to be sent by managers to the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.2.list1.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>any other matter in respect of which provision is, in the opinion of the Board, necessary for the efficient supervision and control of homes.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-30.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, amend, vary or rescind any regulation which it has approved; and thereupon the regulation shall have effect accordingly, but without prejudice to the exercise of the powers of the Board under sub- section (1).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading>Repeals and savings.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-31.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As from the date of the coming into force in any State of this Act, the Women' s and Children' s Institutions (Licensing) Act, 1956 (105 of 1956), or any other Act corresponding to this Act in force in that State immediately before such commencement, shall stand repealed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken (including any direction given, any register or rule or order made or any restriction imposed) under the aid Act shall, in so far as such thing or action is not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act be deemed to have been done or taken under the provisions aforesaid, as if they were in force when such thing was done or such action was taken, and shall continue in force accordingly until superseded by anything done or any action taken under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
