<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1952/53/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1952/53"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Notaries Act, 1952"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1952/53/eng@1952-08-09/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1952/53/eng@1952-08-09"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1952-08-09" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1952/53/eng@1952-08-09/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1952/53/eng@1952-08-09"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-11-28" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Notaries Act, 1952</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[Act, No. 53 of 1952]</p>
      </longTitle>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[9th August, 1952]</docDate>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>An Act to regulate the profession of notaries.</p>
      <p>BE it enacted by Parliament as follows:--</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Notaries Act, 1952.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date2 as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“instrument” includes every document by which any right or liability is, or purports to be, created, transferred, modified, limited, extended, suspended, extinguished or recorded;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“legal practitioner” means an advocate entered in any roll under the provisions of the Advocates Act, 1961 (25 1961);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>“notary” means a person appointed as such under this Act:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that for a period of two years from the commencement of this Act it shall include also a person who, before such commencement was appointed a notary public under the Negotiable Instruments Act, 1881 XXVI of 1881, and is, immediately before such commencement, in practice in any part of India:</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Provided further that in relation to the State of Jammu and Kashmir the said period of two years shall be computed from the date on which this Act comes into force in that State;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>“Register” means a Register of Notaries maintained by the Government under section 4;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>“State Government”, in relation to a Union territory means the administrator thereof.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Power to appoint notaries.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government, for the whole or any part of India, and any State Government, for the whole or any part of the State, may appoint as notaries any legal practitioners or other persons who possess such qualifications as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Registers.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government and every State Government shall maintain, in such form as may be prescribed, a Register of the notaries appointed by that Government and entitled to practise as such under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Every such Register shall include the following particulars about the notary whose name is entered therein, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>his full name, date of birth, residential and professional address;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the date on which his name is entered in the Register;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>his qualifications; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>any other particulars which may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Entry of names in the Register and issue or renewal of certificates of practice.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Every notary who intends to practise as such may, on payment to the Government appointing him of the prescribed fee, if any, be entitled—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to have his name entered in the Register maintained by that Government under section 4; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to a certificate authorising him to practise for a period of five years from the date on which the certificate is issued to him.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government appointing the notary, may, on receipt of an application and the prescribed fee, renew the certificate of practice of any notary for a period of five years at a time.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Annual publication of lists of notaries.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government and every State Government shall, during the month of January each year, publish in the Official Gazette a list of notaries appointed by that Government and in practice at the beginning of that year together with such details pertaining to them as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Seal of notaries.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every notary shall have and use, as occasion may arise, a seal of such form and design as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Functions of notaries.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A notary may do all or any of the following acts by virtue of his office; namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>verify, authenticate, certify or attest the execution of any instrument;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>present any promissory note, hundi or bill of exchange for acceptance or payment or demand better security;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>note or protest the dishonour by non-acceptance or non-payment of any promissory note, hundi or bill of exchange or protest for better security or prepare acts of honour under the Negotiable Instruments Act, 1881 (XXVI of 1881), or serve notice of such note or protest;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>note and draw up ship’s protest, boat’s protest or protest relating to demurrage and other commercial matters;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>administer oath to, or take affidavit from, any person;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>prepare bottomry and respondentia bonds, charter parties and other mercantile documents;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>prepare, attest or authenticate any instrument intended to take effect in any country or place outside India in such form and language as may conform to the law of the place where such deed is entitled to operate;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>translate, and verify the translation of, any document from, one language into another;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.ha">
                <num>(ha)</num>
                <blockList id="section-8.1.list1.ha.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>act as a Commissioner to record evidence in any civil or criminal trial if so directed by any court or authority;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-8.1.list1.ha.list0.hb">
                    <num>(hb)</num>
                    <p>act as an arbitrator, mediator or conciliator, if so required;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>any other act which may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No act specified in sub-section (1) shall be deemed to be a notarial act except when it is done by a notary under his signature and official seal.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Bar of practice without certificate.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this section, no person shall practise as a notary or do any notarial act under the official seal of a notary unless he holds a certificate of practice in force issued to him under section 5:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing in this sub-section shall apply to the presentation of any promissory note, hundi or bill of exchange for acceptance or payment by the clerk of a notary acting on behalf of such notary.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing contained in sub-section (1) shall, until the expiry of two years from the commencement of this Act, apply to any such person as is referred to in the proviso to clause (d) of section 2:</p>
            <p>Provided that in relation to the State of Jammu and Kashmir the said period of two years shall be computed from the date on which this Act comes into force in that State.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Removal of names from Register.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Government appointing any notary may, by order, remove from the Register maintained by it under section 4 the name of the notary if he—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>makes a request to that effect; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>has not paid any prescribed fee required to be paid by him; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>is an undischarged insolvent; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>has been found, upon inquiry in the prescribed manner, to be guilty of such professional or other misconduct as, in the opinion of the Government, renders him unfit to practise as a notary; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>is convicted by any court for an offence involving moral turpitude; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>does not get his certificate of practice renewed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Construction of references to notaries public in other laws.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any reference to a notary public in any other law shall be construed as a reference to a notary entitled to practise under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for falsely representing to be a notary, etc.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any person who—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>falsely represents that he is a notary without being appointed as such, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>practises as a notary or does any notarial act in contravention of section 9, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or with fine, or with both.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Cognizance of offence.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No court shall take cognizance of any offence committed by a notary in the exercise or purported exercise of his functions under this Act save upon complaint in writing made by an officer authorised by the Central Government or a State Government by general or special order in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No magistrate other than a presidency magistrate or a magistrate of the first class shall try an offence punishable under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Reciprocal arrangements for recognition of notarial acts done by foreign notaries.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If the Central Government is satisfied that by the law or practice of any country or place outside India, the notarial acts done by notaries within India are recognized for all or any limited purposes in that country or place, the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare that the notarial acts lawfully done by notaries within such country or place shall be recognized with India for all purposes or, as the case may be, for such limited purposes as may be specified in the notification.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the official Gazette, make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-15.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the qualifications of a notary, the form and manner in which applications for appointment as a notary may be made and the disposal of such applications;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the certificates, testimonials or proofs as to character, integrity, ability and competence which any person applying for appointment as a notary may be required to furnish;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the fees payable for appointment as a notary and for the issue and renewal of a certificate of practice, area of practice or enlargement of area of practice and exemption whether wholly or in part, from such fees in specified classes of cases;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the fees payable to a notary for doing any notarial act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the form of Registers and the particulars to be entered therein;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the form and design of the seal of a notary;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the manner in which inquiries into allegations of professional or other misconduct of notaries may be made;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the acts which a notary may do in addition to those specified in section 8 and the manner in which a notary may perform his functions;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>any other matter which has to be, or may be, prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of Act XXVI of 1881.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Repealed by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1957 (36 of 1957), Section 2 and Schedule I.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
