<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-wbg/act/1950/22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-wbg/act/1950/22"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The West Bengal Animal Slaughter Control Act, 1950"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-wbg/act/1950/22/eng@2017-01-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-wbg/act/1950/22/eng@2017-01-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-wbg/act/1950/22/eng@2017-01-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-wbg/act/1950/22/eng@2017-01-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The West Bengal Animal Slaughter Control Act, 1950</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[6th. April, 1950]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>No. 22 of 1950</p>
        <p>An Act to control the slaughter of certain animals.</p>
        <p>Whereas it is expedient to control the slaughter of certain animals with a view to increase the supply of milk and to avoid the wastage of animal power necessary for improvement pf agriculture;</p>
        <p>It is hereby enacted as follows:—</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the West Bengal Animal Slaughter Control Act, 1950.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of West Bengal.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date or dates as the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint and different dates may be appointed for different parts of West Bengal.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Application of Act.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>This Act applies to the animals specified in the Schedule.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act , unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>“animal” means an animal to which this Act applies;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>“Calcutta” has the same meaning as in clause (11) of section 3 of the Calcutta Municipal Act , 1923;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>“President” means,—</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in relation to a municipality, any person presiding over the affairs of any municipal authority, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in relation to a Panchayat Samiti, any person presiding over the affairs of any Panchayat Samiti,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>by whatever name called, and includes any person nominated by him for the purposes of this Act;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list3.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list3.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>“Veterinary Surgeon” means,—</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in areas other than Calcutta, a Veterinary Surgeon, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in Calcutta, a Veterinary Surgeon of the Directorate of Veterinary Services, Government of West Bengal, acting within the local limits of his jurisdiction, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list3.vi">
                <num>(vi)</num>
                <p>“Veterinary Officer” means—</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in areas other than Calcutta, a District Veterinary Officer, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in Calcutta, a Superintendent of Veterinary Services (Headquarters) of the West Bengal Civil Veterinary Department act ing the local limits of his jurisdiction.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition of slaughter of animal without certificate.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything in any other law for the time being in force or in any usage to the contrary, no person shall slaughter any animal unless he has obtained in respect thereof a certificate under sub-section (2) or sub-section (3) that the animal is fit for slaughter.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The President of a municipality or a Panchayat Samiti, as the case may be, and the Veterinary Surgeon may issue a certificate under their joint signatures that an animal is fit for slaughter if they are both of opinion (which shall be recorded) that—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the animal is over fourteen years of age and unfit for work or breeding, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the animal become permanently incapacitated from work or breeding due to age, injury, deformity or any incurable disease.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where there is a difference of opinion between the President of a municipality or a Panchayat Samiti, as the case may be, and the Veterinary Surgeon as to the issue of a certificate under sub-section (2), the matter shall be referred to the Veterinary Officer and a certificate shall be issued or refused according as the Veterinary Officer is opinion that the animal is fit to be slaughtered or is not so fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where under sub-section (3) a certificate is issued or refused, the order granting or refusing issue of the certificate shall be signed by the Veterinary Officer.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person aggrieved by the refusal to issue a certificate under this section may, within fifteen days from the date of the communication to him of such refusal, appeal to the State Government against the order of refusal, and the State Government may pass such orders thereon as it thinks fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, at any time for the purpose of satisfying itself as to the legality or propriety of any act ion taken under this section, call for and examine the record of any case, and may pass such orders thereon as it thinks fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this section, any action taken under this section shall be final and shall not be called in question in any court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition of slaughter of animals in places not prescribed for the purpose.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No animal in respect of which a certificate has been issued under section 4 shall be slaughtered in any place other than a place prescribed in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Power to enter and inspect premises.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purposes of enforcing the provisions of this Act , the President of a municipality or a Panchayat Samiti, as the case may be, or the Veterinary Surgeon or any person authorised by the Veterinary Assistant Surgeon in writing in this behalf shall have power to enter and inspect any premises within the local limits of his jurisdiction where he has reason to believe that an offence under this Act has been or is likely to be committed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every person in occupation of any such premises as is specified in sub-section (1) shall allow the President of a municipality or a Panchayat Samiti, the Veterinary Surgeon or the person authorised, as the case may be, such access to the premises as he may require for the aforesaid purpose, and shall answer any question put to him by the President of a municipality or a Panchayat Samiti, the Veterinary Surgeon or the person authorised, as the case may be, to the best of his knowledge or behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Penalties.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever contravenes any of the provisions contained in this Act shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Offences to be cognizable.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (Act V of 1898), all offences under this act shall be cognizable.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Abetments and attempts.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever abets any offence punishable under this Act or attempts to commit any such offence shall be punished with the punishment provided in this Act for such offence.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Officers exercising powers under this Act deemed to be public servants.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>All Presidents of municipalities or Panchayat Samitis. Veterinary Surgeons, Veterinary Officers and other persons exercising powers under this Act shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (Act XLV of 1860).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Protections of persons acting in good faith.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall be instituted against any person for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or the rules made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Power to grant exemptions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by general or special order and subject to such conditions as it may think fit to impose, exempt from the operation of this Act the slaughter of any animal for any religious, medicinal or research purposes.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Delegations of functions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, delegate to any officer of State Government all or any of its powers or functions under sub-sections (5) and (6) of section 4, or section 12.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act .</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the form and manner in which applications for certificates under section 4 shall be made;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the fees payable for any certificate which may be issued under section 4 and the form of such certificates;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the time and the places at which animals may be slaughtered in a municipality or a Block in pursuance of this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the conditions subject to which the slaughter of any animal may be permitted under section 12.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-schedule">
      <doc name="schedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-wbg/act/1950/22/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-wbg/act/1950/22"/>
              <FRBRalias value="Schedule"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-wbg/act/1950/22/eng@2017-01-19/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-wbg/act/1950/22/eng@2017-01-19"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-wbg/act/1950/22/eng@2017-01-19/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-wbg/act/1950/22/eng@2017-01-19"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-01-19" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="schedule">
            <paragraph id="schedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>See section 2</p>
                <p>Bulls.</p>
                <p>Bullocks.</p>
                <p>Cows.</p>
                <p>Calves.</p>
                <p>Male and female buffaloes.</p>
                <p>Buffalo calves.</p>
                <p>Castrated buffaloes.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
