<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1957/2/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1957/2"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Karnataka Legislature Salaries, Pensions And Allowances Act, 1956"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1957/2/eng@2017-07-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1957/2/eng@2017-07-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-07-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1957/2/eng@2017-07-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1957/2/eng@2017-07-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-07-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Karnataka Legislature Salaries, Pensions And Allowances Act, 1956</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[24th January 1957]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>ACT No. 2 of 1957</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the salaries, pensions and allowances of the Chairman and the Deputy Chairman, the Speaker and the Deputy Speaker,the Leaders of the Opposition, Government Chief Whips and Opposition Chief Whips and the Members of the Legislative Assembly and the Legislative Council.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the salaries, pensions and allowances of the Chairman and the Deputy Chairman, the Speaker and the Deputy Speaker, the Leaders of the Opposition, the Government Chief Whips, the Opposition Chief Whips and the Members of the Legislative Assembly and the Legislative Council of the State of Karnataka and certain other matters;</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>BE it enacted by the Karnataka State Legislature in the Seventh Year of the Republic of India as follows:—</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Karnataka Legislature Salaries Pensions and Allowances Act, 1956.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the first day of November 1956.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>‘Chairman’ means the Chairman of the Legislative Council</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>‘Deputy Chairman’ means the Deputy Chairman of the Legislative Council;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.bb">
                <num>(bb)</num>
                <p>‘Government Chief Whip’ means a member of the Legislative Assembly or the Legislative Council designated by the Chief Minister as the Government Chief Whip in the Legislative Assembly or the Legislative Council;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>‘highest class’ in relation to journeys by train includes air-conditioned accommodation available in the train;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.cc">
                <num>(cc)</num>
                <p>‘Leader of the Opposition’ means the member of the Legislative Assembly or the Legislative Council who is for the time being recognised as the Leader of the Opposition by the Speaker or the Chairman as the case may be;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.ccc">
                <num>(ccc)</num>
                <p>'Opposition Chief Whip' means a member of the Legislative Assembly or the Legislative Council designated as such by the Leader of the Opposition as the Opposition Chief Whip in the Legislative Assembly or the Legislative Council as the case may be.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>‘prescribed’ means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.dd">
                <num>(dd)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.dd.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>‘recognised group’ means,-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.dd.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>in relation to the Karnataka Legislative Council, every party which has a strength of not less than 10 members i.e., the quorum strength of members in the Legislative Council; in relation to the Karnataka Legislative Assembly, every party which has a strength of not less than twenty three members i.e., the quorum strength of the Legislative Assembly.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>‘residence’ includes staff quarters and buildings appurtenant thereto and the gardens thereof;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>‘Speaker’ means the Speaker of the Legislative Assembly;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>‘Deputy Speaker’ means the Deputy Speaker of the Legislative Assembly.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Salaries and sumptuary allowances of Chairman and Speaker.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be paid to the Chairman a salary of fifty thousand rupees per mensem and a sumptuary allowance of three lakhs rupees 4 per annum.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be paid to the Speaker a salary of fifty thousand rupees per</p>
            <p>mensem and a sumptuary allowance of three lakhs rupees per annum.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Residences of Chairman, Speaker etc.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chairman, Speaker, Deputy Chairman, Deputy Speaker, Leader of Opposition, Government Chief Whip and Opposition Chief Whip each shall be entitled to the use of a furnished residence in the City of Bangalore within thirty kilometres from the limits of the City of Bangalore throughout his term of office and for a period of sixty days immediately thereafter, or, in lieu of such furnished residence, to a house rent allowance at the rate of eighty thousand rupees per mensem. The residence provided under this sub-section shall be furnished on such scales and the plinth area thereof shall not exceed such limits, as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chairman or the Speaker who is entitled to a house rent allowance, shall be entitled for an allowance of twenty thousand rupees per mensem for maintenance and upkeep of the residence and for layout and maintenance of gardens included in such residence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Conveyances of the Chairman and the Speaker.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may provide a suitable motor car each for the use of the Chairman and the Speaker.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be paid to the Chairman and the Speaker each a conveyance allowance equal to the cost of one thousand litres of petrol per mensem.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Charges payable by the Chairman and the Speaker and the Government.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Chairman and the Speaker shall, in respect of their respective residences and the motor cars allotted for their use under sub-section (1) of section 4 and section 5, be liable to pay the following charges, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>cost of petrol required for their respective motor cars in excess of the cost of one thousand litres of petrol paid by the Government; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the first two hundred rupees of the aggregate monthly charges for the consumption of electricity and water in the residence.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All other charges for the maintenance and upkeep of the residence provided under sub-section (1) of section 4 and the motor car provided under section 5 including the cost of repairs thereof, the salaries and allowances of the drivers and cleaners of such motor cars, rates and taxes, and all expenditure for the layout and the maintenance of the gardens included in such residences, shall be borne by the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Travelling Allowances of the Chairman and the Speaker on assuming or relinquishing office.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Chairman and the Speaker shall,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for the journey in respect of assuming office, to the City of Bangalore, from his usual place of residence in the State, if it is outside the City, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>for the journey in respect of relinquishing office, from the City of Bangalore to his usual place of residence in the State before he assumed office, if such place is outside the City, be entitled to travelling allowance for himself and the members of his family and for the transport of his personal effects at the rates hereinafter specified, namely:—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>the actual charges incurred by the Chairman or the Speaker for himself and the members of his family, whether the journey is made by train or by road or both;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>the actual charges incurred for the transport of the personal effects whether by road or by rail: provided that if a railway wagon is reserved for such transport, the charges for such wagon.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Explanation.—For the purpose of this section, member of the family means the husband, wife, son, daughter, father, mother, brother or sister, if wholly dependent on and residing with the Chairman or the Speaker, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Travelling and other allowances of the Chairman, the Deputy Chairman, the Speaker and the Deputy Speaker, the Leaders of the Opposition,the Government Chief Whips and the Opposition Chief Whips on tours.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chairman, the Deputy Chairman, the Speaker and the Deputy Speaker, the Leaders of the Opposition,the Government Chief Whips and the Opposition Chief Whips shall be entitled while touring on duty connected with their offices to travelling and daily or other allowances at the rates and upon the conditions specified in this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>While touring inside India the Chairman, the Deputy Chairman, the Speaker and the Deputy Speaker, the Leaders of the Opposition,the Government Chief Whips and the Opposition Chief Whips shall be entitled,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for journeys by train to two times the single fare of the highest class available in the train:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that if the Chairman, the Deputy Chairman, the Speaker or the Deputy Speaker, the Leaders of Opposition,the Government Chief Whips and the Opposition Chief Whips reserves a compartment for the journey, the charges for such compartment shall be borne by the State Government:</p>
            <blockList id="section-8.2.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Provided further that if any person in addition to the Chariman, the Deputy Chairman, the Speaker or the Deputy Speaker, the Leader of the Opposition,the Government Chief Whips and the Opposition Chief Whips travels in the reserved compartment, the charges in respect of such person shall be recovered and credited to Government.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.2.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>for journeys by road, to road mileage at thirty rupees per kilometre;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>for journeys by air, to one and one fourth times the single fare paid for such journeys and to the prescribed insurance premium for insurance against accidents during such journeys;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list4.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>to daily allowance at rupees two thousand per day for the days of journey and for the days of halt at any place:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that in the case of tours outside the State, the daily allowance shall be at two thousand five hundred rupees and five thousand rupees per diem for stay in hotel or other registered establishment providing lodging and boarding at scheduled rates subject to production of bills.</p>
            <p>Provided further that if the Chairman, the Deputy Chairman, the Speaker, or the Deputy Speaker, the Leaders of the Opposition,the Government Chief Whips and the Opposition Chief Whips is treated as a State Guest, he shall be entitled only to one-fourth of the daily allowance for the period for which he is treated as a State Guest.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2A">
          <num>(2A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When the Chairman, the Deputy Chairman, the Speaker or the Deputy Speaker, the Leaders of the Opposition,the Government Chief Whips and the Opposition Chief Whips while making a journey by road in a motor car provided by the State Government, has to undertake in the public interest further journey by train or by air, he shall be entitled to the petrol charges incurred by him for the return of the motor car to the City of Bangalore from the place at which he ceases to use the motor car:</p>
            <p>Provided that, save as otherwise provided in sub-section (2B), when no motor car is taken with him while on tour outside the State in India, the Chairman, the Deputy Chairman, the Speaker and the Deputy Speaker, the Leaders of the Opposition ,the Government Chief Whips and the Opposition Chief Whips shall be entitled at his option, in lieu of conveyance allowance and to any road mileage to which he is entitled, to the actual hire charges of the motor car, hired by him in the interest of public service. Certificate to the effect that the hiring of the motor car was necessary in public interest shall be furnished by the Chairman, Deputy Chairman, Speaker and Deputy Speaker, the Leaders of the Opposition,the Government Chief Whips and the Opposition Chief Whips, as the case may be, along with the bill.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2B">
          <num>(2B)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chairman, the Deputy Chairman, the Speaker and the Deputy Speaker, the Leaders of the Opposition,the Government Chief Whips and the Opposition Chief Whips shall, in addition to the allowances payable under sub-section (2), be entitled to use without payment of charges, the motor cars maintained by the State Government at the Karnataka Bhavan in New Delhi.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.3.list0">
              <item id="section-8.3.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>The Chairman and the Speaker touring outside India on duty shall be entitled to the same terms in regard to travelling and other expenses as a Minister of the State Government.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.3.list0.aa">
                <num>(aa)</num>
                <p>The Chairman, the Deputy Chairman, the Speaker, the Deputy Speaker, the Leader of the Opposition,the Government Chief Whips and the Opposition Chief Whips travelling outside India for medical treatment shall be entitled to the same terms in regard to travelling and other expenses as a Minister of the State Government.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Medical Attendance.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Subject to rules made by the State Government, the Chairman, the Deputy Chairman, the Speaker and the Deputy Speaker the Leaders of the Opposition,the Government Chief Whips and the Opposition Chief Whips and the members of the family of the Chairman, the Deputy Chairman, the Speaker or the Deputy Speaker, the Leaders of the Opposition,the Government Chief Whips and the Opposition Chief Whips as the case may be, who are residing with and are dependent on him, shall be entitled free of charge to accommodation in hospitals maintained by the State Government, and to medical attendance and treatment. They shall also be entitled, subject to rules made by the State Government, to reimbursement of the expenses incurred by them for medical attendance and treatment obtained at any other place whether within or outside India.</p>
            <p>Explanation.—For the purpose of this section and section 12 member of the family means the husband, wife, son, daughter, father, mother, brother or sister.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Salaries of Deputy Chairman and Deputy Speaker.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be paid to the Deputy Chairman and to the Deputy Speaker each a salary of forty thousand rupees per mensem.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be paid to the Deputy Chairman and the Deputy Speaker a conveyance allowance of equal to the cost of one thousand litres of petrol per mensem.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10A">
        <num>10A.</num>
        <heading>Salary, conveyance and conveyance allowance payable to the Deputy Chairman, Deputy Speaker or the person performing the duties of the Chairman or Speaker.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, while the office of the Chairman is vacant and the duties of the said office are performed by the Deputy Chairman or a member of the Legislative Council appointed under clause (1) of Article 184 of the Constitution, the Deputy Chairman or such member, shall, during the period he so performs such duties, be paid a salary of forty thousand rupees per mensem and provided with a suitable motor car and paid conveyance allowance in accordance with the provisions of sections 5 and 6:</p>
            <p>Provided that during the period aforesaid, the Deputy Chairman or the member shall not be entitled to the salary and special allowance under section 10 or section 11, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, while the office of the Speaker is vacant and the duties of the office are performed by the Deputy Speaker or member of the Legislative Assembly appointed under clause (1) of Article 180 of the Constitution, the Deputy Speaker or such member shall, during the period he so performs such duties, be paid salary of forty thousand rupees per mensem and provided with a suitable motor car and paid conveyance allowance in accordance with the provisions of sections 5 and 6:</p>
            <p>Provided that during the period aforesaid, the Deputy Speaker or the member shall not be entitled to the salary and special allowance under section 10 or section 11, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10C">
        <num>10C.</num>
        <heading>Conveyances of the Deputy Chairman and the Deputy Speaker.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10C.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may provide a suitable motor car each for the use of the Deputy Chairman and the Deputy Speaker.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10D">
        <num>10D.</num>
        <heading>Charges payable by the Deputy Chairman and the Deputy Speaker and the Government.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10D.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10D.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Deputy Chairman and the Deputy Speaker shall, in respect of their respective residences and the motor cars allotted for their use under sub-section (1) of section 4 and section 10C, be liable to pay the following charges, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10D.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>cost of petrol required for their respective motor car in excess of the cost of seven hundred and fifty litres of petrol paid by the Government; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10D.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the first two hundred rupees of the aggregate monthly charges for the consumption of electricity and water in the residence.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10D.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All other charges for the maintenance and upkeep of the residence provided under sub-section (1) of section 4 and the motor car provided under section 10C including the cost of repairs thereof, the salaries and allowances of the drivers and cleaners of such motor cars, rates and taxes, and all expenditure for the layout and the maintenance of the gardens included in such residences shall be borne by the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10E">
        <num>10E.</num>
        <heading>Salary to the Leader of the Opposition.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10E.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>There shall be paid to each Leader of the Opposition a salary of forty thousand rupees per mensem.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10G">
        <num>10G.</num>
        <heading>Conveyance for the Leader of the Opposition.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10G.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may provide a suitable motor car for the use of each Leader of the Opposition.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10G.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be paid to each Leader of the Opposition a conveyance allowance equal to the cost of one thousand litres of petrol per mensem.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10H">
        <num>10H.</num>
        <heading>Omitted</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10I">
        <num>10I.</num>
        <heading>Charges payable by the Leader of the Opposition and the Government.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10I.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10I.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Each Leader of the Opposition shall in respect of the residence and the motor car allotted for his use under sub-section (1) of section 4 and section 10G, be liable to pay the following charges, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10I.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>cost of petrol required for their respective motor car in excess of the cost of seven hundred and fifty litres of petrol paid by the Government; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10I.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the first two hundred rupees of the aggregate monthly charges for the consumption of electricity and water in the residence.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10I.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All other charges for the maintenance and upkeep of the residence provided under sub-section (1) of section 4 and the motor car provided under section 10G including the cost of repairs thereof, the salaries and allowances of the drivers and cleaners of such motor cars, rates and taxes and all expenditure for the layout and the maintenance of the gardens included in such residence, shall be borne by the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10J">
        <num>10J.</num>
        <heading>Salary to the Government Chief Whip.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10J.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>There shall be paid to each Government Chief Whip a salary of thirty five thousand rupees per mensem.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10K">
        <num>10K.</num>
        <heading>Salary to the Opposition Chief Whip.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10K.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>There shall be paid to each Opposition Chief Whip a salary of thirty five thousand rupees per mensem.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10L">
        <num>10L.</num>
        <heading>Conveyance for the Government Chief Whip.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10L.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may provide a suitable motor car for the use of each Government Chief Whip.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10L.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be paid to each Government Chief Whip a conveyance allowance equal to the cost of one thousand litres of petrol per mensem.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10M">
        <num>10M.</num>
        <heading>Conveyance for the Opposition Chief Whip.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10M.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may provide a suitable motor car for the use of each Opposition Chief Whip.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10M.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be paid to each Opposition Chief Whip a conveyance allowance equal to the cost of one thousand litres of petrol per mensem.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10N">
        <num>10N.</num>
        <heading>Charges payable by the Government Chief Whip,and the Opposition Chief Whip.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10N.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10N.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Each Government Chief Whip and each Opposition Chief Whip shall in respect of the residence and the motor car allotted for his use under sub-section (1) of section 4 and section 10L or section 10M, as the case may be, liable to pay the following charges, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10N.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>cost of petrol required for their respective motor cars in excess of the cost of seven hundred and fifty litres of petrol paid by the Government; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10N.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the first two hundred rupees of the aggregate monthly charges for the consumption of electricity and water in the residence.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10N.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All other charges for the maintenance and upkeep of the residence provided under sub-section (1) of section 4 and the motor car provided under section 10L including the cost of repairs thereof, the salaries and allowances of the drivers and cleaners of such motor cars, rates and taxes and all expenditure for the layout and the maintenance of the gardens included in such residence, shall be borne by the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10O">
        <num>10O.</num>
        <heading>Application of Act to Whips.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10O.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If a Minister or a Minister of State or a Deputy Minister is appointed as a Government Chief Whip, he shall not be entitled to any salary or allowances specified in this Act and he shall be governed by the provisions of the Karnataka Ministers Salaries and Allowances Act, 1956.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10P">
        <num>10P.</num>
        <heading>Government to bear electricity and water charges in certain other cases.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10P.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In respect of the residence of the Chairman, the Speaker, the Deputy Chairman, the Deputy Speaker, the Leaders of the Opposition,the Government Chief Whips and Opposition Chief Whips who does not avail the facility of furnished residence, monthly charges in excess of two hundred rupees for consumption of electricity and water together in his residence shall be borne by the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10Q">
        <num>10Q.</num>
        <heading>Deductions in respect of house rent etc.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10Q.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10Q.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>There shall be deducted every month from the salary payable to the Chairman, the Speaker, the Deputy Chairman the Deputy Speaker, a Leader of the Opposition the Government Chief Whips and Opposition Chief Whips,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10Q.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>a sum equal to ten per cent of his salary as house rent if he is, in occupation of a residence provided by the State Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10Q.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>a sum equal to two and a half percent of his salary as rent of the furnishings of his residence if the same has been furnished by the State Government.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Salary of members of the Legislative Assembly and the Legislative Council.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>There shall be paid to every member of the Legislative Assembly or of the Legislative Council a salary of twenty five thousand rupees per mensem which shall accrue to him from the day on which he is declared duly elected, or, in the case of a member nominated by the Governor to fill a seat in the Legislative Assembly or the Legislative Council, from the date on which he is so nominated, or, if such declaration or nomination is made before the vacancy occurs, from the date of occurrence of the vacancy:</p>
            <p>Provided that the salary shall not be paid until the member has made and subscribed the oath or affirmation referred to in Article 188 of the Constitution of India.</p>
            <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided further that,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list3.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>in the case of a member of a new Legislative Assembly constituted after a general election, the salary shall be paid only from the date of commencement of the duration of that Assembly or if the old Legislative Assembly has been dissolved before the aforesaid date, then from the date of such dissolution; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list3.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>in the case of a member of the Legislative Council, the salary shall be paid only from the date on which his term of office as a member of the said Council commences.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided also that where a person who is already a member of the Legislative Assembly or of the Legislative Council, is elected or nominated as a member of the Legislative Council or of the Legislative Assembly, he shall be paid salary as a member of the Legislative Council or of the Legislative Assembly, as the case may be, only from the date on which he ceases to be a member of the Legislative Assembly or of the Legislative Council, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any member entitled to any salary under sub-section (1) may relinquish the whole or any portion thereof at any time by intimating in writing to the Speaker in the case of a member of the Legislative Assembly and to the Chairman in the case of a member of the Legislative Council:</p>
            <p>Provided that any relinquishment made by a member in respect of any salary may be cancelled by him at any time with prospective effect by writing to the Speaker or Chairman accordingly.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11A">
        <num>11A.</num>
        <heading>Pension to the members etc.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11A.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>With effect from the date of commencement of the Karnataka Legislature Salaries, Pensions and Allowances (Amendment) Act, 2009 there shall be paid to every person who has served for a period of five years as,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11A.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>a member of the Legislative Council; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11A.1.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>a member of the Legislative Assembly; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11A.1.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>partly as a member of the Legislative Assembly and partly as a member of the Legislative Council,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>a pension at the rate of forty thousand rupees per mensum for the remainder of his life:</p>
            <p>Provided further that service as such member for a part of the year exceeding six months shall be treated as a full year for the purpose of calculating additional pension:</p>
            <p>Provided also that where a member elected for the first time has been prevented from serving as such for five years on account of dissolution of the Legislative Assembly, he shall be deemed to have served as member for five years:</p>
            <p>Provided also that a person who was a member of the first Legislative Council and whose term was terminated by lots drawn before he could serve the full term of six years, shall be deemed, irrespective of the period for which he held office, to have served as member for five years:</p>
            <p>Provided also that where a person is declared as elected by a court in an election petition and was not able to serve as a member during the pendency of the election petition, shall be deemed, irrespective of the period of actual service, to have served as a member for five years:</p>
            <p>Provided also that where the election of a person is set aside by the Court in an election petition due to technical reasons not attributed to such person and for this reason was not able to serve as a member during the period of five years, shall be deemed irrespective of the period of actual service, to have served as a member for five years.</p>
            <p>Explanation.- For the purpose of this proviso technical reason means inclusion of certain voters in the voter list after the issue of notification of election by the Election Commission of India</p>
            <p>Provided also that where a person is declared as elected in a bye-election or is nominated as a member in the middle of a term and was not able to serve the full term, he shall be deemed, irrespective of the period of actual service, to have served as a member for five years:</p>
            <p>Provided also that where a member resigns , he shall be deemed to have served as member for five years.</p>
            <p>Provided also that where any person has served for more than five years there shall be paid to him an additional pension at the rate of rupees one thousand per mensem for every subsequent completed year.</p>
            <p>Explanation.- For the purpose of this sub-section, a member of the Legislative Assembly or the Legislative Council includes,-</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>a person who prior to the 1st day of November 1956 represented any of the areas which with effect on and from the said date have become part of the new State of Karnataka, as a member of the Legislative Assembly or the Legislative Council of the State of which the said areas were part:</p>
            <p>Provided that in the case of a nominated member of the Legislative Assembly or the Legislative Council he shall be eligible for the pension if during his membership of the Legislative Assembly or the Legislative Council, he permanently resided in any area which forms part of the State of Karnataka.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11A.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>a person who was a member of the following (before the first day of January,1952.) namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11A.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>The Constituent Assembly;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11A.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>The Mysore Representative Assembly;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11A.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>The Mysore Legislative Assembly;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11A.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>The Legislative Assembly or the Legislative Council of any State (including an Indian State) or Province, Which or any area of which now forms part of the State of Karnataka.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-11A.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that no such pension shall be paid to a person unless,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11A.2.list3.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>in the case of a person who served as a member representing a territorial Constituency, he represented; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11A.2.list3.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>in the case of any other member, he permanently resided during such membership in, any area which now forms part of the State of Karnataka</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that in the case of a nominated member of the Legislative Assembly or the Legislative Council he shall be eligible for the pension if during his membership of the Legislative Assembly or the Legislative Council, he permanently resided in any area which forms part of the State of Karnataka.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11A.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where any person entitled to pension under sub-section (1),—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11A.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>is elected to the Office of the President or Vice-President of India or is appointed to the office of the Governor of any State or the Administrator of any Union territory; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11A.2.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>is appointed or elected to the office of a Minister, a Minister of State, a Deputy Minister, a Chairman, Speaker, a Deputy Chairman, a Deputy Speaker, a Leader of the Opposition,a Government Chief Whip or a Opposition Chief Whip</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11A.2.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>becomes a Member of the Council of State, or the House of the People or the Legislative Assembly of a State or Union Territory or any Legislative Council of a State; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11A.2.list1.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>is employed on a salary in any State Government or Central Government or any Corporation owned or controlled by any State Government or the Central Government or any ocal authority or becomes otherwise entitled to any remuneration from such Government, Corporation or local authority, such person shall not be entitled to any pension under sub-section (1) for the period during which he continues to hold such office or as such member, or is so employed or continues to be entitled to such remuneration:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that where the salary payable to such person for holding such office or being such member or so employed or where the remuneration referred to in clause (iv) payable to such person is in either case less than the pension payable to him under sub-section (1), such person shall be entitled to receive only the balance as pension under that sub-section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11A.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In computing the number of years, for the purpose of sub-section (1), the period during which a person has served in any one or more of the following capacities namely, a Minister, a Minister of State, a Deputy Minister, a Parliamentary Secretary, the Chairman, the Speaker, a Leader of the Opposition,a Government Chief Whip or a Opposition Chief Whip by virtue of his membership of the Legislative Assembly or the Legislative Council, shall also be taken into account.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11A.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11A.5.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Every member entitled to pension under sub-section (1)</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11A.5.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>shall be provided with one non transferable pass for him and his companion which shall entitle them at any time to travel by road transport services of the Karnataka State Road Transport Corporation from the ordinary place of residence of such member in Karnataka to any place in the State of Karnataka or outside the State and back in such class of accommodation therein as may be prescribed;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11A.5.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>shall for every financial year be entitled to receive in such manner and subject to such conditions, as may be prescribed, a sum of rupees one lakh per annum payable in two equal installments in the months of April and October for the purpose of travelling either single or with a companion in one or more journeys by air or by railway in India.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11B">
        <num>11B.</num>
        <heading>Family Pension.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11B.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a member dies before the expiry of his term or where a person eligible for pension under section 11-A dies, there shall be paid to his family, a family pension at the rate of fifty percent of pension admissible under section 11A per mensem.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11B.1A">
          <num>(1A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), the family of the deceased person, who was a member of the Legislative Council or the Legislative Assembly whether he was in receipt of pension or not shall be entitled for family pension at the rate specified under sub-section (1).</p>
            <blockList id="section-11B.1A.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation.—For the purposes of sub-sections (1) and (2) ‘family’ means, the following relatives of the deceased member, namely:</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11B.1A.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>wife or the husband;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11B.1A.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>minor sons; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11B.1A.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>unmarried minor daughters.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11B.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11B.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The family pension admissible under sub-section (1) shall be payable in the following order,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11B.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>wife or husband; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11B.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the eldest among the minor sons or unmarried minor daughters, where the deceased member has no surviving spouse:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that where the recipient of the family pension dies or marries or ceases to be a minor, the pension payable shall thereafter be paid to the person next lower in the order of preference.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11C">
        <num>11C.</num>
        <heading>Sumptuary allowance.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11C.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Leaders of the Opposition shall be paid a sumptuary allowance oftwo lakh rupees per annum.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11C.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Deputy Chairman, the Deputy Speaker,the Government Chief Whips and the Opposition Chief Whips shall be paid a sumptuary allowance of two lakh rupees per annum.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Travelling and daily allowances of, and medical and other facilities to, members of the Legislative Assembly and the Legislative Council.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Subject to such conditions as may be determined by rules made under this Act,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>there shall be paid to the members of the Legislative Assembly and of the Legislative Council traveling allowance for journeys at the rate of twenty five rupees per kilometre irrespective of mode of journey subject to such conditions as may be prescribed or fixed traveling allowance rupees one thousand five hundred for each meeting in lieu of traveling allowance calculated on the basis of distance traveled in kilometers.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>there shall be paid,—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>to all members daily allowance for attending the meetings and for the prescribed number of days of holidays, intervals or absence between meetings at the rate of two thousand rupees per-diem within the State and two thousand five hundred rupees and five thousand rupees per diem for stay in hotel or other registered establishment providing boarding and lodging at scheduled tariffs subject to production of bills and also one thousand five hundred rupees towards local transport per-diem outside the State in India;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>to all members daily allowance for two days before the commencement of meetings and for two days after the day of conclusion of the meetings;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>In respect of study tours abroad the T.A. claims of the members shall be regulated as per G.O.No. FD 3 SRA 2011, dated: 15.11.2011 as amended from time to time.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>Every member or on ex-member and the members of his family who are residing with and are dependent on him shall be entitled,—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>free of charge to such accommodation in hospitals and dispensaries maintained by the State Government or in hospitals or dispensaries notified by the Karnataka Legislature and to such medical attendance and treatment as may be prescribed;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>subject to rules made by the State Government to reimbursement of expenses incurred by him for medical attendance and treatment obtained at any other place.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>every ex-member who is in receipt of the pension under section 11A shall be entitled to fixed medical allowance rupees five thousand per month, subject to the condition that the said amount shall be deducted in the medical reimbursement claim if any during the said month.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>Every person who is drawing family pension under section 11B shall be entitled to rupees two thousand five hundred per month as fixed medical allowance.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.cc">
                    <num>(cc)</num>
                    <p>Every member of the Legislative Assembly and of the Legislative Council shall be entitled to receive in the prescribed manner, a sum of rupees forty thousand per month as constituency Traveling Allowance.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.ccc">
                    <num>(ccc)</num>
                    <p>Every member including a Minister, a Minister of State, a Deputy Minister, a Chairman, a Speaker, a Deputy Chairman, a Deputy Speaker, a Leader of the Opposition and a Government Chief Whip and a Opposition Chief Whip 3 shall, for every financial year, be entitled to receive in such manner and subject to such conditions, as may be prescribed, a sum of rupees two lakh rupees in two equal instalments payable in the months of April and October for the purpose of travelling either single or with a companion in one or more journeys by air or by any class or by any railway in India. A member shall not be entitled to any travelling or daily allowance for such journeys.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.d">
                    <num>(d)</num>
                    <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.d.list0">
                      <listIntroduction>members entitled to travelling allowance under clause (a) may, during the days of halt in the City of Bangalore, other than during the period when their attendance is required in connection with the meetings, be provided with fully furnished accommodation on payment of rent as specified by the Board from time to time.</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.d.list0.dd">
                        <num>(dd)</num>
                        <p>members may during the days of halt in New Delhi be provided with accommodation in the Karnataka Bhavan on payment of such rates of rent as the State Government may, from time to time, by order, specify;</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.e">
                    <num>(e)</num>
                    <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.e.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>there shall be paid to the members of a committee, in respect of journeys undertaken by the committee,—</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.e.list1.i">
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <p>with the approval of the Chairman, where the committee is a committee of the Members of the Legislative Council only;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.e.list1.ii">
                        <num>(ii)</num>
                        <p>with the approval of the Speaker, where the committee is a committee of the Members of the Legislative Assembly only; and</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.e.list1.iii">
                        <num>(iii)</num>
                        <p>with the approval of the Chairman and the Speaker, where the committee is a committee of members of both Houses, of the Legislature, travelling allowance for journeys by train and for journeys by road whether within the State or outside the State in India, at the rates specified in clause (a) and for journeys by air within the state and outside the state in India</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>actual air fare shall be paid and for journeys by air outside the State in India at the rate of one and one-fifth times the single air fare paid for such journeys and such insurance premium as may be prescribed for insurance against accidents during such journeys by air and daily allowance of rupees fifteen per diem for the days of halt at any place within the State and at rupees twenty-five per diem for the days of halt at any place outside the State:</p>
            <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that where one-fifth of the single air fare payable under this clause exceeds rupees thirty, the amount so payable shall be limited to rupees thirty.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list4.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list4.f.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>there shall be paid to a member who is the Chairman of any Committee of the Legislative Assembly or of the Legislative Council or of both in respect of journeys outside the State in India in connection with his duties as Chairman of the Committee,—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list4.f.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>travelling allowance for journeys by train and journeys by road at the rates specified in clause (a) and for journeys by air at the rate of one and one-fifth times the, single air fare paid for such journeys:</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list6">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that where one-fifth of the single air fare payable exceeds rupees thirty, the amount so payable shall be limited to rupees thirty;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list6.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>such insurance premium as may be prescribed for insurance against accidents during journeys by air;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list6.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>daily allowance at rupees twenty-five per diem; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list6.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>such charges as may be prescribed towards transportation at the place of his stay for attending the conference of the Chairmen of such Committees.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list6.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>a member including a Minister, a Minister of State, a Deputy Minister, the Chairman, the Speaker, the Deputy Chairman, the Deputy Speaker, a Leader of the Opposition and a Government Chief Whip and a Opposition Chief Whip shall be entitled to have atelephone installed at Government cost at the place of his choice. The expenditure in respect of initial deposit, installation and rental charges shall be borne by the State Government. Where a member has a telephone installed at his own cost 3[at such place,]3 the rental charges in respect thereof shall be borne by the State Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list6.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>every member shall be paid an allowance of,—</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list6.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>twenty thousand rupees per month towards meeting the expenditure incurred by him on telephone and cell phone calls</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list6.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>forty thousand rupees per month as constituency allowances;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list6.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>five thousand rupees per month on postal charges;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list6.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>ten thousand rupees as the salary of the Personal Assistant and the Room Boy of the Member; in the discharge of his duties as a member.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Explanation.—For the purpose of this section, ‘meeting’ means a meeting of the Legislative Assembly or the Legislative Council or of any committee of the said Assembly or Council or of both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12A">
        <num>12A.</num>
        <heading>Omitted</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Minister, a Minister of State, Deputy Minister, Chairman, Deputy Chairman, Speaker, Deputy Speaker, the Leaders of the Opposition, the Government Chief Whips and the Opposition Chief Whips not to draw salaries as members.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A Minister, Minister of State, a Deputy Minister, the Chairman, the Deputy Chairman, the Speaker or the Deputy Speaker or the Leaders of the Opposition the Government Chief Whips or the Opposition Chief Whips shall not, while he draws the salary and allowance for his office, be entitled to any salary or allowance as a member of the Legislative Assembly or of the Legislative Council, as the case may be.</p>
            <p>Provided that the Deputy Chairman or the Deputy Speaker who does not avail the facility provided under section 10B shall be entitled to the allowances specified in clauses (a) and (b) of section 12 as a member of the Legislative Assembly or the Legislative Council, as the case may be:</p>
            <p>Provided further that he shall also be entitled to the allowances admissible under section or under clause (f) of section 12 as the case may be;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.1A">
          <num>(1A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything in sub-section (1), the Leader of the Opposition, the Government Chief Whips or the Opposition Chief Whips who does not avail the facility provide in section 10F or section 10K, as the case may be, shall be entitled to the allowances specified in clauses (a), (b), (e), (f) of section 12 as a member of the Legislative Assembly or the Legislative Council or as a Chairman of any committee of the Legislative Assembly or the Legislative Council or of both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chairman, the Deputy Chairman, the Speaker, the Deputy Speaker, the Leaders of the Opposition,the Government Chief Whips or the Opposition Chief Whips shall not during the tenure of his office practise any profession or engage in any trade or undertake for remuneration, any employment other than his duties as Chairman, the Deputy Chairman, the Speaker, the Deputy Speaker, the Leaders of the Opposition or the Government Chief Whips, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Omitted</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13A">
        <num>13A.</num>
        <heading>Grant of advances for the purchase of Motor Cars, Motor cycles.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Subject to such conditions as may be prescribed, every member shall be entitled to the grant of an advance for the purchase of a motor car or a motor cycle.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13B">
        <num>13B.</num>
        <heading>Recovery of dues.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13B.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13B.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any amount due to the Government or the Legislature Secretariat from a person who is or was a member of the Legislature may, without prejudice to any other mode of collection be recovered,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13B.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>from his salary payable under section 11;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13B.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>from his pension payable under section 11-A;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13B.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>as if it were an arrear of land Revenue.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Explanation.—For the purpose of this section, a member of the Legislature includes a Minister, Minister of State, Deputy Minister, Chairman, Speaker, Deputy Speaker, Leader of the Opposition, the Government Chief Whips or the Opposition Chief Whips.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13C">
        <num>13C.</num>
        <heading>Establishment of Benevolent Fund.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13C.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be constituted a fund called the Karnataka Legislators’ Benevolent Fund (hereinafter referred to as the Fund</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13C.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13C.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Fund specified in sub-section (1) shall consist of,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13C.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>such amount as may be contributed by any member or former member of the Karnataka Legislative Assembly or the Karnataka Legislative Council;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13C.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>such amount as may be contributed or gifted or donated to the Fund by the Government or any other persons;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13C.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the interest earned on the amount in the said Fund.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13C.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Fund shall be operated or administered or maintained by an authority called the Karnataka Legislators’ Benevolent Fund Authority in accordance with such rules as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13C.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Karnataka Legislative Assembly Benevolent Fund Authority shall consist of-</p>
            <table id="section-13C.4.table1">
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p>a</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>The Speaker, Karnataka Legislative Assembly</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>Chairman</p>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p>b</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>The Minister in charge of Parliamentary Affairs, Government of Karnataka</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>Member</p>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p>c</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>Leader of Opposition in the Legislative Assembly</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>Member</p>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p>d</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>The Secretary, Karnataka Legislative Assemble</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>Secretary</p>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </table>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13C.4A">
          <num>(4A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Karnataka Legislative Council Benevolent Fund Authority shall consist of,—</p>
            <table id="section-13C.4A.table1">
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p>a</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>The Chairman, Karnataka Legislative Council</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>Chairman</p>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p>b</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>The Minister in charge of Parliamentary Affairs</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>Member</p>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p>c</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>The Leader of Opposition in the Legislative Council</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>Member</p>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p>d</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>The Secretary, Karnataka Legislative Council</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>Secretary</p>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </table>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13C.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13C.5.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The amount at credit in the said Fund shall subject to such rules as may be prescribed, be applied or invested or expended for the benefit or for the welfare of,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13C.5.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>persons who are entitled to pension under section 11A;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13C.5.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>the family of persons who die while serving as members of the Legislative Assembly or the Legislative Council;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13C.5.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>the family of persons referred in clause (i) after their demise;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Note.—For the purpose of this section, family shall have the same meaning assigned to it in the explanation to sub-section (1) of section 11B.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13D">
        <num>13D.</num>
        <heading>Facilities to the recognised groups.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13D.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The recognised group shall be entitled to telephone and such secretarial facilities as may be prescribed in this behalf:</p>
            <blockList id="section-13D.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that such facilities shall not be provided to such Leader or Deputy Leader as the case may be, who,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13D.1.list2.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>is provided with similar telephone and secretarial facilities by virtue of holding any office of, or representation in a Legislature Committee or other Committee, Council, Board, Commission or other body established by the Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13D.1.list2.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>is provided with similar telephone and secretarial facilities in any other capacity by the Government or a local authority or a Corporation owned or controlled by the Government or any local authority.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13D.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The facilities admissible under sub-section (1) shall be co-terminus with the term of the Leader or Deputy Leader as the case may be of the recognised group.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Saving.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in this Act shall prevent a retired Government servant from drawing his pension in addition to any salary or allowances to which he may be entitled under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Karnataka Gazette, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.1A">
          <num>(1A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any rule under this Act may be made to have effect retrospectively, and if any such rule is made, a statement specifying the reasons for making such a rule shall be laid before both Houses of the State Legislature along with the rule under sub section (2).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of the State Legislature while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two successive sessions, and if before the expiry of the session in which it is so laid or the session immediately following both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, any other law, rule or order, all rules, notifications and orders which may or are required to be made or issued under this Act, relating to the members of the Legislative Assembly and the Legislative Council, the Chairman, the Deputy Chairman, the Speaker, the Deputy Speaker, the Leaders of the Opposition, the Government Chief Whips and the Opposition Chief Whips in respect of their salary, allowances, pensions, medical bills, accommodation, personal staff, journeys and facilities of all types to which they are entitled, shall be made or issued by the Secretary, Karnataka Legislature with the approval of the Special Board, consisting of the Chairman, the Speaker, the Chief Minister and the Minister in charge of Parliamentary Affairs after consultation with the Finance Department and with such person, body, authority or a department of the State Government as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Repeal of Mysore Ordinance No. 3 of 1956 and savings.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Mysore Legislature Salaries Ordinance, 1956, is hereby repealed; but any rules made, anything done and any action taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been made, done, or taken under this Act, as if this Act had come into force on the first day of November 1956 and all rules made under the said Ordinance shall be laid, as soon as may be, after the passing of this Act, before each House of the State Legislature while it is in session for a total period of one month which may be comprised in one session or in two or more sessions and if, before the expiry of the said period, either House of the State Legislature makes any modification in the rules or directs that any rule shall not have effect and, if the modification or direction is agreed to by the other House, the rules shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
