<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1973/18/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1973/18"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Karnataka Acquisition Of Lands For Grant Of House Sites Act, 1972"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1973/18/eng@2017-07-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1973/18/eng@2017-07-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-07-24" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1973/18/eng@2017-07-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1973/18/eng@2017-07-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-07-24" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Karnataka Acquisition Of Lands For Grant Of House Sites Act, 1972</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[23rd July 1973]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No.18 of 1973</p>
        <p>Preamble</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for acquisition of lands for granting house sites to weaker sections of the people in the State.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the acquisition of lands for the public purpose of granting house site to the weaker sections of the people in the State and for purposes connected therewith;</p>
        <p>BE in enacted by the Karnataka State Legislature in the Twenty-third year of the Republic of India as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Karnataka Acquisition of Lands for Grant of House Sites Act, 1972.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force at once.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In this Act unless the context otherwise requires,-</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“Deputy Commissioner” includes any officer specially appointed by the State Government to perform the functions of a Deputy Commissioner under this Act;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“notification” means a notification published in the official Gazette;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“weaker sections of people” means persons belonging to the Scheduled Castes or Scheduled Tribes, landless labourers and such other class or classes of persons as the State Government may, having regard to their economic backwardness, by notification, specify;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the expression “land” and the expression “person interested” shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Land Acquisition Act, 1894 (Central Act 1 of 1894) as amended by the Land Acquisition (Karnataka Extension and Amendment) Act; 1961.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Acquisition of land.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If at any time, in the opinion of the State Government any land is required for the purpose of providing house sites to the weaker sections of people who are houseless, the State Government may, by notification, give notice of its intention to acquire such land.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On the publication of a notification under sub-section (1), the State Government shall serve notice upon the owner or where the owner is not the occupier, on the occupier of the land and on all such persons known or believed to be interested therein to show cause, within thirty days from the date of service of the notice, why the land should not be acquired.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>After considering the cause, if any, shown by the owner of the land and by any other person interested therein, and after giving such owner and person an opportunity of being heard, the State Government may pass such orders as it deems fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>After orders are passed under sub-section (3), where the State Government is satisfied that any land should be acquired for the purpose specified in the notification issued under sub-section (1) a declaration shall, by notification , be made to that effect.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On the publication in the official Gazette of the declaration under sub-section (4), the land shall vest absolutely in the State Government free from all encumbrances.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any land is vested in the State Government under sub-section (5), the State Government may, by notice in writing, order any person who may be in possession of the land to surrender or deliver possession thereof to the State Government or any person duly authorised by it in this behalf within thirty days of the service of the notice.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person refuses or fails to comply with an order made under sub-section (6), the State Government or any officer authorised by the State Government in this behalf may take possession of the land and may for that purpose use such force as may be necessary.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Amount payable.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any land is acquired by the State Government under this Act, the State Government shall pay of such acquisition an amount in accordance with the provisions of this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the amount has been determined by agreement between the State Government and the person whose land has been acquired, it shall be paid in accordance with such agreement.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where no such agreement can be reached, the State Government shall refer the case to the Deputy Commissioner for determination of the amount to be paid for such acquisition as also the person or persons to whom such amount shall be paid.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On receipt of a reference under sub-section (3) the Deputy Commissioner shall serve notice on the owner or occupier of such land and on all persons known or believed to be interested therein to appear before him and state their respective interests in the said land.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Application of Central Act 1 of 1894.—-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of the Land Acquisition Act, 1894 (Central Act 1 of 1894) as amended by the Land Acquisition Karnataka Extension and Amendment) Act, 1961 shall, mutatis mutandis, apply in respect of enquiry and award by the Deputy Commissioner, the reference to Court, the apportionment of amount and the payment of amount in respect of lands acquired under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Delegation of powers by the State Government.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification, delegate subject to such conditions and restrictions as may be specified in such notification, any of its powers under this Act except the power to make rules under section 7, to any of its officers.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this Act shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made before each House of the State Legislature while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the 4 rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall from the date on which the modification or annulment is notified by the State Government in the official Gazette, have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
