<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1962/50/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1962/50"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Petroleum And Minerals Pipelines (Acquisition Of Right Of User In Land) Act, 1962"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1962/50/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1962/50/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1962/50/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1962/50/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-06-08" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Petroleum And Minerals Pipelines (Acquisition Of Right Of User In Land) Act, 1962</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[16th September, 1958.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>ACT NO. 29  OF 1958</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the fixation of rates of wages in respect of working journalists and for matters connected therewith.</p>
      </longTitle>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Ninth Year of the Republic of India as follows:―</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and application.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Petroleum and Minerals Pipelines (Acquisition of Right of User in Land) Act, 1962.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It applies in the first instance to the whole of the State of West Bengal, Bihar, Uttar Pradesh and Gujarat and the Union territory of Delhi; and the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare that this Act shall also apply to such other State or Union territory and with effect from such date as may be specified in that notification and thereupon provisions of this Act shall apply to that State or Union territory accordingly.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“competent authority” means any person or authority authorised by the Central Government, by notification in the Official Gazette, to perform the functions of the competent, authority under this Act and different persons or authorities may be authorised to perform all or any of the functions of the competent authority under this Act in the same area or different areas specified in the notification;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>“corporation” means any body corporate established under any Central, Provincial or State Act, and includes—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>a company formed and registered under the Companies Act, 1956; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>a company formed and registered under any law relating to companies formerly in force in any part of India;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.ba">
                    <num>(ba)</num>
                    <p>“minerals” have the meanings assigned to them in the Mines Act, 1952 (35 of 1952), and include mineral oils and stowing sand but do not include petroleum;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.c">
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <p>“petroleum” has the same meaning as in the Petroleum Act, 1934, and includes natural gas and refinery gas;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.d">
                    <num>(d)</num>
                    <p>“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Publication of notification for acquisition.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whenever it appears to the Central Government that it is necessary in the public interest that for the transport of petroleum or any mineral from one locality to another locality, pipelines may be laid by that Government or by any State Government or a corporation and that for the purpose of laying such pipelines, it is necessary to acquire the right of user in any land under which such pipelines may be laid, it may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare its intention to acquire the right of user therein.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every notification under sub‑section (1) shall give a brief description of the land.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The competent authority shall cause the substance of the notification to be published at such places and in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Power to enter, survey, etc.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>On the issue of a notification under sub-section</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>of section 3, it shall be lawful for any person authorised by the Central Government or by the State Government or the corporation which proposes to lay pipelines for transporting petroleum or any mineral and his servants and workmen—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to enter upon and survey and take levels of any land specified in the notification;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to dig or bore into the sub‑soil;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to set out the intended line or work;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>to mark such levels, boundaries and line by placing marks and cutting trenches;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>where otherwise survey cannot be completed and levels taken and the boundaries and line marked, to cut down and clear away any part of any standing crop, fence or jungle; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>to do all other acts necessary to ascertain whether pipelines can be laid under the land:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that while exercising any power under this section, such person or any servant or workman of such person shall cause as little damage or injury as possible to such land.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Hearing of objections.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person interested in the land may, within twenty‑one days from the date of the notification under sub‑section (1) of section 3, object to the laying of the pipelines under the land.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every objection under sub‑section (1) shall be made to the competent authority in writing and shall set out the grounds thereof and the competent authority shall give the objector and opportunity of being heard either in person or by a legal practitioner and may, after hearing all such objections and after making such further inquiry, if any, as that authority thinks necessary, by order either allow or disallow the objections.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any order made by the competent authority under sub‑section (2) shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Declaration of acquisition of right of user.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where no objections under sub‑section (1) of section 5 have been made to the competent authority with the period specified therein or where the competent authority has disallowed the objection under sub‑section (2) that section, the authority shall, as soon as may be either make a report in respect of the land described in the notification under such‑section (1) of section 3, or make different reports in respect of different parcels of such land, to the Central Government containing his recommendations on the objections, together with the record of the proceedings held by him, for the decision of that Government and upon receipt of such report the Central Government shall, if satisfied that such land is required for laying any pipelines for the transport of petroleum or any mineral declare, by notification in the Official Gazette, that the right of user in the land for laying the pipelines should be acquired and different declarations may be made from time to time in respect of different parcels of the land described in the notification issued under sub‑section (1) of section 3, irrespective of whether one report or different reports have been made by the competent authority under this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On the publication of the declaration under, sub‑section (1), the right of user in the land specified therein shall vest absolutely in the Central Government free from all encumbrances.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where in respect of any land, a notification has been issued under sub-section (1) of section 3 but no declaration in respect of any portion of land covered by that notification has been published under this section within a period of one year from the date of that notification, that notification shall cease to have effect on the expiration of that period.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3A">
          <num>(3A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No declaration in respect of any land covered by a notification issued under sub‑section (1) of section 3, published after the commencement of the Petroleum Pipelines (Acquisition of Right of User in Land) Amendment Act, 1977 shall be made after the expiry of three years from the date of such publication.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub‑section (2), the Central Government may, on such terms and conditions as it may think fit to impose, direct by order in writing, that the right of user in the land for laying the pipelines shall instead of vesting in the Central Government vest, either on the date of publication of the declaration or, on such other date as may be specified in the direction in the State Government or the corporation proposing to lay the pipelines and thereunder the right of such user in the land shall, subject to the terms and conditions so imposed; vest in that State Government or corporation, as the case may be, free from all encumbrances.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Central Government or State Government or Corporation to lay pipelines.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where the right of user in any land has vested in the Central Government or in any State Government or Corporation under section 6—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>it shall be lawful for any person authorised by the Central Government or such State Government or Corporation, as the case may be, and his servant and workmen to enter upon the land and lay pipelines or to do any other act necessary for laying of pipelines:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-7.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that no pipeline shall be laid under—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.1.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any land which, immediately before the date of the notification under sub‑section (1) of section 3, was used for residential purposes;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any land on which there stands any permanent structure which was in existence immediately before the said date;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any land which is appurtenant to a dwelling‑house; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <blockList id="section-7.1.list3.d.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>any land at a depth which is less than one metre from the surface; ***</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-7.1.list3.d.list0.ia">
                    <num>(ia)</num>
                    <p>for laying pipelines for the transport of petroleum, it shall be lawful for any person authorised by the Central Government or such State Government or corporation to use such land for laying pipelines for transporting any mineral and where the right of user in any land has so vested for laying pipelines for transporting any mineral, it shall be lawful for such person to use such land for laying pipelines for transporting petroleum or any other mineral; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-7.1.list3.d.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>such land shall be used only for laying the pipelines and for maintaining, examining, repairing, altering or removing any such pipelines or for doing any other act necessary for any of the aforesaid purposes or for the utilisation of such pipelines.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any dispute arises with regard to any matter referred to in paragraph (b) or paragraph (c) of the proviso to clause (i) of sub-section (1), the dispute shall be referred to the competent authority whose decision thereon shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Power to enter land for inspection etc.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>For maintaining, examining, repairing, altering or removing any pipeline, or for doing any other act necessary for the utilisation of the pipelines or for the making of any inspection or measurement for any of the aforesaid purposes, any person authorised in this behalf by the Central Government, the State Government or the corporation, as the case may be, may, after giving reasonable notice to the occupier of the land under which pipeline has been laid, enter therein with such workmen and assistants as may be necessary:</p>
            <p>Provided that, where such person is satisfied that an emergency exists, no such notice shall be necessary:</p>
            <p>Provided further that, while exercising any powers under this section, such person or any workman or assistant of such person, shall cause as little damage or injury as possible to such land.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Restrictions regarding the use of land.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The owner or occupier of the land with respect to which a declaration has been made under sub‑section (1) of section 6, shall be entitled to use the land for the purpose for which such land was put to use immediately before the date of the notification under sub-section (1) of section 3:</p>
            <blockList id="section-9.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that, such owner or occupier shall not after the declaration under sub‑section (1) of section 6—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.1.list2.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>construct any building or any other structure;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.1.list2.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>construct or excavate any tank, well, reservoir or dam; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.1.list2.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>plant any tree,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>on the land.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The owner or occupier of the land under which any pipeline has been laid shall not do any act or permit any act to be done which will or is likely to cause any damage in any manner whatsoever to the pipeline.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where the owner or occupier of the land with respect to which a declaration has been made under sub‑section (1) of section 6,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>constructs any building or any other structure, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>constructs or excavates any well, tank, reservoir or dam, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.3.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>plants any tree,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>on that land, the court of the District Judge within the local limits of whose jurisdiction such land is situate may, on an application made to it by, the competent authority and after holding such inquiry as it may deem fit, cause the building, structure, reservoir, dam or tree to be removed or the well or tank to be filled up, and the costs of such removal or filling up shall be recoverable from such owner or occupier in the same manner as if the order for the recovery of such costs were a decree made by the court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Compensation.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where in the exercise of the powers conferred by section 4, section 7, or section 8 by any person, any damage, loss or injury is sustained by any person interested in the land under which the pipeline is proposed to be, or is being or has been laid the Central Government, the State Government or the Corporations as the case may be, shall be liable to pay compensation to such person for such damage, loss or injury, the amount of which shall be determined by the competent authority in the first instance.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the amount of compensation determined by the competent authority under sub‑section (1) is not acceptable to either of the parties, the amount of compensation shall, on application by either of the parties to the District Judge within the limits of whose jurisdiction the land or any part thereof is situated, by determined by that District Judge.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The competent authority, or the District Judge while determining the compensation under sub‑section (1) or sub‑section (2), as the case may be, shall have due regard to the damage or loss sustained by any person interested in the land by reason of—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.3.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the removal of tress or standing crops, if any, on the land while exercising the powers under section 4, section 7 or section 8;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.3.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>the temporary severance of the land under which the pipeline has been laid from other lands belonging to, or in the occupation of, such person; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.3.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>any injury to any other property, whether movable or immovable or the earnings of such persons caused in any other manner:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that in determining the compensation no account shall be taken of any structure or other improvement made in the land after the date of the notification under sub‑section (1) of section 3.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the right of user of any land has vested in the Central Government, the State Government or the Corporation, as the case may be, shall, in addition to the compensation; if any, payable under sub‑section (1), be liable to pay to the owner and to any other person whose right of enjoyment in that land has been affected in any manner whatsoever by reason of such vesting, compensation calculated at ten per cent of the market‑value of that land on the date of the notification under sub‑section (1) of section 3.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The market‑value of the land on the said date shall be determined by the competent authority and if the value so determined by that authority is not acceptable to either of the parties, it shall, on application by either of the parties to District Judge referred to in sub‑section (2), be determined by that District Judge.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The decision of the District Judge under sub‑section (2) or sub‑section (5) shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Deposit and payment of compensation.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The amount of compensation determined under section 10 shall deposited by the Central Government, the State Government or the Corporation, as the case may be, with the competent authority within such time and in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the amount of compensation is not deposited within the time prescribed under sub‑section (1), the Central Government, the State Government or the Corporation, as the case may be, shall be liable to pay interest thereon at the rate of six per cent per annum from the date on which the compensation had to be deposited till the date of actual deposit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>As soon as may be after the compensation has been deposited under sub‑section (1), the competent authority shall, on behalf of the Central Government, the State Government or the Corporation, as the case may be, pay the compensation to the persons entitled thereto.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where several persons claim to be interested in the amount of compensation deposited under sub‑section (1), the competent authority shall determine the persons who in its opinion are entitled to receive the compensation and the amount payable to each of them.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any dispute arises as to the appointment of the compensation or any part thereof or as to the persons to whom the same or any part thereof is payable, the competent authority shall refer the dispute to the decision of the District Judge within the limits of whose jurisdiction the land or any part thereof is situated and the decision of the District Judge thereon shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Competent authority to have certain powers of civil court.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The competent authority shall have, for the purposes of this Act, all the powers of a civil court while trying a suit under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908, in respect of the following matters, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person and examining him on oath;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>requiring the discovery and production of any document;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>reception of evidence on affidavits;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>requisitioning any public record from any court or office;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>issuing commission for examination of witnesses.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any person for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any rule or notification made or issued thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central Government, the competent authority or any State Government, or Corporation for any damage, loss or injury caused or likely to be caused by anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any rule or notification made or issued thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Bar of jurisdiction of civil court.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Save as otherwise expressly provided in this Act, no civil court shall have jurisdiction in respect of any matter which the competent authority is empowered by or under this Act to determine and no injunction shall be granted by any court or other authority in respect of any action taken or proposed to be taken in pursuance of any power conferred by or under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Penalty.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever wilfully obstructs any person in doing any of the acts authorised by section 4 or section 7 or section 8 or wilfully fills up, destroys, damages or displaces any trench or mark made under section 4 or wilfully does any act prohibited under section 9, shall be punishable with imprisonment which may extend to six months or with fine or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever wilfully removes, displaces, damages or destroys any pipeline laid under section 7, shall be punishable with rigorous imprisonment for a term which shall be less, than one year, but which may extend to three years and shall also be liable to fine.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Certain offence to be cognizable.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898, an offence falling under sub‑section (2) of section 15 shall be deemed to be cognizable within the meaning of that Code.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-17.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may prove for all or any of the following matters namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the places at which and the manner in which the substance of the notification may be published under sub‑section (3) of section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the time within which and the manner in which the amount of compensation may be deposited under sub‑section (1) of section 11.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this Act shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have affect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so, however, that any such modification of annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Application of other laws not barred.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of this Act shall be in addition to, and not in derogation of, any other law for the time being in force relating to acquisition of land.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
