<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-tmn/act/1878/08/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-tmn/act/1878/08"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Tamil Nadu Coffee-Stealing Prevention Act, 1878"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-tmn/act/1878/08/eng@2017-01-20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-tmn/act/1878/08/eng@2017-01-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-20" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-tmn/act/1878/08/eng@2017-01-20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-tmn/act/1878/08/eng@2017-01-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-20" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Tamil Nadu Coffee-Stealing Prevention Act, 1878</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[28th September, 1878]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[No. 08 of 1878]</p>
        <p>An Act to prevent thefts of Coffee.</p>
        <p>Whereas it is expedient to make special provision to prevent thefts of coffee, and to repress and punish the offence of receiving or disposing of stolen coffee in the neighbourhood of coffee plantations or estates; It is enacted as follows:—</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Tamil Nadu Coffee-stealing Prevention Act, 1878.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Commencement and local extent of Act.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>This Act shall take effect in such districts, divisions or parts of districts, or within such localities or limits within the State of Tamil Nadu, and from such date as the State Government may from time to time direct by notification published in the Official Gazette.</p>
            <p>Power to annul or modify notification.— The State Government may from time to time modify or cancel such direction by notification similarly published.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Interpretation.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In this Act —</p>
            <p>"Labourer".— "labourer" means and includes all persons except resident managers temporarily or permanently employed on a coffee estate in any capacity, whether agricultural, menial or otherwise howsoever:</p>
            <p>"Carrier".— "carrier" means and includes all persons for the time being employed in the transport of coffee whether by porterage, pack-animals, boat, cart or otherwise, and whether as contractors, drivers or otherwise:</p>
            <p>"Coffee-estate".— "coffee-estate" means and includes any land on which coffee is growing:</p>
            <p>"Coffee".— "coffee" means and includes all coffee not roasted or otherwise prepared for immediate consumption.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Coffee not to be taken from labourer.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>It shall not be lawful for anyone to purchase, take in barter or exchange or receive coffee from any labourer employed on a coffee-estate.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Coffee not to be taken from other than labourer, unless particulars entered in book.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>It shall not be lawful for anyone to purchase, take in barter or exchange, or receive coffee from any person other than a labourer employed on a coffee-estate, unless the persons so purchasing, taking in barter or exchange, or receiving such coffee shall immediately thereupon enter or cause to be entered in a book to be kept by him for that purpose a true record of such transaction, specifying—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the name, residence and occupation of the person from whom such coffee was so purchased, taken in barter or exchange, or received:</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the date of the transaction; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the quantity and description of the coffee so purchased, taken in barter or exchange, or received:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Section not to apply to coffee taken for bonafide personal consumption.— Provided that this section shall not apply to coffee purchased, taken in barter or exchange or received from any person other than a labourer employed on a coffee-estate, and intended bona fide for consumption in the house or on the premises of the person purchasing, taking in barter or exchange, or receiving the same as aforesaid.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5A">
        <num>5A.</num>
        <heading>Person in charge of coffee-estate to maintain a book of his transactions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5A.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Every person in charge of a coffee-estate, whether he be owner thereof or not, who sells, gives in barter or exchange, or delivers any coffee, shall immediately thereupon enter or cause to be entered in a book to be kept by him for that purpose a true record of such transaction specifying—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5A.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the name, residence and occupation of the person to whom such coffee was so sold, given in barter or exchange, or delivered;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5A.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the date of the transaction; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5A.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the quantity and description of the coffee so Bold, given in barter or exchange, or delivered.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Books to be produced on Police Officers requisition.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>All books required to be kept by sections 5 and 5-A shall be produced upon the requisition of any police-officer not below the rank of an officer in charge of a police station, generally or specially authorized by any Magistrate to require the production of such books.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Conditions under which coffee may be taken from a carrier.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>It shall not be lawful for anyone to purchase or take in barter or exchange coffee from any carrier, or for any carrier to sell or give in barter or exchange any coffee, unless the person so purchasing or taking in barter or exchange such coffee shall, besides making the entry required by section 5 of this Act , also enter or cause to be entered in the book mentioned in the said section 5 the marks (if any) on the bags or other packages in which such coffee may be contained, and unless the entries required by this section and by the said section 5 be also correctly signed by such carrier in his own name, and attested by a police-officer or the headman of the village within which the transaction takes place; for which attestation no fee shall be chargeable.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for breach of section 4, 5, 5-A, 6 or 7.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any person committing any breach of the provisions contained in section 4, 5, and 5A, 6 or 7 of this Act shall be liable, on conviction by a Magistrate, to pay a fine not exceeding five hundred rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Penalty in case of labourer being found in possession of green coffee for which he cannot account.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any coolie, maistri or other labourer employed on a coffee-estate found with green gathered parchment or cherry-dried coffee in his possession, and failing to account satisfactorily for such possession, shall be liable, on conviction by a Magistrate, to pay a fine not exceeding five hundred rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Coffee not to be carried without permission of owner or agent.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No person shall carry or remove coffee from any coffee-estate, premises or place, or upon any road, highway or footway, without the express permission of the owner or of his authorized agent.</p>
            <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Permission to be in writing etc.— Such permission shall be in writing, dated and signed by the said owner or his authorized agent, and shall contain the following particulars:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the quantity of the coffee to be carried or removed;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the number, description and marks of the packages in which coffee is secured;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the place or destination to which the coffee is to be carried or removed; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the names of the consignor and consignee.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Penalty for breach of this section.— Any person committing any breach of the provisions of this section shall, on conviction by a Magistrate, be liable to pay a fine not exceeding five hundred rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Hours of gathering or removing coffee.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No coffee shall be gathered, moved, loaded or unloaded on any coffee-estate between sunset and sunrise.</p>
            <p>Penalty for breach of above provision.— Any person committing a breach of this provision, or abetting (within the meaning of the Indian Penal Code) (Central Act XLV of 1860) such breach, shall, on conviction by a Magistrate, be liable to pay a fine not exceeding five hundred rupees:</p>
            <p>Section 10 and this section not to apply to ordinary operations of curing.— Provided that nothing in section 10 or in this section shall apply to the ordinary operations of curing the crop on the estate such as pulping or storing.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Procedure if gathering, etc., was done to commit theft.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If it shall appear that such gathering, moving, loading or unloading was for the purpose of committing a theft, the person or persons so engaged shall be liable to be charged with theft, or abetment of theft, and be proceeded against for such offence under the provisions of sections 378 and 379 or sections 107, 108 and 109 of the Indian Penal Code (XLV of 1860), as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Omitted</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Fines to be paid into public treasury.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>All fines paid or levied under this Act shall be paid into the public treasury:</p>
            <p>Magistrate may grant rewards to informers.— Provided that the Magistrate trying any case under this Act may 15[after reasons to be recorded in writing] grant the whole or any portion of any fine levied therein as rewards to persons furnishing such information as may have led to the conviction of offenders under this Act .</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Duties of a person in charge of coffee-estate.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>It shall be the duty of every person in charge of a coffee-estate whether he be owner thereof or not, to keep such books and to furnish such returns in connection with the coffee-estate or the coffee grown thereon at such times and to such authorities as may be prescribed by the State Government of Madras, and to afford to such officers as may be generally or specially designated in that behalf by the Collector all reasonable facilities for verifying the correctness of such books and returns, and for obtaining such other information as may be required for the preparation in public offices of such statistics as the State Government of Madras may prescribe.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The State Government of Madras may after previous publication make rules—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>prescribing forms for the books, returns and statistics referred to in section 15;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>regulating the time at which and the authority to whom such returns are to be furnished;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>regulating the inspection and examination of such books, returns and statistics; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>generally for carrying out the purposes of this Act ; and all such rules shall be published in the Official Gazette and shall thereupon have the force of law</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for failure to comply with the provisions of section 15.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any person failing without reasonable excuse to comply with the provisions of section 15 of this Act shall be liable on conviction by a Magistrate to pay a fine not exceeding one hundred rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
