<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-pun/act/1948/13/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-pun/act/1948/13"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The East Punjab Exchange of Prisoners Act, 1948"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-pun/act/1948/13/eng@1948-04-05/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-pun/act/1948/13/eng@1948-04-05"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1948-04-05" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-pun/act/1948/13/eng@1948-04-05/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-pun/act/1948/13/eng@1948-04-05"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-12-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The East Punjab Exchange Of Prisoners Act, 1948</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[Act 13 of 1948]</p>
        <p>[April 5, 1948]</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <part id="part-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <heading>Preliminary and Interpretation</heading>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title, and extent.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the East Punjab Exchange of Prisoners Act, 1948</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall extend to the whole of State Punjab.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Interpretation.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context ­</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the expression ‘prison’ includes a central, district or subsidiary jail, a judicial lock-up and every place which is used as a place of detention for persons who have been arrested or detained under any law for the time being in force;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the expression ‘prisoner’ includes every person who is detained in a prison by order of a competent authority not being a Civil Court;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the expression ‘transferable prisoner’ means any Muslim prisoner who is in custody in any prison in Punjab under lawful orders of a duly empowered Court or other authority and who is willing to be transferred to *** Pakistan under the provisions of Part II; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the expression ‘repatriated prisoner’ means a person who being in custody in a prison or other place of detention in the Province of Punjab in Pakistan or in any State which being adjacent to that Province, has acceded to Pakistan is conveyed and delivered by a duly authorised official of the Government of Pakistan or the Government of Punjab in Pakistan in compliance with the orders of such Government, to an official of the Punjab Government.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <heading>The Transfer of Prisoners</heading>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Removal of transferable prisoners.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may issue a warrant addressed to the officer in charge of a prison to deliver any transferable prisoner confined therein, along with all the records relating to such prisoner and the personal effects taken from him at the time of his admission to a person to the prison authorised in that behalf in the aforesaid warrant.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The officer in charge of the prison shall forthwith comply with the warrant issued under sub-section (1), and the person to whom delivery of the prisoner and any record or article is made shall furnish to such officer in charge a written receipt in respect of such delivery.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The person taking such delivery shall deliver, the transferable prisoner and any records or article relating to that prisoner at such place as the State Government may specify, and to such official of the Government of Pakistan or the Government of Punjab in Pakistan, as the State Government may by general or special order and either by name or designation provide; and thereupon all Courts, Tribunals or authorities whatsoever in Punjab shall cease to have jurisdiction in relation to such prisoner in respect of the offence or other matter which was the cause of his confinement in Punjab.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may requisition the record of any proceedings (including judicial proceedings) in relation to a prisoner transferred under sub-section (3) from any Court or office where such record may be kept and may direct that such record shall be sent to any official or authority of the Government of Punjab in Pakistan or of the Government of Pakistan.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Examination of witnesses on commission.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>If in regard to any criminal proceeding pending before a court in Pakistan against a transferable prisoner who has been transferable to Pakistan under section 3, a latter of request issued by such Court is received by the District Magistrate of any district in Punjab for the examination of any witness residing in such district, the District Magistrate shall appoint for the purpose any Magistrate subordinate to him and thereupon the provisions of Chapter XL of the Code of Criminal Procedure (V of 1898) shall so far as may be applicable in regard to the compliance with such letter of request:­</p>
              <p>Provided that any person duly authorised in that behalf by the Government of Pakistan or by the Government of Punjab in Pakistan shall be entitled to be present at the examination of such witness.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <heading>The Repatriation of Prisoners</heading>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Custody and removal of repatriated prisoners.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may by general or special order specify the place at which and, either by name or designation, the official by whom custody of a repatriated prisoner, together with any article or records which may have been sent along with him, shall be received and the prison to which he is to be removed, and the officer in charge of such prison shall thereupon receive such prisoner and any article or records which may be produced along with him.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Convicted prisoners.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The officer in charge of the prison shall detain in custody a repatriated prisoner who, before his repatriation, was a convict undergoing a sentence in a prison –</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>according to the tenor of the warrant, writ or order of commitment to prison, if any, relating to such prisoner, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>failing such warrant, writ or order as aforesaid in accordance with the order of the State Government.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Prisoners undergoing trial before repatriation.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may direct any Court, other than the High Court, to enquire into or try any case which may have been pending against a repatriated prisoner immediately before his repatriation :-</p>
              <blockList id="section-7.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that –</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.1.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the offence charged against such prisoner is also an offence under the law in force in Punjab; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.1.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>such court would have been competent to try such offence if it had been committed within the local limits of its jurisdiction.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On the making of an order under sub-section (1) the Court specified in the order shall proceed to enquire into to try such case according to law, as if the offence to which it relates had been committed within the local limits of its jurisdiction, and all the provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure (V of 1898) and all other laws in force in Punjab shall so far as may be, apply to such proceedings.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In any proceedings under sub-section (2), all evidence, both oral and documentary, which has been duly received in the proceedings against the repatriated prisoner held prior to his repatriation, or the copies of such evidence certified under section 76 of the Indian Evidence Act (1 of 1872), may be treated as evidence in the case for all purposes subject to the provisions of the Indian Evidence Act (1 of 1872).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Prisoners repatriated while in police custody.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may in respect of any, repatriated prisoner, who, immediately before repatriation, was held under arrest or detention in police custody during or after completion of a police investigation, specify a Judicial Magistrate of the first class who shall have and exercise jurisdiction.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every repatriated prisoner in respect of whom an order has been made under sub-section (1) shall be produced without delay before the Magistrate specified in the order, and such Magistrate may take cognizance of any offence that such repatriated prisoner may be reported by a police officer to have committed, and may grant him bail.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where the repatriation was effected before completion of the police investigation, or the Magistrate is of the opinion that the evidence is deficient, the repatriated prisoner shall be released upon his entering into a bond with or without sureties, as the Magistrate may direct, to appear if and when so required, and in the meantime, the Magistrate may order such further enquiry into the substance of the allegations as he thinks fit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In every case falling under sub-section (3), the Magistrate may, if he is satisfied at any stage that there is no prospect of securing sufficient evidence to justify commencement of proceedings against the repatriated prisoner, direct that such prisoner be discharged from his bond.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Delegation of power.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, by notification, delegate all or any of its powers under sections 5, 6, 7 and 8 to any public servant, either by name or the designation.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Power of State Government in relation to prisoners detained for reasons of security.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>In relation to any repatriated prisoner whose detention immediately before his repudiation had been ordered under any law authorising preventive detention for reasons connected with public order, the State Government shall have the same power in respect of extension or reduction of the term of detention as it possesses in relation to persons detained under section 3 of the Punjab Public Security Act, 1947 (Punjab Act II of 1947) as in force in Punjab.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Jurisdiction of the High Court.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The High Court of Judicature of the State of Punjab shall have, in relation to a repatriated prisoner, the same jurisdiction which it has in region to a person who has been arrested or detained within the limits of its appellate jurisdiction, in the same circumstances in which such prisoner was arrested or detained immediately before his repatriation.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Power of State Government to suspend, remit or commute sentence.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Government shall have the same power to suspend, remit or commute a sentence of punishment awarded to a repatriated prisoner, whether before or after his repatriation as it possesses in relation to persons who have been sentenced in the State for offences committed within State.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <heading>General</heading>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Lawfulness of custody and retaking upon escape.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>It shall be lawful for any person from a warrant or order under section 3 or under section 5 or Section 6 is directed to retaking hold in custody, convey and deliver the transferable or repatriated prisoner, named in warrant or order as directed therein and if any such prisoner, escapes out of any custody which he may be delivered in pursuance of any warrant, he may be retaken as a person accrued convicted of an offence against the law of the Punjab may be taken upon an escape.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Operation of Ordinance.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of this Act shall have force and operation notwithstanding anything contrary or repugnant thereto in any other law for the time being in force.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Repeal of Ordinance No. 1 of 1948.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The East Punjab (Exchange of Prisoners) Ordinance, 1948, is hereby repealed; and any rules made or notification issued, anything done and any action taken in exercise of any power conferred by or under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been made, issued, as done or taken in exercise of powers conferred by or under this Act if this Act had commenced on the 12th day of January, 1948.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
