<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1963/32/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1963/32"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Karnataka Famine Relief Fund Act 1963"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1963/32/eng@2017-07-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1963/32/eng@2017-07-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-07-24" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1963/32/eng@2017-07-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1963/32/eng@2017-07-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-07-24" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Karnataka Famine Relief Fund Act 1963</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[7th November 1963]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No. 32 of 1963</p>
        <p>Preamble—</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the establishment and maintenance in the State of Karnataka of a Fund for meeting the expenditure on occasions of famine or of distress caused by drought, flood, fire and other natural calamities in the State.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the establishment and maintenance in the State of Karnataka of a Fund for meeting expenditure on occasions of famine, or of distress caused by drought, flood, fire and other natural calamities in the State;</p>
      </longTitle>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by the Karnataka State Legislature in the Fourteenth Year of the Republic of India as follows:—</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Karnataka Famine Relief Fund Act, 1963.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall extend to the whole of the State of Karnataka.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the State Government may, by notification in the official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“Fund” means the established under section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“State” means the State of Karnataka.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Establishment of the Karnataka Famine Relief Fund.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>On the commencement of this Act, the State Government shall establish in and for the State, a Fund called “The Karnataka Famine Relief Fund ”, which shall consist of,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>such of the Government securities which belong to the Famine Relief Fund established under the Bombay Famine Relief Fund Act, 1936 (Bombay Act XIX of 1936), and the Madras Famine Relief Fund Act, 1936 (Madras Act XVI of 1936), and transferred to the State of Karnataka as successor State under section 80 of the States Reorganisation Act, 1956 (Central Act 37 of 1956);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>such amounts of the Famine Relief Funds of the pre-reorganised States of Mysore and Hyderabad as were invested in the securities of the Central or State Governments and transferred to the State of Karnataka as successor State under section 80 of the States Reorganisation Act, 1956 (Central Act 37 of 1956);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>the interest which may from time to time accrue on the securities referred to in clauses (i) and (ii);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>such sums as the State Government may from time to time contribute to the fund under sub-section (2) of section 6 or otherwise; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>the interest which may from time to time accrue on the securities of the Fund invested or re-invested under section 5;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Purpose for which the Fund may be utilised.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Fund shall be expended only upon,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>relief of famine in the State; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>the relief of distress caused by drought, flood, fire or other natural calamities in the State: Provided that when the Fund exceeds sixty lakhs of rupees, the State Government may utilise the excess to meet expenditure on protective minor irrigation works and other works as may be prescribed, for the prevention of famine in the State, or for the grant of loans to cultivators either under the Karnataka land Improvement Loans Act, 1963 (Karnataka Act 16 of 1963), or under the Karnataka Agriculturists’ Loans Act, 1963 (Karnataka Act 17 of 1963), or for relief purposes, or in the repayment of advances made by the State Government, or to meet irrecoverable balances of loans granted under the said Act or for relief purposes.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Investment and re-investment of amounts not required.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government shall from time to time invest or re-invest in the securities of Government all sums to the credit of the Fund which may not be immediately required for any of the purposes mentioned in section 4.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Accounts of the Fund and making up of the deficiency in the Fund.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The accounts of the Fund shall be made up at the end of each financial year, the securities belonging to the Fund being valued at the market value on the last day of such year.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the accounts so made up show that the balance of the Fund at the end of such year falls short of sixty lakhs of rupees, the deficiency shall be made up from the Consolidated Fund of the State:</p>
            <p>Provided that if the deficiency exceeds twenty lakhs of rupees, it may be made up in annual instalments, the amount of such instalments except the last being not less than ten lakhs of rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any expenditure incurred by the State Government under sub-section (2) shall be charged on the Consolidated Fund of the State.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may by notification published in the official Gazette make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of the State Legislature while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session in which it is so laid or the session immediately following, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
