<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1981/61/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1981/61"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Maharashtra Advocates Welfare Fund Act, 1981"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1981/61/eng@2017-03-15/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1981/61/eng@2017-03-15"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-15" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1981/61/eng@2017-03-15/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1981/61/eng@2017-03-15"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-15" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Maharashtra Advocates Welfare Fund Act, 1981</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[5th November, 1981]</docDate>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 61 OF 1981</docNumber>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Preamble</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the constitution of an Advocates Welfare Fund and utilization thereof for payment of certain retirement and other benefits to the Advocates in Maharashtra.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the constitution of an Advocates Welfare Fund and utilization thereof for the payment of certain retirement and other benefits to the Advocates in the State of Maharashtra and for matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.</p>
        <p>It is hereby enacted in the Thirty-second Year of the Republic of India as follows:</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <heading>Preliminary</heading>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title, extent and commencement</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the Maharashtra Advocates Welfare Fund Act, 1981.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Maharashtra.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on such date as the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette appoint.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>“Advocate” means a person whose name has been enrolled on the roll of advocates prepared and maintained by the Bar Council of Maharashtra and Goa under section 17 of the Advocates Act and who is domiciled in the State of Maharashtra and a member of any Bar Association;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>"Advocates Act" means the Advocates Act, 1961;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>"Advocates Welfare Fund" or "Fund" means the fund constituted and maintained under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.ca">
                  <num>(ca)</num>
                  <p>“Amendment Act” means the Maharashtra Advocates Welfare Fund (Amendment) Act, 2015;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>"Bar Association" means an association of Advocates attached to any Court or any Tribunal or such other authority or person as is legally authorised to take evidence or to adjudicate or decide any disputes in the State of Maharashtra and recognised by the Bar Council under section 14;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>"Bar Council" means the Bar Council of Maharashtra and Goa, constituted under section 3 of the Advocates Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>"cessation of practice" means removal of the name of an Advocate from the State roll maintained by the Bar Council on account of his retirement or death;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>“dependents” means wife, husband, father, mother, minor children or any married daughter who is divorced or who is depending on the member of the Fund;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.ga">
                  <num>(ga)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.ga.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>“existing member of the Fund” means an Advocate who is member of the Fund on the date of commencement of the Amendment Act;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.ga.list0.gb">
                      <num>(gb)</num>
                      <p>“fund” means the Advocates Welfare Fund constituted under section 3;</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>"member of the Fund" means an Advocate admitted to the benefit of the Fund and continuing to be a member thereof under the provisions of this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>"prescribed" means prescribed by the Bar Council by regulations made under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>"retirement" means stoppage of practice as an Advocate communicated to and recorded by the Bar Council;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.ja">
                  <num>(ja)</num>
                  <p>“retirement from the Fund” means voluntary retirement of any member of the Fund after being member of the Fund for fifteen years from the date of becoming the member of the Fund;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>"stamp" or "welfare fund stamp" means the stamp printed and distributed by the Bar Council under section 18;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>"State" means the State of Maharashtra;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.m">
                  <num>(m)</num>
                  <p>"suspension of practice" means voluntary suspension of practice as an Advocate or suspension by the Bar Council for misconduct under Advocates Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.n">
                  <num>(n)</num>
                  <p>"Trustee Committee" or "Committee" means the Committee established under section 4;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.o">
                  <num>(o)</num>
                  <p>"Vakalatnama" includes a memorandum of appearance or any other document by whatever name called and includes any authority letter, by which an Advocate is empowered to act, appear or plead before any Court, or any Tribunal or such other authority or person as is referred to in section 14 legally authorised to take evidence or to adjudicate or decide any disputes.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <heading>Constitution of Advocates Welfare Fund</heading>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Constitution of Advocates Welfare Fund.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government shall constitute a fund called the Advocates Welfare Fund.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>There shall be credited to the Fund --</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>an initial amount of Rs. 10,000 or such other higher amount as the Bar Council may credit to this Fund before the 31st December, 1981; and all amounts paid by the Bar Council annually from the year 1982 onwards under sub-section (3);</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>any other contribution made by the Bar Council;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>any voluntary donation or contribution made to the Fund by the Bar Council of India, or any Bar Association or any Advocates;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>all sums collected by way of sale of stamps under section 18;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>any grants which may be made by the State Government to the Fund under appropriation duly made in this behalf;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.2.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>any grants, donations, gifts, benefactions received from other institutions or persons and credited to the Fund, from time to time;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.2.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>any sum borrowed under section 12;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.2.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>all sums received from the Life Insurance Corporation of India on the death of any member of the Fund under any Group Insurance Policy;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.2.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>any profit or dividend received from the Life Insurance Corporation of India in respect of policies of Group Insurance of the members of the Fund;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.2.list1.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>all sums collected under section 16 by way of application fees and subscriptions and interest thereon;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.2.list1.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>any interest or dividend or other return on any investment made of any part of the Fund.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Bar Council shall pay to the Fund annually an amount at such rate not exceeding 20 per cent, of the enrolment fees realised by it, as the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, notify from time to time.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <heading>Establishment of Trustee Committee and Vesting of Welfare Fund in that Committee</heading>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Establishment of Trustee Committee.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, establish, with effect from such date as may be specified therein, a Committee to be called the Maharashtra Advocates Welfare Fund Trustee Committee.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Trustee Committee shall be a body corporate having perpetual succession and a common seal with power to acquire, hold and dispose of property and to contract and shall by the said name sue and be sued.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-4.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Trustee Committee shall consist of the following members, namely :</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the Advocate General of Maharashtra, who shall be the Chairman of the Trustee Committee, ex officio;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.3.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the Secretary to Government, Law and Judiciary Department of the Government of Maharashtra, ex officio;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.3.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>three members nominated by the State Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.3.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>two members of the Bar Council nominated by the Bar Council;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.3.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the accountant of the Bar Council, who shall be the treasurer of the Trustee Committee, ex officio; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.3.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the Secretary of the Bar Council, who shall be the Secretary of the Trustee Committee, ex officio.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A member nominated by the State Government under clause (c) of sub-section (3) shall hold office for a term of four years, unless the State Government terminates his nomination earlier or he is removed under sub-section (2) of section 5 or he resigns his membership and his resignation is accepted by the State Government under sub-section (1) of section 6.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A member nominated by the Bar Council under clause (d) of sub-section (3) shall hold office for a term of four years or for the duration of his membership in the Bar Council, whichever is less, unless he is removed under sub-section (2) of section 5 or he resigns his membership and his resignation is accepted by the Bar Council under sub-section (1) of section 6.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Disqualifications and removal of nominated members of Trustee Committee</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-5.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>A member nominated under clause (c) or clause (d) of sub-section (3) of section 4 shall be disqualified to be a member of the Trustee Committee, if he -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>becomes of unsound mind; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-5.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>is adjudged insolvent; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-5.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>is absent without leave of the Trustee Committee for more than three consecutive meetings of the Committee; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-5.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>is a defaulter to the Fund (in case he is a member of the Fund) or has committed a breach of trust; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-5.1.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>is convicted by a Criminal Court for an offence involving moral turpitude, unless such conviction has been set aside.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may remove any member who is or has become disqualified under sub-section (1) from membership of the Trustee Committee:</p>
              <p>Provided that, no order removing any member shall be passed unless that member and the Bar Council in the case of a member nominated by it have been given an opportunity of being heard:</p>
              <p>Provided further that, nothing in this section shall apply where the State Government terminates the membership of a member nominated by it under sub-section (4) of section 4, on the ground other than incurring any of the disqualification and removal under this subsection.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Resignation by nominated members of Trustee Committee and filling up of casual vacancies.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any member nominated under clause (c) or clause (d) of sub-section (3) of section 4 may resign his office by giving one month's notice in writing to the State Government or the Bar Council, as the case may be, and on such resignation being accepted by the State Government or the Bar Council, shall be deemed to have vacated his office:</p>
              <p>Provided that, the Bar Council shall consult the State Government before accepting the resignation of a member nominated by it.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A casual vacancy in the office of a member nominated under clause (c) or clause (d) of sub-section (3) of section 4 occurring on account of death, resignation, termination or removal of a member may be filled up, as soon as conveniently may be, by nomination of a person thereto by the State Government or, the Bar Council, as the case may be, and a person so nominated shall hold office so long as the member in whose place he is nominated would have held it, if the vacancy had not occurred.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Members to act during vacancy, acts of Trustee Committee, etc., not to be invalidated by informalities.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>During any vacancy in a Trustee Committee the continuing members may act as if no vacancy had occurred.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Trustee Committee shall have power to act, notwithstanding any vacancy in the membership or any defect in the constitution thereof, or any defect or irregularity in the nomination of any person as a member thereof, or any defect or irregularity in any act done or proceeding taken under this Act or the regulations made there under not affecting the merits of the case; and such proceedings of the Committee shall be valid notwithstanding that it is discovered subsequently that some person who was not entitled to do so sat or voted or otherwise took part in the proceedings or that some defect or irregularity as aforesaid existed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Meetings of Trustee Committee.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Trustee Committee shall meet, at least once in three calendar months or more often if found necessary to transact business under this Act or the regulations made there under.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Three members of the Trustee Committee shall form the quorum for a meeting of the Committee.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chairman or, in his absence, a member elected, shall preside over a meeting of the Trustee Committee.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any matter coming up before a meeting of the Trustee Committee shall be decided by a majority of the members present and voting at the meeting and, in the case of an equality of votes, the Chairman or the member presiding over the meeting shall have a casting vote.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Travelling and daily allowance to members of Trustee Committee.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The non-official members of the Trustee Committee shall be eligible to get such travelling allowance and daily allowance as are admissible to the members of the Bar Council:</p>
              <p>Provided that, if a member of the Committee is a Member of the Maharashtra Legislative Assembly or Maharashtra Legislative Council or a Member of Parliament the allowances payable to such member shall be the travelling and daily allowances or such other allowances which are payable to him as a member of the State Legislature or of Parliament, as the case may be, for the purpose of meeting the personal expenditure in attending the meeting of the State Legislature or Parliament or its Committees.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Vesting and application of Fund.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Fund shall vest in, and be held and applied by, the Trustee Committee, subject to the provisions, and for the purposes, of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Functions of Trustee Committee.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Trustee Committee shall administer the Fund.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-11.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In the administration of the Fund, the Trustee Committee shall, subject to the provisions of this Act and the regulations made there under,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>hold the amounts and assets belonging to the Fund in trust;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>receive applications for admission or readmission to the Fund, and dispose of such applications within ninety days from the date of receipt thereof;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>receive applications from the members of the Fund, their nominees or legal representatives, as the case may be, for payment out of the Fund, conduct such enquiry as it deems necessary for the disposal of such applications and dispose of the applications within five months from the date of receipt thereof;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>record in the minute book of the Trustee Committee, its decisions on the applications;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>pay to the applicants amounts at the rates specified in the Schedule;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>sanction employment of such officers and servants as it may think necessary for performance of its duties and functions under this Act and determine their conditions of service;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>send such periodical and annual reports as may be prescribed to the State Government and the Bar Council;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>communicate to the applicants by registered post with acknowledgement due the decisions of the Trustee Committee in respect of applications for admission or readmission to the Fund or claims to the benefit of the Fund.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>do such other acts as are, or may be, required to be done by it under this Act and the regulations made there under.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Funds, borrowing and investment.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-12.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Trustee Committee may, with the recommendation of the Bar Council and the prior approval of the State Government, borrow, from time to time, any sum required for carrying out the purposes of the Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Trustee Committee shall deposit all moneys and receipts forming part of the Fund in any scheduled bank or invest the same in the units issued by the Unit Trust of India, the National Post Office Savings Certificates or any other Government Security or in loans to any corporation owned or controlled by the Central Government or the State Government or in loans floated by the Central Government or the State Government or in any other manner as the Bar Council may, from time to time, direct with the prior approval of the State Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All amounts due and payable under this Act and all expenditure relating to the management and administration of the Fund shall be paid out of the Fund.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The accounts of the Trustee Committee shall be audited annually by the Chief Auditor, Local Fund Accounts or any other person empowered by the State Government to perform the functions of an auditor under the Bombay Local Fund Audit Act, 1930, as if the Fund were a Local Fund and the Trustee Committee were a local authority within the meaning of these expressions in the said Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The accounts of the Trustee Committee, as certified by the auditor, together with the audit report thereon, shall be forwarded to the Bar Council by the Trustee Committee and the Bar Council may issue such directions as it deems fit to the Trustee Committee in respect thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Trustee Committee shall comply with the report of the auditor and the directions issued by the Bar Council under sub-section (5) as early as possible but in any case within a period of three months from the date of receipt of such audit report or directions;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Powers and duties of Secretary.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Secretary of the Trustee Committee shall --</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>be the chief executive authority of the Trustee Committee and responsible for carrying out its decisions;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>represent the Trustee Committee in all suits and proceedings for and against the Committee;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>authenticate by his signature all decisions and instructions of the Trustee Committee;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>operate the bank accounts of the Trustee Committee jointly with the Treasurer;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>convene meetings of the Trustee Committee and prepare their minutes;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>attend the meetings of the Trustee Committee with all the necessary records and information;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>maintain such forms, registers and other records as may be prescribed from time to time and do all correspondence relating to the Trustee Committee;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>inspect and verify periodically the accounts and registers of the Bar Associations regarding the stamps;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>prepare an annual statement of business transacted by the Trustee Committee during each financial year;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>make appointments of the officers and servants of the Trustee Committee as sanctioned by the Committee and have power to take disciplinary action against any such officer or servant;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>do such other acts as may be directed by the State Government, the Trustee Committee and the Bar Council.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <heading>Recognition and Registration of Bar Associations</heading>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Recognition and Registration of Bar Associations.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All associations of Advocates known by any name functioning in any Court, or before any Tribunal, or before any other authority or person legally authorised to take evidence or to adjudicate or decide any disputes may, before a date to be notified or before such extended date as may be notified by the Bar Council in this behalf, apply to the Bar Council, in such form as may be prescribed for recognition and registration.</p>
              <p>Any association of Advocates constituted after the date of commencement of this Act may, at any time thereafter likewise apply to the Bar Council for recognition and registration.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every application for recognition and registration shall be accompanied by the rules or by-rules of the association, the names and addresses of the office-bearers of the association and an up-to-date list of the members of the association showing the name, address, age, date of enrolment and the ordinary place of practice of each member.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Bar Council may, after such enquiry as it deems necessary, recognise the association and issue a certificate of registration in such form as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The decision of the Bar Council regarding the recognition and registration of a Bar Association shall be final.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Duties of Bar Association.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-15.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every Bar Association shall, on or before the 15th April every year, intimate to the Bar Council a list of its members as on the 31st March of that year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-15.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Every Bar Association recognized and registered as per sub­section (1) of section 14 shall intimate to the Bar Council -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-15.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>any change of the office-bearers of the association within fifteen days from such change;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-15.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>any change in the membership, including admissions and readmissions, within thirty days of such change;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-15.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the death, retirement or voluntary suspension of practice of any of its members within thirty days from the date of occurrence thereof; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-15.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>such other matters as may be prescribed or required by the Bar Council from time to time.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <heading>Membership in the Fund and Payment Thereof</heading>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Membership in the Fund.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-16.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every Advocate practising before any Court, or any Tribunal, or any other authority or person legally authorised to take evidence or to adjudicate or decide any disputes in the State and being a member of a Bar Association recognised by the Bar Council under section 14 shall apply to the Trustee Committee for admission as a member of the Fund, in such form as may be prescribed.</p>
              <p>Provided that, every Advocate who is not the existing member of the Fund on the date of commencement of the Amendment Act shall apply for admission as a member of the Fund within a period of six months from the date of commencement of the said Amendment Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On receipt of an application under sub-section (1), the Trustee Committee shall make such enquiry as it deems fit and either admit the applicant to the Fund or for reasons to be recorded in writing reject the application:</p>
              <p>Provided that, no order rejecting an application shall be passed unless the applicant has been given an opportunity of being heard.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-16.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>An application fee shall --</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-16.3.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>in the case of an applicant who, on the date of application has practised for a period of ten years or more, be one thousand rupees; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.3.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>in the case of an applicant who, on the date of application has practised for a period of less than ten years, be five hundred rupees;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that, an applicant belonging to Scheduled Castes or Scheduled Tribes shall pay an application fee equal to the half of the amount of fee specified in clause (i) or clause (ii), as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the event of the rejection of any application the application fees paid shall be refunded to the applicant.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-16.5.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Every member of the Fund shall pay rupees ten thousand only as subscription in the following manner, namely:—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-16.5.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>when the standing of the advocate at the time of his admission as a member of the Fund is ten or more years, he shall pay the said amount in lump sum at one time;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.5.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>when the standing of the advocate at the time of his admission as a member of the Fund is less than ten years, he may pay the said amount in one lump sum or in four equal yearly instalments with the condition that after payment of first instalment, the remaining three instalments will fall due on even dates in subsequent three years:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-16.5.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that, the existing members of the Fund shall pay the said subscription amount after deduction of the annual subscription paid by them prior to the commencement of the Amendment Act: Provided further that, after the date of commencement of the Amendment Act,—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-16.5.list3.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the existing members having standing of ten or more years on the said date, shall pay the balance of subscription within one year from such commencement; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.5.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the existing members having standing of less than ten years on the said date, shall pay the balance of subscription in one lump sum or in four equal instalments with the condition that first instalment shall be paid within one year from such commencement and remaining three instalments will fall due on even dates in subsequent three years.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any advocate fails to pay the lump sum subscription or the instalment, as the case may be, in the manner laid down in sub­section (5), then such advocate shall be liable to pay the penalty of rupees fifty per month for the period of default from the due date till the date of payment.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any member who fails to remit the subscription or yearly instalments, as the case may be, on or before due dates mentioned in sub-section (5) or sub-section (6) shall after giving him one month's notice in writing be liable to be removed by the Trustee Committee from the membership of the Fund.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A person removed from the membership of the Fund under subsection (7) shall be readmitted to the Fund on payment of the arrears with interest at twelve per cent per annum within six months from the date of removal.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every member shall, at the time of admission to the membership of the Fund, make a nomination conferring on one or more persons the right to receive the amount which may be due to him from the Fund in the event of his death before the amount has been paid to him.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.10">
            <num>(10)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a member nominates more than one person under subsection (9), he shall specify in the nomination the amount or share payable to each of the nominees in such manner as to cover the whole of the amount that may be due to him.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.11">
            <num>(11)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A member may at any time cancel nomination by sending a notice in writing to the Trustee Committee, provided that a member shall along with such notice send a fresh nomination.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.12">
            <num>(12)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every member who voluntarily suspends practice or retires shall, within fifteen days of such suspension or retirement, intimate that fact to the Trustee Committee and if any member fails to do so without sufficient reasons the Trustee Committee may reduce, in accordance with such principles as may be prescribed, the amount due to that member.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Payment from the Fund on cessation of practice.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A member of the Fund shall, on cessation of practice be entitled to receive from out of the Fund an amount at the rate specified in the Schedule:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-17.2.list0">
                <item id="section-17.2.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>A member of the Fund shall be eligible and entitled for the retirement benefits at any time after completion of fifteen years from the date of his admission as a member of the Fund, of the amount as mentioned in the Schedule.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.2.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>If any member opts for retirement benefits at any time before the completion of fifteen years from the date of his admission as a member of the Fund, then he shall be entitled only to a refund of the amount which he has paid as subscription with the Trustee Committee together with the interest at the rate of 6 per cent. per annum from the date of payment till the date of his retirement from the Fund.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.2.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>Member suffering from permanent disablement resulting in permanent cessation of practice shall be allowed to retire at any time before completion of fifteen years of his membership of the Fund and shall be entitled to receive the amount as mentioned in the Schedule.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In case a member of the Fund dies within a period of fifteen years of his admission to the Fund, his nominee or legal heir, as the case may be, shall be entitled to get an amount at the rate mentioned in the Schedule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-17.4.list1">
                <listIntroduction>After the commencement of the Amendment Act, if the existing members of the Fund does not pay in lump sum or in instalments his dues or balance of his subscription calculated on the basis of revised rate of one time payable subscription in the manner provided in sub­section (5) of section 16 and he fails to pay the penalty under sub-section (6) of section 16, then he shall be deemed to have been retired from the Fund on the date of commencement of the said Amendment Act; and in case of such deemed retirement,—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.4.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>such member shall be entitled to; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.4.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>in case of death of such member, his nominees, heir or family members shall be entitled to, the benefits as provided by the provisions of the Schedule appended to this Act as existing prior to the commencement of the said Amendment Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Omitted.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An application for payment from the Fund shall be preferred to the Trustee Committee in such form as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Omitted.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An application received under sub-section (6) shall be disposed of by the Trustee Committee after such enquiry as it deems necessary within a period of three months from the date of receipt of said application and the refund, if any, shall be given as early as possible.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VI">
        <num>VI</num>
        <heading>Printing and Distribution of Stamps by Bar Council</heading>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Printing and distribution of stamps and payment of amount of sale proceeds by Bar Council to Trustee Committee.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-18.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Bar Council shall cause to be printed and distributed welfare fund stamps each of the value of twenty rupees with the Bar Council Emblem and its value inscribed thereon.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The stamps shall be of the size 1" x 2" and be sold only to the members of the Fund through the Bar Association or through credit consumer society of the advocates or any other prescribed agency, as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The custody of the stamps shall be with the Bar Council.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Bar Council shall control the distributions and sale of the stamps through the Bar Associations the credit consumer society of the advocates or any other prescribed agency, as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Bar Council and the Bar Associations the credit consumer society of the advocates or any other prescribed agency, as the case may be shall keep proper accounts of the stamps in such form and in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Bar Associations the credit consumer society of the advocates or any other prescribed agency shall purchase the stamps from the Bar Council after paying the value thereof less ten percent of such value towards incidental expenses.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Bar Council shall, after deducting from the sale proceeds of stamps the actual cost of printing and distribution of stamps, pay the amount realised by sale of stamps to the Trustee Committee within 15 days after the end of every quarter.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VII">
        <num>VII</num>
        <heading>Miscellaneous</heading>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Vakalatnama to bear stamp</heading>
          <subsection id="section-19.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every member of the Fund shall affix one welfare fund stamp referred to in sub-section (1) of section 18 on every Vakalatnama filed by him and no Vakalatnama shall be filed before or received by any Court, Tribunal or other authority or person referred to in section 14 unless it is stamped.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The value of the stamp shall neither be cost in the case nor be collected in any event from the client.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any contravention of the provisions of sub-section (2) by any member shall disentitle him to the benefits of the Fund and the Trustee Committee shall report such instances to the Bar Council for appropriate action.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Cancellation of welfare fund stamp affixed on Vakalatnama.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every stamp affixed on Vakalatnama under subsection (1) of section 19 filed before any Court, Tribunal or any other authority or person shall be cancelled in the manner provided in section 42 of the Bombay Court-fees Act, 1959.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Exemption from sections 19 and 20 in certain cases.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Nothing contained in sections 19 and 20 shall apply in the cases of -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the Advocates appointed by the Court or the Tribunal or other authority or person referred to in section 14 in suits or other proceedings to assist the indigent persons in matters before them;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the Advocates appearing in legal aid matters for parties to whom legal aid has been rendered by the Bar Council or its Legal Aid Committees or by the Central Government or the State Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the Advocates appointed for the accused by the Courts to help the Court as amicus curiae or the Advocate otherwise appearing as amicus curiae;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the Advocates appearing on behalf of the Bar Council or any Bar Association.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Appeal against any decisions of Committee.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-22.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An appeal against any decision of the Trustee Committee shall lie to the Bar Council.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-22.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The appeal shall be in the prescribed form and shall be accompanied by --</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-22.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the order appealed against; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-22.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>a fee of one hundred rupees which shall not be refunded.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The appeal shall be filed within thirty days from the date of receipt of the order appealed against.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The decision of the Bar Council on the appeal shall be final.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Group life insurance for members and other benefits for Advocates.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-23.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-23.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Trustee Committee may, for the welfare of the members of the Fund, --</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-23.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>obtain from the Life Insurance Corporation of India policies of Group Insurance for the members of the Fund;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>provide for medical and educational facilities for the members of the Fund and their dependents; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>provide for better library facilities to the recognised and registered Bar Association for the use of the members of the Fund; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>provide for such other benefits and amenities as may be prescribed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, the Trustee Committee may also at its discretion give financial assistance from the Fund to organise welfare schemes for the indigent, disabled or other Advocates, who may or may not be members of the Fund.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Restriction on alienation, attachment, etc. of interest of member in the Fund.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-24.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being in force, the interest of any member in the Fund, or the right of a member or his nominee or legal heirs to receive any amount from the Fund, shall not be assigned, alienated, or charged and shall not be liable to attachment under any decree or order of any Court, Tribunal or other authority or person.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-24.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No creditor shall be entitled to proceed against the Fund or the interest therein of any member or his nominee or legal heirs.</p>
              <p>Explanation,- For the purposes of this section, "creditor" includes the State, or an official assignee or receiver appointed under the Presidency-towns Insolvency Act, 1909, the Provincial Insolvency Act, 1920, or any other law for the time being in force.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-25.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against any person for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any regulations made there under.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Trustee Committee or the Bar Council for any damage caused by anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any regulations made there under.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Bar of jurisdiction of Civil Courts.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No Civil Court shall have jurisdiction to settle, decide or deal with any question or to determine any matter which is by or under this Act required to be settled, decided or dealt with or to be determined by the Trustee Committee or the Bar Council.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Power to summon witnesses and take evidence.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-27.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Trustee Committee and the Bar Council shall, for the purposes of any enquiry under this Act, have the same powers as are vested in a Civil Court while trying a suit under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 in respect of the following matters, namely :--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>enforcing the attendance of any person for examining him on oath;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>requiring the discovery and production of documents;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>receiving evidence on affidavit;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Power to make regulations.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Bar Council may with the previous approval of the State Government, by notification in the Official Gazette, make regulations for the purpose of carrying into effect the provisions of this Act and for matters which are to be or may be prescribed under the Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-schedule">
      <doc name="schedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1981/61/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1981/61"/>
              <FRBRalias value="Schedule"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1981/61/eng@2017-03-15/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1981/61/eng@2017-03-15"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1981/61/eng@2017-03-15/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1981/61/eng@2017-03-15"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-03-15" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="schedule">
            <heading>(See sections 11 and 17)</heading>
            <paragraph id="schedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <table id="schedule.paragraph-0.table0">
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>30 years' membership</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 3,00,000</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>29 years' membership</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 2,90,000</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>28 years' membership</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 2,80,000</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>27 years' membership</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 2,70,000</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>26 years' membership</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 2,60,000</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>25 years' membership</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 2,50,000</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>24 years' membership</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 2,40,000</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>23 years' membership</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 2,30,000</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>22 years' membership</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 2,20,000</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>21 years' membership</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 2,10,000</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>20 years' membership</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 2,00,000</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>19 years' membership</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 1,90,000</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>18 years' membership</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 1,80,000</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>17 years' membership</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 1,70,000</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>16 year's membership</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 1,60,000</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>15 years' membership</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 1,50,000</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>14 years' membership</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 1,40,000</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>13 years' membership</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 1,30,000</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>12 years' membership</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 1,20,000</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>11 years' membership</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 1,10,000</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>10 years' membership</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 1,00,000</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>9 years' membership</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 90,000</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>8 years' membership</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 80,000</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>7 years' membership</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 70,00</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>6 years' membership</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 60,000</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>5 years' membership</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 50,000</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>4 years’ membership</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Rs. 40,000</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </table>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
