<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2017/02/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2017/02"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Specified Bank Notes (Cessation Of Liabilities) Act, 2017"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2017/02/eng@2017-05-09/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2017/02/eng@2017-05-09"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-05-09" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2017/02/eng@2017-05-09/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2017/02/eng@2017-05-09"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-05-09" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Specified Bank Notes (Cessation Of Liabilities) Act, 2017</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[27th February, 2017]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Sixty-eighth Year of the Republic of India as</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No. 2 of 2017</p>
        <p>An Act to provide in the public interest for the cessation of liabilities on the specified bank notes and for matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.</p>
        <p>follows:—</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Specified Bank Notes (Cessation of Liabilities) Act, 2017.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 31st day of December, 2016.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"appointed day" means the 31st day of December, 2016;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"grace period" means the period to be specified by the Central Government, by notification, during which the specified bank notes can be deposited in accordance with this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>"notification" means a notification published in the Official Gazette;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>"Reserve Bank" means the Reserve Bank of India constituted by the Central Government under section 3 of the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>"specified bank note" means a bank note of the denominational value of five hundred rupees or one thousand rupees of the series existing on or before the 8th day of November, 2016.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The words and expressions used and not defined in this Act but defined in the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 or the Banking Regulation Act, 1949 shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in those Acts.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Specified bank notes to cease to be liability of Reserve Bank or Central Government.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>On and from the appointed day, notwithstanding anything contained in the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 or any other law for the time being in force, the specified bank notes which have ceased to be legal tender, in view of the notification of the Government of India in the Ministry of Finance, number S.O. 3407(E), dated the 8th November, 2016, issued under sub-section (2) of section 26 of the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934, shall cease to be liabilities of the Reserve Bank under section 34 and shall cease to have the guarantee of the Central Government under sub-section (1) of section 26 of the said Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Exchange of specified bank notes.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in section 3, the following persons holding specified bank notes on or before the 8th day of November, 2016 shall be entitled to tender within the grace period with such declarations or statements, at such offices of the Reserve Bank or in such other manner as may be specified by it, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>a citizen of India who makes a declaration that he was outside India between the 9th November, 2016 to 30th December, 2016, subject to such conditions as may be specified, by notification, by the Central Government; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>such class of persons and for such reasons as may be specified by notification, by the Central Government.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Reserve Bank may, if satisfied, after making such verifications as it may consider necessary that the reasons for failure to deposit the notes within the period specified in the notification referred to in section 3, are genuine, credit the value of the notes in his Know Your Customer compliant bank account in such manner as may be specified by it.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person, aggrieved by the refusal of the Reserve Bank to credit the value of the notes under sub-section (2), may make a representation to the Central Board of the Reserve Bank within fourteen days of the communication of such refusal to him.</p>
            <p>Explanation.—For the purposes of this section, the expression "Know Your Customer compliant bank account" means the account which complies with the conditions specified in the regulations made by the Reserve Bank under the Banking Regulation Act, 1949.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition on holding transferring or receiving specified bank notes</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>On and from the appointed day, no person shall, knowingly or voluntarily, hold, transfer or receive any specified bank note:</p>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that nothing contained in this section shall prohibit the holding of specified bank notes—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>by any person—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.a.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>up to the expiry of the grace period; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.a.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.a.list0.ii.list0">
                      <listIntroduction>after the expiry of the grace period,—</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.a.list0.ii.list0.A">
                        <num>(A)</num>
                        <p>not more than ten notes in total, irrespective of the denomination; or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.a.list0.ii.list0.B">
                        <num>(B)</num>
                        <p>not more than twenty-five notes for the purposes of study, research or numismatics;</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>by the Reserve Bank or its agencies, or any other person authorised by the Reserve Bank;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>by any person on the direction of a court in relation to any case pending in the court.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for contravention of Section 4.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever knowingly and wilfully makes any declaration or statement specified under sub-section (1) of section 4, which is false in material particulars, or omits to make a material statement, or makes a statement which he does not believe to be true, shall be punishable with fine which may extend to fifty thousand rupees or five times the amount of the face value of the specified bank notes tendered, whichever is higher.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for contravention of Section 5.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever contravenes the provisions of section 5 shall be punishable with fine which may extend to ten thousand rupees or five times the amount of the face value of the specified bank notes involved in the contravention, whichever is higher.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Offences by companies</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a person committing a contravention or default referred to in section 6 or section 7 is a company, every person who, at the time the contravention or default was committed, was in charge of, and was responsible to, the company for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the contravention or default and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to punishment if he proves that the contravention or default was committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised all due diligence to prevent the contravention or default.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the same was committed with the consent or connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary, or other officer or employee of the company, such director, manager, secretary, other officer or employee shall also be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.</p>
            <blockList id="section-8.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation.—For the purpose of this section,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.2.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"a company" means any body corporate and includes a firm, a trust, a co-operative society and other association of individuals;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"director", in relation to a firm or trust, means a partner in the firm or a beneficiary in the trust.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Special provisions relating to offences</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in section 29 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973, the court of a Magistrate of the First Class or the court of a Metropolitan Magistrate may impose a fine, for contravention of the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Government, the Reserve Bank or any of their officers for anything done or intended to be done in good faith under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification, make rules for carrying out the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Power to remove difficulties.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as may appear to it to be necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty:</p>
            <p>Provided that no such order shall be made under this section after the expiry of a period of two years from the date of commencement of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every order made under this section shall, as soon as may be after it is made, be laid before each House of Parliament.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Repeal and savings.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Specified Bank Notes (Cessation of Liabilities) Ordinance, 2016 is hereby repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
