<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2002/35/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2002/35"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Haj Committee Act, 2002"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2002/35/eng@2002-06-11/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2002/35/eng@2002-06-11"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2002-06-11" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2002/35/eng@2002-06-11/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2002/35/eng@2002-06-11"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-02-20" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Haj Committee Act, 2002</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 35 OF 2002</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[11th June, 2002.]</docDate>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>An Act to establish a Haj Committee of India and State Haj Committees for making arrangements for the pilgrimage of Muslims for Haj, and for matters connected therewith.</p>
      <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third Year of the Republic of India as follows:-</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <heading>Preliminary</heading>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title and commencement.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the Haj Committee Act, 2002.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on such date or dates as the Central Government may, by notification, appoint, and different dates may be appointed for different provisions of this Act and for different States.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>"bye-laws" means the bye-laws made under section 45;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>"Chief Executive Officer or the Executive Officer" means the Chief Executive Officer of the Committee or the Executive Officer of the State Committee appointed under sub- section (1) of section 16 or sub- section (1) of section 29, as the case may be</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>"Committee" means the Haj Committee of India constituted under section 3;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>"member" means a member of the Haj Committee of India nominated under section 4 or of a State Haj Committee nominated under section 18, as the case may be, and includes the Chairperson and a Vice- Chairperson;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>"notification" means a notification published in the Gazette of India or the Official Gazette of a State, as the case may be;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>"pilgrim" means a Muslim proceeding to, or returning from, Haj;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>"prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under section 44 by the Central Government or, as the case may be, under section 47 by the State Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>"State Committee" means a State Haj Committee constituted under section 18 and includes Joint State Committee;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>"State Government", in relation to a Union territory, means the Administrator of that Union territory appointed by the President under article 239 of the Constitution.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <heading>Haj committee of india</heading>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Constitution and incorporation of Haj Committee of India.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>With effect from such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint in this behalf, there shall be constituted a Committee by the name of the Ha Committee of India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Committee shall be a body corporate, by the name aforesaid, having perpetual succession and a common seal with power, subject to the provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of property, both movable and immovable, to create a charitable trust or endowment and to contract and shall by the said name sue and be sued.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Committee shall have its headquarters at Mumbai and as and when the Committee considers it functionally necessary, additional regional offices may be opened in consultation with the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Composition of Committee.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Committee shall consist of the following members, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>three members of Parliament of whom two are to be nominated by the Speaker of the House of the People from among its Muslim members, and one by the Chairman of the Council of States from among its Muslim members:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that a member of Parliament shall, upon ceasing to be a member, cease to be a member of the Committee and the Speaker of the House of the People or the Chairman of the Council of States, as the case may be, shall make a fresh nomination upon req est by the Central Government;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list3.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>nine Muslim members of the Committee shall be elected, three from those States sending largest number of pilgrims during last three years and one each from the zones as specified in the Schedule, in such manner as may be prescribed:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that not more than one member shall be elected from a State falling in the zone as specified in the Schedule;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list5.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>four persons not below the rank of Joint Secretary to the Government of India nominated by that Government to represent the Ministries of External Affairs, Home, Finance and Civil Aviation, as ex officio members;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list5.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>seven Muslim members shall be nominated by the Central Government from among the following categories of persons, namely:-</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list5.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>two members who have special knowledge of public administration, finance, education, culture or social work and out of whom one shall be a Shia Muslim;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list5.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>two women members, out of them one shall be Shia Muslim;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list5.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>three members who have special knowledge of Muslim theology and law, out of them one shall be a Shia Muslim.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Notification of members.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>As soon as may be after the nomination of the members of the Committee under section 4, the Central Government shall publish in the Official Gazette the names of all such members.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Term of office.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The term of office of the members of the Committee (other than the ex officio members and members filling casual vacancies) shall be three years, commencing on the day following the publication of the list of members under section:</p>
              <p>Provided that the term of the members of the Committee may be extended by the Central Government by a notification in the Official Gazette for a period not exceeding six months at a time but, in any case, not exceeding beyond a total period of one year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The allowances payable to, and the other terms and conditions of, the Chairperson, Vice- Chairpersons and members shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Chairperson and Vice- Chairperson.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>After the publication of the names of members of the Committee under section 5, the Central Government shall convene within forty- five days of such publication the first meeting of the Committee at which the Commi tee shall elect a Chairperson and two Vice- Chairpersons from amongst its members:</p>
              <p>Provided that a Minister shall not be the Chairperson of the Committee and ex officio members shall not take part in the election of the Chairperson or of the Vice- Chairpersons.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the Committee fails to elect the Chairperson or the Vice- Chairpersons the Central Government may appoint a member of the Committee to be the Chairperson thereof or Vice- Chairpersons, as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chairperson shall exercise such powers and discharge such duties as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Vice- Chairpersons shall exercise such powers and discharge such duties as may be determined by bye- laws made in this behalf by the Committee: Provided that till such bye- laws are made, the Vice- Chairpersons shall exercise such powers and discharge such duties as may be determined by an order made by the Chairperson in this regard.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The election of the Chairperson and the Vice- Chairpersons shall be notified by the Central Government in the Official Gazette.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The term of office of the Chairperson and the Vice- Chairpersons, as the case may be, shall be co- terminus with the term of the Committee and no person shall hold office of the Chairperson or the Vice- Chairpersons, as the case may be, for more than two consecutive terms.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any casual vacancy in the office of the Chairperson or a Vice- Chairperson shall be filled for the remainder of the term in accordance with sub- section (1) or sub- section (2), as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Reconstitution of Committee.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government shall take or cause to be taken all necessary steps for the reconstitution of a new Committee at least four months before the expiry of the term, or the extended term, as the case may be, of the ommittee.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An outgoing member shall be eligible for renomination on the Committee for not more than two terms:</p>
              <p>Provided that not more than fifty per cent. of the members may be renominated for a second term in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Duties of Committee.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-9.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The duties of the Committee shall be-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-9.1.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>to collect and disseminate information useful to pilgrims, and to arrange orientation and training programmes for pilgrims;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.1.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>to advise and assist pilgrims during their stay at the embarkation points in India, while proceeding to or returning from pilgrimage, in all matters including vaccination, inoculation, medical inspection, issue of pilgrim passes and foreign exchange and to liaise with the local authorities concerned in such matters;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.1.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>to give relief to pilgrims in distress;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.1.list1.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>to finalise the annual Haj plan with the approval of the Central Government, and execute the plan, including the arrangements for travel by air or any other means, and to advise in matters relating to accommodations;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.1.list1.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>to approve the budget estimates of the Committee and submit it to the Central Government at least three months before the beginning of the financial year for its concurrence;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.1.list1.vi">
                  <num>(vi)</num>
                  <p>to co- ordinate with the Central Government, railways, airways and travel agencies for the purpose of securing travelling facilities for pilgrims;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.1.list1.vii">
                  <num>(vii)</num>
                  <p>to generally look after the welfare of the pilgrims;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.1.list1.viii">
                  <num>(viii)</num>
                  <p>to publish such proceedings of the Committee and such matters of interest to pilgrims as may be determined by bye- laws made in this behalf by the Committee;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.1.list1.ix">
                  <num>(ix)</num>
                  <p>to discharge such other duties in connection with Haj as may be prescribed by the Central Government.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government shall afford all reasonable assistance to the Committee in the discharge of the duties specified in sub- section (1) .</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Meetings of Committee.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Committee shall meet at least three times in a year before the commencement of the Haj season to plan and make arrangements for Haj and once after that to review all arrangements made by the Committee.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In addition to the meetings specified in sub- section (1), the Committee may hold meetings as and when requisitioned by at least one- third of its members or when considered necessary by the Chairperson.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The number of members required to make a quorum at any meeting of the Committee shall be one- third of its members.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All matters shall be decided by a majority of votes of the members present and, in the event of an equality of votes, the Chairperson or other person presiding shall have a casting vote.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Committee shall observe such rules of procedure in regard to the transaction of business at its meetings as may be determined by bye- laws.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Appointment of Standing Committees and sub- committees.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Committee shall appoint two Standing Committees, each headed by a Vice- Chairperson of the Committee, to deal with matters relating to finance and Haj arrangements, from amongst its member consisting of such number of members and with such powers and functions as may be determined by bye- laws made in this behalf by the Committee:</p>
              <p>Provided that the Chairperson shall preside over the meeting of the Standing Committee in case he attends the meeting.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Committee may also appoint other sub- committees for such purposes as it may think fit and any such sub- committee shall consist of such number of members and other persons as may be determined by bye- laws made in this behalf by the Committee.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Disqualification for being nominated, or for continuing, as a member of Committee.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>A person shall be disqualified for being nominated, or for continuing as a member of the Committee, if he-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>is not a citizen of India;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>is not a Muslim, except for ex officio members as provided in clause (iii) of section 4;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>is less than twenty- five years of age;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>is of unsound mind and stands so declared by a competent court;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>is an undischarged insolvent;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.vi">
                  <num>(vi)</num>
                  <p>has been convicted of an offence which, in the opinion of the Central Government, involves a moral turpitude;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.vii">
                  <num>(vii)</num>
                  <p>has been on a previous occasion-</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>removed from his office as a member; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>removed by an order of a competent authority either for not acting in the interest of the pilgrims or for corruption.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Resignation of Chairperson, Vice- Chairperson and members.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Chairperson, the Vice- Chairperson or any other member may resign his office by writing under his hand addressed to the Central Government and it shall be effective from the date of such re ignation.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Removal of Chairperson, Vice- Chairperson and members.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-14.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, remove the Chairperson, a Vice- Chairperson of the Committee or any member thereof, if he-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-14.1.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>is or becomes subject to any of the disqualifications specified in section 12; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.1.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>refuses to act or is incapable of acting or acts in a manner which the Central Government, after hearing any explanation that he may offer, considers to be prejudicial to the interests of the Committee or the interests of the pilgrims; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.1.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>fails, in the opinion of the Committee, to attend three consecutive meetings of the Committee, without sufficient excuse.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where the Chairperson or a Vice- Chairperson of the Committee is removed under sub- section (1), he shall also cease to be a member of the Committee.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Filling of a casual vacancy.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-15.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When the seat of a member becomes vacant by his removal, resignation, death or otherwise, a new member shall be nominated or elected, as the case may be, in his place and such member shall hold office so long as the m mber whose place he fills would have been entitled to hold office if such vacancy had not occurred.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any casual vacancy under sub- section (1) shall be filled up by the same category to which the former member belonged.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Chief Executive Officer and other employees.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-16.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government shall appoint a person, from a panel of Muslim officers of the Central Government and of the State Governments not below the rank of Deputy Secretary to the Government of India, to be the Chief Executive Officer of the Committee on such terms and conditions as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chief Executive Officer shall be the ex officio Secretary of the Committee.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chief Executive Officer shall be appointed for a period of three years, which may be extended by a maximum period of one year by the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chief Executive Officer shall execute the decisions of the Committee and perform such other functions as may be prescribed:</p>
              <p>Provided that in case of any difference of opinion between the Chief Executive Officer and the Committee, he shall bring the matter to the notice of the Central Government, whose decision thereon shall be final.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Committee may, with the previous sanction of the Central Government, employ such other officers and employees as it deems necessary to carry out the purposes of this Act, on such terms and conditions as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <heading>State haj committees</heading>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Establishment and incorporation of State Haj Committee.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>With effect from such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint in this behalf, the Government of a State shall constitute a Committee by the name of the...... name of the State Haj Committee:</p>
              <p>Provided that in case it appears to the Central Government for any reasons that it is not necessary for a State or Union territory to establish a Haj Committee, it may authorise the State Haj Committee of a contiguous State to deal with those pilgrims an suggest suitable representation of those States and Union territories.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Committee shall be a body corporate, by the name aforesaid, having perpetual succession and a common seal with power, subject to the provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of property, both movable and immovable, to create a c aritable trust or endowment, and to contract and shall by the said name sue and be sued.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-17.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, an agreement may be entered into-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>by two or more Governments of contiguous States, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.3.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>by the Central Government (in respect of one or more Union territories) and one or more Governments of States contiguous to such Union territory or Union territories,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-17.3.list3">
                <listIntroduction>to be in force for such period and to be subject to renewal for such further period, if any, as may be specified in the agreement to provide for the constitution of a Joint State Committee,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.3.list3.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>in a case referred to in clause (a), for all the participating States, and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.3.list3.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>in a case referred to in clause (b), for the participating Union territory or Union territories and the State or States.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An agreement under this section shall be published, in a case referred to in clause (a) of sub- section (2), in the Official Gazette of the participating States and in a case referred to in clause (b) of that sub- section, in the Official Gazette of th participating Union territory or Union territories and participating State or States.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any reference in this Act to the State Committee shall, unless the context otherwise requires, be construed as including a Joint State Committee.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Composition of State Committee.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-18.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A State Committee shall consist of sixteen members, to be nominated by the State Government,</p>
              <blockList id="section-18.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-18.1.list2.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>three members from the Muslim members of-</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.1.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>Parliament representing the State;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.1.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>State Legislative Assembly; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.1.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>Legislative Council, where it exists;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.1.list2.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>three members from Muslim members representing local bodies in the State;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.1.list2.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>three members having expertise in Muslim theology and law including one who shall be a Shia Muslim;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.1.list2.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>five members representing Muslim voluntary organisations working in the fields of public administration, finance, education, culture or social work;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.1.list2.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>the Chairperson of the State Wakf Board; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.1.list2.vi">
                  <num>(vi)</num>
                  <p>Executive Officer of the State Committee, who shall be the ex officio member of the State Committee:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that a Committee for any Union territory or a Joint State Committee shall consist of such number of members as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In case where there is no Muslim member in any of the categories mentioned in clauses (i) and (ii) of sub- section (1), or where there is no Legislative Council in a State, nomination may be made in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Notification of members.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>As soon as may be after the nomination of the members of a State Committee under sub- section (1) of section 18, the State Government shall publish, in the Official Gazette of that State, the names of all such members.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Term of office.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-20.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The term of office of the members of the State Committee (other than the ex officio members and members filling casual vacancies) shall be three years, commencing on the day following the publication of the list of members under section 19.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The allowances payable to, and the other terms and conditions of the Chairperson and members shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Chairperson.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-21.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>After the publication of the names of members of the State Committee under section 19, the State Government shall convene within forty- five days the first meeting of the State Committee at which the State Committee shall elect a Chairperson from amongst its members:</p>
              <p>Provided that an ex officio member shall not take part in the election of the Chairperson.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-21.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the State Committee fails to elect a Chairperson, the State Government may appoint a member of the State Committee to be the Chairperson thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-21.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The election of the Chairperson shall be notified by the State Government in the Official Gazette of the State.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-21.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The term of office of the Chairperson shall be three years and no person shall hold the office of the Chairperson for more than two consecutive terms.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-21.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any casual vacancy in the office of the Chairperson shall be filled in accordance with sub- section (1) or sub- section (2), as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Reconstitution of a State Committee.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-22.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government shall take or cause to be taken all necessary steps for the reconstitution of a new State Committee at least four months before the expiry of the term of the State Committee.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An outgoing member shall be eligible for re- nomination of the State Committee for not more than two terms: Provided that fifty per cent of the nominees may be re- nominated for a second term in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Disqualification for being nominated, or for continuing, as a member of the Committee.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-23.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>A person shall be disqualified for being nominated, or for continuing, as a member of the State Committee, if he-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-23.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>is not a citizen of India;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>is not a resident of that State;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.paragraph-0.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>is not a Muslim, except for an Executive Officer as provided in clause</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.paragraph-0.list1.vi">
                  <num>(vi)</num>
                  <p>of sub- section (1) of section 18;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.paragraph-0.list1.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>is less than twenty- five years of age;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.paragraph-0.list1.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>is of unsound mind and stands so declared by a competent court;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.paragraph-0.list1.vi">
                  <num>(vi)</num>
                  <p>is an undischarged insolvent;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.paragraph-0.list1.vii">
                  <num>(vii)</num>
                  <p>has been convicted of an offence which, in the opinion of the State Government, involves a moral turpitude;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.paragraph-0.list1.viii">
                  <num>(viii)</num>
                  <p>has been on a previous occasion-</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>removed from his office as a member; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>removed by an order of a competent authority either for not acting in the interest of the pilgrims or for corruption.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Resignation of Chairperson and members.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Chairperson or any other member may resign his office by writing under his hand addressed to the State Government and it shall be effective from the date of such resignation.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Removal of Chairperson and members.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-25.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-25.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, remove the Chairperson of the State Committee or any member thereof, if he-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-25.1.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>is or becomes subject to any of the disqualifications specified in section 23; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-25.1.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>refuses to act or is incapable of acting or acts in a manner which the State Government, after hearing any explanation that he may offer, considers to be prejudicial to the interests of the State Committee or the interests of the pilgrims; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-25.1.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>fails, in the opinion of the State Committee, to attend three consecutive meetings of the State Committee, without sufficient excuse.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where the Chairperson of the State Committee is removed under sub- section (1), he shall also cease to be a member of the State Committee.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Filling of casual vacancy.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-26.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When the seat of a member becomes vacant by his removal, resignation, death or otherwise, a new member shall be nominated in his place and such member shall hold office so long as the member whose place he fills would have been entitled to hold office if such vacancy had not occurred.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-26.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any casual vacancy under sub- section (1) shall be filled up by the same category to which the former member belonged.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Duties of State Committee.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-27.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall be the duty of a State Committee to implement the policy and directions of the Committee in the interests of Haj pilgrims.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Committee shall provide assistance to the Haj pilgrims including in the matter of their transport between their home States and the point of exit from India and their transit accommodation at points of exit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Committee shall discharge such other duties in connection with Haj as may be prescribed by the State Government concerned, in consultation with the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Meetings of State Committee.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-28.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A State Committee shall meet at least twice in a year before the Haj day and once after the Haj is over.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-28.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The number of members required to make a quorum at any meeting of the State Committee shall be one- third of its members.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-28.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In addition to the number of meetings specified in sub- section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-28.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, the State Committee may hold meetings as and when requisitioned by at least one- third of its members or when considered necessary by the Chairperson.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-28.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All matters shall be decided by a majority of votes of the members present and, in the event of an equality of votes, the Chairperson or other person presiding shall have a casting vote.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Executive Officer and other employees of State Committee.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-29.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government shall appoint a person, from amongst its officers not below the rank of Deputy Secretary, to be the Executive Officer of the State Committee:</p>
              <p>Provided that the person so appointed shall preferably be a Muslim.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Executive Officer of the State Committee shall act as its Secretary.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Executive Officer shall execute the decisions of the State Committee and perform such other functions as may be prescribed:</p>
              <p>Provided that in case of any difference of opinion between the Executive Officer and the State Committee, he shall bring the matter to the notice of the State Government whose decision thereon shall be final.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Committee shall, with the previous sanction of the State Government, employ such officers and other employees as it deems necessary to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The term of office and conditions of service of officers and other employees shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <heading>Finance, accounts and audit</heading>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading>Central Haj Fund.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-30.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-30.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Committee shall have its own Fund to be called the Central Haj Fund, and there shall be placed to the credit thereof the following sums, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-30.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-30.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>sums realised from any fees and service charges which may be levied by the Committee:-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-30.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>for registration of applications for Haj; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-30.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>for issue of Haj pilgrim travel passes;</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>money collected from pilgrims for performance of Haj;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the income from all deposits and investment of the Committee' s funds;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the sums realised from the sale of the effects of deceased pilgrims and sums of money left by them, which are unclaimed and have lapsed to the Central Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>any sums loaned by the Central or a State Government, or any other source approved by the Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>any amount that may be legally due to the Committee from any source; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the amount standing at the commencement of this Act to the credit of the Haj Fund or the Indigent Pilgrims Fund established under the Haj Committee Act, 1959 (51 of 1959).</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading>Application of Central Haj Fund.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-31.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-31.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Central Haj Fund shall, subject to the provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder, be under the control and management of the Committee, and shall be applied to the following purposes, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-31.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>pay and allowances of the Chief Executive Officer and other employees of the Committee;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-31.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>payment of charges and expenses incidental to the objects specified in section 9; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-31.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>any other expenses which are required to be met by the Committee or a State Committee, as approved by the Central Government.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>State Haj Fund.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-32.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-32.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The State Committee shall have its own fund to be called the State Haj Fund and the following sums shall be placed to the credit thereof, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>all sums of money paid to it or any grant made by the Committee for the purposes of this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>any grant or loan that may be made to the State Committee by the State Government, or any other source for the purposes of this Act, as approved by the State Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.paragraph-0.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>any amount that may be legally due to the State Committee from any source; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.paragraph-0.list1.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>the moneys, if any, standing to the credit of a State Haj Committee, at the commencement of this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading>Application of State Haj Fund.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-33.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-33.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The State Haj Fund shall, subject to any rules that may be made under this Act, be under the control and management of the State Committee and shall be applied to the following purposes, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-33.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>pay and allowances of the employees of the State Committee other than its Executive Officer whose pay and allowances shall be borne by the State Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-33.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>payment of charges and expenses incidental to the due performance of its duties by the State Committee for the objects specified in section 27; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-33.paragraph-0.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>any other expenses, as approved by the State Government which are required to be met by the State Committee.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-34">
          <num>34.</num>
          <heading>Accounts and audit.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-34.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Committee and every State Committee shall maintain proper accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual statement of accounts, in such form as may be prescribed by the Central Government, or as the case may be, the State Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-34.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The accounts shall be examined and audited annually by such auditors as the Central Government or, as the case may be, the State Government may approve.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-34.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The accounts of the Committee or the State Committee as certified by the auditor together with the audit report thereon shall be forwarded annually by the said Committee to the Central Government, or as the case may be, the State Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-34.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government shall, as soon as may be after the receipt of the audit report under sub- section (3), cause the same to be laid before each House of Parliament.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-34.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government shall, as soon as may be, after the receipt of the audit report under sub- section (3), cause the same to be laid before the State Legislature.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <heading>Miscellaneous</heading>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading>Powers of Committee to issue Pilgrim Passes and levy fees.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-35.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Committee shall have the power to issue a travel document called "Pilgrim Pass" to a Haj pilgrim for his departure from India as a bona fide pilgrim to Saudi Arabia and the said Pil rim shall be deemed to be exempted from the provisions of section 3 of the Passports Act, 1967. (15 of 1967).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-35.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Passports Act, 1967 (15 of 1967), the Central Government may, in consultation with the Committee, levy such fees for registration of Haj pilgrims, issuance of Pilgrim Pass by the Committee and other related m tters, as may be prescribed in connection with rendering of such services.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-36">
          <num>36.</num>
          <heading>Supersession of Committee.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-36.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If, in the opinion of the Central Government, the Committee is unable to perform, or persistently makes default in the performance of the duties imposed on it by or under this Act or exceeds or abuses its powers, the Central Government may, by an order published, together with a statement of the reasons therefor, in the Official Gazette, supersede it for such period as may be specified in the order:</p>
              <p>Provided that before making an order of supersession as aforesaid, the Central Government shall give a reasonable opportunity to the Committee to show cause why it should not be superseded.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-36.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>When the Committee is superseded by an order under sub- section (1) ,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-36.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>all members shall, on such date as may be specified in the order, vacate their offices as such members without prejudice to their eligibility for nomination under clause (d);</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-36.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>during the period of supersession of the Committee, all powers and duties conferred and imposed upon the Committee by or under this Act shall be exercised and performed by such officer or authority as the Central Government may appoint in that behalf</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-36.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>all property vested in the Committee shall, until it is reconstituted, vest in the Central Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-36.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>before the expiry of the period of supersession, nominations shall be made by the Central Government for the purpose of reconstituting the Committee.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An order of supersession made under this section together with a statement of the reasons therefor shall be laid before each House of Parliament as soon as may be after it has been made.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A State Government may exercise the same powers and duties in respect of a State Committee as mentioned in sub- sections (1), (2) and (3) of this section subject to the conditions mentioned therein and any directions issued by the Central Government i this regard.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-37">
          <num>37.</num>
          <heading>Membership of Committee or State Committee not to constitute office of profit.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-37.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being in force, the office of a member of the Committee or State Committee shall not be deemed to be an office of profit.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-38">
          <num>38.</num>
          <heading>Vacancies, etc., not to invalidate proceedings of Committee.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-38.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No act or proceeding of the Committee or of a State Committee or of a Joint State Committee, as the case may be, shall be invalid by reason only of the existence of any vacancy amongst its embers, or any defect in the constitution thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-39">
          <num>39.</num>
          <heading>Officers and employees of Committee to be public servants.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-39.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The officers and employees of the Committees and other persons duly appointed to discharge any duty under this Act or rules or bye- laws made thereunder, shall be deemed to be public servants ithin the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-40">
          <num>40.</num>
          <heading>Indemnity.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-40.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Chairperson, Vice- Chairpersons or any member of the Committee or a State Committee in respect of anything in good faith done or purporting to have been done under this Ac, except with the prior permission of the Central or State Government, as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-41">
          <num>41.</num>
          <heading>Power to amend Schedule.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-41.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the Central Government is satisfied that it is necessary or expedient so to do, it may, by notification published in the Official Gazette, amend the Schedule and thereupon the Schedule shall be deemed to have been amen ed accordingly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-41.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A copy of every notification made under sub- section (1) shall be laid before each House of Parliament as soon as may be after it is made.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-42">
          <num>42.</num>
          <heading>Redressal of grievances.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-42.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Any Haj pilgrim, who is aggrieved by the discharge of any of the duties performed by the Haj Committee or the State Haj Committee, shall make a representation for the redressal of his grievance to the Haj Committee or the Sta e Haj Committee, as the case may be, and the same shall be disposed of by the said Committee, if necessary, after hearing the aggrieved person.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-43">
          <num>43.</num>
          <heading>Vesting of properties and other rights, etc., in Committees.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-43.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On and from the commencement of this Act, all assets, rights, leaseholds, powers, authorities and privileges and all properties, movable and immovable, including lands, buildings, stor s, cash balances, cash on hand, reserve funds, investments and all other rights and interests in or arising out of such properties as were immediately before such commencement in the ownership, power or control of Haj Committee, Mumbai, constituted under the Haj Committee Act, 1959 (51 of 1959) and all books of account, registers and all other documents of whatever nature relating thereto shall vest absolutely in and belong to the Committee.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-43.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On and from the commencement of this Act, all assets, rights, leaseholds, powers, authorities and privileges and all properties, movable and immovable, including lands, buildings, stores, cash balances, cash on hand, reserve funds, investments and al other rights and interests in or arising out of such properties as were immediately before such commencement in the ownership, power or control of Haj Committee of a State and, all books of account, registers and all other documents of whatever nature relating thereto shall vest absolutely in and belong to the Haj Committee of a State.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-43.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All debts, obligations and liabilities incurred, all contracts entered into and all matters and things engaged to be done by, with or for the Committee or a State Committee immediately before such commencement for or in connection with the purposes o the Committee or a State Committee shall be deemed to have been incurred, entered into and engaged to be done by, with or for the Committee or a State Committee, as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-43.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All sums of money due to the Committee or a State Committee immediately before such commencement shall be deemed to be due to the Committee or a State Committee, as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-43.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All contracts made with and all instruments executed on behalf of the Haj Committee, Mumbai or the Haj Committee of a State shall be deemed to have been made or executed on behalf of the Committee, or as the case may be, the State Committee and shall be performed accordingly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-43.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In all suits and legal proceedings pending on the commencement of this Act in or to which the Haj Committee, Mumbai or the Haj Committee of a State was a party, the Committee, or as the case may be, the State Committee shall be deemed to have been substituted therefor.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-44">
          <num>44.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-44.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, by notification, make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-44.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-44.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing powers, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-44.2.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the manner of election of members of the Committee under clause</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-44.2.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>of section 4;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-44.2.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>the terms and conditions of the Chairperson and members under sub- section (2) of section 6;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-44.2.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>the powers and duties of the Chairperson under sub- section (3) of section 7;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-44.2.list1.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which the members may be re- nominated under the proviso to sub- section (2) of section 8;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-44.2.list1.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>duties in connection with Haj under clause (ix) of sub- section (1) of section 9;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-44.2.list1.vi">
                  <num>(vi)</num>
                  <p>the functions of the Chief Executive Officer and the terms and conditions of service of the Chief Executive Officer and other employees of the Committee under section 16;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-44.2.list1.vii">
                  <num>(vii)</num>
                  <p>the number of members of a Joint State Committee or of a Committee for Union territory under the proviso to clause (vi) of sub- section (1) of section 18;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-44.2.list1.viii">
                  <num>(viii)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which the accounts shall be maintained by the Committee and the State Committees and the audit of such accounts under section 34;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-44.2.list1.ix">
                  <num>(ix)</num>
                  <p>issue of Haj Pilgrim Pass under sub- section (1) of section 35;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-44.2.list1.x">
                  <num>(x)</num>
                  <p>amendment of the Schedule relating to the zones comprising contiguous States or Union territories under section 41;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-44.2.list1.xi">
                  <num>(xi)</num>
                  <p>any other matter which may be prescribed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-44.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive session, and if, before the expiry of the session in which it is so laid, or the session immediately following, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-45">
          <num>45.</num>
          <heading>Power to make bye- laws.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-45.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-45.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Committee may, by notification, make bye- laws consistent with the provisions of the Act and the rules made thereunder in respect of the following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-45.1.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>powers and duties of the Vice- Chairpersons under sub- section (4) of section 7;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-45.1.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>providing for the publication of the proceedings of the Committee and any matter of interests to pilgrims under clause (viii) of sub- section (1) of section 9;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-45.1.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>laying down the rules of procedure for transaction of business at meeting of the Committee under sub- section (5) of section 10;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-45.1.list1.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>powers and functions of the Standing Committee and determination of number of members and other persons in sub- committees under section 11.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-45.1.list1.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>providing for any other matter which the Committee deems necessary for giving effect to the provisions of this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Bye- laws made by the Committee under this section shall be submitted to the Central Government and shall not take effect until they have been confirmed by the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Bye- laws which have been confirmed by the Central Government shall be published in the Official Gazette.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-46">
          <num>46.</num>
          <heading>Power to delegate.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-46.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder, the Committee may, by general or special order in writing, with the prior approval of the Central Government,</p>
              <p>delegate to any member or Chief Executive Officer o the Committee, and subject to such conditions and limitations, as may be specified in the order, such of its powers under this Act (except the powers to make bye- laws under section 45) as it may deem necessary.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-47">
          <num>47.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules by State Governments.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-47.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Governments may, in consultation with the Central Government, by notification make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act in respect of the State Committees.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-47.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-47.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing powers, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-47.2.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>terms and conditions of the Chairperson and members of the State Committee under sub- section (2) of section 20;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-47.2.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which the members may be re- nominated under the proviso to sub- section (2) of section 22;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-47.2.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>duties of the State Committee under sub- section (3) of section 27;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-47.2.list1.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>the functions of the Executive Officer and the terms and conditions of service of officers and other employees under section 29;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-47.2.list1.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>any other matter which is required to be or may be prescribed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-47.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before the State Legislature.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-48">
          <num>48.</num>
          <heading>Provisions as to employees of the existing Committee before the commencement of this Act.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-48.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every officer and other employee of any of the existing Committee and the State Committee, as the case may be, shall, on and from the commencement of this Act, tand transferred to or become an officer or other employee of the Committee or the State Committee, as the case may be, with such designation as such Committee may determine and shall hold office or service therein by the same tenure, at the same remuner tion, upon the same terms and conditions of service as he would have held under the Haj Committee constituted under the Haj Committee Act, 1959 (51 of 1959) and shall continue to do so as an officer or other employee of the Committee till such time the t rms and conditions are duly altered by such Committee:</p>
              <p>Provided that the tenure, remuneration and terms and conditions of service of any such officer or other employee of the Committee or of a State Committee, as the case may be, shall not be altered to his disadvantage without the previous sanction of the C ntral Government or State Government, as the case may be: Provided further that any service rendered by any such officer or other employee before the commencement of this Act shall be deemed to be the service rendered under the Committee or, as the case may be, the State Committee.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-49">
          <num>49.</num>
          <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-49.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against the Government or any officer or other employee of the Government or the Committee constituted under this Act in respect of anything which is n good faith done or intended to be done under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-50">
          <num>50.</num>
          <heading>Power to remove difficulties.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-50.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government may, by order not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, remove the difficulty: Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a period of two years from the commencement of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-50.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any order made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-51">
          <num>51.</num>
          <heading>Powers to give directions.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-51.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, in exercise of its powers and performance of its functions under this Act, issue directions in writing to the Committee or the State Government or the State Committee and such Committee, State G vernment or State Committee, as the case may be, shall be bound to comply with such directions.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-52">
          <num>52.</num>
          <heading>Repeal.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-52.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Haj Committee Act, 1959 (51 of 1959) is hereby repealed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-52.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding such repeal, the Haj Committee constituted under the said Act shall, until the establishment of the Committee under this Act, continue to function as if this Act had not been passed and on such notification under section 5 on the establishment of the Committee, the former Committee shall stand dissolved.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-52.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken under the Haj Committee Act, 1959 (51 of 1959) shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-theschedule">
      <doc name="theschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2002/35/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2002/35"/>
              <FRBRalias value="THE SCHEDULE"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2002/35/eng@2002-06-11/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2002/35/eng@2002-06-11"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2002/35/eng@2002-06-11/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2002/35/eng@2002-06-11"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-02-20" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="theschedule">
            <heading>[See sections 4(ii) and 41(1)]</heading>
            <paragraph id="theschedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>ZONE-I NATIONAL CAPITAL TERRITORY OF DELHI, RAJASTHAN, JAMMU AND KASHMIR, PUNJAB, HARYANA, HIMACHAL PRADESH AND UNION TERRITORY OF CHANDIGARH.</p>
                <p>ZONE-II UTTAR PRADESH, BIHAR, UTTARANCHAL AND JHARKHAND.</p>
                <p>ZONE-III ANDHRA PRADESH, MADHYA PRADESH, CHHATTISGARH AND ORISSA.</p>
                <p>ZONE-IV ASSAM, WEST BENGAL, TRIPURA, MANIPUR, SIKKIM, MEGHALAYA, ARUNACHAL PRADESH, MIZORAM, NAGALAND AND UNION TERRITORY OF ANDAMAN AND NICOBAR ISLANDS.</p>
                <p>ZONE-V MAHARASHTRA, GUJARAT, GOA AND UNION TERRIORIES OF DAMAN AND DIU AND DADRA AND NAGAR HAVELI.</p>
                <p>ZONE-VI TAMIL NADU, KERALA, KARNATAKA AND UNION TERRITORIES OF PONDICHERRY AND LAKSHADWEEP.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
