<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1949/66/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1949/66"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Central Reserve Police Force Act, 1949"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1949/66/eng@1949-12-28/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1949/66/eng@1949-12-28"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1949-12-28" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1949/66/eng@1949-12-28/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1949/66/eng@1949-12-28"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-10-05" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Central Reserve Police Force Act, 1949</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[28th December, 1949]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No. 66 of 1949</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the constitution and regulation of an armed Central Reserve Police Force.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the constitution and regulation of an armed Central Reserve Police Force;</p>
        <p>It is hereby enacted as follows:—</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and extent.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Central Reserve Police Force Act, 1949.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India, and applies to members of the Force, wherever they may be.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“active duty” means the duty to restore and preserve order in any local area in the event of any disturbance therein;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“close arrest” means confinement within the Force or a detachment of the Force or a post quarter-guard building or tent under charge of a guard;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“the Force” means the Central Reserve Police Force;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>“member of the Force” means a person who has been appointed to the Force by the Commandant, whether before or after the commencement of this Act, and in sections 1, 3, 6, 7, 16, 17, 18 and 19, includes also a person appointed to the Force by the Central Government whether before or after such commencement;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>“open arrest” means confinement within the precincts of any barracks, lines or camp for the time being occupied by any part of the Force;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>“subordinate officer” means a member of the Force of the rank of subedar-major, subedar, jemadar or sub-inspector;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the expressions “assault”, “criminal force”, “fraudulently”, “reason to believe” and “voluntarily causing hurt” have the meanings assigned to them respectively in the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>CONSTITUTION OF THE FORCE</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of the Force.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall continue to be an armed force maintained by the Central Government and called the Central Reserve Police Force.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Force shall be constituted in such manner, and the members of the Force shall receive such pay, pension and other remuneration, as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Appointment and powers of superior officers.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may appoint to the Force a Commandant and such other persons as it thinks fit to be assistant commandants and company officers.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commandant and every other officer so appointed shall have, and may exercise, such powers and authority as may be provided by or under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Enrolment.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Before a person is appointed to be a member of the Force, the statement contained in the recruiting roll set out in the Schedule shall be read out and, if necessary, explained to him in the presence of an officer appointed under sub-section (1) of section 4, and shall be signed by such person in acknowledgement of its having been so read out to him:</p>
            <p>Provided that any person who has for a period of six months served with the Force, shall, on appointment to the Force thereafter, be deemed to be a member of the Force notwithstanding that the provisions of this section have not been complied with in his case.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Resignation and withdrawal from the Force.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>No member of the Force shall be at liberty to—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>resign his appointment during the term of his engagement, except before the expiration of the first three months of his service; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>withdraw himself from all or any of the duties of his appointment, without the previous permission in writing of the Commandant or Assistant Commandant or any other officer authorised by the Commandant to grant such permission.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>GENERAL DUTIES OF MEMBERS OF THE FORCE</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>General duties of members of the Force.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be the duty of every member of the Force promptly to obey and to execute all orders and warrants lawfully issued to him by any competent authority, to detect and bring offenders to justice and to apprehend all persons whom he is legally authorised to apprehend and for whose apprehension sufficient grounds exist.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every member of the Force shall be liable to serve without and beyond, as well as within the territory of India.</p>
            <p>SUPERINTENDENCE, CONTROL AND ADMINISTRATION OF THE FORCE</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Superintendence, control and administration of the Force.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The superintendence of, and control over, the Force shall vest in the Central Government; and the Force shall be administered by the Central Government in accordance with the provisions of this Act and of any rules made thereunder, through such officers as the Central Government may from time to time appoint in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The headquarters of the Force shall be at Neemuch or at such other place as may from time to time be specified by the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>While on active duty outside its headquarters, the Force shall be subject to the general control and direction of such authority or officer as may be prescribed or as may be specially appointed by the Central Government in this behalf.</p>
            <p>OFFENCES AND PUNISHMENTS</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>More heinous offences.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Every member of the Force who—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>begins, excites, causes or conspires to cause or joins in any mutiny, or, being present at any mutiny, does not use his utmost endeavour to suppress it, or knowing, or having reason to believe in, the existence of any mutiny, or of any intention or conspiracy to mutiny or of any conspiracy against the State does not, without delay, give information thereof to his superior officer; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>uses, or attempts to use, criminal force to, or commits an assault on, his superior officer, whether on or off duty, knowing or having reason to believe him to be such; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>shamefully abandons or delivers up any post or guard which is committed to his charge or which it is his duty to defend; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>directly or indirectly holds correspondence with, or assists or relieves any person in arms against the State or omits to discover immediately to his superior officer any such correspondence coming to his knowledge; or</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-9.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>who, while on active duty,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>disobeys the lawful command of his superior officer; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list3.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>deserts the Force; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list3.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>being a sentry, sleeps upon his post or quits it without being regularly relieved or without leave; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list3.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>leaves his commanding officer, or his post or party, to go in search of plunder; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list3.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>quits his guard, picquet, party or patrol without being regularly relieved or without leave; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list3.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>uses criminal force to, or commits an assault on any person bringing provisions or other necessaries to camp or quarters, or forces a safeguard or breaks into any house or other place for plunder, or plunders, destroys or damages property of any kind; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list3.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>intentionally causes or spreads a false alarm in action or in camp, garrison or quarters; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list3.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>displays cowardice in the execution of his duty,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall be punishable with transportation for life for a term of not less than seven years or with imprisonment for a term which may extend to fourteen years or with fine which may extend to three months’ pay or with fine to that extent in addition to such sentence of transportation or imprisonment.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Less heinous offences.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Every member of the Force who—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>is in a state of intoxication when on, or after having been warned for, any duty or on parade or on the line of march; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>strikes or attempts to force any sentry; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>being in command of a guard, picquet or patrol, refuses to receive any prisoner or person duly committed to his charge, or without proper authority releases any person or prisoner placed under his charge, or negligently suffers any such prisoner or person to escape; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>being under arrest or in confinement, leaves his arrest or confinement, before he is set at liberty by lawful authority; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>is grossly in subordinate or insolent to his superior officer in the execution of his office; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>refuses to superintend or assist in the making of any field-work or other work of any description ordered to be made either in quarters or in the field; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>strikes or otherwise ill-uses any member of the Force subordinate to him in rank or position; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>designedly or through neglect injures or loses or fraudulently disposes of his arms, clothes, tools, equipments, ammunition or accoutrements, or any such articles entrusted to him or belonging to any other person; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>malingers or feigns or produces disease or infirmity in himself, or intentionally delays his cure, or aggravates his disease or infirmity; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>with intent to render himself or any other person unfit for service, voluntarily causes hurt to himself or any other person; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>does not, when called upon by his superior officer so to do or upon ceasing to be a member of the Force forthwith deliver up, or duly account for, all or any arms, ammunition, stores, accoutrements or other property issued or supplied to him or in his custody or possession as such member; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>knowingly furnishes a false return or report of the number or state of any men under his command or charge or of any money, arms, ammunition, clothing, equipments, stores or other property in his charge, whether belonging to such men or to the Government or to any member of, or any person attached to the Force, or who, through design or culpable neglect, omits or refuses to make or send any return or report of the matters aforesaid; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>absents himself without leave, or without sufficient cause overstays leave granted to him; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>is guilty of any act or omission which, though not specified in this Act, is prejudicial to good order and discipline; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>contravenes any provision of this Act for which no punishment is expressly provided; or</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>who, while not on active duty,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list3.p">
                <num>(p)</num>
                <p>commits any of the offences specified in clauses (e) to (l) (both inclusive) of section 9,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or with fine which may extend to three months’ pay, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Minor punishments.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Commandant or any other authority or officer as may be prescribed, may, subject to any rules made under this Act, award in lieu of, or in addition to, suspension or dismissal any one or more of the following punishments to any member of the Force whom he considers to be guilty of disobedience, neglect of duty, or remissness in the discharge of any duty or of other misconduct in his capacity as a member of the Force, that is to say,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>reduction in rank;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>fine of any amount not exceeding one month’s pay and allowances;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>confinement to quarters, lines or camp for a term not exceeding one month;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>confinement in the quarter-guard for not more than twenty-eight days, with or without punishment drill or extra guard, fatigue or other duty; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>removal from any office of distinction or special emolument in the Force.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any punishment specified in clause (c) or clause (d) of sub-section (1) may be awarded by any gazetted officer when in command of any detachment of the Force away from headquarters, provided he is specially authorised in this behalf by the commandant.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Assistant Commandant, a company officer or a subordinate officer, not being below the rank of subedar or inspector, commanding a separate detachment or an outpost, or in temporary command at the headquarters of the Force, may, without a formal trial, award to any member of the Force who is for the time being subject to his authority any one or more of the following punishment for the commission of any petty offence against discipline which is not otherwise provided for in this Act, or which is not of a sufficiently serious nature to require prosecution before a criminal court, that is to say,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>confinement for not more than seven days in the quarter-guard or such other place as may be considered suitable, with forfeiture of all pay and allowances during its continuance;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>punishment drill, or extra guard, fatigue or other duty, for not more than thirty days with or without confinement to quarters, lines or camp;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.3.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>censure or severe censure:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that this punishment may be awarded to a subordinate officer only by the Commandant.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A jemadar or sub-inspector who is temporarily in command of a detachment or an outpost may, in like manner and for the commission of any like offence, award to any member of the Force for the time being subject to his authority any of the punishments specified in clause (b) of sub-section (3) for not more than fifteen days.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Place of imprisonment and liability to dismissal on imprisonment.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every person sentenced under this Act to imprisonment may be dismissed from the Force, and shall further be liable to forfeiture of pay, allowance and any other moneys due to him as well as of any medals and decorations received by him.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every such person shall, if he is so dismissed, be imprisoned in the prescribed prison, but if he is not also dismissed from the Force, he may, if the Court or the Commandant so directs, be confined in the quarter-guard or such other place as the Court or the Commandant may consider suitable.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Deductions from pay and allowances.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The following penal deductions may be made from the pay and allowances of a member of the Force by his company officer, that is to say,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>all pay and allowances for every day of absence either on desertion or without leave and for every day of imprisonment awarded by a Criminal Court or of confinement awarded under section 11;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>all pay and allowances for every day whilst he is in custody on a charge for an offence of which he is afterwards convicted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>all pay and allowances for every day on which he is in hospital on account of sickness certified by the medical officer attending on him at the hospital to have been caused by an offence committed by him under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>all pay and allowances ordered to be forfeited under section 11; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>such sum as may be ordered by the Commandant or assistant commandant in order to make good any expenses caused by the member of the Force, or any loss of, or damage or destruction done by him to, any arms, ammunition, equipment, clothing, instruments or decorations belonging to the Force or to any buildings or property.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Collective fines.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whenever any weapon, part of a weapon or ammunition, forming part of the equipment of a company or other similar unit of the Force, is lost or stolen the Commandant may, after making such inquiry as he thinks fit and subject to such rules as may be prescribed, impose a collective fine upon the subordinate officers and men of such unit, or upon so many of them as, in his judgment, should be held responsible for such loss or theft.</p>
            <p>ARREST</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Arrest.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any member of the Force who commits any offence specified in section 9 or section 10 may be placed on open or close arrest by any officer of the Force.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any subordinate officer orders an arrest under sub-section (1), he shall forthwith or at the earliest opportunity report the arrest to his company or detachment Commander who shall after investigating the case order the release or the continued arrest of the member of the Force arrested.</p>
            <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Powers and duties conferrable and imposable on members of the Force.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-16.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by general or special order, confer or impose upon any member of the Force any of the powers or duties conferred or imposed on a police officer of any class or grade by any law for the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898) the Central Government may invest the Commandant or an assistant commandant with the powers of a Magistrate of any class for the purpose of inquiring into or trying any offence committed by member of the Force and punishable under this Act, or any offence committed by a member of the Force against the person or property of another member:</p>
            <blockList id="section-16.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-16.2.list2.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>when the offender is on leave or absent from duty, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list2.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>when the offence is not connected with the offender's duties as a member of the Force, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list2.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>when it is a petty offence, even if connected with the offender's duties as a member of the Force,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>the offence may, if the prescribed authority within the limits of whose jurisdiction the offence has been committed, so directs, be inquired into or tried by an ordinary Criminal Court having jurisdiction in the matter.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Protection for acts of members of the Force.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In any suit or proceeding against any member of the Force for any act done by him in pursuance of a warrant or order of a competent authority it shall be lawful for him to plead that such act was done by him under the authority of such warrant or order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any such plea may be proved by the production of the warrant or order directing the act and if it is so proved the member of the Force shall thereupon be discharged from liability in respect of the act so done by him, notwithstanding any defect in the jurisdiction of the authority which issued such warrant or order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being in force, any legal proceeding (whether civil or criminal) which may lawfully be brought against any member of the Force for anything done or intended to be done under the powers conferred by, or in pursuance of, any provision of this Act or the rules thereunder, shall be commenced within three months after the act complained of was committed, and not otherwise, and notice in writing of such proceeding and of the cause thereof shall be given to the defendant or his superior officer at least one month before the commencement of such proceeding.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-18.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>regulating the classes and grades of, and the pay, pension and other remuneration of members of the Force, and their conditions of service in the Force;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>regulating the powers and duties of officers authorised to exercise any functions by or under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>fixing the period of service for members of the Force;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>regulating the award of minor punishment under section 11, and providing for appeals from, or the revision of, orders under that section, or the remission of fines imposed under that section, and the remission of deductions made under section 13;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>regulating the several or collective liability of members of the Force in the case of the loss or theft of weapons and ammunition;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>for the disposal of criminal cases arising under this Act and for specifying the prison in which a person convicted in any such case may be confined.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule, or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Validation of acts done before commencement of Act.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any order made, thing done, or action taken by or in relation to a member of the Force, on or after the 15th day of August, 1947, but before the commencement of this Act, shall for all purposes be deemed to have been made, done or taken under this Act, as if this Act were in force on the day on which such order was made, thing was done or action was taken.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-theschedulerecruitingroll">
      <doc name="theschedulerecruitingroll">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1949/66/theschedulerecruitingroll"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1949/66"/>
              <FRBRalias value="THE SCHEDULE – RECRUITING ROLL"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1949/66/eng@1949-12-28/theschedulerecruitingroll"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1949/66/eng@1949-12-28"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1949/66/eng@1949-12-28/theschedulerecruitingroll"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1949/66/eng@1949-12-28"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-10-05" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="theschedulerecruitingroll">
            <heading>(See section 5)</heading>
            <paragraph id="theschedulerecruitingroll.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>After you have served in the Force for such period as the Central Government may prescribe, you may, at any time when not on active duty, apply for discharge, through the officer to whom you may be subordinate, to the Commandant, and you will be granted your discharge after two months, from the date of your application, unless your discharge would cause the vacancies in the Force to exceed one-tenth of the sanctioned strength in which case you shall be bound to remain until this objection is waived or removed. But when on active duty, you shall have no claim to a discharge, and you shall be bound to remain to do your duty until the necessity for retaining you in the Force ceases when you may make your application in the above-mentioned manner:</p>
                <p>Provided that, if you wish to withdraw from the Force, you may submit your resignation at any time before the expiration of the first three months of your service, but not afterwards until the completion of the period prescribed as aforesaid; the Commandant may either accept your resignation forthwith or at the end of three months from the date of its receipt:</p>
                <p>Provided, also, that the Commandant may, if he thinks fit, allow you to resign at any time on your giving three months’ notice of your wish to do so.</p>
                <p>................................................................................................</p>
                <p>Signature of the member of the Force in acknowledgement of the above having been read out to him.</p>
                <p>................................................................................................</p>
                <p>Space for impression of the member's left thumb to be taken in the presence of the enrolling officer.</p>
                <p>................................................................................................</p>
                <p>Signed in my presence after I had ascertained that the candidate understood the purport of what he signed.</p>
                <p>....................</p>
                <p>Commandant,</p>
                <p>or other authorised enrolling officer.</p>
                <p>Place....................</p>
                <p>Date......................</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
