<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-tmn/act/2013/22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-tmn/act/2013/22"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Tamil Nadu Police (Reform) Act, 2013"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-tmn/act/2013/22/eng@2017-01-20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-tmn/act/2013/22/eng@2017-01-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-20" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-tmn/act/2013/22/eng@2017-01-20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-tmn/act/2013/22/eng@2017-01-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-20" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Tamil Nadu Police (Reform) Act, 2013</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[11th September 2013]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[Act No. 22 of 2013]</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for a law to carry out the directions of the Hon’ble Supreme Court in Prakash Singh case regarding Police reforms and for matters connected therewith and incidental thereto.</p>
      </longTitle>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by the Legislative Assembly of the State of Tamil Nadu in the Sixty-fourth Year of the Republic of India as follows:-</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Tamil Nadu Police (Reforms) Act, 2013.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 11th day of September 2013.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“Board” means the Police Establishment Board constituted under section 8;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“Commission” means the State Security Commission established under section 5;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“Government” means the State Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>“Police Officer” means any member of the Tamil Nadu Police and includes an Indian Police Service (IPS) officer working in connection with the affairs of the State and the Tamil Nadu Police;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>“subordinate ranks” means all ranks below the rank of Deputy Superintendent of Police or its equivalent;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>“supervisory ranks” means ranks of Deputy Superintendent of Police or its equivalent and above;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Words and expressions used in this Act, but not defined specifically shall have the same meaning as provided in the Police Act, 1861 (Central Act V of 1861), the Tamil Nadu District Police Act, 1859 (Central Act XXIV of 1859), the Chennai City Police Act, 1888 (Tamil Nadu Act III of 1888), the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (Central Act 2 of 1974) and the Indian Penal Code, 1860 (Central Act XLV of 1860).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Selection, appointment and tenure of Director General of Police</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government shall appoint the Director General of Police from amongst the five senior-most Police Officers of the Department empanelled by the Union Public Service Commission for the post of Director General of Police, having regard to length of service, very good record and range of experience for heading the Police Force.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Service Rules, the Director General of Police appointed under sub-section (1) shall hold the post for a minimum period of two years, irrespective of the date of his/her superannuation.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Director General of Police may be relieved of his/her responsibilities under the following circumstances, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>on conviction by a court of law in a criminal case or a case of corruption;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>on punishment of dismissal, removal or compulsory retirement from service or of reduction to a lower post awarded under the provisions of All India Services (Discipline and Appeal) Rules or any other relevant rule;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.3.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>on incapacitation by physical or mental illness or otherwise becoming unable to discharge his/her functions;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.3.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>on appointment to any other post either under the State Government or Central Government, with his/her consent for such posting;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.3.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>on other administrative grounds to be recorded in writing.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Term of office of holder of certain posts</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the service conditions, a Police Officer posted to be in charge of a Police Station, Police District or Commissionerate shall hold office for a minimum period of two years, or till the date of his/her superannuation, whichever is earlier</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The provisions of sub-section (1) shall not apply in cases where any Police Officer referred to in sub-section (1) is—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>convicted by a court of law in a criminal case or a case of corruption;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>involved in a criminal case wherein charges have been framed by a court;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>awarded punishment in disciplinary proceedings;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>placed under suspension;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>subjected to disciplinary proceedings after charges having been framed;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>incapacitated by physical or mental illness or otherwise becoming unable to discharge his/her functions;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>promoted to a higher post;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>to be relieved to fill up a vacancy caused by promotion, transfer or retirement of other officer;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>to be relieved for any other administrative grounds to be recorded in writing.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>State Security Commission</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government shall establish a Commission to be known as State Security Commission.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Commission shall consist of the following members, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the Minister, in-charge of the portfolio of Police, who shall be the Chairperson, ex-officio;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the Leader of the Opposition in the Tamil Nadu Legislative Assembly;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>Chairperson, Tamil Nadu Public Service Commission, ex-officio;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>Chairperson, Tamil Nadu State Human Rights Commission, ex-officio;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>Chairperson, State Women’s Commission, ex-officio;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>Chairperson, State Women’s Commission, ex-officio;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the Chief Secretary, ex-officio;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the Secretary in-charge of the Home Department, ex-officio; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the Director General of Police, who shall be the Member-Secretary, ex-officio.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Functions of Commission</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Commission shall perform the following functions, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to frame broad policy guidelines for promoting efficient, effective, responsive and accountable policing, in accordance with the law;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to identify performance indicators to evaluate the functioning of the Police Force, which shall include operational efficiency, public satisfaction, victim satisfaction in respect of Police investigation and response, accountability, optimum utilisation of resources and observance of human rights standards;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to review and evaluate organisational performance of the Police Force; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>such other functions that may be entrusted by the Government.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Annual Report</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commission shall, at the end of every year, submit to the Government the annual report on its work during the preceding year and on the evaluation of performance of the Police Force which shall include recommendations for improvement.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government shall lay the annual report referred to in sub-section (1) on the table of the Legislative Assembly.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Constitution and functions of the Police Establishment Board and Committees</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>There shall be a Police Establishment Board consisting of the Director General of Police and the following four Senior Police Officers in the rank of Additional Director General of Police, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>Additional Director General of Police (Administration);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>Additional Director General of Police (Law and Order);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>Additional Director General of Police (Head Quarters); and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>Additional Director General of Police (Intelligence).</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Director General of Police shall be the Chairperson and the senior-most Additional Director General of Police shall be the convener of the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The functions of the Board shall be as follows:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>The Board shall consider and recommend promotion, transfer and posting of the officers in the rank of Superintendent of Police and above up to the rank of Inspector General of Police.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>On the recommendations of the Board, the Director General of Police shall send the proposals to the Government for appropriate action.</p>
            <blockList id="section-8.3.list4">
              <listIntroduction>For promotion, transfer and posting of officers above the rank of Inspector General of Police, the Director General of Police shall send the proposals to the Government for appropriate action.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.3.list4.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>The Board shall function as a forum to deal with the representations from officers of the rank of Superintendent of Police and above. The Board shall examine such representations and send its recommendations to the Government by the Director General of Police.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.3.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>The Board shall also make recommendations to the Government for award of Medals.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be a State Police Establishment Committee to consider matters relating to promotion, transfer and postings of officers of and below the rank of Additional Superintendent of Police</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be Zonal, Range, City and District Level Establishment Committees which will be empowered to effect transfers of Police Personnel of subordinate rank within their jurisdiction in accordance with the instructions and guidelines issued by the Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government shall prescribe the composition, responsibilities, functions and powers of the State, Zonal, Range, City and District Level Establishment Committees</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The recruitment and promotions made under this section shall be in accordance with the service rules governing the respective service, category and class.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Law and Order and Criminal Investigation wings – separation</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In every Police Station, except those specifically designated as Crime Police Stations, there shall be a Law and Order Wing and an Investigation Wing, both working under the control of the Station House Officer, who shall ensure co-ordination between the two wings.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Investigation Wing shall be responsible for investigation and prosecution of all cases registered in the station, including cases detected by the Law and Order Wing.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Police Officers of the Investigation Wing may be called Detective Constables, Detective Head Constables and Detective Sub-Inspectors. They shall not be diverted to any bandobust work except with the prior approval of the Zonal Inspector General of Police or Commissioner of Police</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Investigation Wing shall be provided with adequate staff to cope with the work load. The Board shall lay down norms for staff strength taking into account the volume of cases.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Police Station shall have a Missing Person Liaison Officer in the rank of a Detective Sub-Inspector to co-ordinate and follow up the cases of missing persons.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Within the Investigation Wing of each Police Station, at least one officer with aptitude and appropriate training and orientation shall be designated as the ‘Juvenile or Child Welfare Officer’ as required under sub-section (2) of section 63 of the Juvenile Justice (Care and Protection of Children) Act, 2000 (Central Act 56 of 2000) . This Officer will handle juveniles or children in co-ordination with other Police Officers. These officers together will be members of the Special Juvenile Police Unit of the District or City to co-ordinate and to upgrade the Police treatment of juveniles and children.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>State Complaints Authority</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Government shall establish at the State Level, a Police Complaints Authority, which shall have as its Chairperson, the Secretary in-charge of the Home department. The Director General of Police and Additional Director General of Police (Law and Order) shall be the members of the State Police Complaints Authority.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Conduct of Business</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Police Complaints Authority shall frame its own rules for the conduct of its business.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Functions of State Police Complaints Authority</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Police Complaints Authority shall inquire into allegations of “serious misconduct” against the Police Personnel in the supervisory ranks, on a complaint received from a victim in the form of a sworn affidavit duly attested by a notary public:</p>
            <p>Provided that in case of death in Police custody, the complaint can be received from the legal heirs or close relatives of the victim:</p>
            <p>Provided further that the State Police Complaints Authority shall entertain the complaint, only on prima facie satisfaction about the veracity of the complaint:</p>
            <p>Provided also that no anonymous or pseudonymous complaints shall be entertained:</p>
            <p>Provided also that the State Police Complaints Authority shall not entertain complaints of serious misconduct which are the subject matter of any judicial proceedings or inquiry under the Commissions of Inquiry Act, 1952 (Central Act 60 of 1952) or the Protection of Human Rights Act, 1993 (Central Act 10 of 1994) or the Police Standing Orders.</p>
            <blockList id="section-12.1.list6">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation. — For the purpose of this Chapter, “serious misconduct” means any act or omission of a Police Officer that leads to or amounts to—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.1.list6.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>Death in Police custody;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.1.list6.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>Rape;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.1.list6.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>Grievous hurt in Police custody.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Recommendations of State Police Complaints Authority</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any complaint of serious misconduct received by the State Police Complaints Authority which is not covered by the fourth proviso to section 12 shall be referred to the Police Complaints Division for enquiry and report, if necessary, after examining the victim or complainant or any other person and relevant documents.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Police Complaints Authority shall submit its recommendations to the Government for appropriate action.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of District Police Complaints Authority</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government shall, by notification, constitute a District Police Complaints Authority for each District or Commissionerate.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The District Police Complaints Authority shall have as its Chairperson the District Collector/District Magistrate. The Superintendent of Police and the Additional Superintendent of Police shall be the members of the District Police Complaints Authority. In the case of Commissionerates, other than Chennai, the Superintendent of Police of the District and the Deputy Commissioner of the Commissionerate shall be the members. In the case of Commissionerate of Chennai, the District Collector and the Commissioner of Police shall be the members.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Functions of District Police Complaints Authority</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-15.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>The District Police Complaints Authority shall enquire into allegations of misconduct or serious misconduct, against Police Personnel in subordinate ranks, on a complaint received from a victim in the form of a sworn affidavit duly attested by a notary public:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that in the case of death in Police custody, the complaint can be received from the legal heirs or close relatives of the victim:</p>
            <p>Provided further that the District Police Complaints Authority shall entertain the complaint, only on prima facie satisfaction about the veracity of the complaint:</p>
            <p>Provided also that no anonymous or pseudonymous complaints shall be entertained:</p>
            <p>Provided also that the District Police Complaints Authority shall not entertain complaints of serious misconduct or misconduct which are the subject matter of any judicial proceedings or inquiry under the Commissions of Inquiry Act, 1952, (Central Act 60 of 1952) or the Protection of Human Rights Act, 1993, (Central Act 10 of 1994)  or the Police Standing Orders.</p>
            <blockList id="section-15.paragraph-0.list6">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation.— For the purpose of this clause, the expression ‘serious misconduct’ will have the same meaning assigned in the explanation to section 12 and ‘misconduct’ means extortion, land or house grabbing or any other incident involving serious abuse of authority;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list6.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>The District Police Complaints Authority shall refer to the State Police Complaints Authority complaints received by it against Police Officers in the ‘supervisory rank’ and such other matters as it may deem fit.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Procedure to be followed by District Police Complaints Authority</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>District Police Complaints Authority shall follow the following procedure for the disposal of complaints:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>Any complaint of misconduct or serious misconduct received by the District Police Complaints Authority which is not covered by the fourth proviso to section 15 shall be referred to the Police Complaints Division for enquiry and report, if necessary, after examining the victim or complainant or any other person and relevant documents, and after ascertaining from the concerned disciplinary authority whether any disciplinary proceedings have already been initiated in regard to the same complaint of misconduct</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>The District Police Complaints Authority shall submit its recommendations to the Government for appropriate action.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Complaint involving supervisory rank and subordinate rank</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If a complaint of serious misconduct involving both personnel in supervisory ranks as well as subordinate ranks is made, in respect of the same misconduct, it shall be dealt with by the State Police Complaints Authority.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Supporting staff of State Police Complaints Authority and District Police Complaints Authority</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Police Complaints Authority and District Police Complaints Authority shall be assisted by requisite supporting staff with such terms and conditions and allowances as may be prescribed for the efficient discharge of their functions.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Police Complaints Division</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A Police Complaints Division shall be constituted with field units in such manner as may be prescribed to carry out investigations. It will work under the administrative control of an Additional Director General of Police, under the overall control of the Director General of Police. It shall consist of, apart from serving Police Officers, retired Police Officers or Vigilance or Intelligence or Crime Branch Police Officers or personnel serving or retired from other departments.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules</heading>
        <subsection id="section-20.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may make rules to carry out all or any of the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-20.2.list0">
              <item id="section-20.2.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>All rules made under this Act shall be published in the Tamil Nadu Government Gazette, and unless they are expressed to come into force on a particular day, shall come into force on the day on which they are so published</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-20.2.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>All notifications issued under this Act, shall, unless they are expressed to come into force on a particular day, come into force on the day on which they are so published.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made or notification or order issued under this Act, shall, as soon as possible, after it is made or issued, be placed on the table of the Legislative Assembly and if, before the expiry of the session in which it is so placed or the next session, the Legislative Assembly makes any modification in any such rule, notification or order, or the Legislative Assembly decides that the rule, notification or order should not be made or issued, the rule, notification or order shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule, notification or order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Power to remove difficulties</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Government may, by an order published in the Tamil Nadu Government Gazette, make such provisions not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act as appear to them to be necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty:</p>
            <p>Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a period of two years from the date of commencement of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Acts of State Security Commission, Board, State Police Complaints Authority and District Police Complaints Authority not to be invalidated by certain defects</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No act or proceeding of the Commission, Board, State Police Complaints Authority and District Police Complaints Authority shall be called in question merely on the ground of the existence of any vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution of such Commission, Board, State Police Complaints Authority and District Police Complaints Authority.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Repeal and saving</heading>
        <subsection id="section-23.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Tamil Nadu Police (Reforms) Ordinance, 2013 (Tamil Nadu Ordinance 3 of 2013) is hereby repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done, any action taken or any direction given under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done, taken or given under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
