<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1963/33/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1963/33"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Karnataka Prisons Act, 1963"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1963/33/eng@2017-01-20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1963/33/eng@2017-01-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-20" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1963/33/eng@2017-01-20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1963/33/eng@2017-01-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-20" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Karnataka Prisons Act, 1963</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>ACT No. 33 of 1963</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for a uniform law for the regulation of prisons in the State of Karnataka.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for a uniform law for the regulation of prisons in the State of Karnataka</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>BE it enacted by the Karnataka State Legislature in the Fourteenth Year of the Republic of India as follows:—</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <heading>Preliminary</heading>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the Karnataka Prisons Act, 1963.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Karnataka.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on such date as the State Government may, by notification, appoint.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>“civil prisoner” means any prisoner who is not a criminal prisoner;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>“convicted criminal prisoner” means any criminal prisoner under sentence of a Court or Court Martial, and includes a person detained in prison under the provisions of Chapter VIII of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (Central Act V of 1898);</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>“criminal prisoner” means any prisoner duly committed to custody under a writ, warrant or order of any Court or authority exercising criminal jurisdiction or by order of a Court Martial;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>“furlough system” means a system of releasing prisoners in jails on furlough in accordance with the rules made under section 63;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>“history ticket” means the ticket exhibiting such information as is required in respect of each prisoner by this Act or the rules made thereunder;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>“Inspector-General” means the Inspector-General of Prisons;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>“medical subordinate” means an Assistant Surgeon appointed as medical subordinate under section 4;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>“notification” means a notification published in the official Gazette;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.j.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>“prison” means any jail or place used permanently or temporarily under the general or special orders of the State Government for the detention of prisoners, and includes all lands and buildings appurtenant thereto, but does not include,—</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.j.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>any place for the confinement of prisoners who are exclusively in the custody of the Police;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.j.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>any place specially appointed by the State Government under section 541 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.j.list0.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>any place which has been declared by the State Government, by general or special order, to be a subsidiary jail;</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>“prohibited article” means an article the introduction or removal of which into or out of a prison is prohibited by any rule made under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>“remission system” means the system of regulating the award of marks to, and the consequence of shortening of sentences of prisoners in jail in accordance with the rules for the time being in force.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <heading>Maintenance and officers of prisons</heading>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Inspector-General.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Government shall appoint an Inspector-General who shall, subject to the orders of the State Government, exercise the general control and superintendence of all prisons in the State.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Officers of prisons.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>There shall be for every prison a Superintendent, a Medical Officer (who may also be the Superintendent), a Medical Subordinate, a Jailer and such other officers as the State Government thinks necessary:</p>
              <p>Provided that the State Government may declare by order in writing that in any prison specified in the order, the office of Jailer shall be held by the person appointed to be the Superintendent.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Accommodation for prisoners.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Government shall provide, for the prisoners in the State, accommodation in prisons constructed and regulated in such manner as to comply with the requisitions of this Act in respect of the separation of prisoners.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Temporary accommodation.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Whenever it appears to the Inspector-General that the number of prisoners in any prison is greater than can conveniently or safely be kept therein, and it is not convenient to transfer the excess number to some other prison, or whenever from the outbreak of epidemic disease within any prison, or for any other reason it is desirable to provide for the temporary and safe custody of any prisoners, provision shall be made, by such officer and in such manner as the State Government may direct, for the shelter and safe custody in temporary prisons of so many of the prisoners as cannot be conveniently or safely kept in the prison.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <heading>Duties of officers</heading>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>General</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Control and duties of officers of prisons.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>All officers of a prison shall obey the directions of the Superintendent; all officers subordinate to the Jailer shall perform such duties as may be prescribed, or be imposed on them, by the Jailer, with the sanction of the Superintendent.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Officers not to have business dealings with prisoners.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No officer of a prison shall sell or let, nor shall any person in trust for or employed by him sell or let, or derive any benefit from selling or letting, any article to any prisoner or have any money or other business dealings directly or indirectly, with any prisoner.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Officers not to be interested in prison contracts.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No officer of a prison shall, nor shall any person in trust for or employed by him, have any interest, direct or indirect, in any contract for the supply of any article to the prison; nor shall he derive any benefit, directly or indirectly, from the sale or purchase of any article on behalf of the prison or belonging to a prisoner.</p>
              <p>Superintendent.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Superintendent.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the orders of the Inspector-General, the Superintendent shall manage the prison in all matters relating to welfare, discipline, labour, expenditure, punishment and control.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to such general or special direction as may be given by the State Government, the Superintendent of a prison other than a Central Prison, shall obey all orders not inconsistent with this Act or any rule thereunder, which may be given respecting the prison by the District Magistrate, and shall report to the Inspector-General all such orders and the action taken thereon:</p>
              <p>Provided that the District Magistrate shall immediately forward a copy of such order to the Inspector-General of Prisons for ratification.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Records to be kept by Superintendent.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Superintendent shall keep, or cause to be kept, the following records:—</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>a register of prisoners admitted;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>a book showing when each prisoner is to be released;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>a punishment book for the entry of the punishment inflicted on prisoners for prison offences;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>a visitors’ book for the entry of any observations made by the visitors touching any matters connected with the administration of the prison;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>a record of the money and other articles taken from prisoners; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>all such other records as may be prescribed. Medical Officer.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Duties of Medical Officer.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the control of the Superintendent, the Medical Officer shall have charge of the sanitary and health administration of the prison and shall perform such duties as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Medical Officer to report in certain cases.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Whenever the Medical Officer has reason to believe that the mind of a prisoner is, or is likely to be, injuriously affected by the discipline or treatment to which he is subjected, the Medical Officer shall report the case in writing to the Superintendent, together with such observations as he may think proper. The Superintendent shall forthwith send such report, with his orders thereon, to the Inspector-General, for information.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Report on the death of prisoner.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>On the death of any prisoner, the Medical Officer shall forthwith record in a register the following particulars, so far as they can be ascertained, namely:—</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the day on which the deceased first complained of illness or was observed to be ill;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the labour, if any, on which he was engaged on that day;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the scale of his diet on that day;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the day on which the Medical Officer was first informed of the illness;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the day on which he was admitted to hospital;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the nature of the disease;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>when the deceased was last seen before his death, by the Medical Officer or the Medical Subordinate;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>when the prisoner died and reasons therefor; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <p>(in case where a post-mortem examination is made), an account of the appearances after death,</p>
              <p>together with any special remarks that appear to the Medical Officer to be required.</p>
              <p>A copy of the particulars recorded shall be sent to the Inspector-General and the nearest relatives of the deceased prisoner as soon as may be after the record is made.</p>
              <p>Jailer.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Jailer.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-15.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Jailer shall reside in the prison, unless the Superintendent permits him in writing to reside elsewhere.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Jailer shall not, without the sanction of the Inspector-General in writing, be concerned in any other employment.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Jailer to give notice of death of prisoner.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Upon the death of a prisoner, the Jailer shall give immediate notice thereof to the Superintendent and the Medical Officer.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Responsibilities of Jailer.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Jailer shall be responsible for the safe custody of the records to be kept under section 11, for the commitment warrants and all other documents confided to his care and for the money and other articles taken from the prisoners.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Jailer to be present at night.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Jailer shall not be absent from the prison for a night, without the permission in writing from the Superintendent; if absent without leave for a night from unavoidable necessity, he shall immediately report the fact and the cause of it, to the Superintendent.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Powers of Deputy and Assistant Jailers.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Where a Deputy Jailer or Assistant Jailer is appointed to a prison, he shall, subject to the orders of the Superintendent, be competent to perform any of the duties, and be subject to all the responsibilities of a Jailer under this Act, or any rule thereunder.</p>
              <p>Subordinate Officers.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Duties of gatekeeper.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The officer acting as gatekeeper or any other officer of the prison may examine anything carried in or out of the prison, and may stop and search or cause to be searched any person suspected of bringing any prohibited article into or out of the prison or carrying out any property belonging to the prison, and if any such article or property be found, shall give immediate notice thereof to the Jailer.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Subordinate officers not to be absent without leave.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Officers subordinate to the Jailer shall not be absent from the prison without leave from the Superintendent or from the Jailer.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Convict officers.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Prisoners who have been appointed as officers of prisons shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <heading>Admission, removal and discharge of prisoners</heading>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Prisoners to be examined on admission.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-23.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Whenever a prisoner is admitted into prison, he shall be searched, and all weapons and prohibited articles shall be taken from him.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every criminal prisoner shall also, as soon as possible after admission, be examined under the general or special orders of the Medical Officer, who shall enter or cause to be entered in a book to be kept by the Jailer, a record of the state of the prisoner’s health and of any wounds or marks on his person, the class of labour he is fit for if he is sentenced to rigorous imprisonment, and any observations which the Medical Officer thinks fit to add.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the case of female prisoners, search and examination shall be carried out by a Lady Medical Subordinate, if any, or by the Matron under the general or special orders of the Medical Officer.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Effects of prisoners.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>All money or other articles in respect whereof any order of a competent Court has been made and which may with proper authority be brought into the prison by any criminal prisoner or sent to the prison for his use, shall be placed in the custody of the Jailer and the prisoner shall be informed and his signature taken in the prescribed register.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Removal and discharge of prisoners.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-25.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All prisoners, previously to being removed to any other prison shall be examined by the Medical Officer.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No person shall be removed from one prison to another unless the Medical Officer certifies that the prisoner is free from any illness rendering him unfit for removal.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No prisoner shall be discharged against his will from prison, if labouring under any acute or dangerous distemper, nor until, in the opinion of the Medical Officer, such discharge is safe.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <heading>Discipline of prisoners</heading>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Separation of prisoners.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The requisitions of this Act with respect to the separation of prisoners are as follows:—</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-26.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>in a prison containing women as well as men prisoners, the women shall be imprisoned in separate buildings or separate parts of the same building, in such manner as to prevent their seeing or conversing or holding any intercourse with the men prisoners;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-26.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>in a prison where men prisoners under the age of twenty-one years are confined means should be provided for separating them altogether from the other prisoners and for separating those of them who have arrived at the age of puberty from those who have not;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-26.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>unconvicted criminal prisoners shall be kept apart from convicted criminal prisoners; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-26.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>civil prisoners shall be kept apart from criminal prisoners.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Association and segregation of prisoners.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of section 26, convicted criminal prisoners may be confined either in association or individually in cells, or partly in one way and partly in the other.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Solitary confinement.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No cell shall be used for solitary confinement unless it is furnished with the means of enabling the prisoner to communicate at any time with an officer of the Prison and every prisoner so confined in a cell for more than twenty-four hours, whether as a punishment or otherwise, shall be visited at least once a day by the Medical Officer or Medical Subordinate.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Prisoners under sentence of death.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-29.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every person under sentence of death shall immediately on his arrival in the prison after sentence, be searched by, or by order of, the Jailer, and all articles shall be taken from him, which the Jailer deems it to be dangerous or inexpedient to leave in his possession.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every such prisoner shall be confined in a cell apart from all other prisoners and shall be placed by day and by night under the charge of a guard.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VI">
        <num>VI</num>
        <heading>Food, clothing and bedding of civil and unconvicted CRIMINAL PRISONERS</heading>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading>Maintenance of certain prisoners from private sources.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-30.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>A civil prisoner or an unconvicted criminal prisoner shall be permitted to maintain himself and to purchase or receive from private sources at proper hours food, clothing, bedding or writing materials, books, newspapers or other necessaries, subject to examination and to such regulations as may be approved by the Inspector-General.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading>Restrictions on transfer of food and clothing between certain prisoners.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-31.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No part of any food, clothing, bedding or other necessaries belonging to any civil or unconvicted criminal prisoner shall be given, hired or sold to any other prisoner; and any prisoner transgressing the provisions of this section shall lose the privilege of purchasing food or receiving it from private sources, for such time as the Superintendent thinks proper.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>Supply of clothing and bedding to civil and unconvicted criminal prisoners.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-32.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every civil prisoner and unconvicted criminal prisoner unable to provide himself with sufficient clothing and bedding, shall be supplied by the Superintendent with such clothing and bedding as may be necessary.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When a civil prisoner has been committed to prison by a Court in execution of any decree or order in favour of a private person, such person shall immediately deposit or cause to be deposited in Court, to meet the cost of the prisoner’s clothing and bedding, such amount as may be fixed by the Court in accordance with the rules, if any, made by the State Government in that behalf; and in default of such deposit, the prisoner may be released.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VII">
        <num>VII</num>
        <heading>Employment of prisoners</heading>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading>Employment of civil prisoners.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-33.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Civil prisoners may, with the permission of the Superintendent, work and follow any trade or profession.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-33.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Civil prisoners finding their own implements and not maintained at the expense of the prison, shall be allowed to receive the whole of their earnings; but the earnings of such as are furnished with implements or are maintained at the expense of the prison, shall be subject to a deduction to be determined by the Superintendent, for use of implements and the cost of maintenance.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-34">
          <num>34.</num>
          <heading>Employment of criminal prisoners.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-34.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No criminal prisoner sentenced to labour or employed on labour at his own desire, shall, except on an emergency, with the sanction in writing of the Superintendent, be kept to labour for more than eight hours in any one day.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-34.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Medical Officer shall from time to time examine the labouring prisoners while they are employed and shall at least once in every fortnight, cause to be recorded upon the history ticket of each prisoner, employed on labour, the weight and general health of such prisoner at the time.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-34.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When the Medical Officer is of opinion that the health of any prisoner suffers from employment of any kind or class of labour, such prisoner shall not be employed on that labour but shall be placed on such other kind or class of labour as the Medical Officer considers suited for him.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading>Employment of criminal prisoners sentenced to simple imprisonment.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-35.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Superintendent shall make provision for the employment of all criminal prisoners sentenced to simple imprisonment if and as long as they so desire:</p>
              <p>Provided that no prisoner not sentenced to rigorous imprisonment shall be punished for neglect of work but such prisoner may be punished in cases of neglect of work by such alterations in the scale of diet as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VIII">
        <num>VIII</num>
        <heading>Health of prisoners</heading>
        <section id="section-36">
          <num>36.</num>
          <heading>Sick prisoners.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-36.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The names of prisoners desiring to see the Medical Officer or the Medical Subordinate or appearing out of health in mind or body, shall without delay, be reported by the officer in immediate charge of such prisoners, to the Jailer.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Jailer shall, without delay, call the attention of the Medical Officer or the Medical Subordinate to any prisoners desiring to see him, or who is ill or whose state of mind or body appears to require attention and shall carry into effect all written directions given by the Medical Officer or the Medical Subordinate respecting alterations of the discipline or treatment or any such prisoner.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-37">
          <num>37.</num>
          <heading>Record of directions of Medical Officers.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-37.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>All directions given by the Medical Officer or the Medical Subordinate in relation to any prisoner, with the exception of orders for the supply of medicines or directions relating to such other matters as are carried into effect by the Medical Officer himself or under his superintendence, shall be entered day by day in the prisoner’s history ticket or in such other records as may be prescribed; and the Jailer shall make an entry in its proper place, stating in respect of each direction, the fact of its having been or not having been complied with, accompanied by such observations, if any, as the Jailer thinks fit to make and the date of the entry.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-38">
          <num>38.</num>
          <heading>Hospital.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-38.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>In every prison a hospital or proper place for the reception of sick prisoners shall be provided.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-39">
          <num>39.</num>
          <heading>Power of Superintendent to send a prisoner to hospital or asylum for special treatment.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-39.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Superintendent may, if, in his opinion, a prisoner requires special treatment in a hospital outside the prison or in a mental hospital or asylum as defined in the Indian Lunacy Act, 1912 (Central Act IV of 1912), send him to such hospital or asylum, subject to the prisoner or any relative or friend of the prisoner executing such bond and abiding by such conditions, if any, as the State Government may by rule or order prescribe. Any period during which the prisoner is undergoing treatment in such hospital or asylum or spent by him in going thereto, or returning therefrom shall be deemed to be part of the period of his detention in the prison.</p>
              <p>Explanation 1.—</p>
              <p>Nothing contained in this section shall be deemed to affect the operation of section 11 of the Karnataka Prisoners Act, 1963, in cases in which that section applies.</p>
              <p>Explanation 2.—</p>
              <p>In this section “prisoner” means a convicted criminal prisoner.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-39.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any prisoner dealt with under sub-section (1) escapes or attempts to escape from the hospital or asylum to which he has been sent or when going thereto or returning therefrom, he shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years or with fine or with both; and such punishment shall be in addition to the punishment for which the prisoner was liable for the offence of which he was already convicted.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-39.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of Chapter XLII of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898, shall, in so far as may be, apply to the bonds referred to in sub-section (1).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IX">
        <num>IX</num>
        <heading>Visitors to prisoners</heading>
        <section id="section-40">
          <num>40.</num>
          <heading>Visitors to civil and unconvicted criminal prisoners.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-40.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Due provision shall be made for the admission, at proper times and under proper restrictions, into every prison, of persons with whom civil or unconvicted criminal prisoners may desire to communicate, care being taken that, so far as may be consistent with the interest of justice, civil prisoners or prisoners under trial or prisoners intending to prefer an appeal or petition against their conviction, may see their duly qualified legal advisers, without the presence of any other person.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-41">
          <num>41.</num>
          <heading>Search of visitors.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-41.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Jailer may demand the name and address of any visitor to a prisoner and when the Jailer has any ground for suspicion, may search any visitor, or cause him to be searched; but the search shall not be made in the presence of any prisoner or another visitor.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-41.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the case of any such visitor refusing to permit himself to be searched, the Jailer may deny him admission; and the grounds of such proceeding with the particulars thereof, shall be entered in such record as the State Government may direct.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-X">
        <num>X</num>
        <heading>Offences in relation to prisons</heading>
        <section id="section-42">
          <num>42.</num>
          <heading>Penalty for introduction or removal of prohibited articles, into or from prisons and communication with prisoners.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-42.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Whoever, contrary to any rule under this Act, introduces or removes or attempts by any means whatever, to introduce or remove, into or from any prison, or supplies or attempts to supply to any prisoner outside the limits of a prison, any prohibited article, and every officer of a prison who, contrary to any such rule knowingly suffers any such article to be introduced into or removed from any prison, to be possessed by any prisoner or to be supplied to any prisoner outside the limits of a prison, and whoever, contrary to any such rule, communicates or attempts to communicate with any prisoner, and whoever abets any offence made punishable by this section, shall, on conviction, be punished with imprisonment for a term not exceeding six months, or with fine not exceeding two hundred rupees, or with both.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-43">
          <num>43.</num>
          <heading>Power to arrest for offence under section 42.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-43.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>When any person, in the presence of an officer of a prison commits any offence specified in section 42 and refuses on demand of such officer to state his name and residence or gives his name or residence which such officer knows or has reason to believe to be false, such officer may arrest him and shall, without unnecessary delay, make him over to a Police Officer and thereupon such Police Officer shall proceed as if the offence had been committed in his presence.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-44">
          <num>44.</num>
          <heading>Publication of penalties.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-44.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Superintendent shall cause to be affixed in a conspicuous place outside the prison a notice in English and in the languages of the locality in which the prison is situated setting forth the acts prohibited under section 42 and the penalties incurred by their commission.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-XI">
        <num>XI</num>
        <heading>Prison offences</heading>
        <section id="section-45">
          <num>45.</num>
          <heading>Prison offences.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-45.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The following acts are declared to be prison offences when committed by a prisoner:—</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-45.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>such wilful disobedience to any regulation of the prison as shall have been declared by rules made under this Act to be a prison offence;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>any assault or use of criminal force;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the use of insulting or threatening language;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>immoral or indecent or disorderly behaviour;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>wilfully disabling himself from labour;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>contumaciously refusing to work;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>filing, cutting, altering or removing hand-cuffs, fetters or bars without due authority;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>wilful idleness or negligence at work by any prisoner sentenced to rigorous imprisonment;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <p>wilful mismanagement of work by any prisoner sentenced to rigorous imprisonment;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.10">
            <num>(10)</num>
            <content>
              <p>wilful damage to prison property;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.11">
            <num>(11)</num>
            <content>
              <p>tampering with or defacing history ticket, records or documents;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.12">
            <num>(12)</num>
            <content>
              <p>receiving, possessing or transferring any prohibited article;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.13">
            <num>(13)</num>
            <content>
              <p>feigning illness;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.14">
            <num>(14)</num>
            <content>
              <p>wilfully bringing a false accusation against any officer or prisoner;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.15">
            <num>(15)</num>
            <content>
              <p>omitting or refusing to report as soon as it comes to his knowledge the occurrence of any fire, any plot or conspiracy, any escape, attempt or preparation to escape, and any attack or preparation for attack upon any prisoner or prison official; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.16">
            <num>(16)</num>
            <content>
              <p>conspiring to escape or to assist in escaping or to commit any other of the offences aforesaid.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-46">
          <num>46.</num>
          <heading>Punishment of offences under section 45.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-46.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Superintendent may examine any person touching any offence declared to be a prison offence under section 45, and determine thereupon and punish such offence by,—</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-46.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>a formal warning;</p>
              <p>Explanation.—</p>
              <p>A formal warning shall mean a warning personally addressed to a prisoner by the Superintendent and recorded in the punishment book and on the prisoner’s history-ticket.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-46.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>change of labour to some more irksome or severe form for such period as may be prescribed;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-46.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>hard labour for a period not exceeding seven days in case of convicted criminal prisoners not sentenced to rigorous imprisonment;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-46.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>such loss of privileges admissible under the remission or furlough system for the time being in force as may be prescribed;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-46.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>separate confinement for any period not exceeding two months:</p>
              <p>Provided that while executing punishment of separate confinement, no prisoner shall be kept in separate confinement continuously for more than a fortnight at one time and the interval between one period of confinement and the next will be at least a week.</p>
              <p>Explanation.—</p>
              <p>“Separate confinement” means such confinement with or without labour as entirely secludes a prisoner from communication with, but not from sight of, other prisoners.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-47">
          <num>47.</num>
          <heading>Plurality of punishment under section 46.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-47.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-47.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Any two of the punishments enumerated in section 46 may be awarded for combination of offences declared to be prison offences under section 45, subject to the following exceptions, namely:—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-47.1.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>formal warning shall not be combined with any other punishment, except loss of privileges under clause (4) of section 46;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-47.1.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>cellular confinement shall not be combined with separate confinement, so as to prolong the total period of seclusion to which the prisoner shall be liable.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-47.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No punishment will be combined with any other punishment in contravention of the rules made under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-47.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No punishment shall be awarded for an offence under section 45, so as to combine, with the punishment awarded for any other such offence, two of the punishments which may not be awarded in combination for any such offence.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-48">
          <num>48.</num>
          <heading>Award for punishment under section 46 and section 47.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-48.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Superintendent shall have power to award any of the punishments enumerated in section 46 and section 47, subject, in the case of separate confinement for a period exceeding one month, to the previous confirmation of the Inspector-General.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-48.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No officer subordinate to the Superintendent shall have power to award any punishment whatever.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-49">
          <num>49.</num>
          <heading>Punishment for breach of conditions of suspension of sentence, etc.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-49.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-49.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>If any prisoner fails without sufficient cause to observe any of the conditions on which his sentence was suspended or remitted or furlough was granted to him, he shall be deemed to have committed a prison offence and the Superintendent may, after obtaining his explanation, punish such prisoner by,—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-49.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>a formal warning as provided in clause (1) of section 46;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-49.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>reduction in grade if such prisoner has been appointed an officer of prison;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-49.paragraph-0.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>loss of privileges admissible under the remission or furlough system; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-49.paragraph-0.list1.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>loss of such other privileges as the State Government may by a general or special order, direct.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-50">
          <num>50.</num>
          <heading>Punishment to be in accordance with the foregoing except by order of a competent court.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-50.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Except by order of a competent court no punishment other than the punishment specified in section 46, section 47, section 48 or section 49 shall be inflicted on any prisoner and no punishment shall be inflicted on any prisoner otherwise than in accordance with the provisions of those sections.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-51">
          <num>51.</num>
          <heading>Medical Officer to certify to fitness of prisoner for punishment.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-51.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No punishment of change of labour under clause (2) of section 46 shall be executed until the prisoner to whom such punishment has been awarded has been examined by the</p>
              <p>Medical Officer, who, if he considers the prisoner fit to undergo the punishment, shall certify accordingly in the appropriate column of the punishment book prescribed in section 11.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-51.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If he considers the prisoner unfit to undergo the punishment, he shall in like manner record his opinion in writing and shall state whether the prisoner is absolutely unfit for punishment of the kind awarded, or whether he considers any modification necessary.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-51.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If he considers any modification necessary he shall state what extent of punishment he thinks the prisoner can undergo without injury to his health.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-52">
          <num>52.</num>
          <heading>Entries in punishment books.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-52.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the punishment-book prescribed in section 11, there shall be recorded in respect of every punishment inflicted, the prisoner’s name, register number and the class (whether habitual or not) to which he belongs, the prison offence of which he was guilty, the date on which such prison offence was committed, the number of previous prison offences recorded against the prisoner, and the date of his last prison offence, the punishment awarded and the date of infliction.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-52.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the case of every serious prison offence names of the witnesses proving the offence shall be recorded.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-52.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Against the entries relating to each punishment, the Jailer and the Superintendent shall affix their initials as evidence of the correctness of the entries.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-53">
          <num>53.</num>
          <heading>Procedure on committal of heinous offence.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-53.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>If any prisoner is guilty of any offence against any prison discipline which, by reason of his having frequently committed such offences, or otherwise, in the opinion of the Superintendent is not adequately punishable by the infliction of any punishment which he has power under this Act to award, the Superintendent may forward such prisoner to any Magistrate of the First Class having jurisdiction together with a statement of the circumstances, and such Magistrate shall thereupon inquire into and try the charge so brought against the prisoner, and, upon conviction, may sentence him to imprisonment which may extend to one year, such term to be in addition to any term for which such prisoner was undergoing imprisonment when he committed such offence, or may sentence him to any of the punishments to which he is liable under section 46:</p>
              <p>Provided that no person shall be punished twice for the same offence.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-54">
          <num>54.</num>
          <heading>Offences by prison subordinates.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-54.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-54.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Every Jailer or officer of a prison subordinate to him,—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-54.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>who shall be guilty of any violation of duty or wilful breach or neglect of any rule or regulation, or lawful order made by competent authority; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-54.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>who shall withdraw from the duties of his office without permission or without having given previous notice in writing of his intention for the period of two months; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-54.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>who shall wilfully overstay any leave granted to him; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-54.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>who shall engage without authority in any employment other than his prison duty; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-54.1.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>who shall be guilty of cowardice;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>shall, on conviction, be punished with fine not exceeding two hundred rupees, or with imprisonment for a period not exceeding three months, or with both.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-54.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No person shall under this section be punished twice for the same offence.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-XII">
        <num>XII</num>
        <heading>Temporary release of prisoners</heading>
        <section id="section-55">
          <num>55.</num>
          <heading>Power to release certain prisoners temporarily.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-55.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government or any authority to which the State Government may delegate its power in this behalf may, subject to such conditions as may be prescribed, release temporarily for a period not exceeding ten days in a year (excluding the time required for journeys and the days of departure from and the arrival at prison) any prisoner who has been sentenced to a term of imprisonment of not less than three years.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-55.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of sub-section (1) shall not apply to a prisoner who has been classified as habitual criminal for the purposes of this Act and who has had more than three convictions.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-55.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-55.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>No person shall be released under sub-section (1) unless,—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-55.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>he has at the time of his release served one half of his sentence including remission or a period not less than two years of sentence including remission, whichever is less;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-55.3.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>his conduct in prison has been good;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-55.3.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>twelve months have elapsed from the date of the expiry of the period of his previous release, if any, under this section.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-55.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The period of release of a prisoner under sub-section (1) shall not count towards the total period of his sentence.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-56">
          <num>56.</num>
          <heading>Release on parole.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-56.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government or any authority to which the State Government may delegate its power in this behalf, may, subject to such conditions as may be prescribed, release on parole for such period as it may deem necessary, any prisoner in case of any serious illness or death of any member of the prisoner’s family or of any of his nearest relatives or for any other sufficient cause.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-56.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The period of release of a prisoner under sub-section (1) shall not count towards the total period of his sentence.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-57">
          <num>57.</num>
          <heading>Prisoner to surrender himself on the expiration of the period otherwise liable to be arrested.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-57.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On the expiry of the period for which a prisoner was released temporarily under sub-section (1) of section 55, or on parole under sub¬section (1) of section 56, he shall surrender himself to the officer in charge of the prison from which he was released.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-57.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a prisoner fails to surrender himself as required by sub-section (1), he may be arrested by any Police Officer without a warrant and produced before a Judicial Magistrate who shall remand him to undergo the unexpired portion of the sentence.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-58">
          <num>58.</num>
          <heading>Penalty for failure to surrender.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-58.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Any prisoner who fails to surrender himself, as required by sub-section (1) of section 57, shall, on conviction, be punished with imprisonment of either description for a term which may extend to two years or with fine, or with both.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-XIII">
        <num>XIII</num>
        <heading>Miscellaneous</heading>
        <section id="section-59">
          <num>59.</num>
          <heading>Extra mural custody, control and employment of prisoners.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-59.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>A prisoner, when being taken to or from any prison in which he may be lawfully confined or whenever he is working outside or is otherwise beyond the limits of any such prison, in or under the lawful custody or control of a prison officer belonging to such prison, shall be deemed to be in prison and shall be subject to all the same incidents as if he was actually in prison.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-60">
          <num>60.</num>
          <heading>Confinement in irons.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-60.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Whenever the Superintendent considers it necessary (with reference either to the state of the prison or the character of the prisoners) for the safe custody of any prisoners that they should be confined in irons he may, subject to such regulations and instructions as may be laid down by the Inspector-General with the sanction of the State Government, so confine them.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-61">
          <num>61.</num>
          <heading>Confinement in irons of prisoners under sentence of imprisonment for life.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-61.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Prisoners under sentence of imprisonment for life may, subject to such conditions as may be prescribed, be confined, in fetters for the first three months after admission to prison.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-61.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Should the Superintendent consider it necessary either for the safe custody of the prisoner himself or for any other reason that fetters should be retained on any such prisoner for more than three months, he shall apply to the Inspector-General for sanction to their retention for such period as may be necessary, and the Inspector-General may sanction such retention accordingly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-62">
          <num>62.</num>
          <heading>Prisoners not to be put in irons by Jailer except under necessity.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-62.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No prisoner shall be put in irons or under any mechanical restraint by the Jailer on his own authority, except in cases of urgent necessity.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-62.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Whenever the Jailer on his own authority puts a prisoner in irons, a report thereof shall forthwith be sent to the Superintendent.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-63">
          <num>63.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-63.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may after previous publication by notification make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-63.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-63.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing provisions, such rules may be made for,—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-63.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>defining the acts which shall constitute prison offences;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-63.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>determining classification of prison offences into serious and minor offences;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-63.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>fixing the punishments admissible under this Act, which may be awarded for commission of prison offences or classes thereof;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-63.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>declaring the circumstances in which acts constituting both a prison offence and an offence under the Indian Penal Code may or may not be dealt with as a prison offence;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-63.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the award of marks, granting remission or furlough, determining the conditions on which and the authority by which such remission or furlough may be granted and the consequent shortening of the sentences;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-63.2.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>regulating the use of arms against any prisoner or batch of prisoners in case of an outbreak or attempt to escape;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-63.2.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>defining the circumstances and regulating the conditions under which prisoners in danger of death may be released;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-63.2.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>the classification of prisons and description and construction of wards as well as other places of detention;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-63.2.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the regulation by numbers, length or character of sentences or otherwise, of the prisoners to be confined in each class of prisons;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-63.2.list1.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>the governance of prisons and the appointment of all officers appointed under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-63.2.list1.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>providing food, bedding and clothing of criminal prisoners and of civil prisoners maintained otherwise than at their own cost;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-63.2.list1.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>the employment, instruction and control of convicts within or without prisons;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-63.2.list1.m">
                  <num>(m)</num>
                  <p>defining the articles, the introduction or removal of which into or out of the prisons without due authority is prohibited;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-63.2.list1.n">
                  <num>(n)</num>
                  <p>classifying and prescribing the forms of labour and regulating the periods of rest from labour;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-63.2.list1.o">
                  <num>(o)</num>
                  <p>regulating the disposal of the proceeds of employment of prisoners;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-63.2.list1.p">
                  <num>(p)</num>
                  <p>regulating the confinement in fetters of prisoners sentenced to imprisonment for life;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-63.2.list1.q">
                  <num>(q)</num>
                  <p>classification and separation of prisoners;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-63.2.list1.r">
                  <num>(r)</num>
                  <p>regulating the confinement of convict criminal prisoners under section 27;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-63.2.list1.s">
                  <num>(s)</num>
                  <p>the preparation and maintenance of history tickets;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-63.2.list1.t">
                  <num>(t)</num>
                  <p>the selection and appointments of prisoners as officers of prisons;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-63.2.list1.u">
                  <num>(u)</num>
                  <p>rewards for good conduct;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-63.2.list1.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>regulating the transfers of prisoners whose term of imprisonment is about to expire subject to the consent of the Government of any other State to which the prisoner is to be transferred;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-63.2.list1.w">
                  <num>(w)</num>
                  <p>the treatment of prisoners and the disposal of criminal lunatics or recovered criminal lunatics confined in prisons;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-63.2.list1.x">
                  <num>(x)</num>
                  <p>regulating the transmission of appeals and petitions from prisoners and their communications with their friends and relatives;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-63.2.list1.y">
                  <num>(y)</num>
                  <p>the appointment and guidance of visitors of prisons;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-63.2.list1.z">
                  <num>(z)</num>
                  <p>extending any or all the provisions of this Act and of the rules thereunder to subsidiary jails; or special places of confinement appointed under section 541 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898, and to the officers employed and the prisoners confined therein;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-63.2.list1.aa">
                  <num>(aa)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-63.2.list1.aa.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>the admission, custody, employment, diet, treatment and release of prisoners; and</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-63.2.list1.aa.list0.bb">
                      <num>(bb)</num>
                      <p>generally for anything prescribed under this Act.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-64">
          <num>64.</num>
          <heading>Rules and notifications to be laid before the State Legislature.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-64.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made under this Act and every notification issued under section 68, shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made or issued, before each House of the State Legislature while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session in which it is so laid or the session immediately following, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or the notification or both Houses agree that the rule or the notification should not be made or issued, the rule or the notification shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however, that any modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule or notification.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-65">
          <num>65.</num>
          <heading>Exhibition of copies of Rules.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-65.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Copies of rules made under section 63 shall, so far as they affect the governance of prisons be exhibited both in English and in the regional language in some conspicuous place to which all persons employed within a prison have access.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-66">
          <num>66.</num>
          <heading>Exercise of powers of Superintendent and Medical officers.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-66.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>All or any of the powers and duties conferred or imposed by this Act on a Superintendent or a Medical officer may, in his absence, be exercised and performed by such other officer as the State Government may appoint in this behalf, either by name or by his official designation.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-67">
          <num>67.</num>
          <heading>Repeal and savings.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-67.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The enactments specified in the Schedule to this Act are hereby repealed:</p>
              <p>Provided that section 6 of the Karnataka General Clauses Act, 1899 Karnataka Act III of 1899), shall be applicable in respect of such repeal and section 8 and section 24 of the said Act shall be applicable as if the said enactments are enactments within the meaning of the said Act and had been repealed and re-enacted by this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-68">
          <num>68.</num>
          <heading>Removal of difficulties.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-68.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act in consequence of the transition to the said provisions from the corresponding provisions of the Acts in force therein immediately before the commencement of this Act, the State Government may, by notification in the official Gazette make such provisions as appear to it to be necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-68.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act (otherwise than in relation to the transition from the provisions of the corresponding Acts in force before the commencement of this Act) the State Government may, by notification, make such provisions not inconsistent with the purposes of this Act as appear to it to be necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-schedule">
      <doc name="schedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1963/33/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1963/33"/>
              <FRBRalias value="Schedule"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1963/33/eng@2017-01-20/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1963/33/eng@2017-01-20"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1963/33/eng@2017-01-20/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1963/33/eng@2017-01-20"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-01-20" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="schedule">
            <heading>(See section 67)</heading>
            <subsection id="schedule.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Mysore Prisons Act, 1943 (Mysore Act XLIV of 1943) as in force in the Mysore Area;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedule.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Hyderabad Prisons Act, 1954 (Hyderabad Act XXIX of 1954) as in force in the Gulbarga Area;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="schedule.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Prisons Act, 1894, (Central Act No. IX of 1894) as in force respectively in the Belgaum Area, Mangalore and Kollegal Area and the Coorg District.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
