<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1997/24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1997/24"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Telecom Regulatory Authority Of India Act, 1997"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1997/24/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1997/24/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1997/24/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1997/24/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-11-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Telecom Regulatory Authority Of India Act, 1997</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>An Act to provide for the establishment of the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India and the Telecom Disputes Settlement and Appellate Tribunal to regulate the telecommunication services, adjudicate disputes, dispose of appeals and to protect the interests of service providers and consumers of the telecom sector, to promote and ensure orderly growth of the telecom sector and for matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.</p>
      <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty-eighth Year of the Republic of India as follows:-</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India Act, 1997.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 25th day of January, 1997.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“appointed day” means the date with effect from which the Authority is established under sub-section (1) of section 3;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>( aa) “Appellate Tribunal” means the Telecom Disputes Settlement and Appellate Tribunal established under section 14;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“Authority” means the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India established under sub-section (1) of section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“Chairperson” means the Chairperson of the Authority appoint­ed under sub-section (3) of section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>“Fund” means the Fund constituted under sub-section (1) of section 22;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>“Licensee” means any person licensed under sub-section (1) of section 4 of the Indian Telegraph Act, 1885 (13 of 1885) for provid­ing specified public telecommunication services;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list5">
              <listIntroduction>( ea) “licensor” means the Central Government or the telegraph authority who grants a licence under section 4 of the Indian Telegraph Act, 1885 (13 of 1885);</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list5.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>“member” means a member of the Authority appointed under sub-section (3) of section 3 and includes the Chairperson and the Vice-Chairperson;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list5.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>“notification” means a notification published in the Official Gazette;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list5.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list5.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>“regulations” means regulations made by the Authority under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list5.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>“service provider” means the Government as a service provider and includes a licensee;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list5.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>“telecommunication service” means service of any description (including electronic mail, voice mail, data services, audio tax services, video tax services, radio paging and cellular mobile telephone services) which is made available to users by means of any transmission or reception of signs, signals, writing, images and sounds or intelligence of any nature, by wire, radio, visual or other electromagnetic means but shall not include broadcasting services:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that the Central Government may notify other service to be telecommunication service including broadcasting services.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Words and expressions used and not defined in this Act but defined in the Indian Telegraph Act, 1885 (13 of 1885) or the Indian wireless telegraphy Act, 1933 (17 of 1933) shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in those Acts.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any reference in this Act to a law which is not in force in the State of Jammu and Kashmir shall in relation to that State be construed as a reference to the corresponding law, if any, in that State.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Establishment and incorporation of Authority.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>With effect from such date as the Central Government may, by notifica­tion appoint, there shall be established, for the purposes of this Act, an Authority to be called the Telecom Regulatory Au­thority of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Authority shall be a body corporate by the name afore­said, having perpetual succession and a common seal, with power, subject to the provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of property, both movable and immovable, and to contract, and shall, by the said name, sue or be sued.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Authority shall consist of a Chairperson, and not more than two whole-time members and not more than two part-time members, to be appointed by the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The head office of the Authority shall be at New Delhi.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Qualifications for appointment of Chairperson and other members.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Chairperson and other members of the Authority shall be appointed by the Central Government from amongst persons who have special knowledge of, and professional experience in, telecommunication, industry, finance, accountancy, law, management or consumer affairs:4. Qualifications for appointment of Chairperson and other members.—</p>
            <p>Provided that a person who is, or has been, in the service of Government shall not be appointed as a member unless such person has held the post of Secretary or Additional Secretary, or the post of Additional Secretary and Secretary to the Government of India or any equivalent post in the Central Government or the State Government for a period of not less than three years.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Term of office, conditions of service, etc., of Chairperson and other members.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Before appointing any person as the Chair­person or member, the Central Government shall satisfy itself that the person does not have any such financial or other inter­est as is likely to affect prejudicially his functions as such member.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chairperson and other members shall hold office for a term not exceeding three years, as the Central Government may notify in this behalf, from the date on which they enter upon their offices or until they attain the age of sixty-five years, whichever is earlier.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On the commencement of the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India (Amendment) Act, 2000, a person appointed as Chairperson of the Authority and every other person appointed as member and holding office as such immediately before such commencement shall vacate their respective offices and such Chairperson and such other members shall be entitled to claim compensation not exceeding three months pay and allowances for the premature termination of the term of their offices or of any contract of service.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The employee of the Government on his selection as the Chairperson or whole-time member shall have to retire from service before joining as the Chairperson or a whole-time member.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The salary and allowances payable to and the other terms and conditions of service of the Chairperson and whole-time members shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The salary, allowances and other conditions of service of the Chairperson or of a member shall not be varied to his disadvan­tage after appointment.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.6A">
          <num>(6A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The part-time members shall receive such allowances as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.7.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (2), a member may—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.7.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>relinquish his office by giving in writing to the Central Government notice of not less than three months; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.7.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>be removed from his office in accordance with the provisions of section 7.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.8.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Chairperson and the whole-time members shall not, for a period of two years from the date on which they cease to hold office as such, except with the previous approval of the Central Government, accept—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.8.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any employment either under the Central Government or under any State Government; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.8.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any appointment in any company in the business of telecommunication services.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A vacancy caused to the office of the Chairperson or any other member shall be filled up within a period of three months from the date on which such vacancy occurs.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Powers of Chairperson and Vice-Chairperson.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chairperson shall have powers of general superintendence and directions in the conduct of the affairs of the Authority and he shall, in addition to presiding over the meetings of the Authority, exer­cise and discharge such powers and functions of the Authority and shall discharge such other powers and functions as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may appoint one of the members to be a Vice-Chairperson of the Authority who shall exercise and dis­charge such powers and functions of the Chairperson as may be prescribed or as may be delegated to him by the Authority.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Removal and suspension of member from office in certain circumstances.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government may remove from office any member, who,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>has been adjudged an insolvent; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>has been convicted of an offence which, in the opinion of the Central Government, involves moral turpitude; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>has become physically or mentally incapable of acting as a member; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>has acquired such financial or other interest as is likely to affect prejudicially his functions as a member; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>has so abused his position as to render his continuance in office prejudicial to the public interest.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No such member shall be removed from his office under clause (d) or clause (e) of sub-section (1) unless he has been given a reasonable opportunity of being heard in the matter.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Meetings.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Authority shall meet at such times and places, and shall observe such rules of procedure in regard to the transaction of business at its meetings (including quorum at such meetings) as may be provided by regulations.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chairperson or, if for any reason, he is unable to attend a meeting of the Authority, Vice-Chairperson and in his absence, any other member chosen by the members present from amongst themselves at the meeting shall preside at the meeting.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All questions which come up before any meeting of the Author­ity shall be decided by a majority vote of the members present and voting, and in the event of an equality of votes, the Chair­person or in his absence, the person presiding, shall have a second or casting vote.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Authority may make regulations for the transaction of business at it meetings.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Vacancies, etc., not to invalidate proceedings of Authority.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>No act or proceeding of the Authority shall be in­valid merely by reason of—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution of, the Authority; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any defect in the appointment of a person acting as a member of the Authority; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any irregularity in the procedure of the Authority not af­fecting the merits of the case.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Officers and other employees of Authority.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Authority may appoint officers and such other employees as it considers necessary for the efficient discharge of its functions under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The salary and allowances payable to and the other conditions of service of the officers and other employees of the Authority appointed under sub-section (1) shall be such as may be prescribed:</p>
            <p>Provided that any regulation, in respect of the salary and allowances payable to and other conditions of service of the officers and other employees of the Authority, made before the commencement of the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India (Amendment) Act, 2000, shall cease to have effect immediately on the notification of rules made under clause (ca) of sub-section (2) of section 35.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Functions of Authority.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Indian Telegraph Act, 1885 (13 of 1885), the functions of the Authority shall be to—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-11.1.list1.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>make recommendations, either suo motu or on a request from the licensor, on the following matters, namely:—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-11.1.list1.a.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>need and timing for introduction of new service provider;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-11.1.list1.a.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>terms and conditions of licence to a service provider;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-11.1.list1.a.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>revocation of licence for non-compliance of terms and conditions of licence;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-11.1.list1.a.list0.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>measures to facilitate competition and promote efficiency in the operation of telecommunication services so as to facilitate growth in such services;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-11.1.list1.a.list0.v">
                    <num>(v)</num>
                    <p>technological improvements in the services provided by the service providers;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-11.1.list1.a.list0.vi">
                    <num>(vi)</num>
                    <p>type of equipment to be used by the service providers after inspection of equipment used in the network;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-11.1.list1.a.list0.vii">
                    <num>(vii)</num>
                    <p>measures for the development of telecommunication technology and any other matter relatable to telecommunication industry in general;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-11.1.list1.a.list0.viii">
                    <num>(viii)</num>
                    <p>efficient management of available spectrum;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-11.1.list1.b.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>discharge the following functions, namely:—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-11.1.list1.b.list1.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>ensure compliance of terms and conditions of licence;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-11.1.list1.b.list1.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>notwithstanding anything contained in the terms and conditions of the licence granted before the commencement of the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India (Amendment) Act, 2000, fix the terms and conditions of inter-connectivity between the service providers;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-11.1.list1.b.list1.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>ensure technical compatibility and effective inter-connection between different service providers;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-11.1.list1.b.list1.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>regulate arrangement amongst service providers of sharing their revenue derived from providing telecommunication services;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-11.1.list1.b.list1.v">
                    <num>(v)</num>
                    <p>lay-down the standards of quality of service to be provided by the service providers and ensure the quality of service and conduct the periodical survey of such service provided by the service providers so as to protect interest of the consumers of telecommunication service;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-11.1.list1.b.list1.vi">
                    <num>(vi)</num>
                    <p>lay-down and ensure the time period for providing local and long distance circuits of telecommunication between different service providers;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-11.1.list1.b.list1.vii">
                    <num>(vii)</num>
                    <p>maintain register of interconnect agreements and of all such other matters as may be provided in the regulations;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-11.1.list1.b.list1.viii">
                    <num>(viii)</num>
                    <p>keep register maintained under clause (vii) open for inspection to any member of public on payment of such fee and compliance of such other requirement as may be provided in the regulations;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-11.1.list1.b.list1.ix">
                    <num>(ix)</num>
                    <p>ensure effective compliance of universal service obligations;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>levy fees and other charges at such rates and in respect of such services as may be determined by regulations;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>perform such other functions including such administrative and financial functions as may be entrusted to it by the Central Government or as may be necessary to carry out the provisions of this Act:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that the recommendations of the Authority specified in clause (a) of this sub-section shall not be binding upon the Central Government:</p>
            <p>Provided further that the Central Government shall seek the recommendations of the Authority in respect of matters specified in sub-clauses (i) and (ii) of clause (a) of this sub-section in respect of new licence to be issued to a service provider and the Authority shall forward its recommendations within a period of sixty days from the date on which that Government sought the recommendations:</p>
            <p>Provided also that the Authority may request the Central Government to furnish such information or documents as may be necessary for the purpose of making recommendations under sub-clauses (i) and (ii) of clause (a) of this sub-section and that Government shall supply such information within a period of seven days from receipt of such request:</p>
            <p>Provided also that the Central Government may issue a licence to a service provider if no recommendations are received from the Authority within the period specified in the second proviso or within such period as may be mutually agreed upon between the Central Government and the Authority:</p>
            <p>Provided also that if the Central Government having considered that recommendation of the Authority, comes to a prima facie conclusion that such recommendation cannot be accepted or needs modifications, it shall, refer the recommendation back to the Authority for its reconsideration, and the Authority may within fifteen days from the date of receipt of such reference, forward to the Central Government its recommendation after considering the reference made by that Government. After receipt of further recommendation if any, the Central Government shall take a final decision.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Indian Telegraph Act, 1885 (13 of 1885), the Authority may, from time to time, by order, notify in the Official Gazette the rates at which the telecommunication services within India and outside India shall be provided under this Act including the rates at which messages shall be transmitted to any country outside India:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Authority may notify different rates for dif­ferent persons or class of persons for similar telecommunication services and where different rates are fixed as aforesaid the Authority shall record the reasons therefor.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>While discharging its functions</p>
            <p>under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) the Authority shall not act against the interest of the sovereignty and integrity of India, the security of the State, friendly relations with foreign States, public order, decency or morality.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Authority shall ensure transparency while exercising its powers and discharging its functions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Powers of Authority to call for information, conduct investi­gations, etc.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-12.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where the Authority considers it expedient so to do, it may, by order in writing,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>call upon any service provider at any time to furnish in writing such information or explanation relating to its affairs as the Authority may require; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>appoint one or more persons to make an inquiry in relation to the affairs of any service provider; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>direct any of its officers or employees to inspect the books of account or other documents of any service provider.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-12.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where any inquiry in relation to the affairs of a service provider has been undertaken under sub-section (1),—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>every officer of the Government Department, if such service provider is a department of the Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>every director, manager, secretary or other officer, if such service provider is a company; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>every partner, manager, secretary or other officer, if such service provider is a firm; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>every other person or body of persons who has had dealings in the course of business with any of the persons mentioned in clauses (b) and (c),</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall be bound to produce before the Authority making the in­quiry, all such books of account or other documents in his custody or power relating to, or having a bear­ing on the subject-matter of such inquiry and also to furnish to the Authority with any such statement or information relating there­to, as the case may be, required of him, within such time as may be specified.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every service provider shall maintain such books of account or other documents as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Authority shall have the power to issue such directions to service providers as it may consider necessary for proper functioning by service providers.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Power of Authority to issue directions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Authority may, for the discharge of its functions under sub-section</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of section 11, issue such directions from time to time to the serv­ice providers, as it may consider necessary:</p>
            <p>Provided that no direction under sub-section (4) of section 12 or under this section shall be issued except on the matters specified in clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 11.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Establishment of Appellate Tribunal.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government shall, by notification, establish an Appellate Tribunal to be known as the Telecom Disputes Settlement and Appellate Tribunal to—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>adjudicate any dispute—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>between a licensor and a licensee;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>between two or more service providers;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>between a service provider and a group of consumers:</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-14.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that nothing in this clause shall apply in respect of matters relating to—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list3.A">
                <num>(A)</num>
                <p>the monopolistic trade practice, restrictive trade practice and unfair trade practice which are subject to the jurisdiction of the Monopolies and Restrictive Trade Practices Commission established under sub-section (1) of section 5 of the Monopolies and Restrictive Trade Practices Act, 1969 (54 of 1969);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list3.B">
                <num>(B)</num>
                <p>the complaint of an individual consumer maintainable before a Consumer Disputes Redressal Forum or a Consumer Disputes Redressal Commission or the National Consumer Redressal Commission established under section 9 of the Consumer Protection Act, 1986 (68 of 1986);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list3.C">
                <num>(C)</num>
                <p>dispute between telegraph authority and any other person referred to in sub-section (1) of section 7B of the Indian Telegraph Act, 1885 (13 of 1885);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>hear and dispose of appeal against any direction, decision or order of the Authority under this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14A">
        <num>14A.</num>
        <heading>Application for settlement of disputes and appeals to Appellate Tribunal.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14A.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government or a State Government or a local authority or any person may make an application to the Appellate Tribunal for adjudication of any dispute referred to in clause</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14A.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>of section 14.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government or a State Government or a local authority or any person aggrieved by any direction, decision or order made by the Authority may prefer an appeal to the Appellate Tribunal.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every appeal under sub-section (2) shall be preferred within a period of thirty days from the date on which a copy of the direction or order or decision made by the Authority is received by the Central Government or the State Government or the local authority or the aggrieved person and it shall be in such form, verified in such manner and be accompanied by such fee as may be prescribed:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Appellate Tribunal may entertain any appeal after the expiry of the said period of thirty days if it is satisfied that there was sufficient cause for not filing it within that period.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14A.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On receipt of an application under sub-section (1) or an appeal under sub-section (2), the Appellate Tribunal may, after giving the parties to the dispute or the appeal an opportunity of being heard, pass such orders thereon as it thinks fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14A.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Appellate Tribunal shall send a copy of every order made by it to the parties to the dispute or the appeal and to the Authority, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14A.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The application made under sub-section (1) or the appeal preferred under sub-section (2) shall be dealt with by it as expeditiously as possible and endeavour shall be made by it to dispose of the application or appeal finally within ninety days from the date of receipt of application or appeal, as the case may be:</p>
            <p>Provided that where any such application or appeal could not be disposed of within the said period of ninety days, the Appellate Tribunal shall record its reasons in writing for not disposing of the application or appeal within that period.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14A.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Appellate Tribunal may, for the purpose of examining the legality or propriety or correctness, of any dispute made in any application under sub-section (1), or of any direction or order or decision of the Authority referred to in the appeal preferred under sub-section (2), on its own motion or otherwise, call for the records relevant to deposing of such application or appeal and make such orders as it thinks fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14B">
        <num>14B.</num>
        <heading>Composition of Appellate Tribunal.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14B.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Appellate Tribunal shall consist of a Chairperson and not more than two Members to be appointed, by notification, by the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14B.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The selection of Chairperson and Members of the Appellate Tribunal shall be made by the Central Government in consultation with the Chief Justice of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14B.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14B.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Subject to the provisions of this Act,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14B.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the jurisdiction of the Appellate Tribunal may be exercised by the Benches thereof;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14B.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>a Bench may be constituted by the Chairperson of the Appellate Tribunal with one or two Members of such Tribunal as the Chairperson may deem fit;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14B.3.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the Benches of the Appellate Tribunal shall ordinarily sit at New Delhi and at such other places as the Central Government may, in consultation with the Chairperson of the Appellate Tribunal, notify;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14B.3.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the Central Government shall notify the areas in relation to which each Bench of the Appellate Tribunal may exercise its jurisdiction.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14B.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (2), the Chairperson of the Appellate Tribunal may transfer a Member of such Tribunal from one Bench to another Bench.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14B.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If at any stage of the hearing of any case or matter it appears to the Chairperson or a Member of the Appellate Tribunal that the case or matter is of such a nature that it ought to be heard by a Bench consisting of two Members, the case or matter may be transferred by the Chairperson to such Bench as the Chairperson may deem fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14C">
        <num>14C.</num>
        <heading>Qualifications for appointment of Chairperson and Members.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14C.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14C.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A person shall not be qualified for appointment as the Chairperson or a Member of the Appellate Tribunal unless he—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14C.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in the case of Chairperson, is, or has been, a Judge of the Supreme Court or the Chief Justice of a High Court;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14C.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in the case of a Member, has held the post of Secretary to the Government of India or any equivalent post in the Central Government or the State Government for a period of not less than two years or a person who is well versed in the field of technology, telecommunication, industry, commerce or administration.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14D">
        <num>14D.</num>
        <heading>Term of office.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14D.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Chairperson and every other Member of the Appellate Tribunal shall hold office as such for a term not exceeding three years from the date on which he enters upon his office:</p>
            <blockList id="section-14D.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that no Chairperson or other Member shall hold office as such after he has attained,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14D.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in the case of Chairperson, the age of seventy years;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14D.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in the case of any other Member, the age of sixty-five years.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14E">
        <num>14E.</num>
        <heading>Terms and conditions of service.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14E.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The salary and allowances payable to and the other terms and conditions of service of the Chairperson and other Members of the Appellate Tribunal shall be such as may be prescribed:</p>
            <p>Provided that neither the salary and allowances nor the other terms and conditions of service of the Chairperson or a Member of the Appellate Tribunal shall be varied to his disadvantage after appointment.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14F">
        <num>14F.</num>
        <heading>Vacancies.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14F.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If, for reason other than temporary absence, any vacancy occurs in the office of the Chairperson or a Member of the Appellate Tribunal, the Central Government shall appoint another person in accordance with the provisions of this Act to fill the vacancy and the proceedings may be continued before the Appellate Tribunal from the stage at which the vacancy is filled.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14G">
        <num>14G.</num>
        <heading>Removal and resignation.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14G.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14G.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government may remove from office, the Chairperson or any Member of the Appellate Tribunal, who—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14G.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>has been adjudged an insolvent; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14G.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>has been convicted of an offence which, in the opinion of the Central Government, involves moral turpitude; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14G.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>has become physically or mentally incapable of acting as the Chairperson or a Member; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14G.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>has acquired such financial or other interest as is likely to affect prejudicially his functions as the Chairperson or a Member; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14G.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>has so abused his position as to render his continuance in office prejudicial to the public interest.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14G.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), the Chairperson or a Member of the Appellate Tribunal shall not be removed from his office on the ground specified in clause (d) or clause (e) of that sub-section unless the Supreme Court on a reference being made to it in this behalf by the Central Government, has, on an enquiry, held by it in accordance with such procedure as it may specify in this behalf, reported that the Chairperson or a Member ought on such ground or grounds to be removed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14G.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may suspend from office, the Chairperson or a Member of the Appellate Tribunal in respect of whom a reference has been made to the Supreme Court under sub-section (2), until the Central Government has passed an order on receipt of the report of the Supreme Court on such reference.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14H">
        <num>14H.</num>
        <heading>Staff of Appellate Tribunal.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14H.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government shall provide the Appellate Tribunal with such officers and employees as it may deem fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14H.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The officers and employees of the Appellate Tribunal shall discharge their functions under the general superintendence of its Chairperson.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14H.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The salaries and allowances and other conditions of service of such officers and employees of the Appellate Tribunal shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14I">
        <num>14I.</num>
        <heading>Distribution of business amongst Benches.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where Benches are constituted, the Chairperson of the Appellate Tribunal may, from time to time, by notification, make provisions as to the distribution of the business of the Appellate Tribunal amongst the Benches and also provide for the matters which may be dealt with by each Bench.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14J">
        <num>14J.</num>
        <heading>Power of Chairperson to transfer cases.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14J.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>On the application of any of the parties and after notice to the parties, and after hearing such of them as he may desire to be heard, or on his own motion without such notice, the Chairperson of the Appellate Tribunal may transfer any case pending before one Bench, for disposal, to any other Bench.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14K">
        <num>14K.</num>
        <heading>Decision to be by majority.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14K.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If the Members of a Bench consisting of two Members differ in opinion on any point, they shall state the point or points on which they differ, and make a reference to the Chairperson of the Appellate Tribunal who shall hear the point or points himself and such point or points shall be decided according to the opinion of the majority who have heard the case, including those who first heard it.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14L">
        <num>14L.</num>
        <heading>Members, etc., to be public servants.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14L.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Chairperson, Members and other officers and employees of the Appellate Tribunal shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14M">
        <num>14M.</num>
        <heading>Transfer of pending cases.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14M.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>All applications, pending for adjudication of disputes before the Authority immediately before the date of establishment of the Appellate Tribunal under this Act, shall stand transferred on that date to such Tribunal:</p>
            <p>Provided that all disputes being adjudicated under the provisions of Chapter IV as it stood immediately before the commencement of the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India (Amendment) Act, 2000, shall continue to be adjudicated by the Authority in accordance with the provisions, contained in that Chapter, till the establishment of the Appellate Tribunal under the said Act:</p>
            <p>Provided further that all cases referred to in the first proviso shall be transferred by the Authority to the Appellate Tribunal immediately on its establishment under section 14.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14N">
        <num>14N.</num>
        <heading>Transfer of appeals.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14N.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All appeals pending before the High Court immediately before the commencement of the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India (Amendment) Act, 2000, shall stand transferred to the Appellate Tribunal on its establishment under section 14.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14N.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14N.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where any appeal stands transferred from the High Court to the Appellate Tribunal under sub-section (1),—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14N.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the High Court shall, as soon as may be after such transfer, forward the records of such appeal to the Appellate Tribunal; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14N.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the Appellate Tribunal may, on receipt of such records, proceed to deal with such appeal, so far as may be from the stage which was reached before such transfer or from any earlier stage or de novo as the Appellate Tribunal may deem fit.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Civil court not to have jurisdiction.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No civil court shall have jurisdiction to entertain any suit or proceeding in respect of any matter which the Appellate Tribunal is empowered by or under this Act to determine and no injunction shall be granted by any court or other authority in respect of any action taken or to be taken in pursuance of any power conferred by or under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Procedure and powers of Appellate Tribunal.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-16.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Appellate Tribunal shall not be bound by the procedure laid down by the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), but shall be guided by the principles of natural justice and, subject to the other provisions of this Act, the Appellate Tribunal shall have powers to regulate its own procedure.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-16.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Appellate Tribunal shall have, for the purposes of discharging its functions under this Act, the same powers as are vested in a civil court under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), while trying a suit, in respect of the following matters, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person and examining him on oath;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>requiring the discovery and production of documents;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>receiving evidence on affidavits;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>subject to the provisions of sections 123 and 124 of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872), requisitioning any public record or document or a copy of such record or document, from any office;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses or documents;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>reviewing its decisions;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>dismissing an application for default or deciding it, ex parte;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>setting aside any order of dismissal of any application for default or any order passed by it, ex parte; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>any other matter which may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every proceeding before the Appellate Tribunal shall be deemed to be a judicial proceeding within the meaning of sections 193 and 228, and for the purposes of section 196 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860) and the Appellate Tribunal shall be deemed to be a civil court for the purposes of section 195 and Chapter XXVI of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Right to legal representation.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The applicant or appellant may either appear in person or authorise one or more chartered accountants or company secretaries or cost accountants or legal practitioners or any of its officers to present his or its case before the Appellate Tribunal.</p>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <blockList id="section-17.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>For the purposes of this section,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.paragraph-0.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“chartered accountant” means a chartered accountant as defined in clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Chartered Accountants Act, 1949 (38 of 1949) and who has obtained a certificate of practice under sub-section (1) of section 6 of that Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“company secretary” means a company secretary as defined in clause (c) of sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Company Secretaries Act, 1980 (56 of 1980) and who has obtained a certificate of practice under sub-section (1) of section 6 of that Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“cost accountant” means a cost accountant as defined in clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Cost and Works Accountants Act, 1959 (23 of 1959), and who has obtained a certificate of practice under sub-section (1) of section 6 of that Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>“legal practitioner” means an advocate, vakil or an attorney of any High Court, and includes a pleader in practice.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Appeal to Supreme Court.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) or in any other law, an appeal shall lie against any order, not being an interlocutory order, of the Appellate Tribunal to the Supreme Court on one or more of the grounds specified in section 100 of that Code.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No appeal shall lie against any decision or order made by the Appellate Tribunal with the consent of the parties.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every appeal under this section shall be preferred within a period of ninety days from the date of the decision or order appealed against:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Supreme Court may entertain the appeal after the expiry of the said period of ninety days, if it is satisfied that the appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from preferring the appeal in time.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Orders passed by Appellate Tribunal to be executable as a decree.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-19.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An order passed by the Appellate Tribunal under this Act shall be executable by the Appellate Tribunal as a decree of civil court, and for this purpose, the Appellate Tribunal shall have all the powers of a civil court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), the Appellate Tribunal may transmit any order made by it to a civil court having local jurisdiction and such civil court shall execute the order as if it were a decree made by that court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for wilful failure to comply with orders of Appellate Tribunal.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any person wilfully fails to comply with the order of the Appellate Tribunal, he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to one lakh rupees and in case of a second or subsequent offence with fine which may extend to two lakh rupees and in the case of continuing contravention with additional fine which may extend to two lakh rupees for every day during which such default continues.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Grants by Central Government.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in this behalf, make to the Authority grants of such sums of money as are re­quired to pay salaries and allowances payable to the Chairperson and the members and the administrative expenses including the salaries, allowances and pension payable to or in respect of officers and other employees of the Authority.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Fund.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-22.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-22.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>There shall be constituted a fund to be called the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India General Fund and there shall be credited thereto—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-22.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>all grants, fees and charges received by the Authority under this Act; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-22.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>all sums received by the Authority from such other sources as may be decided upon by the Central Government.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-22.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-22.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Fund shall be applied for meeting—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-22.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the salaries and allowances payable to the Chairperson and members and the administrative expenses including the sala­ries, allowances and pension payable to or in respect of officers and other employees of the Authority; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-22.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the expenses on objects and for purposes authorised by this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Accounts and audit.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-23.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Authority shall maintain proper accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual state­ment of accounts in such form as may be prescribed by the Central Government in consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The accounts of the Authority shall be audited by the Comp­troller and Auditor General of India at such intervals as may be specified by him and any expenditure incurred in connection with such auditor shall be payable by the Authority to the Comptroll­er and Auditor-General of India.</p>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <p>For the removal of doubts it is hereby declared that the decisions of the Authority taken in discharge of its functions under clause (b) of sub-section (1) and sub-section (2) of section 11 and section 13, being matters appealable to the Appellate Tribunal, shall not be subject to audit under this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Comptroller and Auditor-General of India and any other person appointed by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the Authority shall have the same rights and privileges and authority in connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor-General generally has, in connection with the audit of the Government accounts and, in particular, shall have the right to demand the production of books, accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and to inspect any of the offices of the Authority.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The accounts of the Authority as certified by the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India or any other person appointed by him in this behalf together with the audit report thereon shall be forwarded annually to the Central Government and that Government shall cause the same to be laid before each House of Parliament.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Furnishing of returns, etc., to Central Government.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-24.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Authority shall furnish to the Central Government at such time and in such form and manner as may be prescribed or as the Cen­tral Government may direct, such returns and statements and such particulars in regard to any proposed or existing programme for the promotion and development of the telecommunication services, as the Central Government from time to time, require.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Authority shall prepare once every year in such form and at such time as may be prescribed, an annual report giving a summary of its activities during the previous year and copies of the report shall be forwarded to the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A copy of the report received under sub-section (2) shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is received, before each House of Parliament.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to issue directions.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-25.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, from time to time, issue to the Au­thority such directions as it may think necessary in the interest of the sovereignty and integrity of India, the security of the State, friendly relations with foreign States, public order, decency or morality.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Without prejudice to the foregoing provisions, the Authority shall, in exercise of its powers or the performance of its func­tions, be bound by such directions on questions of policy as the Central Government may give in writing to it from time to time:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Authority shall, as far as practicable, be given an opportunity to express its views before any direction is given under this sub-section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The decision of the Central Government whether a question is one of policy or not shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Members, officers and employees of Authority to be public servants.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>All members, officers and other employees of the Authority shall be deemed, when acting or purporting to act in pursuance of any of the provisions of this Act to be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Bar of jurisdiction.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No civil court shall have jurisdiction in respect of any matter which the Authority is empowered by or under this Act to determine.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28">
        <num>28.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against the Central Government or the Authority or any officer of Central Government or any member, officer or other employees of the Authority for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or the rules or regu­lations made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29">
        <num>29.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for contravention of directions of Authority.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-29.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If a person violates directions of the Authority, such person shall be punishable with fine which may extend to one lakh rupees and in case of second or subsequent offence with fine which may extend to two lakh rupees and in the case of continuing contravention with additional fine which may extend to two lakh rupees for every day during which the default continues.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-30">
        <num>30.</num>
        <heading>Offences by companies.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-30.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an offence under this Act has been committed by a company, every person who at the time the offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible to, the company for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accord­ingly:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to any punishment provided in this Act if he proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or that he has exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-30.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is attributable to, any neglect on the part of any director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.</p>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <blockList id="section-30.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>For the purposes of this section,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-30.2.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“company” means any body corporate and includes a firm or other association of individuals; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-30.2.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“director”, in relation to a firm, means a partner in the firm.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-31">
        <num>31.</num>
        <heading>Offences by Government Departments.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-31.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an offence under this Act has been committed by any Department of Government, the Head of the Department shall be deemed to be guilty of the of­fence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly unless he proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or that he exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-31.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1) where an offence under this Act has been committed by a Department of Government and it is proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any officer, other than the Head of the Department, such officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-32">
        <num>32.</num>
        <heading>Exemption from tax on wealth and income.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-32.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Wealth-tax Act, 1957 (27 of 1957), the Income-tax Act, 1961 (43 of 1961), or any other enactment for the time being in force relating to tax on wealth, income, profits or gains, the Authority shall not be liable to pay wealth-tax, income-tax or any other tax in respect of their wealth, income, profits or gains derived.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-33">
        <num>33.</num>
        <heading>Delegation.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-33.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Authority may, by general or special order in writing, delegate to any member, officer of the Authority or any other person subject to such conditions, if any, as may be specified in the order, such of its powers and functions under this Act (except the power to settle dispute under Chapter IV and to make regulation under section 36) as it may deem necessary.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-34">
        <num>34.</num>
        <heading>Cognizance of offences.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-34.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No court shall take cognizance of any offence punishable under this Act or the rules or regulations made thereunder, save on a complaint made by the Authority.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-34.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No court inferior to that of a Chief Metropolitan Magistrate or a Chief Judicial Magistrate of first class shall try any offence punishable under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-35">
        <num>35.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-35.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-35.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-35.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-35.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-35.2.list1.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>the salary and allowances payable to and the other conditions of service of the Chairperson and members under sub-section (5) of section 5;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-35.2.list1.a.list0.aa">
                    <num>(aa)</num>
                    <p>the allowance payable to the part-time members under sub-section (6A) of section 5;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-35.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the powers and functions of the Chairperson under sub-section (1) of section 6;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-35.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <blockList id="section-35.2.list1.c.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>the procedure for conducting an inquiry made under sub-section (2) of section 7;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-35.2.list1.c.list1.ca">
                    <num>(ca)</num>
                    <p>the salary and allowances and other conditions of service of officers and other employees of the Authority under sub-section (2) of section 10;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-35.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <blockList id="section-35.2.list1.d.list2">
                  <listIntroduction>the category of books of account or other documents which are required to be maintained under sub-section (3) of section 12;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-35.2.list1.d.list2.da">
                    <num>(da)</num>
                    <p>the form, the manner of its verification and the fee under sub-section (3) of section 14A;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-35.2.list1.d.list2.db">
                    <num>(db)</num>
                    <p>the salary and allowances payable to and other terms and conditions of service of the Chairperson and other Members of the Appellate Tribunal under section 14E;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-35.2.list1.d.list2.dc">
                    <num>(dc)</num>
                    <p>the salary and allowances and other conditions of service of the officers and employees of the Appellate Tribunal under sub-section (3) of section 14H;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-35.2.list1.d.list2.dd">
                    <num>(dd)</num>
                    <p>any other power of a civil court required to be prescribed under clause (i) of sub-section (2) of section 16;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-35.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the period within which an application is to be made under sub-section (1) of section 15;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-35.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the manner in which the accounts of the Authority shall be maintained under sub-section (1) of section 23;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-35.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the time within which and the form and manner in which re­turns and report are to be made to the Central Government under sub-sections (1) and (2) of section 24;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-35.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>any other matter which is to be, or may be, prescribed, or in respect of which provision is to be made, by rules.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-36">
        <num>36.</num>
        <heading>Power to make regulations.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-36.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Authority may, by notifi­cation, make regulations consistent with this Act and the rules made thereunder to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-36.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-36.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such regulations may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-36.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the times and places of meetings of the Authority and the procedure to be followed at such meetings under sub-section (1) of section 8, including quorum necessary for the transaction of business;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-36.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the transaction of business at the meetings of the Authority under sub-section (4) of section 8;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-36.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>***</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-36.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>matters in respect of which register is to be maintained by the authority under sub-clause (vii) of clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 11;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-36.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>levy of fee and lay down such other requirements on fulfil­ment of which a copy of register may be obtained under sub-clause (viii) of clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 11;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-36.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>levy of fees and other changes under clause (c) of sub-section (1) of section 11;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-37">
        <num>37.</num>
        <heading>Rules and regulations to be laid before Parliament.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-37.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every rule and every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or regulation or both Houses agree that the rule or regulation should not be made, the rule or regulation shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be with­out prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule or regulation.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-38">
        <num>38.</num>
        <heading>Application of certain laws.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-38.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of this Act shall be in addition to the provisions of the Indian Telegraph Act, 1885 (13 of 1885) and the Indian Wireless Telegraphy Act, 1933 (17 of 1933) and, in particular, nothing in this Act shall affect any jurisdiction, powers and functions required to be exercised or performed by the Telegraph Authority in relation to any area falling within the jurisdiction of such Authority.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-39">
        <num>39.</num>
        <heading>Power to remove difficulties.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-39.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government may, by order, published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act as may appear to be necessary for removing the difficulty:</p>
            <p>Provided that no order shall be made under this section after the expiry of two years from the date of commencement of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-39.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every order made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-40">
        <num>40.</num>
        <heading>Repeal and saving.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-40.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Telecom Regulatory Authority of India Ordinance, 1997 (Ord. 11 of 1997) is hereby repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-40.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
