<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1932/9/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1932/9"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Indian Partnership Act, 1932"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1932/9/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1932/9/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1932/9/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1932/9/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-12-16" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Indian Partnership Act, 1932</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[Act No. 9 of 1932]</p>
      </longTitle>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[8th April, 1932]</docDate>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>An Act to define and amend the law relating to partnership.</p>
      <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to define and amend the law relating to partnership. It is hereby enacted as follows:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Indian Partnership Act, 1932.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on the 1st day of October, 1932, except section 69, which shall come into force on the 1st day of October, 1933.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>an “act of a firm” means any act or omission by all the partners, or by any partner or agent of the firm which gives rise to a right enforceable by or against the firm;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“business” includes every trade, occupation and profession;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>“third party” used in relation to a firm or to a partner therein means any person who is not a partner in the firm; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>expressions used but not defined in this Act and defined in the Indian Contract Act, 1872 (9 of 1872), shall have the meanings assigned to them in that Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Application of provisions of Act 9 of 1872.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The unrepealed provisions of the Indian Contract Act, 1872, save in so far as they are inconsistent with the express provisions of this Act, shall continue to apply to firms.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Definition of “partnership”, “partner”, “firm” and “firm name”.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>"Partnership” is the relation between persons who have agreed to share the profits of a business carried on by all or any of them acting for all.</p>
            <p>Persons who have entered into partnership with one another are called individually “partners” and collectively a “firm”, and the name under which their business is carried on is called the “firm name”.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Partnership not created by status.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The relation of partnership arises from contract and not from status;</p>
            <p>and, in particular, the members of a Hindu undivided family carrying on a family business as such, or a Burmese Buddhist husband and wife carrying business as such, are not partners in such business.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Mode of determining existence of partnership.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In determining whether a group of persons is or is not a firm, or whether a person is or is not a partner in a firm, regard shall be had to the real relation between the parties, as shown by all relevant facts taken together.</p>
            <p>Explanation 1.—</p>
            <p>The sharing of profits or of gross returns arising from property by persons holding a joint or common interest in that property does not of itself make such persons partners.</p>
            <p>Explanation 2.—</p>
            <p>The receipt by a person of a share of the profits of a business, or of a payment contingent upon the earning of profits or varying with the profits earned by a business, does not of itself make him a partner with the persons carrying on the business;</p>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list6">
              <listIntroduction>and in particular, the receipt of such share or payment—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list6.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>by a lender of money to persons engaged or about to engage in any business,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list6.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>by a servant or agent as remuneration,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list6.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>by the widow or child of a deceased partner, as annuity, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list6.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>by a previous owner or part owner of the business, as consideration for the sale of the goodwill or share thereof,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>does not of itself make the receiver a partner with the persons carrying on the business.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Partnership at will.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where no provision is made by contract between the partners for the duration of their partnership, or for the determination of their partnership, the partnership is ‘partnership at will’.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Particular partnership.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A person may become a partner with another person in particular adventures or undertakings.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>General duties of partners.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Partners are bound to carry on the business of the firm to the greatest common advantage, to be just and faithful to each other, and to render true accounts and full information of all things affecting the firm to any partner or his legal representative.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Duty to indemnify for loss caused by fraud.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every partner shall indemnify the firm for any loss caused to it by his fraud in the conduct of the business of the firm.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Determination of rights and duties of partners by contract between the partners.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the mutual rights and duties of the partners of a firm may be determined by contract between the partners, and such contract may be expressed or may be implied by a course of dealing.</p>
            <p>Such contract may be varied by consent of all the partners, and such consent may be expressed or may be implied by a course of dealing.</p>
            <p>Agreements in restraints of trade.—</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in section 27 of the Indian Contract Act, 1872 (9 of 1872), such contracts may provide that a partner shall not carry on any business other than that of the firm while he is a partner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>The conduct of the business.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Subject to contract between the partners,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>every partner has a right to take part in the conduct of the business;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>every partner is bound to attend diligently to his duties in the conduct of the business;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any difference arising as to ordinary matters connected with the business may be decided by a majority of the partners, and every partner shall have the right to express his opinion, before the matter is decided, but no change may be made in the nature of the business without the consent of all the partners; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>every partner has a right to have access to and to inspect and copy any of the books of the firm.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Mutual rights and liabilities.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Subject to contract between the partners,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>a partner is not entitled to receive remuneration for taking part in the conduct of the business;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the partners are entitled to share equally in the profits earned, and shall contribute equally to the losses sustained by the firm;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>where a partner is entitled to interest on the capital subscribed by him such interest shall be payable only out of profits;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>a partner making, for the purposes of the business, any payment or advance beyond the amount of capital he has agreed to subscribe, is entitled to interest thereon at the rate of six per cent. per annum;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.e.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>the firm shall indemnify a partner in respect of payments made and liabilities incurred by him—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.e.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>in the ordinary and proper conduct of the business, and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.e.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>in doing such act, in an emergency, for the purpose of protecting the firm from loss, as would be done by a person of ordinary prudence, in his own case, under similar circumstances; and</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>a partner shall indemnify the firm for any loss caused to it by his wilful neglect in the conduct of the business of the firm.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>The property of the firm.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Subject to contract between the partners, the property of the firm includes all property and rights and interests in property originally brought into the stock of the firm, or acquired, by purchase or otherwise, by or for the firm, or for the purposes and in the course of business of the firm, and includes also the goodwill of the business.</p>
            <p>Unless the contrary intention appears, property and rights and interests in property acquired with money belonging to the firm are deemed to have been acquired for the firm.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Application of the property of the firm.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Subject to contract between the partners, the property of the firm shall be held and used by the partners exclusively for the purposes of the business.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Personal profits earned by partners.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Subject to contract between the partners,</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>if a partner derives any profit for himself from any transaction of the firm, or from the use of the property or business connection of the firm or the firm name, he shall account for that profit and pay it to the firm;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>if a partner carries on any business of the same nature as and competing with that of the firm, he shall account for and pay to the firm all profits made by him in that business.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Rights and duties of partners.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-17.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Subject to contract between the partners,</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>after a change in the firm.—</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-17.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>where a change occurs in the constitution of a firm, the mutual rights and duties of the partners in the reconstituted firm remain the same as they were immediately before the change, as far as may be;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>after the expiry of the term of the firm, and.—</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-17.paragraph-0.list5">
              <listIntroduction>where a firm constituted for a fixed term continues to carry on business after the expiry of that term, the mutual rights and duties of the partners remain the same as they were before the expiry, so far as they may be consistent with the incidents of partnership at will; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.paragraph-0.list5.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>where additional undertakings are carried out.—</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>where a firm constituted to carry out one or more adventures or undertakings carries out other adventures or undertakings, the mutual rights and duties of the partners in respect of the other adventures or undertakings are the same as those in respect of the original adventures or undertakings.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Partner to be agent of the firm.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act, a partner is the agent of the firm for the purpose of the business of the firm.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Implied authority of partner as agent of the firm.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-19.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of section 22, the act of a partner which is done to carry on, in the usual way, business of the kind carried on by the firm, binds the firm.</p>
            <p>The authority of a partner to bind the firm conferred by this section is called his “implied authority”.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-19.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In the absence of any usage or custom of trade to the contrary, the implied authority of a partner does not empower him to—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>submit a dispute relating to the business of the firm to arbitration,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>open a banking account on behalf of the firm in his own name,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>compromise or relinquish any claim or portion of a claim by the firm,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>withdraw a suit or proceeding filed on behalf of the firm,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>admit any liability in a suit or proceeding against the firm,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>acquire immovable property on behalf of the firm,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>transfer immovable property belonging to the firm, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>enter into partnership on behalf of the firm.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Extension and restriction of partner’s implied authority.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The partners in a firm may, by contract between the partners, extend or restrict the implied authority of any partner.</p>
            <p>Notwithstanding any such restriction, any act done by a partner on behalf of the firm which falls within his implied authority binds the firm, unless the person with whom he is dealing knows of the restriction or does not know or believe that partner to be a partner.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Partner’s authority in an emergency.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A partner has authority, in an emergency, to do all such acts for the purpose of protecting the firm from loss as would be done by a person of ordinary prudence, in his own case, acting under similar circumstances, and such acts bind the firm.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Mode of doing act to bind firm.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In order to bind a firm, an act or instrument done or executed by a partner or other person on behalf of the firm shall be done or executed in the firm name, or in any other manner expressing or implying an intention to bind the firm.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Effect of admissions by a partner.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>An admission on representation made by a partner concerning the affairs of the firm is evidence against the firm, if it is made in the ordinary course of business.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Effect of notice to acting partner.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notice to a partner, who habitually acts in the business of the firm of any matter relating to the affairs of the firm operates as notice to the firm, except in the case of a fraud on the firm committed by or with the consent of that partner.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Liability of a partner for acts of the firm.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every partner is liable, jointly with all the other partners and also severally, for all acts of the firm done while he is a partner.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Liability of the firm for wrongful acts of a partner.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where, by the wrongful act or omission of a partner acting in the ordinary course of the business of a firm, or with the authority of his partners, loss or injury is caused to any third party, or any penalty is incurred, the firm is liable therefor to the same extent as the partner.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Liability of firm for misapplication by partners.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-27.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where,</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>a partner acting within his apparent authority receives money or property from a third party and misapplies it, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>a firm in the course of its business receives money or property from a third party, and the money or property is misapplied by any of the partners while it is in the custody of the firm the firm is liable to make good the loss.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28">
        <num>28.</num>
        <heading>Holding out.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-28.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any one who by words spoken or written or by conduct represents himself or knowingly permits himself to be represented, to be a partner in a firm, is liable as a partner in that firm to any one who has on the faith of any such representation given credit to the firm, whether the person representing himself or represented to be a partner does or does not know that the representation has reached the person so giving credit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-28.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where after a partner’s death the business is continued in the old firm name, the continued use of that name or of the deceased partner’s name as a part thereof shall not of itself make his legal representative or his estate liable for any act of the firm done after his death.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29">
        <num>29.</num>
        <heading>Rights of transferee or a partner’s interest.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-29.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A transfer by a partner of his interest in the firm, either absolute or by mortgage, or by the creation by him of a change on such interest, does not entitle the transferee, during the continuance of the firm, to interfere in the conduct of the business, or to require accounts, or to inspect the books of the firm, but entitles the transferee only to receive the share of profits of the transferring partner, and the transferee shall accept the account of profits agreed to by the partners.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the firm is dissolved or if the transferring partner ceases to be a partner, the transferee is entitled as against the remaining partners to receive the share of the assets of the firm to which the transferring partner is entitled, and, for the purpose of ascertaining that share, to an account as from the date of the dissolution.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-30">
        <num>30.</num>
        <heading>Minors admitted to the benefits of partnership.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-30.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A person who is a minor according to the law to which he is subject may not be a partner in a firm, but, with the consent of all the partners for the time being, he may be admitted to the benefits of partnership.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-30.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Such minor has a right to such share of the property and of the profits of the firm as may be agreed upon, and he may have access to and inspect and copy any of the accounts of the firm.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-30.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Such minor’s share is liable for the acts of the firm, but the minor is not personally liable for any such act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-30.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Such minor may not sue the partners for an account or payment of his share of the property or profits of the firm, save when severing his connection with the firm, and in such case the amount of his share shall be determined by a valuation made as far as possible in accordance with the rules contained in section 48:</p>
            <p>Provided that all the partners acting together or any partner entitled to dissolve the firm upon notice to other partners may elect in such suit to dissolve the firm, and thereupon the court shall proceed with the suit as one for dissolution and for settling accounts between the partners, and the amount of the share of the minor shall be determined along with the shares of the partners.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-30.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>At any time within six months of his attaining majority, or of his obtaining knowledge that he had been admitted to the benefits of partnership, whichever date is later, such person may give public notice that he has elected to become or that he has elected not to become a partner in the firm, and such notice shall determine his position as regards the firm:</p>
            <p>Provided that, if he fails to give such notice, he shall become a partner in the firm on the expiry of the said six months.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-30.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any person has been admitted as a minor to the benefits of partnership in a firm, the burden of proving the fact that such person had no knowledge of such admission until a particular date after the expiry of six months of his attaining majority shall lie on the persons asserting that fact.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-30.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-30.7.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where such person becomes a partner,</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-30.7.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>his rights and liabilities as a minor continue up to the date on which he becomes a partner, but he also becomes personally liable to third parties for all acts of the firm done since he was admitted to the benefits of partnership, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-30.7.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>his share in the property and profits of the firm shall be the share to which he was entitled as a minor.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-30.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-30.8.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where such person elects not to become a partner,</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-30.8.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>his rights and liabilities shall continue to be those of a minor under this section up to the date on which he gives public notice,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-30.8.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>his share shall not be liable for any acts of the firm done after the date of the notice, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-30.8.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>he shall be entitled to sue the partners for his share of the property and profits in accordance with sub-section (4).</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-30.9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in sub-sections (7) and (8) shall affect the provisions of section 28.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-31">
        <num>31.</num>
        <heading>Introduction of a partner.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-31.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to contract between the partners and to the provisions of section 30, no person shall be introduced as a partner into a firm without the consent of all the existing partners.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-31.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of section 30, a person who is introduced as a partner into a firm does not thereby become liable for any act of the firm done before he became a partner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-32">
        <num>32.</num>
        <heading>Retirement of a partner.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-32.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-32.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A partner may retire,</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-32.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>with the consent of all the other partners,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-32.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in accordance with an express agreement by the partners, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-32.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>where the partnership is at will, by giving notice in writing to all the other partners of his intention to retire.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-32.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A retiring partner may be discharged from any liability to any third party for acts of the firm done before his retirement by an agreement made by him with such third party and the partners of the reconstituted firm, and such agreement may be implied by a course of dealing between such third party and the reconstituted firm after he had knowledge of the retirement.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-32.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding the retirement of a partner from a firm, he and the partners continue to be liable as partners to third parties for any act done by any of them which would have been an act of the firm if done before the retirement, until public notice is given of the retirement:</p>
            <p>Provided that a retired partner is not liable to any third party who deals with the firm without knowing that he was a partner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-32.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notices under sub-section (3) may be given by the retired partner or by any partner of the reconstituted firm.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-33">
        <num>33.</num>
        <heading>Expulsion of a partner.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-33.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A partner may not be expelled from a firm by any majority of the partners, save in the exercise in good faith of powers conferred by contract between the partners.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-33.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of sub-sections (2), (3) and (4) of section 32 shall apply to an expelled partner as if he were a retired partner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-34">
        <num>34.</num>
        <heading>Insolvency of a partner.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-34.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a partner in a firm is adjudicated an insolvent he ceases to be a partner on the date on which the order of adjudication is made, whether or not the firm is hereby dissolved.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-34.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where under a contract between the partners the firm is not dissolved by the adjudication of a partner as an insolvent, the estate of a partner so adjudicated is not liable for any act of the firm and the firm is not liable for any act of the insolvent, done after the date on which the order of adjudication is made.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-35">
        <num>35.</num>
        <heading>Liability of estate of deceased partner.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-35.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where under a contract between the partners the firm is not dissolved by the death of a partner, the estate of a deceased partner is not liable for any act of the firm done after his death.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-36">
        <num>36.</num>
        <heading>Right of outgoing partner to carry on competing business.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-36.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-36.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>An outgoing partner may carry on a business competing with that of the firm and he may advertise such business, but, subject to contract to the contrary, he may not,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-36.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>use the firm name,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-36.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>represent himself as carrying on the business of the firm, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-36.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>solicit the custom of persons who were dealing with the firm before he ceased to be a partner.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Agreements in restraint of trade.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-36.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A partner may make an agreement with his partners that on ceasing to be a partner he will not carry on any business similar to that of the firm within a specified period or within a specified local limits; and, notwithstanding anything contained in section 27 of the Indian Contract Act, 1872 (9 of 1872), such agreement shall be valid if the restrictions imposed are reasonable.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-37">
        <num>37.</num>
        <heading>Right of outgoing partner in certain cases to share subsequent profits.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-37.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where any member of a firm has died or otherwise ceased to be a partner, and the surviving or continuing partners carry on the business of the firm with the property of the firm without any final settlement of accounts as between them and the outgoing partner or his estate, then, in the absence of a contract to the contrary, the outgoing partner or his estate is entitled at the option of himself or his representatives to such share of the profits made since he ceased to be a partner as may be attributable to the use of his share of the property of the firm or to interest at the rate of six per cent. per annum on the amount of his share in the property of the firm:</p>
            <p>Provided that whereby contract between the partners an option is given to surviving or continuing partners to purchase the interest of a deceased or outgoing partner, and that option is duly exercised, the estate of the deceased partner, or the outgoing partner or his estate, as the case may be, is not entitled to any further or other share of profits; but if any partner assuming to act in exercise of the option does not in all material respects comply with the terms thereof, he is liable to account under the foregoing provisions of this section.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-38">
        <num>38.</num>
        <heading>Revocation of continuing guarantee by change in firm.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-38.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A continuing guarantee given to a firm, or to a third party in respect of the transactions of a firm, is, in the absence of agreement to the contrary, revoked as to future transactions from the date of any change in the constitution of the firm.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-39">
        <num>39.</num>
        <heading>Dissolution of a firm.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-39.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The dissolution of partnership between all the partners of a firm is called the ‘dissolution of the firm’.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-40">
        <num>40.</num>
        <heading>Dissolution by agreement.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-40.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A firm may be dissolved with the consent of all the partners or in accordance with a contract between the partners.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-41">
        <num>41.</num>
        <heading>Compulsory dissolution.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-41.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-41.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A firm is dissolved,</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-41.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>by the adjudication of all the partners or of all the partners but one as insolvent, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-41.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>by the happening of any event which makes it unlawful for the business of the firm to be carried on or for the partners to carry it on in partnership:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that, where more than one separate adventure or undertaking is carried on by the firm the illegality of one or more shall not of itself cause the dissolution of the firm in respect of its lawful adventures and undertakings.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-42">
        <num>42.</num>
        <heading>Dissolution on the happening of certain contingencies.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-42.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-42.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Subject to contract between the partners a firm is dissolved,</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-42.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>if constituted for a fixed term, by the expiry of that term;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-42.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>if constituted to carry out one or more adventures or undertakings, by the completion thereof;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-42.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>by the death of a partner; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-42.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>by the adjudication of a partner as an insolvent.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-43">
        <num>43.</num>
        <heading>Dissolution by notice of partnership at will.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-43.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the partnership is at will, the firm may be dissolved by any partner giving notice in writing to all the other partners of his intention to dissolve the firm.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-43.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The firm is dissolved as from the date mentioned in the notice as the date of dissolution or, if no date is so mentioned, as from the date of the communication of the notice.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-44">
        <num>44.</num>
        <heading>Dissolution by the Court.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-44.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-44.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>At the suit of a partner, the Court may dissolve a firm on any of the following grounds, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-44.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>that a partner has become of unsound mind, in which case the suit may be brought as well by the next friend of the partner who has become of unsound mind as by any other partner;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>that a partner, other than the partner suing, has become in any way permanently incapable of performing his duties as partner;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>that a partner, other than the partner suing, is guilty of conduct which is likely to affect prejudicially the carrying on of the business, regard being had to the nature of the business;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>that a partner, other than the partner suing, wilfully or persistently commits breach of agreements relating to the management of the affairs of the firm or the conduct of its business, or otherwise so conducts himself in matters relating to the business that it is not reasonably practicable for the other partners to carry on the business in partnership with him;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>that a partner, other than the partner suing, has in any way transferred the whole of his interest in the firm to a third party, or has allowed his share to be charged under the provisions of rule 49 of Order XXI of the First Schedule to the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) or has allowed it to be sold in the recovery of arrears of land revenue or of any dues recoverable as arrears of land revenue due by the partner;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>that the business of the firm cannot be carried on save at a loss; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-44.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>on any other ground which renders it just and equitable that the firm should be dissolved.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-45">
        <num>45.</num>
        <heading>Liability for acts of partners done after dissolution.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-45.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding the dissolution of a firm, the partners continue to be liable as such to third parties for any act done by any of them which would have been an act of the firm if done before the dissolution, until public notice is given of the dissolution:</p>
            <p>Provided that the estate of a partner who dies, or who is adjudicated an insolvent, or of a partner who, not having been known to the person dealing with the firm to be a partner, retires from the firm, is not liable under this section for acts done after the date on which he ceases to be a partner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-45.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notices under sub-section (1) may be given by any partner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-46">
        <num>46.</num>
        <heading>Right of partners to have business wound up after dissolution.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-46.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>On the dissolution of a firm every partner or his representative is entitled, as against all the other partners or their representatives, to have the property of the firm applied in payment of the debts and liabilities of the firm, and to have the surplus distributed among the partners or their representatives according to their rights.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-47">
        <num>47.</num>
        <heading>Continuing authority of partners for purposes of winding up.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-47.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>After the dissolution of a firm the authority of each partner to bind the firm, and the other mutual rights and obligations of the partners continue notwithstanding the dissolution, so far as may be necessary to wind up the affair of the firm and to complete transactions begun but unfinished at the time of the dissolution, but not otherwise:</p>
            <p>Provided that the firm is in no case bound by the acts of a partner who has been adjudicated insolvent; but this proviso does not affect the liability of any person who has after the adjudication represented himself or knowingly permitted himself to be represented as a partner of the insolvent.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-48">
        <num>48.</num>
        <heading>Mode of settlement of accounts between partners.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-48.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-48.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In settling the accounts of a firm after dissolution, the following rules shall, subject to agreement by the partners, be observed:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-48.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>losses, including deficiencies of capital, shall be paid first out of profits, next out of capital, and, lastly, if necessary, by the partners individually in the proportions in which they were entitled to share profits;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-48.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-48.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>the assets of the firm, including any sums contributed by the partners to make up deficiencies of capital, shall be applied in the following manner and order:—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-48.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>in paying the debts of the firm to third parties;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-48.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>in paying to each partner rateably what is due to him from the firm for advances as distinguished from capital;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-48.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>in paying to each partner rateably what is due to him on account of capital; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-48.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>the residue, if any, shall be divided among the partners in the proportions in which they were entitled to share profits.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-49">
        <num>49.</num>
        <heading>Payment of firm debts and of separate debts.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-49.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where there are joint debts due from the firm, and also separate debts due from any partner, the property of the firm shall be applied in the first instance in payment of the debts of the firm, and, if there is any surplus, then the share of each partner shall be applied in payment of his separate debts or paid to him. The separate property of any partner shall be applied first in the payment of his separate debts, and the surplus (if any) in the payment of the debts of the firm.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-50">
        <num>50.</num>
        <heading>Personal profits earned after dissolution.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-50.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Subject to contract between the partners, the provisions of clause (a) of section 16 shall apply to transactions by any surviving partner or by the representatives of a deceased partner, undertaken after the firm is dissolved on account of the death of a partner and before its affairs have been completely wound up:</p>
            <p>Provided that where any partner or his representative has brought the goodwill of the firm, nothing in this section shall affect his right to use the firm name.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-51">
        <num>51.</num>
        <heading>Return of premium on premature dissolution.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-51.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-51.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where a partner has paid a premium on entering into partnership of a fixed term, and the firm is dissolved before the expiration of that term otherwise than by the death of a partner, he shall be entitled to repayment of the premium or of such part thereof as may be reasonable, regard being had to the terms upon which he became a partner and to the length of time during which he was partner, unless</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-51.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the dissolution is mainly due to his own misconduct, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-51.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the dissolution is in pursuance of an agreement containing no provision for the return of the premium or any part of it.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-52">
        <num>52.</num>
        <heading>Rights where partnership contract is rescinded for fraud or misrepresentation.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-52.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-52.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where a contract creating partnership is rescinded on the ground of the fraud or misrepresentation of any of the parties thereto the party entitled to rescind is, without prejudice to any other right, entitled,</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-52.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to a lien on, or a right of retention of, the surplus or the assets of the firm remaining after the debts of the firm have been paid, for any sum paid by him for the purchase of a share in the firm and for any capital contributed by him;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-52.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to rank as a creditor of the firm in respect of any payment made by him towards the debts of the firm; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-52.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to be indemnified by the partner or partners guilty of the fraud or misrepresentation against all the debts of the firm.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-53">
        <num>53.</num>
        <heading>Right to restrain from use of firm name or firm property.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-53.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>After a firm is dissolved, every partner or his representative may, in the absence of a contract between the partners to the contrary, restrain any other partner or his representative from carrying on a similar business in the firm name or from using any of the property of the firm for his own benefit, until the affairs of the firm have been completely wound up:</p>
            <p>Provided that where any partner or his representative has bought the goodwill of the firm, nothing in this section shall affect his right to use the firm name.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-54">
        <num>54.</num>
        <heading>Agreements of restraint of trade.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-54.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Partners may, upon or in anticipation of the dissolution of the firm, make an agreement that some or all of them will not carry on a business similar to that of the firm within a specified period or within specified local limits; and notwithstanding anything contained in section 27 of the Indian Contract Act, 1872 (9 of 1872), such agreement shall be valid if the restrictions imposed are reasonable.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-55">
        <num>55.</num>
        <heading>Sale of goodwill after dissolution.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-55.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In settling the accounts of a firm after dissolution, the goodwill shall, subject to contract between the partners, be included in the assets, and it may be sold either separately or along with other property of the firm.</p>
            <p>Rights of buyer and seller of goodwill.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-55.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-55.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where the goodwill of a firm is sold after dissolution, a partner may carry on a business competing with that of the buyer and he may advertise such business, but, subject to agreement between him and the buyer, he may not,</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-55.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>use the firm name,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-55.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>represent himself as carrying on the business of the firm, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-55.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>solicit the custom of persons who were dealing with the firm before its dissolution.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Agreements in restraint of trade.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-55.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any partner may, upon the sale of the goodwill of a firm, make an agreement with the buyer that such partner will not carry on any business similar to that of the firm within a specified period or within specified local limits and, notwithstanding anything contained in section 27 of the Indian Contract Act, 1872 (9 of 1872), such agreement shall be valid if the restrictions imposed are reasonable.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-56">
        <num>56.</num>
        <heading>Power to exempt from application of this Chapter.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-56.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government of any State may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that the provisions of this Chapter shall not apply to that State or to any part thereof specified in the notification.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-57">
        <num>57.</num>
        <heading>Appointment of Registrars.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-57.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may appoint Registrars of Firms for the purposes of this Act, and may define the areas within which they shall exercise their powers and perform their duties.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-57.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Registrar shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-58">
        <num>58.</num>
        <heading>Application for registration.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-58.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-58.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The registration of a firm may be effected at any time by sending by post or delivering to the Registrar of the area in which any place of business of the firm is situated or proposed to be situated, a statement in the prescribed form and accompanied by the prescribed fee, stating,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-58.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the firm name,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-58.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the place or principal place of business of the firm,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-58.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the names of any other places where the firm carries on business,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-58.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the date when each partner joined the firm,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-58.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the names in full and permanent addresses of the partners, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-58.1.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the duration of the firm.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>The statement shall be signed by all the partners, or by their agents specially authorised in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-58.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Each person signing the statement shall also verify it in the manner prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-58.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A firm name shall not contain any of the following words, namely:—</p>
            <p>“Crown”, “Emperor”, “Empress”, “Empire”, “Imperial”, “King”, “Queen”, “Royal”, or words expressing or implying the sanction, approval or patronage of Government, except when the State Government signifies its consent to the use of such words as part of the firm name by order in writing ***.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-59">
        <num>59.</num>
        <heading>Registration.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-59.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>When the Registrar is satisfied that the provisions of section 58 have been duly complied with, he shall record an entry of the statement in a register called the Register of Firms, and shall file the statement1.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-60">
        <num>60.</num>
        <heading>Recording of alterations in firm name and principal place of business.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-60.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When an alteration is made in the firm name or in the location of the principal place of business of a registered firm, a statement may be sent to the Registrar accompanied by the prescribed fee, specifying the alteration and signed and verified in the manner required under section 58.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-60.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When the Registrar is satisfied that the provisions of sub-section (1) have been duly complied with, he shall amend the entry relating to the firm in the Register of Firms in accordance with the statement, and shall file it along with the statement relating to the firm filed under section 59.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-61">
        <num>61.</num>
        <heading>Noting of closing and opening of branches.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-61.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>When a registered firm discontinued business at any place or begins to carry on business at any place, such place not being its principal place of business, any partner or agent of the firm may send intimation thereof to the Registrar, who shall make a note of such intimation in the entry relating to the firm in the Register of Firms, and shall file the intimation along with the statement relating to the firm filed under section 59.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-62">
        <num>62.</num>
        <heading>Noting of changes in names and addresses of partners.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-62.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>When any partner in a registered firm alters his name or permanent address, an intimation of the alteration may be sent by any partner or agent of the firm to the Registrar, who shall deal with it in the manner provided in section 61.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-63">
        <num>63.</num>
        <heading>Recording of changes in and dissolution of a firm.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-63.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When a change occurs in the constitution of a registered firm any incoming, continuing or outgoing partner, and when a registered firm is dissolved any person who was a partner immediately before the dissolution, or the agent of any such partner or person specially authorised in this behalf, may give notice to the Registrar of such change or dissolution, specifying the date thereof; and the Registrar shall make a record of the notice in the entry relating to the firm in the Register of Firms, and shall file the notice along with the statement relating to the firm filed under section 59.</p>
            <p>Recording of withdrawal of a minor.—</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-63.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When a minor who has been admitted to the benefits of partnership in a firm attains majority and elects to become or not to become a partner, and the firm is then a registered firm, he, or his agent specially authorised in this behalf, may give notice to the Registrar that he has or has not become a partner, and the Registrar shall deal with the notice in the manner provided in sub-section (1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-64">
        <num>64.</num>
        <heading>Rectification of mistakes.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-64.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Registrar shall have power at all times to rectify any mistake in order to bring the entry in the Register of Firms relating to any firm into conformity with the documents relating to that firm filed under this Chapter.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-64.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On application made by all the parties who have signed any document relating to a firm filed under this Chapter, the Registrar may rectify any mistake in such document or in the record or note thereof made in the Register of Firms.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-65">
        <num>65.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of Register by order of Court.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-65.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A Court deciding any matter relating to a registered firm may direct that the Registrar shall make any amendment in the entry in the Register of Firms relating to such firm which is consequential upon its decision; and the Registrar shall amend the entry accordingly.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-66">
        <num>66.</num>
        <heading>Inspection of Register and filed documents.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-66.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Register of Firms shall be open to inspection by any person on payment of such fee as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-66.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All statements, notices and intimations filed under this Chapter shall be open to inspection, subject to such conditions and on payment of such fee as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-67">
        <num>67.</num>
        <heading>Grant of copies.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-67.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Registrar shall on application furnish to any person, on payment of such fee as may be prescribed, a copy, certified under his hand, of any entry or portion thereof in the Register of Firms.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-68">
        <num>68.</num>
        <heading>Rules of evidence.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-68.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any statement, intimation or notice recorded or noted in the Register of Firms shall, as against any person by whom or on whose behalf such statement, intimation or notice was signed, be conclusive proof of any fact therein stated.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-68.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A certified copy of an entry relating to a firm in the Register of Firms may be produced in proof of the fact of the registration of such firm, and of the contents of any statement, intimation or notice recorded or noted therein.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-69">
        <num>69.</num>
        <heading>Effect of non-registration.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-69.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No suit to enforce a right arising from a contract or conferred by this Act shall be instituted in any court by or on behalf of any person suing as a partner in a firm against the firm or any person alleged to be or to have been a partner in the firm unless the firm is registered and the person suing is or has been shown in the Register of Firms as a partner in the firm.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-69.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No suit to enforce a right arising from a contract shall be instituted in any Court by or on behalf of a firm against any third party unless the firm is registered and the persons suing are or have been shown in the Register of Firms as partners in the firm.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-69.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-69.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The provisions of sub-sections (1) and (2) shall apply also to a claim of set-off or other proceeding to enforce a right arising from a contract, but shall not affect,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-69.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the enforcement of any right to sue for the dissolution of a firm or for accounts of a dissolved firm, or any right or power to realise the property of a dissolved firm, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-69.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the powers of an official assignee, receiver or Court under the Presidency-towns Insolvency Act, 1909 (3 of 1909) or the Provincial Insolvency Act, 1920 (5 of 1920) to realise the property of an insolvent partner.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-69.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-69.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>This section shall not apply,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-69.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to firms or to partners in firms which have no place of business in the territories to which this Act extends, or whose places of business in the said territories, are situated in areas to which, by notification under section 56, this Chapter does not apply, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-69.4.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to any suit or claim of set-off not exceeding one hundred rupees in value which, in the Presidency-towns, is not of a kind specified in section 19 of the Presidency Small Cause Courts Act, 1882 (5 of 1882), or, outside the Presidency-towns, is not of a kind specified in the Second Schedule to the Provincial Small Cause Courts Act, 1887 (9 of 1887), or to any proceeding in execution or other proceeding incidental to or arising from any such suit or claim.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-70">
        <num>70.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for furnishing false particulars.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-70.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any person who signs any statement, amending statement, notice or intimation under this Chapter containing any particular which he knows to be false or does not believe to be true, or containing particulars which he knows to be incomplete or does not believe to be complete, shall be punishable with imprisonment which may extend to three months, or with fine, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-71">
        <num>71.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-71.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may by notification in the Official Gazette make rules describing the fees which shall accompany documents sent to the Registrar of Firms, or which shall be payable for the inspection of documents in the custody of the Registrar of Firms, or for copies from the Register of Firms:</p>
            <p>Provided that such fees shall not exceed the maximum fees specified in Schedule I.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-71.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-71.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The State Government may also make rules,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-71.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>prescribing the form of statement submitted under section 58, and of the verification thereof;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-71.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>requiring statements, intimations and notices under sections 60, 61, 62 and 63 to be in prescribed form, and prescribing the form thereof;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-71.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>prescribing the form of the Register of Firms, and the mode in which entries relating to firms are to be made therein, and the mode in which such entries are to be amended or notes made therein;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-71.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>regulating the procedure of the Registrar when disputes arise;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-71.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>regulating the filing of documents received by the Registrar;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-71.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>prescribing conditions for the inspection of original documents;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-71.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>regulating the grant of copies;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-71.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>regulating the elimination of registers and documents;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-71.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>providing for the maintenance and form of an index to the Register of Firms; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-71.2.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>generally, to carry out the purposes of this Chapter.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-71.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All rules made under this section shall be subject to the condition of previous publication.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-71.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made by the State Government under this section shall be laid, as soon as it is made, before the State Legislature.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-72">
        <num>72.</num>
        <heading>Mode of giving public notice.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-72.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-72.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A public notice under this Act is given—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-72.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>where it relates to the retirement or expulsion of a partner from a registered firm, or to the dissolution of a registered firm, or to the election to become or not to become a partner in a registered firm by a person attaining majority who was admitted as a minor to the benefits of partnership, by notice to Registrar of Firms under section 63, and by publication in the Official Gazette and in at least one vernacular newspaper circulating in the district where the firm to which it relate has its place or principal place of business, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-72.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in any other case, by publication in the Official Gazette and in at least one vernacular newspaper circulating in the district where the firm to which it relates has its place or principal place of business.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-73">
        <num>73.</num>
        <heading>Repeals.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-73.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Rep. by the Repealing Act, 1938 (1 of 1938), sec. 2 and Sch..</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-74">
        <num>74.</num>
        <heading>Savings.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-74.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-74.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Nothing in this Act or any repeal effected thereby shall affect or be deemed to affect,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-74.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any right, title, interest, obligation or liability already acquired, accrued or incurred before the commencement of this Act, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-74.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any legal proceeding or remedy in respect of any such right, title, interest, obligation or liability, or anything done or suffered before the commencement of this Act, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-74.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>anything done or suffered before the commencement of this Act, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-74.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>any enactment relating to partnership not expressly repealed by this Act, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-74.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>any rule of insolvency relating to partnership, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-74.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>any rule of law not inconsistent with this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-thefirstschedule">
      <doc name="thefirstschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1932/9/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1932/9"/>
              <FRBRalias value="THE FIRST SCHEDULE"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1932/9/eng@1980-01-01/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1932/9/eng@1980-01-01"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1932/9/eng@1980-01-01/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1932/9/eng@1980-01-01"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-12-16" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="thefirstschedule">
            <heading>(See sub-section (1) of section 71)</heading>
            <paragraph id="thefirstschedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>MAXIMUM FEES</p>
                <table id="thefirstschedule.paragraph-0.table1">
                  <tr>
                    <th>
                      <p>Document or act in respect of which the fee is payable</p>
                    </th>
                    <td>
                      <p>Maximum fee</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>Statement under section 58</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Three rupees.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>Statement under section 60</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>One rupee.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>Intimation under section 61</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>One rupee.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>Intimation under section 62</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>One rupee.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>Notice under section 63</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>One rupee.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>Application under section 64</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>One rupee.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>Inspection of the Register of Firms under sub-section (1) of section 66</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Eight annas for inspecting one volume of the Register.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>Inspection of documents relating to a firm under sub-section (2) of section 66</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Eight annas for the inspection of all documents relating to one firm.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                  <tr>
                    <td>
                      <p>Copies from the Register of Firms</p>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                      <p>Four annas for each hundred words or part thereof.</p>
                    </td>
                  </tr>
                </table>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-thesecondschedule">
      <doc name="thesecondschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1932/9/thesecondschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1932/9"/>
              <FRBRalias value="THE SECOND SCHEDULE"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1932/9/eng@1980-01-01/thesecondschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1932/9/eng@1980-01-01"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1932/9/eng@1980-01-01/thesecondschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1932/9/eng@1980-01-01"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-12-16" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="thesecondschedule">
            <paragraph id="thesecondschedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>* Omitted</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
