<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1985/16/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1985/16"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Karnataka Parks, Play-Fields And Open Spaces (Preservation and Regulation) Act, 1985"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1985/16/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1985/16/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/1985/16/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/1985/16/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-27" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Karnataka Parks, Play-Fields And Open Spaces (Preservation And Regulation) Act, 1985</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No. 16 of 1985</p>
        <p>An Act, to provide for the preservation and regulation of Parks, Play-fields and Open Spaces in the State of Karnataka.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for preservation and regulation of Parks, Play-fields and Open Spaces in the State of Karnataka;</p>
      <p>BE it enacted by the Karnataka State Legislature in the Thirty-Sixth year of the Republic of India as follows;-</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Karnataka Parks, Play-fields and Open Spaces (Preservation and Regulation) Act, 1985</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Karnataka</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 26th day of December 1984 in the Cities of Bangalore, Belgaum, Gulbarga, Hubli-Dharwar, Mangalore and Mysore and in the local areas comprised within a City Municipality in the State and on such date and in such other local areas of the State as the Government may by, notification, specify and the Government may cancel or modify any such notification</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"Chief Controlling Authority" means in the case of the Cities of Bangalore, Belgaum, Gulbarga, Hubli-Dharwar, Mangalore and Mysore, the Government, and in other cases the Commissioner ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"Commissioner" means the Divisional Commissioner of the revenue division ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>"executive authority" means the Chief Executive Authority of the local authority concerned who is vested with general executive powers under any law for the time being in force providing for the constitution of such local authority ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>"Government" means the State Government ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>"local authority" means a municipal corporation a municipal council, the Bangalore Development Authority, an improvement board, a sanitary board or a notified area committee or a town board constituted or continued under any law for the time being in force and such other authority as may be specified by the Government, by notification, as a local authority;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>"open space" means any land on which there are no buildings or of which not more than one twentieth part is covered with buildings and the whole or the remainder of which is used or meant for the purposes of recreation, air or light or set apart for civic amenity purposes ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>"park" means a piece of land on which there are no buildings or of which not more than one twentieth part is covered with buildings, and the whole or remainder of which is laid out as a garden with trees, plants or flower beds or as a lawn or as a meadow and maintained as a place for the resort of the public for recreation, air or light ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>"play-field" means a piece of land adopted for the purposes of play, game or sport and used by schools or colleges or clubs or general public and includes land set apart as a play-field by a local authority.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Preparation and submission of list of parks, play-fields and open spaces by executive authorities.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The executive authority of every local authority shall, not later than six months from the date on which this Act comes into the force in the area within the jurisdiction of the local authority concerned, prepare, and submit for the approval of the Government a correct and complete list with plans and maps with dimensions of all the parks, play-fields and open spaces in the area aforesaid containing such other particulars as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government shall, as soon as may be, after the receipt of the list and other documents referred to in sub-section (1), publish the list together with a notice of the date (not being less than three months from the date of publication) before which representation in connection therewith may be submitted in the prescribed manner and such publication shall state at what place and time the plans, maps and documents aforesaid will be available to the public for inspection:</p>
            <p>Provided that if any private land is included in any park, play-field or open space specified in the list, a copy of the list with the concerned plans and maps shall cause to be served on the owner of that private land.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Approval of list by Government.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person interested, may submit his representations, objections or suggestions in writing in respect of anything contained in or relating to the list, to the Government, within the time specified in the publication of the list under sub-section (2) of section 3.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, after considering the representations, objections and suggestions, if any, and making such inquiry as it thinks fit, approve the list with or without modifications.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The order of the Government approving the list under sub-section (2) together with the list approved shall be published in the prescribed manner and such publication shall state at which place and time particulars relating to the matter mentioned in the list will be available to the public for inspection.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Inclusion of new lands.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may at any time either suo-motu or at the instance of the local authority concerned or of any person interested include new lands in the list.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Before including such new lands the Government shall publish in the prescribed manner a draft notification proposing such inclusion together with a notice specifying a date on or after which such draft will be taken into consideration, and shall consider any objection or suggestion which may be received in respect of such draft from the local authority concerned or any person interested before the date so specified.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition of the use of parks, play-fields and open spaces in certain cases.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No park, play-field or open space specified in the list published under section 4 or section 5 shall be used for any purpose other than the purpose or purposes for which it was used on the date of commencement of this Act in such area.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Maintenance of parks, play-fields and open spaces.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The local authority concerned shall maintain in a clean and proper condition all parks, play-fields and open spaces belonging to or vested in it and included in the list published under section 4 or section 5.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition of construction of buildings etc.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No person shall construct any building or put up any structure likely to affect the utility of the park, play-field or open space or make any encroachment in or over any park, play-field or open space specified in the list published under section 4 or section 5 :</p>
            <p>Provided that the executive authority may, subject to such rules as may be prescribed, permit the construction of such buildings or putting up of such structures as may be necessary for the improvement or more beneficial utilisation of the park, play-field or open space.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No land or building within a park, play-field or open space specified in the list published under section 4 or section 5 shall be alienated by way of sale, lease, gift, exchange, mortgage or otherwise and no licence for the use of any such land or buildings for any other purposes shall be granted and any alienation made or licence granted in contravention of this section shall be null and void.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Obligation of owner of parks and play-fields.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In the case of parks and play-fields not vested in the local authority but included in the list published under section 4 or section 5, the executive authority, may, by notice, require the owner or the person or authority in occupation of such park or play-field,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>to maintain such park or play-field in a clean condition ; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.1.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>to remove or alter any projection, encroachment or obstruction in or over any such park or play field or to execute such repairs to any building in such park or play-field as the executive authority may consider necessary within the date specified in the notice.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If the owner or the person or authority in occupation fails to comply with the notice under sub-section (1), the executive authority shall itself arrange to,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>maintain such park or play-field in a clean and proper condition ; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>remove or alter the projection, encroachment or obstruction; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>execute such repairs as it may consider necessary and the cost of such maintenance, removal, alteration or repairs shall be recoverable from the owner or the person or authority in occupation in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any dispute as to the amount of cost shall be decided by the Government and its decision shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The executive authority, may, instead of or in addition to taking action as indicated in sub-section (2), proceed to acquire the land under the Land Acquisition Act, 1894 for the purpose of effective management of the land as a park or play-field.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Submission of annual returns.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The executive authority shall submit to the Government through the Commissioner in such form and with such particulars as may be prescribed, an annual return in respect of the parks, play-fields and open spaces which are situated within the limits of the local authority concerned and which are specified in the list published under section 4 or section 5. The return shall also contain a list of the parks and play-fields in respect of which action was taken under sub-section (2) of section 9 together with particulars as regards the nature of the action taken in respect of them and the steps taken in regard to their proper maintenance.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Penalties.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever contravenes the provisions of section 6 or section 8 or throws any rubbish into any park, play-field or open space specified in the list published under section 4 or section 5 shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months or with fine or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Offences by companies.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an offence under this Act is committed by a company, the company, as well as every person in charge of and responsible to the company for the conduct of its business at the time of the commission of the offence, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly :</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to any punishment if he proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or that he exercised all due diligence to prevent commission of such offence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1) where an offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or that the commission of the offence is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary, or other officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.</p>
            <blockList id="section-12.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation.- For the purpose of this section,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.2.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"company" means a body corporate and includes a firm or other association of individuals ; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.2.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"director" in relation to a firm means a partner in the firm.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Control.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the Chief Controlling Authority is satisfied, after giving the executive authority an opportunity of being heard, that the executive authority has failed to enforce effectively the provisions of this Act or to execute any work which under this Act the executive authority is required to execute, it may order the local authority concerned to do all things necessary for enforcing the provisions of this Act effectively or for executing any work which under this Act the executive authority is required to execute.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purposes of this section, the Chief Controlling Authority shall have the same powers of calling for records, causing inspection to be made, and of enforcing its orders by appointing persons to enforce them as the Government has under sections 94, 96 and 97 of Karnataka Municipal Corporations Act, 1976 (Karnataka Act 14 of 1977).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification, and after previous publication, make rules for the purpose of carrying out the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing provisions such rules may provide for,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>controlling or regulating the admission of persons to, and the conduct of persons in, and in the vicinity of parks, play-fields and open spaces ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>restricting or prohibiting the admission of animals or any class of animals to any park, play-field or open space ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>conditions subject to which permission may be granted to construct buildings under section 8 ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the time within which the annual return under section 10 shall be submitted to the Government ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>all matters expressly required or allowed by this Act to be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All rules made, all notification issued and all lists of parks, play-fields and open spaces published under this Act shall, as soon as may be, after they are made or published be laid before each House of the State Legislature while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions and if, before the expiry of the session in which it is so laid or the session immediately following both Houses agree in making any modification in such rule, notification or list, or both Houses agree that such rule, notification or list should not be made or published, such rule notification or list shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything done under that rule, or notification or list.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Repeal and Savings.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Karnataka Parks, Play fields and Open spaces (Preservation and Regulation) Ordinance, 1984 (Karnataka Ordinance No. 19 of 1984) is hereby repealed,</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding such repeal anything done or any action taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or taken under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
