<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1999/44/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1999/44"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The National Trust for Welfare of Persons with Autism, Cerebral Palsy, Mental Retardation and Multiple Disabilities Act, 1999"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1999/44/eng@1999-12-30/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1999/44/eng@1999-12-30"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1999-12-30" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1999/44/eng@1999-12-30/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1999/44/eng@1999-12-30"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-10-17" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The National Trust For Welfare Of Persons With Autism, Cerebral Palsy, Mental Retardation And Multiple Disabilities Act, 1999</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and extent.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the National Trust for Welfare of Persons with Autism, Cerebral Palsy, Mental Retardation and Multiple Disabilities Act, 1999.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“autism” means a condition of uneven skill development primarily affecting the communication and social abilities of a person, marked by repetitive and ritualistic behaviour;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“Board” means Board of trustees constituted under section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“cerebral palsy” means a group of non-progressive conditions of a person characterised by abnormal motor control posture resulting from brain insult or injuries occurring in the pre-natal, perinatal or infant period of development;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>“Chairperson” means the Chairperson of the Board appointed under clause (a) of sub-section (4) of section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>“Chief Executive Officer” means the Chief Executive Officer appointed under sub-section (1) of section 8;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>“Member” means a Member of the Board and includes the Chairperson;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>“mental retardation” means a condition of arrested or incomplete development of mind of a person which is specially characterised by sub-normality of intelligence;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>“multiple disabilities” means a combination of two or more disabilities as defined in clause (i) of section 2 of the Persons with Disabilities (Equal Opportunities, Protection of Rights and Full Participation) Act, 1995 (1 of 1996);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>“notification” means a notification published in the Official Gazette;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>“person with disability” means a person suffering from any of the conditions relating to autism, cerebral palsy, mental retardation or a combination of any two or more of such conditions and includes a person suffering from severe multiple disability;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>“professional” means a person who is having special expertise in a field which would promote the welfare of persons with disability;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>“registered organisation” means an association of persons with disability or an association of parents of persons with disability or a voluntary organisation, as the case may be, registered under section 12;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>“regulations” means the regulations made by the Board under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>“severe disability” means disability with eighty per cent. or more of one or more of multiple disabilities;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.p">
                <num>(p)</num>
                <p>“Trust” means the National Trust for Welfare of Persons with Autism, Cerebral Palsy, Mental Retardation and Multiple Disability constituted under sub-section (1) of section 3.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of the National Trust for Welfare of Persons with Autism, Cerebral Palsy, Mental Retardation and Multiple Disability, etc.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>With effect from such date as the Central Government may, by notification, appoint, there shall be constituted, for the purposes of this Act, a body by the name of the National Trust for Welfare of Persons with Autism, Cerebral Palsy, Mental Retardation and Multiple Disabilities, which shall be a body corporate by the name aforesaid, having perpetual succession and a common seal, with power, subject to the provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of property, both movable and immovable, and to contract, and shall, by the said name, sue or be sued.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The general superintendence, direction and management of the affairs and business of the Trust shall vest in a Board which may exercise all powers and do all acts and things which may be exercised or done by the Trust.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The head office of the Trust shall be at New Delhi and the Board may, with the previous approval of the Central Government, establish offices at other places in India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Board shall consist of—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>a Chairperson to be appointed by the Central Government from amongst the persons having expertise and experience in the field of autism, cerebral palsy, mental retardation and multiple disability;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.4.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>nine persons to be appointed in accordance with such procedure as may be prescribed from amongst the registered organisations out of which three members each shall be from voluntary organisations, association of parents of persons with autism, cerebral palsy, mental retardation and multiple disability and from association of persons with disability,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.4.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that initial appointment under this clause shall be made by the Central Government by nomination; Provided that initial appointment under this clause shall be made by the Central Government by nomination;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.4.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>eight persons not below the rank of Joint Secretary to the Government of India nominated by that Government to represent the Ministries or Departments of Social Justice and Empowerment, Women and Child Development, Health and Family Welfare, Finance, Labour, Education, Urban Affairs and Employment and Rural Employment and Poverty Alleviation, Members, ex officio;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.4.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>three persons to be nominated by the Board representing the associations of trade, commerce and industry engaged in philanthropic activities,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.4.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the Chief Executive Officer, who, shall be of the rank of Joint Secretary to the Government of India, Member-Secretary, ex officio.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board may associate with itself, in such manner and for such purposes as may be determined by regulations, any person whose assistance or advice it may desire for carrying out the objects of the Trust:</p>
            <p>Provided that such person shall have a right to take part in the discussions relevant to that purpose but shall not have a right to vote at a meeting of the Board and shall not be a member for any other purpose:</p>
            <p>Provided further that the maximum number of persons so associated shall not exceed eight and so far as possible the person so associated shall belong to the registered organisation or from the professionals.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Term of office of Chairperson and Members, meeting of Board, etc.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chairperson or a Member shall hold office for a term of three years from the date of his appointment or until his successor shall have been duly appointed, whichever is longer:</p>
            <p>Provided that no person shall hold office as the Chairperson or other Member after he has attained the age of sixty-five years.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The conditions of service of the Chairperson and other Members shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A casual vacancy in the Board shall be filled in accordance with the provisions of section 3 and a person appointed shall hold office only for the remainder of the term for which the member, in whose place he was appointed, would have held that office.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Before appointing any person as the Chairperson or a Member, the Central Government shall satisfy itself that the person does not and will not, have any such financial or other interest as is likely to affect prejudicially his functions as such Member.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No Member of the Board shall be a beneficiary of the Trust during the period such Member holds office.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall meet at least once in three months at such time and place as may be determined by the Board by regulations and shall observe such rules of procedure in the transaction of business at a meeting as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chairperson, if for any reason is unable to attend the meeting of the Board, any Member elected by the Members present from amongst themselves at the meeting, shall preside at the meeting.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All questions which come up before any meeting of the Board shall be decided by a majority of votes of the Members present and voting, and in the event of an equality of votes, the Chairperson, or in his absence, the person presiding shall have a second or casting vote.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Resignation of Chairperson and Members.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chairperson may resign his office by writing under his hand addressed to the Central Government:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Chairperson shall continue in office until the appointment of his successor is made by the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A Member may resign from office by writing under his hand addressed to the Chairperson.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Disqualifications.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>No person shall be a Member if he—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>is, or becomes, of unsound mind or is so declared by a competent court; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>is, or has been convicted of an offence, which in the opinion of the Central Government, involves moral turpitude; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>is, or at any time has been, adjudicated as an insolvent.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Vacation of office by Members.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If a member—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>becomes subject to any of the disqualifications mentioned in section 6; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>is, without obtaining leave of absence, absent from three consecutive meetings of the Board; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>tenders his resignation under section 5,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>his seat shall thereupon become vacant. his seat shall thereupon become vacant.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Chief Executive Officer and staff of Trust.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government shall appoint the Chief Executive Officer to exercise such powers and perform such duties under the direction of the Board as may be prescribed or as may be delegated to him by the Chairperson.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall, with the previous approval of the Central Government, appoint such other officers and employees as it considers necessary to carry out the objectives of the Trust.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The salary and allowances payable to, and the other terms and conditions of service of, the Chief Executive Officer, other officers and employees of the Trust shall be such as may be determined by regulations.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Vacancies in Board not to invalidate acts, etc.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No act or proceeding of the Board shall be called in question on the grounds merely of the existence of any vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution of, the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Objects of Trust.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The objects of the Trust shall be—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to enable and empower persons with disability to live as independently and as fully as possible within and as close to the community to which they belong;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to strengthen facilities to provide support to persons with disability to live within their own families;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to extend support to registered organisations to provide need based services during the period of crisis in the family of persons with disability;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>to deal with problems of persons with disability who do not have family support;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>to promote measures for the care and protection of persons with disability in the event of death of their parent or guardian;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>to evolve procedure for the appointment of guardians and trustees for persons with disability requiring such protection;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>to facilitate the realisation of equal opportunities, protection of rights and full participation of persons with disability; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>to do any other act which is incidental to the aforesaid objects.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Powers and duties of Board.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Board shall,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>receive from the Central Government a one-time contribution of rupees one hundred crores for a corpus, the income whereof shall be utilised to provide for adequate standard of living for persons with disability;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>receive bequest of movable property from any person for the benefit of the persons with disability in general and for furtherance of the objectives of the Trust in particular:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that it shall be obligatory on the part of the Board to make arrangement for adequate standard of living for the beneficiary named in the bequest, if any, and to utilise the property bequeathed for any other purpose for which the bequest has been made:</p>
            <blockList id="section-11.1.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Provided further that the Board shall not be under any obligation to utilise the entire amount mentioned in the bequest for the exclusive benefit of the persons with disability named as beneficiary in the bequest;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.1.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>receive from the Central Government such sums as may be considered necessary in each financial year for providing financial assistance to registered organisations for carrying out any approved programme.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>For the purposes of sub-section (1), the expression “approved programme” means—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-11.2.list1.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>any programme which promotes independent living in the community for persons with disability by—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-11.2.list1.a.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>creating a conducive environment in the community;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-11.2.list1.a.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>counselling and training of family members of persons with disability;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-11.2.list1.a.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>setting up of adult training units, individual and group homes;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any programme which promotes respite care, foster family care or day care service for persons with disability;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>setting up of residential hostels and residential homes for persons with disability;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>development of self-help groups of persons with disability to pursue the realisation of their rights;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>setting up of local level committee to grant approval for guardianship; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>such other programmes which promote the objectives of the Trust.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>While earmarking funds for the purposes of clause (c) of sub-section (2), preference shall be given to women with disability or to persons with severe disability and to senior citizens with disability.</p>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <blockList id="section-11.3.list3">
              <listIntroduction>For the purposes of this sub-section, the expression,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.3.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“persons with severe disability” shall have the same meaning as is assigned to it under sub-section (4) of section 56 of the Persons with Disabilities (Equal Opportunities, Protection of Rights and Full Participation) Act, 1995 (1 of 1996);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.3.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“senior citizen” means a person who is above the age of sixty-five years or more.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Procedure for registration.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any association of persons with disability, or any association of parents of persons with disability or a voluntary organisation whose main object is promotion of welfare of persons with disability may make an application for registration to the Board. 12. Procedure for registration.—</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An application for registration shall be made in such form and manner and at such place as the Board may by regulation provide and shall, contain such particulars and accompanied with such documents and such fees as may be provided in the regulations.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On receipt of application for registration, the Board may make such enquiries as it thinks fit in respect of genuineness of the application and correctness of any particulars thereon.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon receipt of such application the Board shall either grant registration to the applicant or reject such application for reasons to be recorded in writing.</p>
            <p>Provided that where registration has been refused to the applicant, the said applicant may again make an application for registration after removing defects, if any, in its previous application.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of local level committees.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall constitute a local level committee for such area as may be specified by it from time to time.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A local level committee shall consist of—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>an officer of the civil service of the Union or of the State, not below the rank of a District Magistrate or a District Commissioner of a district;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>a representative of a registered organisation; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>a person with disability as defined in clause (t) of section 2 of the Persons with Disabilities (Equal Opportunities, Protection of Rights and Full Participation) Act, 1995 (1 of 1996).</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A local level committee shall continue to work for a period of three years from the date of its constitution or till such time it is reconstituted by the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A local level committee shall meet at least once in every three months or at such interval as may be necessary.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Appointment for guardianship.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A parent of a person with disability or his relative may make an application to the local level committee for appointment of any person of his choice to act as a guardian of the persons with disability. 14. Appointment for guardianship.—</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any registered organisation may make an application in the prescribed form to the local level committee for appointment of a guardian for a person with disability\:</p>
            <p>Provided that no such application shall be entertained by the local level committee, unless the consent of the guardian of the disabled person is also obtained.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>While considering the application for appointment of a guardian, the local level committee shall consider—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>whether the person with disability needs a guardian;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the purposes for which the guardianship is required for person with disability.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The local level committee shall receive, process and decide applications received under sub-sections (1) and (2), in such manner as may be determined by regulations:</p>
            <p>Provided that while making recommendation for the appointment of a guardian, the local level committee shall provide for the obligations which are to be fulfilled by the guardian.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The local level committee shall send to the Board the particulars of the applications received by it and orders passed thereon at such interval as may be determined by regulations.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Duties of guardian.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every person appointed as a guardian of a person with disability under this Chapter shall, wherever required, either have the care of such person of disability and his property or be responsible for the maintenance of the person with disability.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Guardian to furnish inventory and annual accounts.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-16.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every person appointed as a guardian under section 14 shall, within a period of six months from the date of his appointment, deliver to the authority which appointed him, an inventory of immovable property belonging to the person with disability and all assets and other movable property received on behalf of the person with disability, together with a statement of all claims due to and all debts and liabilities due by such person with disability.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every guardian shall also furnish to the said appointing authority within a period of three months at the close of every financial year, an account of the property and assets in his charge, the sums received and disbursed on account of the person with disability and the balance remaining with him.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Removal of guardian.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-17.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Wherever a parent or a relative of a person with disability or a registered organisation finds that the guardian is -</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>abusing or neglecting a person with disability; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>misappropriating or neglecting the property,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>it may in accordance with the prescribed procedure apply to the committee for the removal of such guardian.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon receiving such application the committee may, if it is satisfied that there is a ground for removal and for reasons to be recorded in writing, remove such guardian and appoint a new guardian in his place or if such a guardian is not available make such other arrangements as may be necessary for the care and protection of person with disability.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person removed under sub-section (2) shall be bound to deliver the charge of all property of the person with disability to the new guardian, and to account for all moneys received or disbursed by him.</p>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <p>For the purposes of this Chapter, the expression “relative” includes any person related to the person with disability by blood, marriage or adoption.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Accountability.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The books and documents in the possession of the Board shall be open to inspection by any registered organisation.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any registered organisation can submit a written requisition to the Board for getting a copy of any book or document maintained by the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall frame such regulations as it thinks necessary for allowing the access of any book or document to a registered organisation.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Monitoring.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall determine by regulations the procedure for evaluating the prefunding status of registered organisations seeking financial assistance from it and such regulations may also provide for the guidelines for monitoring and evaluating the activities of the registered organisations who are receiving financial assistance from the Trust.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Annual general meeting.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-20.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall in each year hold an annual general meeting of registered organisations, and not more than six months shall elapse between the date of one annual general meeting and that of the next.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A notice of the annual general meeting along with a statement of accounts and records of its activities during the preceding year shall be sent by the Board to every registered organisation at such time as may be determined by regulations.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The quorum for such meeting shall be such number of persons of the registered organisations as may be determined by regulations.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Grants by the Central Government.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in this behalf, make to the Trust a one-time contribution of rupees one hundred crores for a corpus, the income whereof may be utilised to achieve the objects of the Trust under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Fund.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-22.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-22.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>There shall be constituted a Fund to be called the National Trust for Welfare of Persons with Autism, Cerebral Palsy, Mental Retardation and Multiple Disabilities Fund and there shall be credited thereto—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-22.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>all moneys received from the Central Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-22.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>all moneys received by the Trust by way of grants, gifts, donations, benefactions, bequests or transfers;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-22.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>all moneys received by the Trust in any other manner or from any other source.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-22.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All moneys belonging to the fund shall be deposited in such banks or invested in such manner as the Board may, subject to the approval of the Central Government, decide.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-22.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The funds shall be applied towards meeting the administrative and other expenses of the Trust including expenses incurred in the exercise of its powers and performance of duties by the Board in relation to any of its activities under section 10 or for anything relatable thereto.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Budget.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall prepare, in such form and at such time in each financial year as may be prescribed, the budget for the next financial year showing the estimated receipt and expenditure of the Trust and shall forward the same to the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Accounts and audit.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-24.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall maintain proper accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual statement of accounts of the Trust including the income and expenditure accounts in such form as the Central Government may prescribe and in accordance with such general direction as may be issued by that Government in consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The accounts of the Trust shall be audited by the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India at such intervals as may be specified by him and any expenditure incurred by him in connection with such audit shall be payable by the Board to the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Comptroller and Auditor-General of India and any other person appointed by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the Trust shall have the same rights, privileges and authority in connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India generally has in connection with the audit of the Government accounts and in particular, shall have the right to demand the production of books of account, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and to inspect any of the offices of the Trust.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The accounts of the Trust as certified by the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India or any other person appointed by him in this behalf, together with the audit report thereon, shall be forwarded annually to the Central Government, and that Government shall cause the same to be laid before each House of Parliament.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Annual report.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall prepare every year, in such form and within such time as may be prescribed an annual report giving a true and full account of its activities during the previous year and copies thereof shall be forwarded to the Central Government and that Government shall cause the same to be laid before each House of Parliament.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Authentication of orders, etc.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>All orders and decisions of the Board and instruments issued in the name of the Trust shall be authenticated by the signature of the Chairperson, the Chief Executive Officer or any other officer authorised by the Chairperson in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Returns and information.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall furnish to the Central Government such reports, returns and other information as that Government may require from time to time.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28">
        <num>28.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to issue directions.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-28.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Without prejudice to the foregoing provisions of this Act, the Board shall, in exercise of its powers or the performance of its duties under this Act, be bound by such directions on questions of policy as the Central Government may give in writing to it from time to time:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Board shall, as far as practicable, be given an opportunity to express its views before any direction is given under this sub-section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-28.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The decision of the Central Government whether a question is one of policy or not shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29">
        <num>29.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to supersede Board.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-29.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the Central Government on the complaint of a registered organisation or otherwise has reason to believe that the Board is unable to perform or has persistently made default in the performance of the duties imposed on it, the Central Government may issue notice to the Board asking why it should not be superseded:</p>
            <p>Provided that no order superseding the Board shall be made by the Central Government, unless a notice affording reasonable opportunity to the Board has been given in writing that why it should not be superseded.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government after recording reasons in writing and by issuing a notification in the Official Gazette supersede the Board for a period of not more than six months:</p>
            <p>Provided that on the expiration of the period of supersession, the Central Government may reconstitute the Board, in accordance with section 3.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-29.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Upon the publication of the notification under sub-section (2),—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-29.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>all the members of the Board shall, notwithstanding that their term of office had not expired as on the date of supersession, vacate their office as such members;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-29.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>all the powers and duties which may, by or under the provisions of this Act, be exercised or performed by or on behalf of the Trust shall, during the period of supersession, be exercised and performed by such person or persons as the Central Government may direct.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-29.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>On the expiration of the period of supersession specified in the notification issued under sub-section (2), the Central Government may—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-29.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>extend the period of supersession for such further period as it may consider necessary so that the total period of supersession does not exceed more than six months; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-29.4.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>reconstitute the Board in the manner provided in section 3.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-30">
        <num>30.</num>
        <heading>Exemption from tax on income.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-30.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Income-tax Act, 1961 (43 of 1961), or any other law for the time being in force relating to tax on income, profits or gains, the Trust shall not be liable to pay income-tax or any other tax in respect of its income, profits or gains derived.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-31">
        <num>31.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-31.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central Government or the Trust or any member of the Board or Chief Executive Officer or any officer or other employee of the Trust or any other person authorised by the Board to perform duties under this act for any loss or damage caused or likely to be caused by anything which is done in good faith.</p>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <p>For the purposes of this section, the expression “good faith” shall have the same meaning as is assigned to it in the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-32">
        <num>32.</num>
        <heading>Chairperson, Members and officers of Trust to be public servants.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-32.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>All Members, Chief Executive Officer, other officers and employees of the Trust shall be deemed, when acting or purporting to act in pursuance of any of the provisions of this Act, to be public servant within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-33">
        <num>33.</num>
        <heading>Delegation.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-33.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Board may, by general or special order in writing, delegate to the Chairperson or any member or any officer of the Trust or any other person subject to such conditions and limitations, if any, as may be specified in the order such of its powers under this Act (except the power to make regulations under section 35) as it may deem necessary.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-34">
        <num>34.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-34.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the provisions of this Act. 34.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-34.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-34.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing powers, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-34.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the procedure in accordance with which the persons representing registered organisation shall be elected under clause (b) of sub-section (4) of section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-34.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the conditions of service of the Chairperson and Members under sub-section (2) of section 4;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-34.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the rules of procedure in the transaction of business at meetings of the Board under sub-section (6) of section 4;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-34.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the powers and duties of the Chief Executive Officer under sub-section (1) of section 8;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-34.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the form in which an application for guardianship may be made by a registered organisation under sub-section (2) of section 14;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-34.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the procedure in accordance with which a guardian may be removed under section 17;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-34.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the form in which, and the time within which, the budget of the Trust shall be forwarded to the Central Government under section 23;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-34.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the form in which the annual statement of accounts shall be maintained under sub-section (1) of section 24;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-34.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the form in which, and the time within which, the annual reports shall be prepared and forwarded under section 25;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-34.2.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>any other matter which is required to be, or may be, prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-35">
        <num>35.</num>
        <heading>Power to make regulations.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-35.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board may, with the previous approval of the Central Government, by notification in the Official Gazette, make regulations consistent with this Act and rules generally to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-35.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-35.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such regulations may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely\:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-35.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the manner and purpose for which a person may be associated under sub-section (5) of section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-35.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the time and place at which the Board shall meet under sub-section (6) of section 4;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-35.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the terms and conditions of service of, Chief Executive Officer, other officers and employees of the Trust under sub-section (3) of section 8;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-35.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the form and manner in which the application shall be made for registration under sub-section (2) of section 12 and the particulars which such application shall contain under that sub-section;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-35.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the manner in which application for guardianship shall be received, processed and decided by the local level committee under sub-section (4) of section 14;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-35.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the particulars of applications and orders passed thereon by the local level committee under sub-section (5) of section 14;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-35.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the procedure for evaluating the pre-funding status of the registered organisations and framing of guidelines for monitoring and evaluating the activities of such registered organisations under section 19;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-35.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the time within which notice for annual general meeting shall be sent and quorum for such meeting under sub-sections (2) and (3) of section 20; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-35.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>any other matter which is required to be, or may be, provided by regulations.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-36">
        <num>36.</num>
        <heading>Rules and regulations to be laid before Parliament.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-36.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every rule and every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or regulation or both Houses agree that the rule or regulation should not be made, the rule or regulation shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule or regulation.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
