<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1948/1/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1948/1"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Andhra Pradesh Home Guards Act, 1948"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1948/1/eng@2017-01-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1948/1/eng@2017-01-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-24" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1948/1/eng@2017-01-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1948/1/eng@2017-01-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-24" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Andhra Pradesh Home Guards Act, 1948</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No. 1 of 1948</p>
      </longTitle>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[24th February, 1948]</docDate>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>An Act to provide for the constitution of Home Guards in the State of Andhra Pradesh</p>
      <p>Whereas it is necessary to constitute a volunteer organisation for use in emergencies in the State of Andhra Pradesh;</p>
      <p>It is hereby enacted as follows:-</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Andhra Pradesh Home Guards Act. 1948</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It is extends to the whole of the State of Andhra Pradesh</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-1.3.list0">
              <item id="section-1.3.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>This section shall come into force at once in the whole of the State</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1.3.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>The rest of this Act shall come into force at once in the districts of East Godavari, West Godavari, Krishna, Guntur, Kurnool, Anantapur, Cuddapah, and Nellore.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1.3.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Andhra Pradesh Gazette extend the rest of this Act to any other area in the State with effect from such date as may be specified in the notification.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"Home Guard" means a person who is appointed a Home Guard under this Act.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of Home Guards and appointment of officers</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may constitute for each of the area specified in Section 1 (3) (b), and for each of the other areas notified under Section 1 (3)(c), a volunteer body called the "Home Guards", every member of which shall have such powers and discharge such duties in relation to the protection of persons, the security of property, and the preservation of public order or tranquility as may be assigned to him by or under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government or any person empowered by them in this behalf may appoint as</p>
            <p>many officers as the State Government may consider necessary for the proper governance and conduct of the Home Guards; one of the officers so appointed may be Commandant for all the Home Guards of the State.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Appointment and removal of Home Guards</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder, any person possessing the prescribed qualifications and willing to serve may be appointed as a Home Guard by such authority and in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Home Guard shall receive a certificate of appointment which shall be in such form and shall be issued by such authority as may be prescribed and thereupon he shall have the powers, privileges and protection conferred, and discharge the duties imposed, on a Home Guard by or under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The prescribed authority may, subject to such conditions as may be prescribed, suspend dismiss or remove any Home Guard from his office and thereupon the certificate received by him shall cease to have effect.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Period of service and discharge</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A Home Guard shall be bound to serve the State Government for such period and in such areas as may be prescribed, but he may be discharged at any time by such authority and subject to such conditions as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Calling out of Home Guards</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Commissioner of Police in the Cities of Hyderabad and Secunderabad, and the District Superintendent of Police in the district concerned may, at any time, call out in such manner and through such officer as may be prescribed, any Home Guard for the cities aforesaid or district, as the case may be, for training or for discharging any duties assigned to him by or under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Powers, privileges and protection of Home Guards</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A Home Guard, when called out under Section 6, shall have the same powers, privileges and protection as an Officer of the Police appointed under the Hyderabad City Police Act (Act IX of 1348 F.) or the Andhra Pradesh (Andhra Area) District Police Act, 1859, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No prosecution shall be instituted against a Home Guard in respect of any act done or purporting to be done in the exercise of his powers or the discharge of his duties as such except</p>
            <p>with the previous sanction of the Commissioner of Police in the Cities of Hyderabad and Secunderabad and of the District Superintendent of Police in the district concerned.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Control by Officers of Police force</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A Home Guard, when called out under Section 6 in aid of the police force, shall be under the control of the officers of the police force in such manner and to such extent as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Penalties</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any Home Guard, without sufficient cause, neglects or refuses to obey the orders of any superior authority or officer or fails to discharge any other duty, or deserts his post, or is guilty of any willful breach or neglect of any provision of this Act or of any rule or lawful order made or issued thereunder by a competent authority, he shall be punishable with simple imprisonment for a term which may extend to three months or with fine which may extend to two hundred and fifty rupees or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No prosecution shall be instituted against any Home Guard for any offence punishable under sub-section (1), without the previous sanction of an officer empowered by the State Government in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An offence punishable under sub-section (1) shall be cognizable.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Rules</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Andhra Pradesh Gazette makes rules consistent with this Act for giving effect to the purposes thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for or regulate the following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>all matters required or allowed by this Act to be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the exercise by any police officer or any officer of the Home Guards of the powers</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-10.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>conferred by Section 6 on the Commissioner of Police, or the District Superintendent of Police concerned, as the case may be;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.2.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the exercise of control by officers of the police force over Home Guards when acting in aid of the police force;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the organization, appointment, discipline, training, arms, accouterments and clothing, conditions of service powers, and duties of Home Guards;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the exercise by Home Guards of any of the powers exercisable under Section 7, sub-section (1).</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Home Guards to be public servants</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Home Guards acting in the exercise of their powers or the discharge of their duties under this Act shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of Section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (Central Act 45 of 1860).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Section 12</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Repealed by Section 2 of and the First Schedule to the Madras Act XI of 1952.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
