<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-wbg/act/2000/13/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-wbg/act/2000/13"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The West Bengal Prohibition Of Ragging In Educational Institutions Act, 2000"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-wbg/act/2000/13/eng@2017-01-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-wbg/act/2000/13/eng@2017-01-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-wbg/act/2000/13/eng@2017-01-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-wbg/act/2000/13/eng@2017-01-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-12-07" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The West Bengal Prohibition Of Ragging In Educational Institutions Act, 2000</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[29th May, 2000]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[No. 13 of 2000]</p>
        <p>An Act to prohibit ragging in educational institutions in West Bengal.</p>
        <p>Whereas it is expedient to prohibit ragging in educational institutions in West Bengal;</p>
        <p>It is hereby enacted as follows:—</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the West Bengal Prohibition of Ragging in Educational Institutions Act, 2000.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of West Bengal.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the State Government may by notification appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In this Act , unless the context otherwise requires,—</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>“educational institution” means any educational institution, by whatever name called, whether or not maintained and managed by the State Government,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>recognised or deemed to have been recognised under any law for the time being in force, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>affiliated to a University as defined in the University Grants Commission Act, 1956;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“notification” means a notification published in the Official Gazette;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act ;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>“ragging” means the doing of any act which causes, or is likely to cause, any physical, psychological or physiological harm or apprehension or shame or embarrassment to a student, and includes—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>teasing or abusing of, playing practical joke on, or causing hurt to, any student, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.4.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>asking any student to do any act , or perform any thing, which he would not, in the ordinary course, be willing to do or perform;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“student” means a student who has been prosecuting his studies in an educational institution.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition of ragging.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Ragging within an educational institution is hereby prohibited.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No person shall participate in, abet, or propagate, ragging in any educational institution.</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation:—For the purposes of this section, educational institution shall include—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the premises or the campus of the educational institution, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the hall, that is to say, the unit of residence of students maintained by the educational institution, if any, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the hostel, that is to say, the unit of residence for students, if any, not maintained by the educational institution but recognised under any law for the time being in force.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for ragging.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever contravenes the provisions of section 3 shall be punished with imprisonment of either description for a term which may extend to two years, or with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Dismissal of student on conviction and bar to admission or re-admission.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any student is convicted of an offence punishable under section 4, he shall be dismissed from the educational institution in which he has been prosecuting his studies for the time being, and shall not be readmitted to that educational institution.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Expulsion of student.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Without prejudice to the foregoing provisions of this Act , where a student complains of ragging by any other student to the head of the educational institution or to any other person responsible for the management of the educational institution, such head of the educational institution or person responsible for the management of the educational institution shall forthwith inquire into the complaint and if, on such enquiry, the complaint is found to be true, he shall expel the student, who has committed the offence, from the educational institution.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of Committee.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in section 5 or section 6, any student dismissed under section 5 or expelled under section 6, may appeal in the prescribed manner to the Committee to be constituted by the State Government in the manner prescribed, and the decision of the Committee on such appeal shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Failure or negligence to comply with the provisions of section 6.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the head of the educational institution or the person responsible for the management of the educational institution fails or neglects to comply with the provisions of section 6, a complaint of such failure may be made to the Committee, constituted under section 7, by the student who complains of ragging under section 6 or by his guardian.</p>
            <p>Explanation:—“Guardian” shall mean a person having the care of the student or any other person who has been declared to be the guardian of the student in the record, if any, maintained by the educational institution.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On receipt of the complaint under sub-section (1), the Committee shall hold such inquiry as it may deem fit and shall make its recommendations to the managing committee or the governing body of the educational institution or such authority as the Committee considers appropriate and, thereupon, the managing committee or the governing body of the educational institution or the authority, as the case may be, shall take act ion in accordance with the recommendations as aforesaid.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Act to have overriding effect.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained in any other law for the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may by notification make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act .</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All rules made under this Act shall, unless some later date is appointed by the State Government, come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
