<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1983/48/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1983/48"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Public Financial Institutions (Obligation As To Fidelity And Secrecy) Act, 1983"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1983/48/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1983/48/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1983/48/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1983/48/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-06-08" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Public Financial Institutions (Obligation As To Fidelity And Secrecy) Act, 1983</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[30th December, 1983.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>ACT NO. 48  OF  1983</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the obligation of public financial institutions as to fidelity and secrecy.</p>
      </longTitle>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty-fourth Year of the Republic of India as follows:—</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Public Financial Institutions (Obligation as to Fidelity and Secrecy) Act, 1983.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, “public financial institution” means—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the Industrial Credit and Investment Corporation of India Limited, a company formed and registered under the Indian Companies Act, 1913 (7 of 1913);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the Industrial Reconstruction Corporation of India Limited, a company formed and registered under the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956); or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any other institution, being a company as defined in section 617 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) or a company to which the provisions of section 619 of that Act apply, which the Central Government may, having regard to the nature of the business carried on by such institution, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify to be a public financial institution for the purposes of this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every notification issued under clause (c) of sub-section (1) shall, as soon as may be, after it is issued, be laid before each House of Parliament.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Obligation as to fidelity and secrecy.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A public financial institution shall not, except as otherwise provided in sub-section (2) or in any other law for the time being in force, divulge any information relating to, or to the affairs of, its constituents except in circumstances in which it is, in accordance with the law or practice and usage, customary among bankers, necessary or appropriate for the public financial institution to divulge such information.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A public financial institution may, for the purpose of efficient discharge of its functions, collect from, or furnish to,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the Central Government; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the State Bank of India constituted under section 3 of the State Bank of India Act, 1955 (23 of 1955), any subsidiary bank within the meaning of the State Bank of India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, 1959 (38 of 1959), any corresponding new bank constituted under section 3 of the Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings) Act, 1970 (5 of 1970) or under section 3 of the Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings) Act, 1980 (40 of 1980), any other scheduled bank within the meaning of the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934); or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any other public financial institution,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>such credit information or other information as it may consider useful for the purpose, in such manner and at such time as it may think fit.</p>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <p>For the purposes of this sub-section, the expression “credit information” shall have the same meaning as in clause (c) of section 45A of the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934) subject to the modification that the banking company referred to therein shall mean a bank referred to in clause (b) of this sub-section or a public financial institution.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing contained in this section shall apply to the credit information disclosed under the Credit Information Companies (Regulation) Act, 2005.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Declaration of fidelity and secrecy.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Every director, member of any committee, auditor or officer or any other employee of a public financial institution to which this Act applies, shall,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>before entering upon his duties; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>where he has entered upon his duties as such before the date on which this Act became applicable to such institution, within thirty days from the date on which this Act became applicable to such institution,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>make a declaration of fidelity and secrecy in the form set out in the Schedule to this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of Act 15 of 1942.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1988 (19 of 1988), sec. 2 and Sch. I (w.e.f. 31-3-1988).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of Act 63 of 1951.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1988 (19 of 1988), sec. 2 and Sch. I (w.e.f. 31-3-1988).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-theschedule">
      <doc name="theschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1983/48/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1983/48"/>
              <FRBRalias value="The Schedule"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1983/48/eng@1980-01-01/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1983/48/eng@1980-01-01"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1983/48/eng@1980-01-01/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1983/48/eng@1980-01-01"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-06-08" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="theschedule">
            <paragraph id="theschedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>Declaration of Fidelity And Secrecy</p>
                <p>I, ........................., do hereby declare that I will faithfully, truly and to the best of my skill and ability, execute and perform the duties required of me as director, member of any committee, auditor, officer or other employee (as the case may be) of the ........................................* and which properly relate to the office or position held by me in, or in relation to, the..................................................*</p>
                <p>I further declare that I will not communicate or allow to be communicated to any person not legally entitled thereto any information relating to the affairs of the ................ ................................................* to the affairs of any person having any dealing with the............................................................* nor will I allow any such person to inspect, or have access to, any books or documents belonging to, or in the possession of, the..................................................................* and relating to the business of the ..................................................* or the business of any person having any dealing with the ..................................................*</p>
                <p>Signed before me Signature.</p>
                <p>* Here insert the name of the public financial Institution concerned.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
