<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/2011/23/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/2011/23"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Karnataka Professional Education Institutions (Regulation of Admission and Fixation of Fee) (Special Provisions) Act, 2011"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/2011/23/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/2011/23/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kar/act/2011/23/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kar/act/2011/23/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-04-10" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Karnataka Professional Educational Institutions (Regulation Of Admission And Fixation Of Fee) (Special Provisions) Act, 2011</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No. 23 of 2011</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for recognition of the consensual arrangement or agreement entered into between the State Government and the Private Unaided Educational Institutions imparting Professional Educational Courses and for other matters, as provided in the judgment of the Supreme Court of India in P.A. Inamdar and others Vs. State of Maharashtra reported in 2005(6) SCC 537.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>Whereas the State Government, to protect the interest of the students of Karnataka domicile and students belonging to educationally and socially backward classes, have entered into a consensual arrangement or agreement with the Private Unaided Professional Educational Institutions for the years 2008-09, 2009-10, 2010-11 and has proposed to enter into a consensual arrangement or agreement for the year 2011-2012 and felt that the Karnataka Professional Educational Institutions (Regulation of Admission and Determination of Fee) Act, 2006 (Karnataka Act 8 of 2006) be kept in abeyance for the academic years 2008-09, 2009-10, 2010-11 and 2011-12 and for the purposes hereinafter appearing;</p>
      <p>Be it enacted by the Karnataka State Legislature in the sixty second year of the Republic of India, as follows:-</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, commencement and application.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Karnataka Professional Educational Institutions (Regulation of Admission and Fixation of Fee) (Special Provisions) Act, 2011.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be deemed to have come into force with effect from 1st day of June, 2008.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Karnataka Professional Educational Institutions (Regulation of Admission and Determination of Fee) Act, 2006 (Karnataka Act 8 of 2006), admissions and fixation of fee in an unaided Private Professional Educational Institution for the academic years 2008-09, 2009-10, 2010-11 and 2011-12 shall be governed by the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"Common Entrance Test" means the entrance test conducted for determination of merit of the candidates followed by centralized counseling for the purpose of admission to professional educational courses through a single window procedure;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“Common Entrance Test Cell” means the agency of the State Government which conducts the common entrance test;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>"Consensual arrangement or agreement" means any agreement that may be entered into between the State Government and association of unaided Private Professional Educational Institutions relating to admission and fixation of fee in professional courses;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>"Institution" means Professional Educational Institutions offering Professional Educational courses;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>"One Man Regulatory Committee" means the Committee constituted by the State Government under section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>"Professional Educational Courses" means,-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f.list0.I">
                    <num>(I)</num>
                    <p>In Medical and Dental Institutions,-</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>Bachelor of Medicine and Bachelor of Surgery; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>Bachelor of Dental Surgery.</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list1.II">
                    <num>(II)</num>
                    <p>In Engineering Institutions,</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>Bachelor of Engineering;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>Bachelor of Technology;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list2">
                  <listIntroduction>Bachelor of Architecture; and</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list2.III">
                    <num>(III)</num>
                    <p>such other courses as may be notified by the State Government</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>"Unaided institution" means any privately managed professional educational institution, which is not receiving aid or grant-in-aid from the State Government.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of One Man Regulatory Committee.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>There shall be a One-Man Regulatory Committee appointed by the State Government, who shall be a former Vice-Chancellor of any University in the State. The said One-Man Regulatory Committee shall oversee the admission to professional courses and the implementation of the consensual arrangement or agreement.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Fixation of fee.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding the fee fixed in respect of Professional Educational Institutions which are in force on the date of commencement of this Act, the State Government may, in accordance with the consensual arrangement or agreement, by notification, fix the fee payable for admission to the Unaided Private Professional Educational Institutions. Different rates of fees may be fixed for different categories of students.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Regulation of admission and seat matrix.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For effective implementation of the consensual arrangement or agreement, seats in a Private Unaided Professional Educational Institution shall be filled in the following manner, namely:-</p>
            <blockList id="section-5.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>'(I) (i) Out of the total intake of seats for the academic year 2008-09,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in non-minority institution offering Engineering courses not less than, fifty five percent of total seats;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in minority institution offering Engineering courses not less than forty five percent of total seats;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>in non-minority institution offering Medical courses not less than forty percent of total seats;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>in minority institution offering Medical courses not less than twenty five percent of total seats;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>in non-minority institution offering Dental courses not less than thirty five percent of total seats;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <blockList id="section-5.1.list2.f.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>in minority institution offering Dental courses not less than twenty five percent of total seats;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-5.1.list2.f.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>Out of the total intake of seats for the academic year 2009-10,-</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in non-minority institution offering Engineering courses not less than, fifty percent of total seats;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in minority institution offering Engineering courses not less than forty five percent of total seats;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>in non-minority institution offering Medical courses not less than forty two percent of total seats;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>in minority institution offering Medical courses not less than twenty seven percent of total seats;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>in non-minority institution offering Dental courses not less than thirty five percent of total seats;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <blockList id="section-5.1.list2.f.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>in minority institution offering Dental courses not less than twenty five percent of total seats;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-5.1.list2.f.list1.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>Out of the total intake of seats for the academic year 2010-11,-</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in non-minority institution offering Engineering courses not less than, fifty percent of total seats;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in minority institution offering Engineering courses not less than forty percent of total seats;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>in non-minority institution offering Medical courses not less than forty two percent of total seats;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>in minority institution offering Medical courses not less than twenty seven percent of total seats;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>in non-minority institution offering Dental courses not less than thirty five percent of total seats;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>in minority institution offering Dental courses not less than twenty five percent of total seats;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <blockList id="section-5.1.list2.g.list2">
                  <listIntroduction>in minority and non-minority institutions offering Indian System of medicine and Homeopathy not less than twenty percent of total seats;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-5.1.list2.g.list2.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>for the year 2011-12 such number of seats as may be agreed to by the Government under the consensual arrangement or agreement;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall be filled through the Common Entrance Test Cell in accordance with the Karnataka Selection of Candidates for Admission to Government seats in Professional Educational Institutions Rules, 2006.</p>
            <p>'(II) The remaining seats shall be filled through the Common Entrance Test conducted by the association of Private Professional Educational Institutions or the association of religious and linguistic minority institutions, as the case may be followed by centralized counseling, in a fair and transparent manner on the basis of merit determined subject to such rules as may be prescribed except otherwise specified in the consensual arrangement or agreement.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to reservation policy of the State Government and the consensual arrangement or agreement, the State Government may, by notification, publish the seat matrix to be filled by the Common Entrance Test Cell and the management, by different categories of students in respect of different categories of institutions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Invalidation of admissions made in violation of this Act.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>All admissions made in violation of the provisions of this Act or the consensual arrangement or agreement by any Private Unaided Professional Educational Institutions for the academic years 2008-09, 2009-10,2010-11 and 2011-12 whether made before or after commencement of this Act shall be invalid. In case of such violation, the State Government may direct the concerned university to cancel such admissions or affiliation of such institution as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Power to remove difficulties.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the State Government may, by order published in the official Gazette, make provisions not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act as appear it to be necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification, in the official Gazette, make rules prospectively or retrospectively for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this Act shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made before each House of the State Legislature while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Validation of admissions and collection of fee.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in any judgment, decree or order of any Court, Tribunal or other authority to the contrary, all admissions made or purporting to have been made or the fee collected with effect from the 1st day of June, 2008 in accordance with the consensual arrangement or agreement or the provisions of this Act by the Professional Educational Institutions or the State Government shall be and shall be deemed to be valid and effective as if such admission or collection of fee had been done or made under the provisions of this Act,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>all acts, proceedings or things done or taken by the Professional Educational Institutions or by the State Government in connection with the admissions and collection of fee be deemed to be, and to have always been done or taken in accordance with law;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>no suit or other proceedings shall be maintained or continued in any Court or Tribunal or authority for the refund of any such fee;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>no Court shall enforce any decree or order directing the refund of any such fee.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
