<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1988/41/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1988/41"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Religious Institutions (Prevention Of Misuse) Act, 1988"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1988/41/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1988/41/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1988/41/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1988/41/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-02-20" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Religious Institutions (Prevention Of Misuse) Act, 1988</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 41 OF 1988</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[1st September, 1988.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to prevent the misuse of religious institutions for political and other purposes.</p>
      </longTitle>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty-ninth Year of the Republic of India as follows:—</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Religious Institutions (Prevention of Misuse) Act, 1988.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 26th day of May, 1988.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“ammunition” shall have the same meaning as in clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Arms Act, 1959 (54 of 1959);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“arms” shall have the same meaning as in clause (c) of sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Arms Act, 1959 (54 of 1959);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“manager”, in relation to a religious institution, means every person, including, any religious functionary (by whatever name called), who, for the time being, either alone or in association with other persons, administers, manages or otherwise controls the affairs of that institution, its functions or properties;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>“political activity” includes any activity promoting or propagating the aims or objects of a political party or any cause, issue or question of a political nature by organising meetings, demonstrations, processions, collection or disbursement of funds, or by the issue of directions or decrees, or by any other means, and includes also such activity by or on behalf of a person seeking election as a candidate for any election to Parliament, any State Legislature or any local authority;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>“political party” means an association or body of persons—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>which is, or is deemed to be, registered, with the Election Commission of India as a political party under the Election Symbols (Reservation and Allotment) Order, 1968, as in force for the time being; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>which has set up candidates for election to any legislature, but is not registered, or deemed to be registered, as a political party, under the Election Symbols (Reservation and Allotment) Order, 1968; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>organised to carry on any political activity or to acquire or exercise political power through election or otherwise;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>“religious institution” means an institution for the promotion of any religion or persuasion, and includes any place or premises used as a place of public religious worship, by whatever name or designation known.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition of use of religious institutions for certain purposes.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>No religious institution or manager thereof shall use or allow the use of any premises belonging to, or under the control of, the institution—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for the promotion or propagation of any political activity; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>for the harbouring of any person accused or convicted of an offence under any law for the time being in force; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>for the storing of any arms or ammunition; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>for keeping any goods or articles in contravention of any law for the time being in force; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>for erecting or putting up of any construction or fortification, including basements, bunkers, towers or walls without a valid licence or permission under any law for the time being in force; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>for the carrying on of any unlawful or subversive act prohibited under any law for the time being in force or in contravention of any order made by any court; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>for the doing of any act which promotes or attempts to promote disharmony of feelings of enmity, hatred or ill-will between different religious, racial, language or regional groups or castes or communities; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>for the carrying on of any activity prejudicial to the sovereignty, unity and integrity of India; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>for the doing of any act in contravention of the provisions of the Prevention of Insults to National Honour Act, 1971 (69 of 1971).</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Restrictions on carrying arms and ammunition into a religious institution.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No religious institution or manager thereof shall allow the entry of any arms or ammunition or of any person carrying any arms or ammunition into the religious institution:</p>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that nothing in this section shall apply to—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the wearing and carrying of a kirpan by any person professing the Sikh religion; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any arms which are used as part of any religious ceremony or ritual of the institution as established by custom or usage.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition of use of funds of religious institutions for certain activities.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No religious institution or manager thereof shall use or allow the use of any funds or other properties belonging to, or under the control of, the institution for the benefit of any political party or for the purpose of any political activity or for the commission of any act which is punishable as an offence under any law.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition of religious fora for propagating political ideas.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No religious institution or manager thereof shall allow any ceremony, festival, congregation, procession or assembly organised or held under its auspices to be used for any political activity.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Penalties.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where any religious institution or manager thereof contravenes the provisions of section 3, section 4, section 5 or section 6, the manager and every person connected with such contravention shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years and with fine which may extend to ten thousand rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Disqualification of persons convicted or charge-sheeted under this Act.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any manager or other employee of a religious institution shall, upon conviction for an offence under this Act, stand removed from his office or post and shall, notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any other law, be disqualified for appointment in any religious institution as manager or in any other capacity for a period of six years from the date of his conviction.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any manager or other employee of a religious institution is accused of an offence under this Act and a charge-sheet for the prosecution of such person is filed in any court and the court is of the opinion, after considering the charge-sheet and after hearing the prosecution and the accused, that a prima facie case exists, it shall pass an order or direction restraining the person from exercising the powers or discharging the duties of his office or post pending trial.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any manager or other employee has been removed under sub-section (1), or restrained under sub-section (2), the vacancy arising out of such removal or restraint may be filled in the manner provided in the law applicable to the said religious institution.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Certain persons bound to give information to police.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every manager or other employee of a religious institution shall be bound to give information to the officer incharge of the police station within whose local jurisdiction the religious institution is situate of any contravention or any impending contravention of the provisions of this Act and any failure to do so shall be punishable under section 176 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Repeal and saving.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Religious Institutions (Prevention of Misuse) Ordinance, 1988 (Ord. 3 of 1988) is hereby repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
