<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2011/15/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2011/15"/>
          <FRBRalias value="﻿The Orissa (Alteration Of Name) Act, 2011"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2011/15/eng@2011-09-23/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2011/15/eng@2011-09-23"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2011-09-23" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2011/15/eng@2011-09-23/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2011/15/eng@2011-09-23"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-30" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>﻿The Orissa (Alteration Of Name) Act, 2011</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 15 OF 2011</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[23rd September, 2011.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to alter the name of the State of Orissa.</p>
      </longTitle>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Sixty-second Year of the Republic of India as follows:—</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Orissa (Alteration of Name) Act, 2011.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date1 as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“appointed day” means the date appointed under sub-section (2) of section 1 for the coming into force of this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“appropriate Government” means, as respects a law relating to a matter enumerated in List I in the Seventh Schedule to the Constitution, the Central Government, and as respects any other law, the State Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“law” includes any enactment, Ordinance, regulation, order, bye-law, rule, scheme, notification or other instrument having the force of law in the whole or any part of the State of Orissa.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Alteration of name of State of Orissa.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>As from the appointed day, the State of Orissa shall be known as the State of Odisha.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of article 164.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In article 164 of the Constitution, in clause (1), in the proviso, for the word “Orissa”, the word “Odisha” shall be substituted.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of article 273.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In article 273, in clause (1), for the word “Orissa”, the word “Odisha” shall be substituted.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of First Schedule to the Constitution.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In the First Schedule to the Constitution, under the heading “I. THE STATES”, in entry 10, under the column “Name”, for the word “Orissa”, the word “Odisha” shall be substituted.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of Fourth Schedule to the Constitution.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In the Fourth Schedule to the Constitution, under the heading “TABLE”, in entry 14, in the second column, for the word “Orissa”, the word “Odisha” shall be substituted.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Power to adapt laws.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of giving effect to the alteration of the name of the State of Orissa by section 3, the appropriate Government may, before the expiration of one year from the appointed day, by order, make such adaptations and modifications of any law made before the appointed day, whether by way of repeal or amendment, as may be necessary or expedient, and thereupon every such law shall have effect subject to the adaptations and modifications so made.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in sub-section (1) shall be deemed to prevent a competent Legislature or other competent authority from repealing or amending any law adapted or modified by the appropriate Government under the said sub-section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Power to construe laws.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding that no provision or insufficient provision has been made under section 8 for the adaptation of a law made before the appointed day, any court, tribunal or authority, required or empowered to enforce such law, may construe the law in such manner, without affecting the substance, as may be necessary or proper in regard to the matter before the court, tribunal or authority.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Legal proceedings.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where immediately before the appointed day any legal proceedings are pending to which the State of Orissa is a party, the State of Odisha shall be deemed to have been substituted for the State of Orissa in those proceedings.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
