<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1976/61/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1976/61"/>
          <FRBRalias value="Andhra Pradesh Mutta, Jattu, Hamal And Other Manual Workers (Regulation Of Employment And Welfare) Act, 1976"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1976/61/eng@2017-05-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1976/61/eng@2017-05-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-05-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1976/61/eng@2017-05-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1976/61/eng@2017-05-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-05-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>Andhra Pradesh Mutta, Jattu, Hamal And Other Manual Workers (Regulation Of Employment And Welfare) Act, 1976</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No.61 of 1976</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for regulating the employment of unprotected manual workers such as mutta, jattu and hamal engaged in market areas, factories and the like in the State of Andhra Pradesh in connection with loading, packing, weighing, measuring, stitching, etc., for ensuring an adequate supply and full and proper utilisation of, such workers to prevent avoidable unemployment, for securing to such workers better terms and conditions of employment and for matters connected therewith.</p>
        <p>Be it enacted by the Legislature of the State of Andhra Pradesh in the Twenty Seventh year of the Republic of India as follows :-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement:-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Andhra Pradesh Mutta, Jattu, Hamal and other Manual Workers (Regulation of Employment and Welfare) Act, 1976.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Andhra Pradesh.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It applies to employments specified in the schedule thereto.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the State Government may, by notification appoint, and different dates may be appointed for different areas, for different employments, and for different provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions:-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires :-</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>`Advisory Committee' means an Advisory Committee constituted under Section 14;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>`Board' means a Board established under Section 6;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>`contractor' in relation to an unprotected worker, means a person, who undertakes to execute any work for an establishment by engaging such workers on hire or otherwise or who supplies such workers either in groups, gangs (mutta or jattu) or as individuals; and includes a sub-contractor, an agent, a mugaddam or a maistry;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>`employer' in relation to any unprotected worker engaged by or through contractor, means the principal employer and in relation to any other unprotected worker, the person who has ultimate control over the affairs of the establishment and includes any other person to whom the affairs of such establishment are entrusted, whether such person is called an agent, manager or is called by any other name prevailing in the scheduled employment;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>`establishment' means any place or premises including the precincts thereof, in which or any part of which any scheduled employment is being or is ordinarily carried on;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>`Government' means the State Government;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>`Inspector' means an Inspector appointed under Section 15;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>`member of the family' in relation to an employer, means the spouse, son, daughter, father, mother, brother or sister of such employer who lives with him and is wholly dependent on him;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>`notification' means a notification published in the A.P. Gazette and the word notified shall be construed accordingly;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.10">
          <num>(10)</num>
          <content>
            <p>`prescribed' means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>`principal employer' means an employer who engages unprotected workers by or through a contractor in any scheduled employment;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.12">
          <num>(12)</num>
          <content>
            <p>`scheduled employment' means any employment specified in the Schedule hereto or any process or branch of work forming part of such employment;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.13">
          <num>(13)</num>
          <content>
            <p>`Scheme' means a scheme made under this Act;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.14">
          <num>(14)</num>
          <content>
            <p>`unprotected worker' means a manual worker who is engaged or to be engaged in any scheduled employment;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.15">
          <num>(15)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.15.list1">
              <listIntroduction>`wages' means all remuneration expressed in terms of money or capable of being so expressed which would if the terms of contract or employment, express or implied, were fulfilled, be payable to an unprotected worker in respect of work done in any scheduled employments but does not include----</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.15.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the value of any house accommodation, supply of light, water, medical attendance or any other amenity or any service excluded from the computation of wages by general or special order of the Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.15.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>any contribution paid by the employer to any pension fund or provident fund or under any scheme of social insurance and the interest which may have accrued thereon;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.15.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>any travelling allowance or the value of any travelling concession;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.15.list1.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>any sum paid to the worker to defray special expenses entitled on him by the nature of his employment; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.15.list1.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>any gratuity payable on discharge.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.16">
          <num>(16)</num>
          <content>
            <p>`worker' means a person who is engaged or to be engaged directly or through any agency, whether for wages or not, to do manual work in any schedule employment, and includes any person not employed by any employer or a contractor but working with the permission of, or under agreement with, the employer or contractor, but does not include any member of the family of an employer.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Schemes for ensuring regular employment of unprotected workers :-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of ensuring an adequate supply and full and proper utilisation of unprotected workers in scheduled employments, and generally for making better provisions for the terms and conditions of employment of such workers whether registered or not, the Government may by means of a scheme provide for the registration of employers and unprotected workers in all or any of the scheduled employments and provide for the terms and conditions of work of such unprotected workers, whether registered or not, to make provision for their general welfare.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, a scheme may provide for--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the application of the scheme to such classes of employers and unprotected workers, as may be specified therein;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>defining the obligations of employers and unprotected workers subject to the fulfilment of which the scheme may apply to them;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>regulating the recruitment and entry into the scheme of unprotected workers, and the registration of employers and unprotected workers including the maintenance of registers, removal either temporarily or permanently, of names from the registers and provision for appeal against such removal to the prescribed authority, and the imposition of fees for registration;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>regulating the employment of unprotected workers whether registered or not, and the terms and conditions of such employment including rates of wages; hours of work, maternity benefit, over time payment, leave with wages, provision for gratuity and conditions as to weekly and other holidays and pay in respect thereof;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>securing minimum wage subject to the conditions of the scheme to registered workers in respect of periods during which employment or full employment is not made available to them although they are available for work;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>prohibiting, restricting or otherwise controlling the employment of unprotected workers either by employers or otherwise, to whom the scheme does not apply;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the welfare of unprotected workers covered by the scheme in so far as satisfactory provision therefor does not exist, apart from the scheme;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>health and safety measures in places where the unprotected workers are engaged, in so far as satisfactory provision therefor is required but does not exist, apart from the scheme;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the constitution of any funds, including provident fund for the benefit of unprotected workers, the vesting of such funds, the payment and contributions to be made to such funds and all matters relating thereto;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>the manner in which, and the persons by whom, the cost of operating the scheme is to be defrayed, including any contributions to be paid by employers and unprotected workers, and the rate of such contribution.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>the appointment of persons or authorities who are to be responsible for the administration of the scheme or funds aforesaid;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>such incidental and supplemental matters, as may be necessary or expedient for giving effect to the purposes of a scheme.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The scheme may further provide that a contravention of any provision thereof shall be punished with imprisonment for such term as may be specified, but in no case exceeding three months in respect of a first contravention or six months in respect of any subsequent contravention with fine which may extend to such amount as may be specified, but in no case exceeding five hundred rupees in respect of the first contravention, or one thousand rupees in respect of any subsequent contravention or with both imprisonment and fine.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Making variation and revocation of scheme:-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Government may, by notification after consultation with the Advisory Committee, and subject to the conditions of previous publication, make one or more schemes for any scheduled employment or group of scheduled employments in one or more areas specified in the notification, and in like manner add to, amend, vary or substitute another scheme made by them:</p>
            <p>Provided that no such notification shall come into force unless a period of one month has expired from the date on which it is notified;</p>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided further that,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>if the Government considers it necessary, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>if a demand or request is made by a majority of the employers or workers in any other scheduled employment, the Government may, after consulting the employers and workers in such other scheduled employment by notification, apply the provisions of the scheme or part thereof to any other schedule employment, with such modifications, if any, as may be specified, in the notification that the provisions of any scheme so made for any scheduled employment or any part thereof should be applied to such other scheduled employments.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Disputes regarding application of scheme:-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any question arises whether any scheme applies to employers or any class of unprotected workers, the matter shall be referred to the Government and the decision of the Government on the question, which shall be taken after consulting the Advisory Committee, shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Establishment of Board:-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification, establish a Board to be known by such name as may be specified in the notification for any scheduled employment in any area; and they may establish one Board for two or more scheduled employments or areas.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every such Board shall be a body corporate with the name aforesaid, having perpetual succession and common seal, with power to acquire, hold and dispose of property, and to contract and may by that name, sue or be sued.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall consist of members nominated by the Government, representing the employers, the unprotected workers and the Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The members representing employers, and unprotected workers, shall be equal in number, and the members representing the Government shall not exceed one-third of the total number of members presenting employers and unprotected workers.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chairman of the Board shall be nominated by the Government, from among the members representing the Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>After nomination of all the members of the Board including the Chairman the Government shall, by notification, publish the names of all the members of the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The term of the office of members of the Board shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The meeting of the Board and procedure to be followed for the purpose and all matters supplementary or ancillary thereto, shall subject to the approval of the Government, be regulated by the Board itself.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Powers and duties of Boards:-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall be responsible for administering a scheme, and shall perform such functions as may be conferred on it by the scheme.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board may take such measures as it may deem fit for administering the scheme.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall submit to Government, as soon as may be, after the 1st day of April, every year, and not latter than the 31st day of October, an annual report on the working of the scheme during the preceding year ending on the 31st day of March of that year. Every report so received shall be laid as soon as may be after it is received before each House of the State Legislature if it is in session, or in the session immediately following the date of receipt of the report.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the performance of its functions, the Board shall be bound by such directions as the Government may, for reasons to be recorded in writing give to it from time to time.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Accounts and audit:-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall maintain proper accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual statement of accounts, including a balance sheet in such forms as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The accounts of the Board shall be audited annually by such qualified person as the Government may appoint in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The auditor shall at all reasonable time have access to the books of accounts and other documents of the Board, and may, for the purposes of the audit, call for such explanation and information as he may require, or examine any member or officer of the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The accounts of the Board certified by the auditor, together with the audited report thereon shall be forwarded annually to the Government before such date as the Government may specify in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall comply with such directions as the Government may, after perusal of the report of the auditor, think fit to issue.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The cost of audit, as determined by the Government, shall be paid out of the funds of the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Disqualifications and removal of members of Board:-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A person shall be disqualified for being chosen as or for continuing as a member of the Board, if he--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>is a salaried officer of the Board; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>is or at any time has been adjudged insolvent; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>is found to be a lunatic or becomes of unsound mind; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>is or has been convicted of any offence involving moral turpitude.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Government may remove from office any member who--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>is or has become subject to any of the disqualifications mentioned in sub-section (1); or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>is absent without leave of the Board for more than three consecutive meetings of the Board.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Resignation of office by member:-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any member of the Board may at any time, resign his office by writing under his hand addressed to the Government, and his office shall on acceptance of resignation, become vacant.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Vacancy to be filled as early as possible:-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In the event of any vacancy occurring on account of death, resignation, disqualification or removal or otherwise the Board shall forthwith communicate the occurrence to the Government and the vacancy shall be filled not later than ninety days from the date of the occurrence of the vacancy and the person nominated to fill in the vacancy, shall hold office for the residue of term of his predecessor;</p>
            <p>Provided that, during any such vacancy, the continuing members may act as if no vacancy has occurred.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Validity of proceedings of Board :-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No act or proceeding of the Board shall be questioned or invalidated merely by reason of any vacancy in its membership or by reason of any defect in the constitution thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Recovery of monies due to Board :-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On an application made by the Board for the recovery of arrears of any sum payable to it under this Act or any schemes and on its furnishing a statement of accounts in respect to such arrears the Collector may after making such inquiries as he deems fit, grant a certificate for the recovery of the amount stated therein to be due as arrears.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A certificate by the Collector shall be final and conclusive as to the arrears stated to be due therein and shall then be recoverable as arrears of land revenue.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Advisory Committee :-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may constitute an Advisory Committee to advise upon such matters, arising out of the administration of this Act or any scheme made under this Act or relating to the application of the provisions of this Act to any employer or any particular class of unprotected workers, or co-ordination of the work of various Boards, as the Advisory Committee may itself consider to be necessary or as the Government may refer to it for advice.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The members of the Advisory Committee shall be appointed by the Government and shall be of such number and chosen in such manner as may be prescribed:</p>
            <p>Provided that, the Advisory Committee shall include an equal number of members representing employers, workers and the Legislature of the State and members representing the Government not exceeding one-fourth of its total number of members.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chairman of the Advisory Committee shall be nominated by the Government from among the members representing the Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government shall, by notification, publish the names of all the members of the Advisory Committee.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The meetings of the Advisory Committee and procedure to be followed thereat shall be regulated according to rules under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The term of office of members of the Advisory Committee shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Inspectors and their powers :-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board may appoint such persons as it thinks fit to be Inspectors possessing the prescribed qualifications for the purposes of this Act or of any scheme and may define the limits of their jurisdiction.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-15.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Subject to any rules made by the Government in this behalf, an Inspector may--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>enter and search at all reasonable hours, with such assistance as he thinks fit, any premises or place where unprotected workers are employed or work is given out to unprotected workers in any scheduled employment, for the purpose of examining any register, record of wages or notices required to be kept or exhibited under any scheme and require the production thereof for inspection;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>examine any person whom he finds in any such premises or place and whom he had reason to believe, is an unprotected worker employed therein or an unprotected worker to whom work is given out therein;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>require any person giving any work to an unprotected worker or to a group of unprotected workers to give any information, which is in his power to give in respect of the names and addresses of the persons to whom the work is given, and in respect of payments made or to be made for the said work;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>seize or take copies of such registers, records of wages or notices or portions thereof, as he may consider relevant, in respect of an offence under this Act or scheme, which he has reason to believe, has been committed by an employer; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>exercise such other powers as may be prescribed;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that no person shall be required under the provisions of this section to answer any question or make any statement tending to incriminate himself;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Inspector appointed under this section shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of Section 21 of the Indian Penal Code.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition of employment of children :-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No child shall be required or allowed to work in any scheduled employment.</p>
            <p>Explanation :- "Child" means a person who has not completed fourteen years of age.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Cognizance of offences :-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No court shall take cognizance of any offence made punishable by a scheme or of any abetment thereof, except on a complaint, in writing, made by an Inspector or by a person specially authorised in this behalf by the Board or Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 an offence made punishable by a scheme or an abetment thereof shall be triable only by a Magistrate of the first class.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Application of Workmen's Compensation Act to unprotected workers :-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of the Workmen's Compensation Act, 1923, and the rules made from time to time thereunder, shall mutatis mutandis apply to unprotected workers employed in any scheduled employment to which this Act applies; and for that purpose they shall be deemed to be workmen within the meaning of that Act; and in relation to such workmen, employer shall mean where a Board makes payment of wages to any such workmen, the Board, and in any other case, the employer as defined in this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Application of Payment of Wages Act to workers :-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-19.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything in the Payment of Wages Act 1936 hereinafter referred to in this section as "the said Act", the Government may, by notification direct that all or any of the provisions of the said Act or the rules made thereunder shall apply to unprotected workers employed in any scheduled employment to which this Act applies with the modification that in relation to unprotected workers, employer shall mean where a Board makes payment of wages to any such worker, the Board, and in any other case, the employer as defined in this Act and on such application of the provisions of the said Act an Inspector appointed under this Act shall be deemed to be the Inspector for the purpose of the enforcement of such provisions of the said Act within the local limits of this jurisdiction.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, only if the Advisory Committee so advises, by a like notification, cancel or vary any notification issued under sub-section (1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Application of Maternity Benefit Act to unprotected women workers :-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything in the Maternity Benefit Act, 1961 (hereinafter referred to in this section as "the said Act") the Government may by notification direct that all or any of the provisions of the said Act or the rules made thereunder shall apply to unprotected women workers employed in any scheduled employment to which this Act applies; and for that purpose they shall be deemed to be women within the meaning of the said Act; and in relation to such women, employer shall mean where a Board makes payment of wages to such women the Board and in any other case, the employer as defined in this Act and on such application of the provisions of the said Act, an Inspector appointed under this Act shall be deemed to be the Inspector for the purpose of enforcement of such provisions of the said Act, within the local limits of this jurisdiction.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Rights and privileges under other laws not affected in certain cases :-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in this Act shall affect any rights or privileges, which any unprotected worker employed in any scheduled employment is entitled on the date on which this Act comes into force, under any other law, contract, custom or usage applicable to such worker, if such rights or privileges are more favourable to him than those to which he would be entitled under this Act and a scheme made thereunder;</p>
            <p>Provided that such worker shall not be entitled to receive any corresponding benefit under the provisions of this Act and the scheme.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Exemption :-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Government may after consulting the Advisory Committee, by notification, and subject to such conditions and for such period as may be specified in the notifications, exempt from the operation of all or any of the provisions of this Act or any scheme made thereunder, all or any class or classes of unprotected workers employed in any scheduled employment or any establishment or part of any scheduled employment, if in the opinion of the Government all such unprotected workers of such class or classes of workers, are in the enjoyment of benefits which are on the whole not less favourable to such unprotected workers than the benefits provided by or under this Act or any scheme made thereunder:</p>
            <p>Provided that before any such notification is issued, the Government shall publish in the Andhra Pradesh Gazette, a notice of its intention to issue such notification and invite objections and suggestions in respect thereto and no such notification shall be issued until the objections and suggestions have been considered and a period of one month expired from the date of first publication of the notice:</p>
            <p>Provided further that the Government may, by notification at any time, for reasons to be specified rescind the aforesaid notification.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Enquiry into working of Board :-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-23.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, at any time, appoint any person to investigate or enquire into the working of any Board or scheme and submit a report to the Government in that behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall give to the person so appointed all facilities for the proper conduct of the investigation, or enquiry, and furnish to him such documents, accounts or information in possession of the Board as he may require.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person so appointed to investigate or enquire into the working of any Board or scheme may exercise all the powers of an Inspector appointed under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Supersession of the Board :-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-24.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-24.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If the Government, on consideration of the report referred to in sub-section (1) of Section 23 or otherwise are of the opinion--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-24.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>that the Board is unable to perform its functions; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>that the Board has persistently made default in the discharge of its functions or has exceeded or abused its powers, the Government, may by notification supersede the Board and constitute it in the prescribed manner, within a period of twelve months from the date of supersession. The period of supersession may be extended for sufficient reasons by a like notification or by not more than six months.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that before issuing a notification under this sub-section on any of the grounds mentioned in clause (b), the Government shall give a reasonable opportunity to the Board to show cause why it should not be superseded, and shall consider the explanations and objections, if any, of the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>After the supersession of the Board or until it is reconstituted the functions of the Board under this Act shall be performed by the Government, or any such officer or officers as the Government may appoint for this purpose.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-24.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>When the Board is superseded the following consequences shall ensue, that is to say--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-24.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>all the members of the Board shall, as from the date of publication of the notification under sub-section (1), vacate their office;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>all the functions which may be performed by the Board shall during the period of supersession, be performed by such persons as may be specified in the notification;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.3.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>all funds and other property vesting in the Board shall, during the period of supersession, vest in the Government and on the constitution of the Board, such funds and property shall revest in the Board.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Contracting out :-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any contract or agreement, whether made before or after the commencement of this Act whereby an unprotected worker relinquishes any right conferred by, or any privilege or concession accruing to him under this Act or any scheme, shall be void and of no effect in so far as it purports to deprive him of such right or privilege or concession.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of Schedule :-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification after giving not less than three months notice of its intention so to do, add to the Schedule any employment in respect of which they are of opinion that the provisions of this Act should apply; and the provisions of this Act shall thereupon apply to such employment.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>General penalty for offences :-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Save as otherwise expressly provided in this Act any person who contravenes any of the provisions of this Act or any rule made thereunder shall, on conviction, be punished with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, and in case of continued contravention thereof, with an additional fine which may extend to one hundred rupees per day, for every day during which such contravention continues.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28">
        <num>28.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules :-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-28.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification, and subject to the conditions of previous publication, make rules for carrying out all or any of the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-28.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every scheme under this Act and rule made under this section shall immediately after it is made be laid before each House of the State Legislature if it is in session, and if it is not in session, in the session immediately following for a total period of fourteen days which may be comprised in one session or in two successive sessions, and if, before the expiration of the session in which it is so laid or the session immediately following, both Houses agree in making any modification in the scheme or rule or in the annulment of the rule or scheme, or any provision thereof the rule or scheme shall, from the date on which the modification or annulment is notified, have effect only in such modified form or stand annulled as the case may be; so however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done or omitted to be done under that scheme, provisions, or rule, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29">
        <num>29.</num>
        <heading>Savings :-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-29.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Nothing contained in this Act, shall apply to contract labour governed by the Indian Railways Act, 1890, the Factories Act, 1948 or the Contract Labour (Regulation and Abolition) Act, 1970.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-30">
        <num>30.</num>
        <heading>Repeal of Ordinance 15 of 1976 :-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-30.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Andhra Pradesh Mutta, Jattu, Hamal and other Manual workers (Regulation of Employment and Welfare) Ordinance, 1976, is hereby repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-theschedule">
      <doc name="theschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1976/61/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1976/61"/>
              <FRBRalias value="THE SCHEDULE"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1976/61/eng@2017-05-25/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1976/61/eng@2017-05-25"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1976/61/eng@2017-05-25/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1976/61/eng@2017-05-25"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-05-25" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="theschedule">
            <paragraph id="theschedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>[See Section 2(12)]</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <section id="section-1">
              <num>1.</num>
              <heading>Employment in connection with loading, unloading, packing carrying, weighing, measuring or such other work, including work preparatory or incidental to such operations--</heading>
              <subsection id="section-1.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in iron and steel markets or shops;</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-1.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in cloth and cotton markets or shops;</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-1.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>In docks, not being employment of dock-worker within the meaning of the Dock-Workers (Regulation of Employment) Act, 1948 Central Act 9 of 1948);</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-1.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in grocery markets or shops;</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-1.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in bus depots in so far as it relates to loading of goods into public transport vehicle or unloading of goods therefrom and any other operation incidental and connected thereto;</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-1.6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in vegetable and fruit markets (including onions and potatoes markets);</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-1.7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>in markets or subsidiary markets established under the Andhra Pradesh (Agricultural Produce and Live-stock) Markets Act, 1966 (Andhra Pradesh Act 16 of 1966).</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-2">
              <num>2.</num>
              <heading>Employment in timber markets.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-3">
              <num>3.</num>
              <heading>Employment in salt pans.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-4">
              <num>4.</num>
              <heading>Employment in fishing industry.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-5">
              <num>5.</num>
              <heading>Employment in connection with the loading, unloading, and carrying of food-grains into godowns and such other work incidental and connected thereto.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-6">
              <num>6.</num>
              <heading>Employment in markets, and other establishments, in connection with loading, unloading, stocking, carrying, weighing, measuring or such other work, including work preparatory or incidental to such operations carried on by workers not covered by any other entries in this Schedule.</heading>
            </section>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
