<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/2015/10/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/2015/10"/>
          <FRBRalias value="Andhra Pradesh (Issuance Of Integrated Registration And Furnishing Of Combined Returns Under Various Labour Laws By Certain Establishments) Act, 2015"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/2015/10/eng@2017-05-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/2015/10/eng@2017-05-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-05-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/2015/10/eng@2017-05-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/2015/10/eng@2017-05-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-05-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>Andhra Pradesh (Issuance Of Integrated Registration And Furnishing Of Combined Returns Under Various Labour Laws By Certain Establishments) Act, 2015</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT No. 10 OF 2015</docNumber>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An act to provide for issuance of integrated and furnishing of combined returns under certain labour laws by certain establishments in the state of Andhra Pradesh.</p>
        <p>Be it enacted by the Legislature of the State of Andhra Pradesh in the Sixty-sixth Year of the Republic of India, as follows.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Andhra Pradesh (Issuance of Integrated Registration and Furnishing of Combined Returns under various Labour Laws by certain Establishments) Act, 2015;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Andhra Pradesh;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Government may, by notification in the Andhra Pradesh Gazette, appoint and different dates may be appointed for different provisions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“employer” in relation to the concerned Scheduled Act, means the person who is required to obtain Registration and furnish Returns under that Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"Commissioner of Labour" means the Head of the Office of the Commissioner of Labour;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“establishment" has the meaning assigned to it in the concerned Scheduled Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>"Form" means the forms specified in the Second Schedule;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>"Government" means the State Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>“notification" means a notification published in the Andhra Pradesh Gazette and the word - 'notified' shall be construed accordingly;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>"Scheduled Act" means an Act specified in the First Schedule;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>"State" means the State Government of Andhra Pradesh;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>"Rules" means the rules framed under the Scheduled Acts.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Effect of laws specified in schedule-I</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>On and from the commencement of this Act, the Act at SI, No.1 of the First Schedule and the Andhra Pradesh Rules made under the Central Acts specified in the First Schedule shall have effect subject to the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Application for Integrated registration under the scheduled Acts and filing of the Combined Return</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On and from the commencement of this Act, an employer, in relation to an establishment to which the Scheduled Acts apply, shall apply for integrated registration online under the First Schedule Acts in Form-A of the Second Schedule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Registration Certificate in Form-C shall be issued instantaneously subject to verification after issuance.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Manual issuance of Registration Certificate shall be prohibited from the date to be notified by the Commissioner of Labour.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The validity of the Registration shall be upto 31st March of the third Year from the date of issue. The Registration, wherever requires renewal under the Scheduled Acts, shall be renewed for a further period of three years within 31 days before the expiry of the Registration.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Fee payable for issuance of the Integrated Registration shall be as notified by the Commissioner of Labour.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An employer in relation to an establishment to which the Scheduled Acts apply, shall submit Combined Return on Form-B of the '°Second Schedule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The relevant provisions of the State Act and the Andhra Pradesh Rules made under the respective Central Acts in the First Schedule shall be deemed to have been amended to that extent.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Savings</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The commencement of this Act shall not affect,</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the previous operation of any provision of any Scheduled Act or the validity, invalidity, effect or consequence of anything done or suffered under that provision, before the relevant period;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>any right, privilege, obligation or liability already acquired, accrued or incurred under any Scheduled Act, before the relevant period;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>any penalty forefeiture or punishment incurred or inflicted in respect of any offence committed under any Scheduled Act, before the relevant period;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>any investigation, legal proceeding or remedy in respect of any such right, privilege, obligation, liability, penalty, forfeiture or punishment aforesaid and any such investigation, legal proceeding or remedy in respect of any such right, privilege, obligation, liability, penalty, forfeiture or punishment shall be instituted, continued or disposed of as case may be, in accordance with that Scheduled Act.</p>
            <p>Explanation: For the purpose of this section, the expression "relevant period" means the period in which an establishment is or was covered under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Power to amend Forms</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, if it is of opinion that it is expedient so to do, by notification in the official Gazette, amend any Form and thereupon such Form shall, subject to the provisions of this Act shall be deemed to have been amended accordingly.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Power to remove difficulties</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Government may, by notification remove difficulties by orders not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, but which appear to them to be necessary or expedient to remove such difficulty.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Powers to give directions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of giving effect to the provisions of this Act, it shall be competent for the Government to issue such directions as they deem fit to the officers, and authorities subordinate to them and also to any local authority and it shall be the duty of such officers, authorities and local authorities to comply with such directions.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Powers to amend Schedules</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification, alert, add to or cancel any of the Schedules;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a notification has been issued under sub-section (1), there shall, unless the notification is in the meantime rescinded, be introduced in the Legislature of the State, as soon as may be but in any case during the next session of the Legislature of the State following the of the issue of the notification, a Bill on behalf of the Government, to give effect to the alteration, addition or cancellation, as the case may be, of the Schedule specified in the notification and the notification shall cease to have effect when such bill become law, whether with or without modifications, but without modifications, but without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done thereunder;</p>
            <p>Provided that if the notification under sub-section (1) is issued when Legislative of the State is in session, such a Bill shall be introduced in the Legislature of the State during that session;</p>
            <p>Provided further that where for any reason a Bill as aforesaid does not become law within six months from the date of its introduction in the Legislature of the State, the notification shall cease to have effect on the expiration of the said period of six months.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-firstschedule">
      <doc name="firstschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/2015/10/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/2015/10"/>
              <FRBRalias value="FIRST SCHEDULE"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/2015/10/eng@2017-05-25/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/2015/10/eng@2017-05-25"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/2015/10/eng@2017-05-25/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/2015/10/eng@2017-05-25"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-05-25" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="firstschedule">
            <paragraph id="firstschedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>[See Sec. 2 (c) and (i)]</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <subsection id="firstschedule.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Andhra Pradesh Shops and Establishments Act, 1988 (Act No. 20 of 1988) and the Andhra Pradesh Shops and establishments Rules., 1990 framed thereunder;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="firstschedule.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Motor Transport Workers Act 1961 (Central Act 27 of 1961) and the Andhra Pradesh Motor Transport Workers Rules, 1963 framed thereunder;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="firstschedule.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Contract Labour (Regulation and Abolition) Act, 1970 (Central Act No.37 of 1970) and the Andhra Pradesh Contract Labour (Regulation and Abolition) Rules, 1971 framed thereunder;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="firstschedule.4">
              <num>(4)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Inter State Migrant Workmen (Regulation of Employment and Conditions of Service) Act, 1979 (Central Act No 30 of 1979) and the Andhra Pradesh Inter State Migrant Workmen (Regulation of Employment and Conditions of Service) Rules, 1982 framed thereunder;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="firstschedule.5">
              <num>(5)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Building and Other Construction Workers (Regulation of Employment and Conditions of Service) Act, 1996 (Central Act No.27 of 1996) and the Andhra Pradesh Building and Other Construction Workers (Regulation of Employment and Other Conditions of Service) Rules, 1999 framed thereunder;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="firstschedule.6">
              <num>(6)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Payment of Gratuity Act, 1972 (Central Act No. 39 of 1972) and the Andhra Pradesh Compulsory Gratuity Insurance Rules, 2011 framed thereunder;</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
