<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-asm/act/1947/23/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-asm/act/1947/23"/>
          <FRBRalias value="Assam Opium Prohibition Act, 1947"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-asm/act/1947/23/eng@2016-12-14/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-asm/act/1947/23/eng@2016-12-14"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-12-14" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-asm/act/1947/23/eng@2016-12-14/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-asm/act/1947/23/eng@2016-12-14"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-12-14" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>Assam Opium Prohibition Act, 1947</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>(Assam Act XXIII of 1947)</p>
        <p>An Act to prohibit consumption (except for medical purposes) and smuggling of opium in the Province of Assam</p>
        <p>Preamble.</p>
        <p>Whereas it is expedient to prohibit consumption (except for medicinal purposes) and smuggling of opium in the Province of Assam; and whereas it is necessary to enlist non-official support to exercise an effective control over the smuggling of opium to achieve the aforesaid object;</p>
        <p>It is hereby enacted as follows:</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <heading>Preliminary</heading>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the Assam Opium (Prohibition) Act, 1947.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It extents to the whole of Assam.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on such date as the State Government may, by notification in the official Gazatte, appoint.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>"buy" with all its grammatical variations, means any receipt for price paid in cash or kind, and also any receipt by gift, loan or otherwise;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>"State Anti-Drug and Prohibition Council" means the body of non¬official residents of the State as may be constituted by he State Government by the notification in the official Gazatte;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>"excise opium" means opium issued from a Government Treasury in the State;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>"exports" means to take out of the State otherwise than across customs frontiers;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>"import" means to bring into the State otherwise than across customs frontiers;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>"opium" means and includes opium as defined in S. 3 of the Opium Act, 1878 (Act I of 1878), and in Cl. (a) of S. 2 of the Assam Opium Smoking Act, 1927 (Assam Act III of 1927), and also any other substance or preparation containing morphine in any proportion whatsoever;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>"prescribed" means prescribed by rules framed under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>"Prohibition Officer" means a person appointed under S. 31;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>"State" means that State of Assam;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>a) "section" means a section of this Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>"sell" with all its grammatical variations, means any transfer, including a gift as a loan or otherwise;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-2.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>"smuggler" means a person who brings any opium into the State otherwise than across customs frontiers in contravention of the provisions of this Act, or any other law; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.m">
                  <num>(m)</num>
                  <p>"transport" means to take from one place to another within the State.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <heading>Prohibition</heading>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Prohibition.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>No person shall -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>import, export, transport, or possess opium;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>sell or buy opium;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>consume opium;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>use or keep any material, utensil, implement or apparatus whatsoever for -</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>the manufacturer of nay opium smoking preparation or any drink containing opium,</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>smoking opium,</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>weighing opium, or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0.iv">
                      <num>(iv)</num>
                      <p>preserving opium.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <heading>Exemptions</heading>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Exemptions.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of this Act shall not apply to any shop or place licensed for the sale of opium for medicinal purposes, or to any person who buy opium from any place or shop as aforesaid under a prescription from a registered medical practitioner, or to any hospital or dispensary, or to the import, export, transport, possession, sale or purchase of excise opium.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of this Act shall not apply to any registered medical practitioner who acquires, possesses, prescribes or dispenses opium in any form in due fulfillment of his medical duties.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <heading>Offences and penalties</heading>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Punishment for contravention.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Whoever, in contravention of the provisions of this Act or rules made thereunder-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>imports, exports, transports or possesses opium, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>sells or buys opium, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>consumes opium, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>uses or keeps any material, utensil, implement, or apparatus whatsoever for -</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>the manufacturer of any opium smoking preparations or any drink containing opium,</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>smoking opium shall be punished with imprisonment of either description for a term which may extend to six years, and with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees,</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>weighing opium, or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0.iv">
                      <num>(iv)</num>
                      <p>preserving opium.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Punishment for allowing premises to be used for the commission of an offence.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Whoever, being the owner or the occupier or having the use of any house, room, enclosure, space, vessel, vehicle or place, knowingly permits it to be used for the commission by any other person, of an offence punishable under this Act or rules made thereunder, shall be punished with imprisonment of either description for a term which may extend to three years, or with fine which, may extend to two thousand rupees, or both .</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Enhanced punishment for certain offences after previous conviction.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Whenever, any person, having been convicted of an offence under Cl. (a) or Cl. (b) of S.5, is again convicted of an offence under either of the aforesaid clauses, the imprisonment with which he shall be punished shall be rigorous imprisonment for a term which may extend to ten years and fine:</p>
              <p>Provided that an accused who is found on evidence to be a smuggler of opium or a seller of opium shall not receive a sentence of less than three year's rigorous imprisonment and fine.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Security for abstaining from commission of offences.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>whenever any person is convicted of an offence punishable under S. 5 or under S. 6, and the Court convicting him is of opinion that it is necessary to require such person to execute a bond for abstaining from the commission of such offence, the Court may, at time of passing sentence on such person, order him to execute a bond for a sum proportionate to his means with or without sureties for abstaining from the commission of such offence during such period, not exceeding three years, as it thinks fit to fix.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The bond shall be in the prescribed form, and the provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (Act V of 1898), shall, in so far as they are applicable, apply to all matters connected with such bond as if it were bond to keep the peace ordered to be executed under S 106 of that Code.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the conviction is set aside on appeal or otherwise, the bond executed shall become void.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any order under this section may also be made by an Appellate Court or by the High Court when exercising its powers of revision.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Attempts.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Whoever attempts to commit an offence punishable under S.5 or to cause such an offence to be committed, and in such attempt does any act towards the commission of the offence or towards the causing of its commission, shall be punished with the punishment provided for the offence.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Abetments.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Whoever abets an offence punishable under S.5 or S. 6 shall, whether such offence be or be not committed in consequence of such abetment, be punished with the punishment provided for the offence.</p>
              <p>Whoever, knowing or having reason to believe that an offence has been committed under this Act, causes any evidence of the commission of that offence to disappear or gives any information respecting offence with that intention of screening the offender from punishment under the Act, or with that intention gives any information respecting the offence which he knows or believes to be false shall be punished with the punishment provided for the offence.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <heading>Security from habitual offenders to desist from committing offences</heading>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Security for desisting from committing offences.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-11.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Whenever a District Magistrate or a Sub-divisional Magistrate of the first class specially empowered by the State Government in this behalf receives information that any person within the limits of his jurisdiction habitually-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>commits offences under S.5 or S. 6, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>protects or harbours smugglers, receives or sellers of opium, or opium eaters,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>such Magistrate may, in manner hereinafter provided, require such person to show cause why he should not be ordered to execute a bond, with sureties, to desist from committing any offence mentioned in this sub¬section for such period, not exceeding three years, as the Magistrate thinks fit to fix.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Order to be made.</p>
              <p>When a Magistrate acting under sub-S. (1) deems it necessary to require any person to show cause under it he shall make an order in writing, setting forth the substance of the information received, the amount of the bond to be executed, the term for which it is to be in force, and the number, character and class of sureties required.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Procedure in respect of persons present in Court.</p>
              <p>If the person, in respect of whom such order is made, is present in Court, it shall be read over to him or if he so desires the substance there of shall be explained to him.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Procedure in respect of persons not present in Court.</p>
              <p>If such person is not present in Court, the Magistrate shall issue a summons requiring him to appear, or, when such person is in custody a warrant directing the officer in whose custody he is, to bring him before the Court:</p>
              <p>Provided that whatever it appears to such Magistrate, upon a report or upon other information (the substance whereof to be recorded) that there is reason</p>
              <p>to apprehend that any person against whom proceedings under this section have been initiated is likely to abscond and his presence before the Magistrate cannot be secured unless a warrant of arrest be issued against such person, the Magistrate may issue a warrant of arrest accordingly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Processes how served.</p>
              <p>Every summons or warrant issued under sub-S. (4) shall be accompanied by a copy of the order made under sub-S (2), and such copy shall be delivered by the officer serving or executing such summons or warrant to the person against whom the order is made</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-11.6.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Inquiry as to truth of information.</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.6.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>When an order under sub-S (2) has been read and explained to a person present in Court under sub-S (3) or where any person appears or is brought before a Magistrate shall proceed to inquire into the truth of the information upon which action has been taken and to take such evidence as may appear necessary.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.6.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>Such inquiry shall be made as nearly as may be practicable according to the procedure prescribed for the trial of warrant cases in the Criminal Procedure Code, 1898 (Act of 1898), except that no charge need be framed.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.6.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>If the Magistrate considers that immediate measures are necessary for the prevention of the commission of any offence under this Act, pending the conclusion of the inquiry under Cl. (i), he may, fro reasons to be recorded, direct the person in respect of whom the order under sub-S. (2) has been made, to execute a bond with sureties to desist from committing any offence mentioned in sub-S. (1) until the conclusion of the inquiry and may detain him in custody until such bond is executed, or in default of execution, until the inquiry is concluded.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Evidence of general repute.</p>
              <p>For the purposes of this section, and S. 16 the fact that a person is a habitual offender within the meaning of sub-S. (1) may be proved by evidence of general repute or otherwise.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Joinder of inquiries.</p>
              <p>When two or more persons are alleged to have been associated together in the matter under inquiry, they may be dealt with in the same or separate proceedings as the Magistrate shall think just.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Order to give security.</p>
              <p>If upon such inquiry, the Magistrate is satisfied that it is necessary that the person, in respect of whom the inquiry is made, should execute a bond with sureties to desist from committing the offences specified, the Magistrate shall make an order accordingly.</p>
              <p>Provided -</p>
              <p>Firstly, that no person shall be ordered to give surety of a nature different from or for an amount larger than or for a period longer than that specified in the order made under sub-S. (2);</p>
              <p>Secondly, that the amount of such bond shall be fixed with due regard to the circumstances of the case; and</p>
              <p>Thirdly, that when the person in respect of whom the inquiry is made is a minor, the bond shall be executed only by his surety.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.10">
            <num>(10)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Discharge of person proceeded against.</p>
              <p>If upon such inquiry, the Magistrate is not satisfied that it is necessary that the person in respect of whom the inquiry is made should execute a bond, the Magistrate shall make an entry on the record to that effect, and if such person is in custody only for the purposes of the inquiry shall release him, or if such person is not in custody, shall discharge him.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Proceedings subsequent to the order to furnish security.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-12.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any person in respect of whom an order requiring security is made under sub-S (9) of S. 11 is, at the time when such order is made, sentenced to or undergoing a sentence of imprisonment, the period for which the security is required shall commence on the expiration of such sentence.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In all other cases, such period shall commence on the date of such order, unless the Magistrate, for sufficient reason, fixes a later date.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Contents of the bond.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The bond to be executed by such person shall bind him to desist from committing any of the acts mentioned in sub-S (1) of S. 11, and shall be in the prescribed from.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Power to reject security.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>A Magistrate may refuse to accept any security offered or may reject any security previously accepted by him or by his predecessor under this Chapter on the ground that such surety is an unfit person for the purposes of the bond:</p>
              <p>Provided that before so refusing to accept or rejecting any such surety, he shall afford the person bound down and the surety an opportunity to show cause against the proposed order, and either himself hold an inquiry into the fitness of the surety or cause such inquiry to be held and report to be made thereon by Magistrate subordinate to him.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Imprisonment in default of security.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-15.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any person ordered to give security under sub-S. (9) of S. 11 does not give such security on or before the date of the commencement of the period for which such security is to be given, or if the security of any person previously accepted is rejected under the provisions of S. 14, he shall be committed to prison, or, if he is already in prison, be detained in prison until the date of expiry of such period or any earlier date on which he gives security as ordered.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the security is tendered to the officer-in-charge of the jail, he shall forthwith refer the matter to the</p>
              <p>Magistrate who made the order and shall await the orders of such Magistrate.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Imprisonment for failure to furnish security under this chapter shall be rigorous.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VI">
        <num>VI</num>
        <heading>Externment of habitual smugglers</heading>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Externment of habitual smugglers.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Whenever a District Magistrate or a Sub-divisional Magistrate or a Magistrate of the first class specially empowered by the State Government in this behalf receives information that any person within the limits of his jurisdiction is by habit a smuggler of opium for a seller or stockist of opium such Magistrate may, in the manner hereinafter provided, require such person to show cause why he should not be externed from the State or from any part thereof for such period as the Magistrate may deem fit.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Procedure of externment.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions in Chapter V of this Act shall, in so far as they are applicable, apply to all proceedings under S. 16 and if upon such inquiry the Magistrate is satisfied that it is necessary to extern the person in respect of whom the inquiry is made, he shall make an order accordingly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Magistrate making the order under sub-S. (1) shall direct the person concerned to leave the Province within such time, by such route or routes and for such period as may be stated in the order.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person against who, an order has been made under sub-S. (1) may appeal to the Court of Session, whose decision shall be final.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Punishment for non-compliance.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-18.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>When any person, against whom an order has been made or confirmed in appeal as the case may be under sub-S. 17-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>fails to comply with such order within the time specified therein, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>after complying with the said order returns or remains in the area from which he was externed before the expiry of the period stated in the order, he shall be punished with rigorous imprisonment for a term which may extend to ten years, and with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VII">
        <num>VII</num>
        <heading>Procedure</heading>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Power to issue warrants</heading>
          <subsection id="section-19.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A District Magistrate or a Sub-divisional Magistrate or a Magistrate of the first class, or an officer of the Excise Department not below the rank of a Deputy Superintendent specially empowered by the State Government in this behalf, may issue a warrant for the arrest of any person whom he has reason to believe to have committed a offence punishable under this Act or the rules thereunder, or for the search, whether by day or by night, of any building, vessel or place in which he has reason to believe any opium, material, utensil, implement or apparatus, in respect of which an offence punishable under this Act has been committed, is kept or concealed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The officers to whom a search warrant under sub-S. (1) is addressed shall have all the powers of officer under S. 20.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Power of entry, search, seizure and arrest without warrant.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-20.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-20.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Any officer of the Department of Excise not below the rank of Jamadar, any police officer not below the rank of Assistant Sub-Inspector, any officer of the Department of Revenue not below the rank of Sub-Deputy Collector, and the Inspecting Officer and Intelligence Officers of the Narcotics Intelligence Bureau, Government of India, and any Prohibition Officer authorized in this behalf by the State Government who has reason to believe, from personal knowledge or from information received from any person, and taken down in writing and attested by the informant that any opium, material, utensil, implement or apparatus in respect of which a offence punishable under this Act or the rules thereunder has been committed is kept or concealed in any building, vessel or enclosed place, may, between sunrise and sunset -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-20.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>enter into such building, vessel or place:</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-20.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>in case of resistance, break open any door and remove any other obstacle to such entry;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-20.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>seize such opium, material, utensil, implement or apparatus, and any other article liable to confiscation under S. 29, and any document or other article may furnish evidence of the commission of the offence; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-20.1.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>detain, search and arrest any person whom he has reason to believe to have committed an offence against this Act relating to such opium, material, utensil, implement or apparatus:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that if such officer has reason to believe that a search warrant cannot be obtained without affording opportunity for the concealment of evidence or facility for the escape of an offender, he may, after recording the ground of his belief enter and search such building, vessel or enclosed place at any time between sunset and sunrise.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where an officer takes down any information in writing under sub-S (1), or records grounds for his belief under the provision thereto, he shall forthwith send a copy thereof to his immediate official superior.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Power of seizure and arrest in public places.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Any officer of any of the departments referred to in S. 20 or any Prohibition Officer may-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>seize, in any public place or in transit, any opium, material, utensil, implement or apparatus in respect of which he has reason to believe an offence punishable under this Act or the rules thereunder has been committed, and along with it, any other articles liable to confiscation under S. 29, and any document or other article which may furnish evidence of the commission of the offence; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>detain, search and arrest any person whom he has reason to believe to have committed an offence against this Act relating to such opium, material, utensil, implement or apparatus.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Mode of executing warrants and of making searches and arrests.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The provision of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (Act V of 1898) shall, in so far as they are applicable, apply to execution of warrants and making of searches and arrests under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Obligation to assist.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-23.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person shall, upon notice being given or request made, be legally bound to assist an officer acting under this Chapter in carrying out the provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person contravening the provisions of sub-S. (1) shall be punished with simple imprisonment for a term</p>
              <p>which may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Report of arrest and seizure.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Any Officer making an arrest or seizure under this Act shall, within 24 hours after such seizure and arrest, make a full report of all the particulars of such arrest or seizure to his immediate officer superior.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Disposal of persons arrested and articles seized.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-25.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every person arrested and article seized under a warrant issued under S. 19 shall be produced within 24 hours of such arrest and seizure, exclusive of the time for actual transit, before the authority by whom the warrant was issued.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every person arrested and article seized under S. 20 or 21 shall be produced within 24 hours of such arrest and seizure, exclusive of the time for actual transit, before the officer-in-charge of the nearest police-station or the nearest officer of the Excise Department under S. 26.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The officer whom any person or article is forwarded under this section shall, with all convenient dispatch, take such measures as may be necessary for the disposal, according to law, of such person or article.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Power to invest Excise Officer.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may invest any officer of the Excise Department, not below the rank of Sub-Inspector, and the Inspecting Officers of the Narcotics Intelligence Bureau, Government of India, with the Powers of an Officer-in-charge of a police station for the Investigation of offences under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Jurisdiction to try offences.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (Act V of 1898), the State Government may invest any District Magistrate, Sub-divisional Magistrate or Magistrate of the first class with power to try as a Magistrate all or any specified offences arising in his jurisdiction under S. 5, S. 6, S. 7, S. 8, S. 9, S. 10 or S. 18, and every Court of a Magistrate so empowered may pass any sentence authorized by the aforesaid sections respectively.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Presumption.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-28.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In trials under Cls. (a) to (c) of S. 5, it shall be presumed, unless and until the contrary is proved, that the accused has committed the offence with which he is charged in respect of the opium for the possession of which he fails to account satisfactorily.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-28.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In trials under Cl. (d) of S. 5, it shall be presumed, unless and until the contrary is proved, that the</p>
              <p>accused has committed the offence with which he is charged in respect of the material, utensil, implement or apparatus for the possession of which he cannot account satisfactorily.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Things liable to confiscation.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-29.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>When, in the opinion of the Court, an offence has been committed against this Act, the opium, material, utensil, implement or apparatus in respect of, or by means of which the offence was committed shall be confiscated (whether or not any person has been put on trial or convicted) along with all receptacles packages, vessels, covering, animals, carts or other vehicles used or employed to contain or carry the same, unless, for sufficient reasons to be recorded in writing the Court directs otherwise:</p>
              <p>Provided that any person having a lawful claim to any such commodity, article, animal, or other thing mentioned above, may file, before the Court, a claim in respect thereof within 30 days of such order of confiscation, and if the claim is made out to the satisfaction of the Court, the order of confiscation shall be cancelled and the opium or other thing shall be retuned to such claimant.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VIII">
        <num>VIII</num>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-30.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>For the purposes of this Chapter, the State Government may, by notification in the official Gazatte, constitute for the State and for such period as it may deem fit a State Anti-Drug and Prohibition Council consisting two or more non-official residents of the State as may be prescribed by the State Government. The State Government may also, by like notification, dissolve or reconstitute any such Council.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading>Prohibition Officers.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-31.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>For the purposes of Ss. 20 and 21 of this Act, the State Government may, by notification in the official Gazatte, appoint any member of a Prohibition Committee, by virtue of office or otherwise, to be a Prohibition Officer; and the relation of officers so appointed to the State Anti-Drug and  Prohibition Council shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-32.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Anti-Drug and Prohibition Council may, by notification in the official Gazatte, constitute for any district or part thereof and for such period as it may deem fit, Prohibition Committees each consisting of two or more non-official residents of the district. The State Anti-Drug and Prohibition Council may also, by notification, dissolve or reconstitute such Prohibition Committees.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The duties to be performed by the State Anti-Drug Prohibition Council and the Prohibition Committees and the relation between the Council and the Committees and the relation of such Committees to the Council shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IX">
        <num>IX</num>
        <heading>Miscellaneous</heading>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading>Punishment for vexatious entry, search, seizure or arrest, etc.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-33.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-33.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Any person acting under the powers given by S. 20 or S. 21 who -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-33.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>without reasonable grounds of suspicion, enters or searches, or causes to be entered or searched, any building, vessel or place; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-33.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>vexatiously and unnecessarily seizes the property of any person on the pretence of seizing or searching for any opium or other article liable to be confiscated under S. 29, or of seizing any document or other article to seizure under S. 20 or 21; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-33.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>vexatiously and unnecessarily detains, searches or arrests any person, or fails to produce, within the time specified in S. 25, the person arrested or the article seized before the proper authority shall be punished with imprisonment of either description for a term which may extend to six months or with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, or with both.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-34">
          <num>34.</num>
          <heading>Punishment for unlawful release, etc.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-34.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-34.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Any person acting under the powers given by S. 20 or S. 21 who -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-34.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>unlawfully releases any person arrested under either of those sections; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-34.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>abets the unlawful escape of such a person.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>shall be punished with imprisonment of either description for a term which may extend to one year, or with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, or with both.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading>Punishment for malicious information.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-35.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Any person who maliciously and falsely lays information leading to a search, seizure, detention or arrest shall be punished with imprisonment of either description for a term which may extend six months, or with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, or with both.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-36">
          <num>36.</num>
          <heading>Obligation to give information.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-36.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every person shall be bound to give immediate information to any of the nearest officers referred to in Ss. 20 and 21 of any breach of any of the provisions of this Act or the rules made thereunder.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person contravening the provisions of sub-S. (1) shall be punished with simple imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, or with both.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-37">
          <num>37.</num>
          <heading>Indemnity.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-37.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No action shall lie against any officer for damages in any Civil Court bona fide done or ordered to be done in pursuance of thus Act or the Rules thereunder.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-38">
          <num>38.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-38.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, subject to the condition of previous publication, make rules for carrying out the provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-38.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-38.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such Rules may prescribe-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-38.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the relation of the Prohibition Officers to the State Prohibition Council;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-38.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the duties to be performed by a Prohibition Committee and its relation to the State Prohibition Council and other Committees;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-38.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the procedure for disposal of articles confiscated and proceeds thereof;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-38.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the licensing of a shop or place under sub-S (1) of S. 4; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-38.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>any other matter as may, or require to be prescribed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-38.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In making rules under this section, the State Government may attach a penalty for the breach of any particular rule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
