<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1854/5/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1854/5"/>
          <FRBRalias value="Bengal Bonded Warehouse Association"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1854/5/eng@1854-02-10/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1854/5/eng@1854-02-10"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1854-02-10" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1854/5/eng@1854-02-10/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1854/5/eng@1854-02-10"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>Bengal Bonded Warehouse Association</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 5 OF 1854</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 10th February, 1854.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to amend Act No. V of 1838, relating to the Bengal Bonded</p>
        <p>Warehouse Association.</p>
        <p>Preamble.-- WHEREAS the Bengal Bonded Warehouse Association are  desirous that the provisions of Act No. V of 1838 should be amended,</p>
        <p>and it appears reasonable that such amendment should be made, it is  enacted as follows:--</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Repeal of sections 12, 14, 32 and 37, Act V of 1838. Rep. by  the Repealing Act, 1870 (14 of 1870), s. 1 and Sch., Pt. II.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Management of business.-- The business of the said Association  shall be managed by six Directors, three of whom shall form a quorum.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Annual election of Directors.-- The two Directors who are to go  out of office by rotation in every year shall go out of office in the  month of May, before the holding of the Ordinary General Meeting of</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Proprietors directed to be holden in that month, and at such Ordinary</p>
            <p>General Meeting two Directors shall be chosen, and the Directors so  going out of office, or either of them, shall be capable of being re-</p>
            <p>elected in the same year at such General Meeting.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Qualification of Directors.-- No person shall be capable of  being a Director of the said Association who shall not be a proprietor  in his own right of five shares of the capital stock of the said</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Association.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Ordinary General Meetings.-- Ordinary General Meetings of the  said proprietors shall be held at least twice in every year, that is  to say, on the second Wednesday in the month of May, and the second</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Wednesday in the month of November, and at every such Ordinary Meeting  the Directors of the said Association shall present a report in  writing of the state of the affairs of the said Association and a  balance sheet; and such General Meeting may declare a dividend out of  the profits of the said Association, provided that no dividend shall  be made which shall diminish the capital of the said Association.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Bye- laws.-- It shall be lawful for the said Association to make</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Bye- laws for the regulation of its own proceedings, which Bye- laws  shall be binding only on its own Members and Officers, provided that  no such Bye- law shall be valid till it shall have been approved of by  one Extraordinary General Meeting of proprietors especially convened  for that purpose, provided also that no such Bye- law shall be valid  till it shall have been confirmed by the  Central Government].</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Dissolution of Corporation.-- At any time after the 14th day of</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>March, 1860, it shall be lawful for the Central Government by an order  in Council to direct that the said Association shall be dissolved at  the expiration of five years from the date of such order and such  order shall of itself have the effect of dissolving the said</p>
            <p>Corporation at the expiration of the said space of five years, except  for the purposes mentioned in section 39, Act No. V of 1838.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
