<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-bih/act/1979/01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-bih/act/1979/01"/>
          <FRBRalias value="Bihar Protected Places Act, 1979"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-bih/act/1979/01/eng@2017-01-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-bih/act/1979/01/eng@2017-01-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-bih/act/1979/01/eng@2017-01-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-bih/act/1979/01/eng@2017-01-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>Bihar Protected Places Act, 1979</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[Act No. 01 of 1979]</p>
      </longTitle>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[27th March, 1979]</docDate>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>An act to provide for controlling and regulating the admission of persons to a place or area declared by the State Government to be a protected place or areas and conduct of persons in and in the vicinity of</p>
      <p>such place or area.</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title extent and commencement.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-1.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>This Act may be called the Bihar Protected Places Act, 1979.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Bihar.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>It shall come into force atonce.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definition.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant to the subject or context:­</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"District Magistrate" or "Deputy Commissioner", includes an Additional District Magistrate or an Additional Deputy Commissioner;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"'Protected Place" means a place declared to be a protected place under  Section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>"Vicinity" means neighbourhood (at least five hundred metres) of the protected place;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Protected Place.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If the State Government considers it necessary or expedient that for the maintenance of the public order and for preventing or suppressing subversive acts, special precaution should be taken to prevent entry of unauthorized person, it may, by notification in the official gazette, declare a place or class of places of the categories mentioned below to be protected place for the purpose of this Act;—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>Public Sector undertakings, Corporations and all installations and establishments connected with their work.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>Industrial establishments, factories, workshops, and godowns;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>Mines, mineral installations, establishments and works shops;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>Refineries and washeries;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>Gas Plants;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.vi">
                <num>(vi)</num>
                <p>Oil depots;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.vii">
                <num>(vii)</num>
                <p>Civil aerodromes;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.viii">
                <num>(viii)</num>
                <p>Railways;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.ix">
                <num>(ix)</num>
                <p>Magazine Depots;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.x">
                <num>(x)</num>
                <p>Water works, pump-houses;­</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.xi">
                <num>(xi)</num>
                <p>Telephone, telegraph and other communication installations and establishments including Radio Stations and transmission lines;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.xii">
                <num>(xii)</num>
                <p>Dams, barrages and bridges;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.xiii">
                <num>(xiii)</num>
                <p>Any other place or class of places similar to above categories.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Explanation.—A protected, place shall also include the appartenant area the boundary of which shall be notified in notification.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No person, except a Police Officer in uniform, not below the rank of Assistant Sub­Inspector of Police of the District in which the protected place is situated, shall, without the permission of the District Magistrate, Deputy Commissioner or the Sub-divisional Magistrate or a person authorized by the District Magistrate Deputy Commissioner or the Sub­divisional Magistrate in this behalf, by general or special order in writing, enter, or be on or in or pass over or loiter in the place of the vicinity, of such protected place.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where in pursuance of sub-section (2), any person is granted permission to enter, or to be on or in, or to pass over a protected place, that person shall while acting under such permission comply with such orders for regulating his conduct as may be given by the District Magistrate, the Deputy Commissioner or the Sub-divisional Magistrate, or a person authorized by the District Magistrate, the Deputy Commissioner or the Sub-divisional Magistrate in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any Police Officer or any other person authorized in this behalf by the District Magistrate Deputy Commissioner or the Sub­divisional Magistrate by general or special order in writing may search any person entering or seeking to enter or being on or in or leaving a protected place and any Vehicles animal or article brought in by such person and may, for the purpose of the search, detain such person, vehicle, animal and article:</p>
            <p>Provided that no female shall be searched in pursuance of this sub-section except by a female.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person is in a protected place in contravention of this Section, then, without prejudice</p>
            <p>to any other proceedings which may be taken against him, he may be removed therefrom by any Police Officer or by any other person authorized in this behalf by the District Magistrate, Deputy Commissioner or the Sub­divisional Magistrate by general or special order in writing.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person is in a protected place in contravention of any of the provisions of this Section, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years or with fine up to five thousand rupees or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Power to prohibit any person from entering etc. in place without permit.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The District Magistrate or the Deputy Commissioner or the Sub­divisional Magistrate, may by order in writing prohibit any person from entering a protected place without a permit granted by, and unless he complies with such conditions as may be imposed by, the District Magistrate or the Deputy Commissioner or the Sub­divisional Magistrate or a person authorized by the, District Magistrate or the Deputy Commissioner or the Sub­divisional Magistrate in this behalf by general or special order in writing.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any order tinder sub-section (1) shall be served on the person in respect of whom it is made in the manner provided in  Section 134 of the code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (II of 1974).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Certain persons and persons incharge of animal or vehicles to comply with directions issued by the District Magistrate or the Deputy Commissioner or the Sub­divisional Magistrate.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In any protected place,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>Any person, or any class of persons, specified by order in writing by the District Magistrate or the Deputy Commissioner or the Sub­divisional Magistrate or by a person authorized by the District, Magistrate or the Deputy Commissioner or the Sub­divisional Magistrate in this behalf by general or special order in writing, and any person inc-harge of any vehicle or animal or of any class of vehicle or animals, specified by order in writing by the District­Magistrate or the Deputy Commissioner or the Sub-divisional Magistrate or by a person authorized in this behalf by the District Magistrate or the Deputy Commissioner or the Sub­divisional Magistrate by general or special order in writing, shall comply with such direction as the District Magistrate or the Deputy Commissioner or the Sub­divisional Magistrate or a person so authorized by him in this behalf, may by order in writing give for the purpose of prohibiting or controlling in any public thoroughfare the movements of any such person, vehicle or animal or such class of persons, vehicles or animals as the case may be; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>any person or class of persons specified by order in­writing by the District Magistrate or the Deputy Commissioner or the Sub­divisional Magistrate in this behalf by general or special order in writing, shall—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>report himself or themselves in such manner and at such time as may be specified in the order,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>cond of himself or them selves in such manner and abstain from such action, in respect of my property in his or their possession, as may be specified in the holder.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Power of District Magistrate or the Deputy Commissioner or the Sub­divisional Magistrate to restrict or control exercise of power delegated by him.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The District Magistrate or the Deputy Commissioner or the Sub­divisional Magistrate may while granting authority by general or special order in writing to any person, to exercise any power under this Act—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>specify the person or class of persons or the cases or class of cases in respect of whom or of which the powers, conferred by the authority so granted, shall be exercised.;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>direct that the powers conferred by the authority so granted shall not be exercised in respect of such persons or class of persons or cases or class of cases as the District Magistrate or the Sub­divisional Magistrate may specify, without the previous approval of the District Magistrate or the Deputy Commissioner or the Sub­divisional Magistrate.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Forcing or evading a guard.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any person who effects or attempts to effect entry into a place or area declared under Section 3 of the said Act, to be a protected place—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>by using or threatening to use criminal force to any person posted for the purpose of protecting or preventing or controlling access to such place</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>after taking precaution to conceal his entry or attempted entry from any such person;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall be punishable with 'imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years or with fine upto five thousand rupees or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Orders for certain places.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Without prejudice to any other provisions of this Act, the State­Government in respect of any place, declared by it to be a protected place, may make orders for controlling or regulating the admission of persons, to, and the conduct of persons in and in the vicinity of such place.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing, provisions the following provisions may be made for orders made under subjection (1) in relation to any place:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for restricting the admission of persons to such place and for removing therefrom any person who is therein in contravention of the orders or who has been convicted for contravention of the provisions of this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>for requiring the presence of any person or class of persons in such, place to be notified, to an authority appointed by the State Government and for requiring any person who has been convicted of any such offence as is mentioned in clause (a) of this sub-section to report his movements while in such place and to observe any other condition imposed upon him by an authority appointed by the State Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>for requiring any person or class of persons in such place to carry documentary evidence of identity as may be prescribed by an order made by the State Government under this Act; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>for prohibiting any person or class of persons from being in possession or control of any article prescribed by an order made by the State Government under this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An order made under this Section in respect of a protected place may exempt such place from all or any of the provisions of this Act which are expressed to apply to or in relation to a protected place or may direct that all or any of the said provisions shall apply subject of such modifications as may be specified in the order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person contravenes any order made under this Section, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years or with fine up to five thousand rupees or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Duty of giving information as to Commission of offence.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be the duty of every person to give on demand to a Superintendent of Police, or other police officer not below the rank of Sub­Inspector, empowered by the Inspector General of Police in this behalf, any information in his power relating to an offence or suspected offence under s 3, 4 and 5 and, if so required, to attend at such reasonable time and place as may be specified in an order for the purpose of furnishing such information.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person fails to give any such information as aforesaid within one week of the receipt of the order under sub-section (1) or within such extended time not exceeding fifteen days as may be allowed by the officer giving the order under sub-section (1), he shall be punishable with imprisonment which may extend to three years or with fine upto five thousand rupees or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Power to arrest without warrant.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any Police Officer may arrest without warrant any person; who is reasonably, suspected of having committed an offence punishable under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Delegation of power's and duties of State Government.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government, may by order direct that any power or duty which is conferred or imposed on the State Government, shall in such circumstances and under such conditions, if any, as may be specified in the order, be exercised or discharged by any officer or authority not below the rank of a Sub­divisional Magistrate.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action to be taken under this Act.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against any person for anything in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Application of other laws not barred.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of this Act shall be in addition, to and not in derogation of, any other law for the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
