<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1879/17/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1879/17"/>
          <FRBRalias value="Dekkhan Agriculturists' Relief Act, 1879"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1879/17/eng@1879-10-29/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1879/17/eng@1879-10-29"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1879-10-29" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1879/17/eng@1879-10-29/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1879/17/eng@1879-10-29"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>Dekkhan Agriculturists' Relief Act, 1879</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 17 OF 1879</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 29th October, 1879.] Prea</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act for the relief of Indebted Agriculturists in certain parts of  the Dekkhan.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, Commencement. This Act may be cited as the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Dekkhan Agriculturists' Relief Act, 1879: and it shall come into force  on the first day of November, 1879.</p>
            <p>Local extent.</p>
            <p>This section and] sections 11, 56, 60 and 62 extend to  the  whole of India except  the territories which, immediately before the</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1st">
        <num>1st.</num>
        <heading>November, 1956, were comprised in Part B States]]. The rest of  this Act  extends only to the districts of Poona, Satara, Sholapur  and Ahmednagar  but may, from time to time, be extended wholly or in  part by the State Government  to any other district or districts  in the  territories which, immediately before the 1st November,</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1956">
        <num>1956.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1956.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>, were comprised in the State of Bombay,]]  or to any part or  parts of any other such district or districts].</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Agriculturists to be sued where they reside. Every suit of  the description mentioned in section 3, clause (w)  may, if the  defendant, or, when there are several defendants, one only of such  defendants, is an agriculturist, be instituted and tried in a Court  within the local limits of whose jurisdiction such defendant resides,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>and not elsewhere.</p>
            <p>Every such suit in which there are several defendants who are  agriculturists may be instituted and tried in a Court within the local  limits of whose jurisdiction any one of such defendants resides, and  not elsewhere.</p>
            <p>Nothing herein contained shall affect sections 22 to 25 (both   inclusive) of the  Code of Civil Procedure.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-56">
        <num>56.</num>
        <heading>Instruments executed by agriculturist not to be deemed valid  unless executed before a Village registrar. No instrument which  purports to create, modify, transfer, evidence or extinguish an  obligation for the payment of money or a charge upon any property, or  to be a conveyance or lease, and which is executed after this Act  comes into force by an agriculturist residing in any local area for  which a Village- registrar has been appointed, shall be admitted in  evidence for any purpose by any person having by law or consent of  parties authority to receive evidence, or shall be acted upon by any  such person or by any public officer, unless such instrument is  written by, or under the superintendence of, and is attested by, a</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-56.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Village- registrar:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing herein contained shall prevent the  admission of any instrument in evidence in any criminal proceeding,</p>
            <p>or apply to any instrument which is executed by an agriculturist  merely as a surety,]  or to any instrument required by section 17 of  the  Indian Registration Act, 1877 (3 of 1877.), to be registered  under that Act.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-60">
        <num>60.</num>
        <heading>Registration under this Act to be deemed equivalent to  registration under Indian Registration Act, 1877. Every instrument  executed and registered in accordance with the foregoing provisions  shall be deemed to have been duly registered under the provisions of  the  Indian Registration Act, 1877 (3 of 1877.); and no instrument  which ought to have been executed before a Village- registrar but has  been otherwise executed shall be registered by any</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-60.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>officer acting under the said Act, or in any public office, or shall  be authenticated by any public officer.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-62">
        <num>62.</num>
        <heading>Exemption of instruments to which the Government or any  officer of the Government is a party. Nothing in this Act shall be  deemed to require any instrument, to which the Government or any  officer of the Government in his official capacity is a party, to be  executed before a Village- registrar .</heading>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
