<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1982/43/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1982/43"/>
          <FRBRalias value="Governors (Emoluments, Allowances And Privileges) Act, 1982"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1982/43/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1982/43/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1982/43/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1982/43/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>Governors (Emoluments, Allowances And Privileges) Act, 1982</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act XX of 1982</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called  the Governors (Emoluments, Allowances and Privileges) Act, 1982.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu  and Kashmir.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date' as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" Governor" means the Governor, or any person  discharging the functions of the Governor, of any State or of  two or more States;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>" maintenance",-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>provision of electricity, gas and water;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>and allowances of chauffeurs and the provision of oil  and petrol or other fuel;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" members of the family", in relation to a Governor,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>means the spouse and the dependent children of the Governor;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>" official residences" in relation to a Governor, means  such residences as may be specified by the President, by  notification in the Official Gazette, as the official  residences of the Governor and includes the staff quarters  and other buildings appurtenant thereto and the gardens  thereof;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>" rules" means rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>" State" does not include a Union territory.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Emoluments. There shall be paid to every Governor emoluments  at the rate of rupees eleven thousand per mensem.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that if a Governor, at the time of his appointment,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>is in receipt of a pension (other than disability or   wound pension) in respect of any previous service under the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Government of India or any of its predecessor Governments or  under the Government of a State or any of its predecessor</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Governments his emoluments shall be reduced,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list4.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>by the amount of that pension; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list4.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>if he hag, before such appointment, received in  lieu of a portion of the pension due to him in respect  of such previous service, the commuted value thereof, by  the amount of that portion of the pension;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>is in receipt of any benefit by way of contributory  provident fund, his emoluments shall be reduced by the  pension equivalent of such benefit.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Leave allowance.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to any rules made in this behalf,</p>
            <p>the President' shall grant such leave to a Governor as he may  consider necessary.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a Governor is granted leave by the President, he  shall, during the period of such leave, be paid leave allowance at  such rate as the President may by order determine:</p>
            <p>Provided that such leave allowance shall be reduced to the  extent, if any, to which the emoluments of the Governor are liable to  be reduced under the proviso to section 3.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>A Use and maintenance of official residences. Governor shall be  entitled, without payment of rent, to the use of his official  residences throughout his term of office and no charge shall fall on  the Governor personally in respect of the furnishing or the main-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>tenance of such residences.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Household establishment. Subject to any rules made in this  behalf, no charge shall fall on a Governor personally in respect of  pay, allowances or pension or other emoluments paid to or facilities  provided for, the members of the household establishment provided to  the Governor.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Medical treatment. Subject to any rules made in this behalf, a</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Governor and the members of his family shall be entitled during the  term of his office and</p>
            <p>thereafter also. to free medical attendance, accommodation and treat-</p>
            <p>ment in the hospitals maintained by the Central Government or the</p>
            <p>Government of any State.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Conveyance.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A Governor shall be entitled to use without  payment of rent or hire, such number of motor vehicles as the</p>
            <p>President may by order determine.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the maintenance of the motor vehicles referred to in sub- section (1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>by the members of the family of a Governor shall be regulated by rules  made in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Travelling allowance on assumption or vacation of office.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Subject to any rules made in this behalf, a Governor shall be entitled  to travelling allowance for himself and the members of his family and  for the transport of his and his family' s effects-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in respect of the journey for assuming office from  the place where he is ordinarily residing to the place  of his duty; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in respect of the journey on relinquishing office  from the place of his duty to the place where he would  ordinarily reside thereafter or if he is to take up any  other office under the Government (including the office   of the Governor of another State) after such  relinquishment, to the place of duty with respect to  such other office.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Allowances for renewing furnishings and for maintenance of  official residences. Subject to any rules made in this behalf a</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Governor shall be entitled to such allowances for renewing the  furnishings and for the maintenance of the official residences, as the</p>
            <p>President may by order determine.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Other privileges and allowances. For the purpose of enabling a</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Governor to discharge conveniently and with dignity the duties of his  office. he shall be-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>cribed by rules made in this behalf, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>such amount, as the President mat by general or special  order, determine by way of the following, namely:-</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>entertainment allowance;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>hospitality grant;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>household establishment expenses;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>office expenses;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>contract allowance, i. e., an allowance for  miscellaneous expenses;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>tour expenses; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>such other allowances or expenses as may be  provided for by rules.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Additional expenses.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where, in the case of any Governor,</p>
            <p>the President is satisfied that the amount authorised under this Act  by way of any allowances or for meeting any expenses with respect to  any matter requires to be increased or that a need has arisen to  sanction expenses with respect to any matter for which provision,</p>
            <p>though permissible, has not been made in the rules made under this</p>
            <p>Act, he may by special order increase such amount or sanction such  expenses to such extent as may be specified in such order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An order may be made under sub- section (1) so as to have  retrospective effect.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every order made under this section shall be laid, as soon  as may be after it is made, before both Houses of Parliament.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The President may, by notification in  the Official Gazette, make rules for the purpose of giving effect to  the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of  the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>grant of leave to a Governor under section 4;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>matters relating to the household establishment  provided to a Governor under section 6;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>medical attendance, accommodation and treatment of a</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-13.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Governor and the members of his family under section 7;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.2.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the use of motor vehicles by the members of the family  of a Governor under sub- section (3) of section 8;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the travelling allowance on assumption or vacation of  office of Governor under section 9:</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list3.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>allowances for renewing the furnishings and for the  maintenance of the official residences under section 10;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list3.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the privileges to which a Governor is entitled and the  allowances or expenses payable to a Governor under section</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-11.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made by the President under this Act shall be  laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of</p>
            <p>Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days,</p>
            <p>which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive  sessions and if, before the expiry of the session immediately  following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid both Houses  agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that  the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect  only in such modified form or be of no effect as the case may be; so,</p>
            <p>however that any such modification or annulment shall be without  prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>validation.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every special order issued before the  commencement of this Act, by the President in regard to the allowances  expenses (including medical expenses) or privilege-, of any Governor</p>
            <p>(other than the Governor of Nagaland) shall, notwithstanding that such  order was made with retrospective effect, or is inconsistent with any  general order issued under any law with respect to those matters be as  valid and effective a.-, if such special order formed part of this  sub- section and this sub- section had been in force at all material  times.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>commencement of this Act, by the President in regard to the  allowances, expenses (including medical expenses) or privileges of the</p>
            <p>Governor of Nagaland shall, notwithstanding that such order was made  with retrospective effect, be as valid and effective as if it formed  part of this sub- section and this sub- section had been in force at all  material times.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Saving. Nothing contained in this Act or the rules made  thereunder shall, a have effect so as to diminish the emoluments and  allowances of any Governor during his term of office.</heading>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
