<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-guj/act/1867/8/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-guj/act/1867/8"/>
          <FRBRalias value="Gujarat Village Police Act, 1867"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-guj/act/1867/8/eng@1867-12-21/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-guj/act/1867/8/eng@1867-12-21"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1867-12-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-guj/act/1867/8/eng@1867-12-21/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-guj/act/1867/8/eng@1867-12-21"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-13" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>Gujarat Village Police Act, 1867</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[Act No. 08 of 1867]</p>
      </longTitle>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[21st December, 1867]</docDate>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>An Act for the regulation of the Village Police in the Presidency of Bombay.</p>
      <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the regulation of the Village-police in the Presidency of Bombay; It is enacted as follows:--</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Interpretation clause</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The terms "District Superintendent" and "Assistant Superintendent of Police", and "Police officer", when used in this Act, mean officers so appointed or deemed to be appointed under the Bombay Police Act, 1951 (Bom. XXII of 1951).</p>
            <p>The term "Executive Magistrate" when used in this Act has the meaning assigned to it in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (V of 1898).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Extent</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>On and from the commencement of Bombay Village Police (Gujarat Extension and Amendment) Act, 1961 (Guj. XXX-IV of 1961), this Act shall extend also to that part of the State of Gujarat to which it did not extend before such commencement.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Administration, control and direction of village-police, in whom vested</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The administration of the village-police throughout each district shall under the control and direction of the ""State Government , be exercised by the Magistrate of the district, who may, with the sanction of the State Government , delegate any portion thereof to any Magistrate with full powers having also revenue charge as an Assistant or Deputy Collector.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Power to depute to District Superintendent authority over village-police-officer</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>It shall be lawful for the Magistrate of a district, with the sanction of the State Government , to depute to the District Superintendent of Police any authority which may be exercised by the Magistrate of a district for the purposes of police over any village-police-officer.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Village-police in villages under charge of Police-patel</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The village-police in each village shall be under the charge of such person as the State Government shall appoint in writing to be Police-Patel, and unless the State Government , owing to the size of the village or other good cause, see fit to separate the appointments, the State Government shall appoint the person conducting the duties of Revenue-patel to be Police-patel.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In making the appointment, the State Government shall have due regard to the provisions in force for regulating the services of hereditary officers, so far as the same may be applicable; but, when the Revenue-patel is not appointed Police-patel, and more persons than one claim by reason of hereditary right to perform the duties, in rotation or otherwise, it shall be lawful for the State Government to appoint the most fit from among their number.</p>
            <p>Police-patels may be appointed for different divisions of town or place.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In any town or place in which the duties cannot be efficiently performed by one Police-patel the State Government may, appoint a sufficient number of Police-patel for the different divisions of the town or place.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The powers of the State Government under this section may also be exercised by the Magistrate of a district.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
