<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-guj/act/1949/27/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-guj/act/1949/27"/>
          <FRBRalias value="Gujarat Repatriated Prisoners Act, 1949"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-guj/act/1949/27/eng@1949-06-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-guj/act/1949/27/eng@1949-06-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1949-06-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-guj/act/1949/27/eng@1949-06-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-guj/act/1949/27/eng@1949-06-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-13" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>Gujarat Repatriated Prisoners Act, 1949</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[Act No. 27 of 1949]</p>
      </longTitle>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[01st June, 1949]</docDate>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>An Act to provide for the reception, detention and trial of prisoners transferred from Pakistan to the Province of Bombay.</p>
      <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the reception, detention and trial of prisoners transferred from Pakistan to the Province of Bombay; It is hereby enacted as follows:--</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Gujarat Repatriated Prisoners Act, 1949.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the Province of Bombay.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Provincial Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"prison" includes a central, district or subsidiary jail or judicial lock-up, and every place which is used as a place of detention for persons who have been arrested or detained under any law for the time being in force;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"prisoner" includes every person who is detained in a prison by order of a competent authority not being a Civil Court;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>"repatriated prisoner" means a prisoner who being in custody in a prison or other place of detention in Pakistan has been conveyed and delivered by a duly authorised officer to any officer of this Province.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Custody and removal of repatriated prisoners</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Provincial Government may, by general or special order, specify the place at which and, either by name or designation, the officer by whom, custody of a repatriated prisoner, together with any article or records which may have been sent along with him, shall be received and the prison to which he is to be removed, and the officer in charge of such prison shall thereupon receive such prisoner and any article or records which may be produced along with him.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Convicted prisoners</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The officer in charge of the prison shall detain in custody a repatriated prisoner who, before his repatriation, was a convict undergoing a sentence in a prison--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>according to the tenor of the warrant, writ or order of commitment to prison, if any, relating to such prisoner, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>failing such warrant, writ or order as aforesaid in accordance with the order of the Provincial Government.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Prisoners undergoing trial before repatriation</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Provincial Government may by order direct any Court, other than the High Court, to enquire into or try any case which may have been pending against a repatriated prisoner immediately before his repatriation:</p>
            <blockList id="section-5.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the offence charged against such prisoner is also an offence under the law in force in the Province; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>such Court would have been competent to try such offence if it had been committed within the local limits of its jurisdiction.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On the making of an order under sub-section (1), the Court specified in the order shall proceed to enquire into or try such case according to law, as if the offence to which it relates had been committed within the local limits of its jurisdiction, and all the provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898(V of 1898), and of all other: aws in force in this Province shall, so far as may be, apply to such proceedings.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In any proceedings under sub-section (2), all evidence, both oral and documentary, which has been duly received in the proceedings against the repatriated prisoner held prior to his repatriation, or the copies of such, evidence certified under section 76 of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (I of 1872), may be treated as evidence in the case for all purposes subject to the provisions of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (I of 1872).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Prisoners repatriated while in police custody</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Provincial Government may by order in respect of any repatriated prisoner who, immediately before repatriation, was held under arrest or detention in police custody during or after completion of a police investigation, specify a Presidency Magistrate or Magistrate of the first class, as the case may be, who shall have and exercised jurisdiction for the purposes of this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every repatriated prisoner in respect of whom an order has been made under sub-section (1) shall be produced without dealy before the Magistrate specified in the order and such Magistrate may take cognizance of any offence that such repatriated prisoner may be reported by a police officer to have committed and may grant him bail.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the repatriation was effected before completion of the police investigation or the Magistrate is of the opinion that the evidence is deficient, the repatriated prisoner shall be released upon his entering into a bond, with or without sureties, as the Magistrate may direct, to appear if and when so required, and in the meantime the Magistrate may order such further enquiry into the substance of the allegations as he thinks fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In every case falling under sub-section (3), the Magistrate may, if he is satisfied at any stage that there is no prospect of securing sufficient evidence to justify commencement of proceedings against the repatriated prisoner, direct that such prisoner be discharged from his bond.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Delegation of powers</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Provincial Government may by order direct that the powers conferred on it by section 3, 4, 5 or 6 shall be also exercisable by such officer or authority and in such circumstances and under such conditions, if any, as may be specified in the order.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Powers of Provincial Government in relation to prisoners detained for reasons of security</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In relation to any repatriated prisoner whose detention immediately before his repatriation had been ordered under any law authorising preventive detention for reasons connected with the maintenance of public order, the Provincial Government shall have the same power in respect of extension or reduction of the term of detention as it possesses in relation to persons detained under section 2 of the Bombay Public Security Measures Act, 1947 (Bom. VI of 1947).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Jurisdiction of the High Court</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The High Court shall have, in relation to a repatriated prisoner, the same jurisdiction which it has in relation to a person who has been arrested or detained within the limits of its appellate jurisdiction in the same circumstances in which such prisoner was arrested or detained immediately before his repatriation.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Powers of Provincial Government to suspend, remit or commute sentences</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Provincial Government shall have the same powers to suspend, remit or commute a sentence of punishment awarded to a repatriated prisoner whether before or after his repatriation, as it possesses in relation to persons who have been sentenced in the Province for offences committed within the Province.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Lawfulness of custody and retaking upon escape</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>It shall be lawful for any officer to whom an order under section 3 or under section 4 is directed to receive, to hold in custody, convey and deliver the repatriated prisoner, named in the order as directed therein and if any such prisoner escapes out of any custody to which he may be delivered in pursuance of the order, he may be retaken as a person accused or convicted of an offence may be retaken upon an escape.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Powers to make rules</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Provincial Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
