<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1973/59/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1973/59"/>
          <FRBRalias value="Homoeopathy Central Council Act, 1973"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1973/59/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1973/59/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1973/59/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1973/59/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>Homoeopathy Central Council Act, 1973</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Homoeopathy Central Council Act, 1973.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India .</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force in a State on such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint in this behalf for such State and different dates may be appointed for different States and for different provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"Board" means a Board, Council, Examining Body or Faculty of Homoeopathy (by whatever name called) constituted by the State Government under any law for the time being in force regulating the award of medical qualifications in, and registration of practitioners of, Homoeopathy;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"Central Council" means the Central Council of Homoeopathy constituted under section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>"Central Register of Homoeopathy" means the register maintained by the Central Council under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>" Homoeopathy" means the Homoeopathy system of medicine and includes the use of Biochemic remedies;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>"medical institution" means any institution within or without India which grants degrees, diplomas or licenses in Homoeopathy;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>"prescribed" means prescribed by regulations;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>"recognized medical qualification" means any of the medical qualifications, in Homoeopathy, included in the Second or the Third Schedule;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>"regulation" means a regulation made under section 33</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>"State Register of Homoeopathy" means a register or registers maintained under any law for the time being in force in any State regulating the registration of practitioners of Homoeopathy;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>"University" means any University in India established by law and having a Faculty of Homoeopathy and includes a University in India established by law in which instruction, teaching, training or research in Homoeopathy is provided.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any reference in this Act to a law which is not in force in the State of Jammu and Kashmir shall, in relation to that State, be construed as a reference to the corresponding law, if any, in force in that State.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute for the purposes of this Act a Central Council consisting of the following members, namely:</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>such number of members not exceeding five as may be determined by the Central Government in accordance with the provisions of the First Schedule from each State in which a State Register of Homoeopathy is maintained, to be elected from amongst themselves by persons enrolled on that register as practitioners of Homoeopathy;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>one member from each University to be elected from amongst themselves by the members of the Faculty or Department (by whatever name called) of Homoeopathy of that University:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that until any such Faculty or Department of Homoeopathy is started in at least seven Universities, the Central Government may nominate such number of members not exceeding seven as may be determined by the Central Government from amongst the teaching staff of medical institutions within India, so however, that the total number of members so nominated and elected under this clause shall in no case exceed seven;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>such number of members, not exceeding forty per cent. of the total number of members elected under clauses (a) and (b), as may be nominated by the Central Government, from amongst persons having special knowledge or practical experience in respect of Homoeopathy or other related disciplines:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that until members are elected under clause (a) or clause (b) in accordance with the provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder, the Central Government shall nominate such number of members, being persons qualified to be chosen as such under the said clause (a) or clause (b), as the case may be, as that Government thinks fit; and references to elected members in this Act shall be construed as including references to members so nominated.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The President and the Vice-President of the Central Council shall be elected by the members of the Central Council from amongst themselves in such manner as may be prescribed:</p>
            <p>Provided that for two years from the first constitution of the Central Council, the President and the Vice-President shall be nominated by the Central Government from amongst the members of the Central Council and the President and the Vice-President so nominated shall, notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1) of section 7, hold office during the pleasure of the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Mode of election</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>An election under clause</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>or clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 3 shall be conducted by the Central Government in accordance with such rules as may be made by it in this behalf.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any dispute arises regarding any election to the Central Council, it shall be referred to the Central Government whose decision shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Restriction on elections and membership</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No person shall be eligible for election to the Central Council unless he possesses any of the medical qualifications included in the Second or the Third Schedule, is enrolled on any State Register of Homoeopathy and resides in the State concerned.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No person may at the same time serve as a member in more than one capacity.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Incorporation of Central Council The Central Council shall be a body corporate by the name of the Central Council of Homoeopathy having perpetual succession and a common seal, with power to acquire, hold and dispose of property, both movable and immovable, and to contract, and shall by the said name sue and be sued.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Term of office of President, Vice-President and members of Central Council</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The President, Vice-President or a member of the Central Council shall hold office for a term of five years from the date of his election or nomination, as the case may be, or until his successor shall have been duly elected or nominated, whichever is longer.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A person who holds, or who has held, office as President or Vice-President of the Central Council, shall be eligible for re-election to that office once, but only once.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Members of the Central Council shall be eligible for re-election or re-nomination.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An elected or nominated member shall be deemed to have vacated his seat if he is absent without excuse, sufficient in the opinion of the Central Council, from three consecutive ordinary meetings of the Central Council or, in the case of a member elected under clause (a) of sub-section (1) of section 3, if he ceases to be enrolled on the concerned State Register of Homoeopathy, or in the case of a member elected under clause (b) of that sub-section, if he ceases to be a member of the Faculty or Department (by whatever name called) of Homoeopathy of the University concerned.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A casual vacancy in the Central Council shall be filled by election or nomination, as the case may be, and the person elected or nominated to fill the vacancy shall hold office only for the remainder of the term for which the member whose place he takes was elected or nominate</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the said term of five years is about to expire in respect of any member, a successor may be elected or nominated at any time within three months before the said term expires but he shall not assume office until the said term has expired.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Meetings of Central Council</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Council shall meet at least once in each year at such time and place as may be appointed by the Central Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Unless otherwise prescribed, one-third of the total number of members of the Central Council shall form a quorum, and all the acts of the Central Council shall be decided by a majority of the members present and voting.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>The Executive Committee and other committees</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Council shall constitute from amongst its members an Executive Committee and such other committees for general or special purposes as the Council deems necessary to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.2.list0">
              <item id="section-9.2.list0.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>The Executive Committee (hereafter in this section referred to as the Committee), shall consist of the President and Vice-President, who shall be members ex officio, and not less than five and not more than seven members who shall be elected by the Central Council from amongst its members.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list0.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>The President and the Vice-President shall be the President and Vice-President respectively of the Committee.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list0.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>In addition to the powers and duties conferred and imposed upon it by this Act, the Committee shall exercise and discharge such powers and duties as the Central Council may confer or impose upon it by any regulations which may be made in this behalf.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Meetings of committees</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The committees constituted under section 9 shall meet at least twice in each year at such time and place as may be appointed by the Central Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Unless otherwise prescribed, one-third of the total number of members of a committee shall form a quorum, and all the acts of the committee shall be decided by a majority of the members present and voting.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Officers and other employees of Central Council The Central Council shall-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>appoint a Registrar who shall also act as Secretary;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>employ such other persons as it deems necessary to carry out the purposes of this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>require and take from the Registrar or from any other employee, such security for the due performance of his duties as the Central Council deems necessary; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>with the previous sanction of the Central Government, fix the remuneration and allowances to be paid to the President, Vice-President and members of the Central Council and to the members of the committees thereof and determine the conditions of service of the employees of the Central Council.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Vacancies in the Central Council and committees thereof not to invalidate acts, etcNo act or proceeding of the Central Council or any committee thereof shall be called in question on the ground merely of the existence of any vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution of the Central Council or the committee, as the case may be.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Recognition of medical qualification granted by certain medical institutions in India</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The medical qualifications granted by any University, Board or other medical institution in India which are included in the Second Schedule shall be recognized medical qualifications for the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any University, Board or other medical institution in India which grants a medical qualification not included in the Second Schedule may apply to the Central Government to have any such qualification recognized, and the Central Government, after consulting the Central Council, may, by notification in the Official Gazette, amend the Second Schedule so as to include such qualification therein, and any such notification may also direct that an entry shall be made in the last column of the Second Schedule against such medical qualification only when granted after a specified date.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Recognition of medical qualifications granted by medical institutions in States or countries outside India</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The medical qualifications granted by medical institutions outside India which are included in the Third Schedule shall be recognized medical qualifications for the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14.2.list0">
              <item id="section-14.2.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>The Central Council may enter into negotiations with the authority in any State or country outside India, which by the law of such State or country is entrusted with the maintenance of a Register of practitioners of Homoeopathy, for setting of a scheme of reciprocity for the recognition of medical qualifications in Homoeopathy, and in pursuance of any such scheme, the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, amend the Third Schedule so as to include therein any medical qualification which the Central Council has decided should be recognized, and any such notification may also direct that an entry shall be made in the last column of the Third Schedule against such medical qualification declaring that it shall be a recognized medical qualification only when granted after a specified date.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.2.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>Where the Council has refused to recommend any medical qualification which has been proposed for recognition by any authority referred to in clause (a) and that authority applies to the Central Government in this behalf, the Central Government, after considering such application and after obtaining from the Council a report, if any, as to the reasons for any such refusal, may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare that such qualification shall be a recognized medical qualification and the provisions of clause (a) shall apply accordingly</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Rights of persons possessing qualifications included in Second or the Third Schedule to be enrolled</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the other provisions contained in this Act, any medical qualification included in the Second or the Third Schedule shall be sufficient qualification for enrolment on any State Register of Homoeopathy.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-15.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>No person, other than a practitioner of Homoeopathy who possesses a recognized medical qualification and is enrolled on a State Register or the Central Register of Homoeopathy,</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>shall hold office as Homoeopathy physician or any other office (by whatever designation called) in Government or in any institution maintained by a local or other authority;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>shall practice Homoeopathy in any State;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>shall be entitled to sign or authenticate a medical or fitness certificate or any other certificate required by any law to be signed or authenticated by a duly qualified medical practitioner;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>shall be entitled to give any evidence at any inquest or any court of law as an expert under section 45 of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 on any matter relating to Homoeopathy.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-15.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Nothing contained in sub-section (2) shall affect-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the right of a practitioner of Homoeopathy enrolled on a State Register of Homoeopathy to practice Homoeopathy in any State merely on the ground that, on the commencement of this Act, he does not possess a recognized medical qualification;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the privileges (including the right to practice Homoeopathy) conferred by or under any law relating to registration of practitioners of Homoeopathy for the time being in force in any State, on a practitioner of Homoeopathy enrolled on a State Register of Homoeopathy;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.3.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the right of a person to practice Homoeopathy in a State in which, on the commencement of this Act, a State Register of Homoeopathy is not maintained if, on such commencement, he has been practicing Homoeopathy for not less than five years;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.3.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the rights conferred by or under the Indian Medical Council Act, 1956 including the right to practice medicine as defined in clause (f) of section 2 of the said Act or the Indian Medicine Central Council Act, 1970 of persons possessing any qualifications included in the respective Schedules to the said Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person who acts in contravention of any provision of sub-section (2) shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both. v</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Power to require information as to courses of study and examinations Every University, Board or medical institution in India which grants a recognized medical qualification shall furnish such information as the Central Council may, from time to time, require as to the courses of study and examinations to be undergone in order to obtain such qualification, as to the ages at which such courses of study and examinations are required to be undergone and such qualification is conferred and generally as to the requisites for obtaining such qualification</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Inspectors at examinations</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Council shall appoint such number of medical inspectors as it may deem requisite to inspect any medical college, hospital or other institution where education in Homoeopathy is given, or to attend any examination held by any University, Board or medical institution for the purpose of recommending to the Central Government recognition of medical qualifications granted by that University, Board or medical institution.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The medical inspectors shall not interfere with the conduct of any training or examination, but shall report to the Central Council on the adequacy of the standards of education including staff, equipment, accommodation, training and other facilities prescribed for giving education in Homoeopathy, as the case may be, or on the sufficiency of every examination which they attend.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Council shall forward a copy of any such report to the University, Board or medical institution concerned, and shall also forward a copy with the remarks of the University, Board or medical institution thereon, to the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Visitors at examinations</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Council may appoint such number of visitors as it may deem requisite to inspect any medical college, hospital or other institution where education in Homoeopathy is given or to attend any examination for the purpose of granting recognized medical qualification.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person, whether he is a member of the Central Council or not, may be appointed as a visitor under this section but a person who is appointed as an inspector under section 17 for any inspection or examination shall not be appointed as a visitor for the same inspection or examination.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The visitors shall not interfere with the conduct of any training or examination, but shall report to the President of the Central Council on the adequacy of the standards of education including staff, equipment, accommodation, training and other facilities prescribed for giving education in Homoeopathy or on the sufficiency of every examination which they attend.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The report of a visitor shall be treated as confidential unless in any particular case the President of the Central Council otherwise directs:</p>
            <p>Provided that if the Central Government requires a copy of the report of a visitor, the Central Council shall furnish the same.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Withdrawal of recognition</heading>
        <subsection id="section-19.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-19.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>When upon report by the inspector or the visitor, it appears to the Central Council</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-19.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>that the courses of study and examination to be undergone in, or the proficiency required from candidates at any examination held by, any University, Board or medical institution, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>that the staff, equipment, accommodation, training and other facilities for instruction and training provided in such University, Board or medical institution or in any college or other institution affiliated to the University, do not conform to the standard prescribed by the Central Council, the Central Council shall make a representation to that effect to the Central Government.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>After considering such representation, the Central Government may send it to the Government of the State in which the University, Board or medical institution is situated and the State Government shall forward it along with such remarks as it may choose to make to the University, Board or medical institution, Board or medical institution may submit its explanation to the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On the receipt of the explanation, or, where no explanation is submitted within the period fixed, then, on the expiry of that period, the State Government shall make its recommendations to the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government, after making such further inquiry, if any, as it may think fit, may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that an entry shall be made in the Second Schedule against the said medical qualification declaring that it shall be a recognized medical qualification only when granted before a specified date, or that the said medical qualification if granted to students of a specified college or institution affiliated to any University shall be recognized medical qualification only when granted before a specified date or, as the case may be, that the said medical qualification shall be recognized medical qualification in relation to a specified college or institution affiliated to any University only when granted after a specified date</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Minimum standards of education in Homoeopathy</heading>
        <subsection id="section-20.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Council may prescribe the minimum standards of education in Homoeopathy, required for granting recognized medical qualifications by Universities, Boards or medical institutions in India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Copies of the draft regulations and of all subsequent amendments thereof shall be furnished by the Central Council to all State Governments and the Central Council shall, before submitting the regulations or any amendment thereof, as the case may be, to the Central Government for sanction, take into consideration the comments of any State Government received within three months from the furnishing of the copies as aforesaid.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>The Central Register of Homoeopathy</heading>
        <subsection id="section-21.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-21.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Council shall cause to be maintained in the prescribed manner, a register of practitioners of Homoeopathy to be known as the Central Register of Homoeopathy which shall contain</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-21.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in Part I, the names of all persons who are for the time being enrolled on any State Register of Homoeopathy and possess any of the recognized medical qualifications;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-21.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in Part II, the names of all persons, other than those included in Part I, who are for the time being enrolled on any State Register of Homoeopathy.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-21.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be the duty of the Registrar of the Central Council to keep and maintain the Central Register of Homoeopathy in accordance with the provisions of this Act and of any orders made by the Central Council, and from time to time to revise the register and publish it in the Gazette of India and in such other manner as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-21.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Such register shall be deemed to be a public document within the meaning of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872, and may be proved by a copy published in the Gazette of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Supply of copies of State Register of Homoeopathy Each Board shall supply to the Central Council three printed copies of the State Register of Homoeopathy as soon as may be after the commencement of this Act and subsequently after the first day of April of each year, and each Board shall inform the Central Council without delay of all additions to, and other amendments in, the State Register of Homoeopathy made from time to time.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Registration in the Central Register of HomoeopathyThe Registrar of the Central Council may on receipt of the report of registration of a person in a State Register of Homoeopathy or on application made in the prescribed manner by any person, enter his name in the Central Register of Homoeopathy, provided that the Registrar is satisfied that the person concerned is eligible under this Act for such registration.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Professional conduct</heading>
        <subsection id="section-24.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Council may prescribe standards of professional conduct and etiquette and a code of ethics for practitioners of Homoeopathy.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Regulations made by the Central Council under sub-section (1) may specify which violations thereof shall constitute infamous conduct in any professional respect, that is to say, professional misconduct, and such provision shall have effect notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Removal of names from the Central Register of Homoeopathy</heading>
        <subsection id="section-25.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the name of any person enrolled on a State Register of Homoeopathy is removed there from in pursuance of any power conferred by or under any law relating to registration of practitioners of Homoeopathy for the time being in force in any State, the Central Council shall direct the removal of the name of such person from the Central Register of Homoeopathy.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the name of any person has been removed from a State Register of Homoeopathy on any ground other than that he is not possessed of the requisite medical qualifications or where any application by the said person for restoration of his name to the State Register of Homoeopathy has been rejected, he may appeal in the prescribed manner and subject to such conditions, including conditions as to the payment of a fee, as may be prescribed, to the Central Government whose decision, which shall be given after consulting the Central Council, shall be binding on the State Government and on the authorities concerned with the preparation of the State Register of Homoeopathy.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Privileges of persons who are enrolled on the Central Register of Homoeopathy</heading>
        <subsection id="section-26.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the conditions and restrictions laid down in this Act regarding practice of Homoeopathy by persons possessing certain recognized medical qualifications, every person whose name is for the time being borne on Part I of the Central Register of Homoeopathy shall be entitled according to his qualifications to practice Homoeopathy, in any part of India and to recover in due course of law in respect of such practice any expenses, charges in respect of medicaments or other appliances or any fees to which he may be entitled.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of sub-section (3) of section 15, any person whose name is for the time being borne on Part II of the Central Register of Homoeopathy, may practice Homoeopathy in any State, other than the State where he is enrolled on the State Register of Homoeopathy, with the previous approval of the Government of the State where he intends to practice.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Registration of additional qualifications</heading>
        <subsection id="section-27.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person whose name is entered in the Central Register of Homoeopathy obtains any title, diploma or other qualification for proficiency in Homoeopathy, which is a recognized medical qualification, he shall, on application made in this behalf in the prescribed manner, be entitled to have an entry stating such other title, diploma or other qualification made against his name in the Central Register of Homoeopathy either in substitution for or in addition to any entry previously made.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The entries in respect of any such person in a State Register of Homoeopathy shall be altered in accordance with the alterations made in the Central Register of Homoeopathy.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28">
        <num>28.</num>
        <heading>Persons enrolled on Central Register of Homoeopathy to notify change of place of residence or practice Every person registered in the Central Register of Homoeopathy shall notify any transfer of the place of his residence or practice to the Central Council and to the Board concerned, within ninety days of such transfer, failing which his right to participate in the election of members to the Central Council or a Board shall be liable to be forfeited by order of the Central Government either permanently or for such period as may be specified therein.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29">
        <num>29.</num>
        <heading>Information to be furnished by Central Council and publication thereof</heading>
        <subsection id="section-29.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Council shall furnish such reports, copies of its minutes, abstracts of its accounts, and other information to the Central Government as that Government may require</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may publish in such manner as it may think fit, any report, copy, abstract or other information furnished to it under this section or under section 18.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-30">
        <num>30.</num>
        <heading>Commission of inquiry</heading>
        <subsection id="section-30.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whenever it is made to appear to the Central Government that the Central Council is not complying with any of the provisions of this Act, the Central Government may refer the particulars of the complaint to a commission of inquiry consisting of three persons, two of whom shall be appointed by the Central Government, one being a Judge of a High Court, and one by the Central Council, and such commission shall proceed to inquire in a summary manner and to report to the Central Government as to the truth of the matters charged in the complaint, and in case of any charge of default or of improper action being found by the commission to have been established, the commission shall recommend the remedies, if any, which are in its opinion necessary.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-30.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may require the Central Council to adopt the remedies so recommended within such time as, having regard to the report of the commission, it may think fit, and if the Central Council fails to comply with any such requirement, the Central Government may amend the regulations of the Central Council, or make such provision or order or take such other steps as may seem necessary to give effect to the recommendations of the commission.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-30.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A commission of inquiry shall have power to administer oaths, to enforce the attendance of witnesses and the production of documents, and shall have all such other necessary powers for the purpose of any inquiry conducted by it as are exercised by a civil court under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-31">
        <num>31.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Government, the Central Council or a Board or any committee thereof or any officer or servant of the Government or the Central Council or the Board or the committee aforesaid for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-32">
        <num>32.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules</heading>
        <subsection id="section-32.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-32.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-33">
        <num>33.</num>
        <heading>Power to make regulations</heading>
        <subsection id="section-33.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-33.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Council may, with the previous sanction of the Central Government, make, by notification in the official gazette regulations generally to carry out the purposes of this Act, and, without prejudice to the generality of this power, such regulations may provide for-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-33.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the manner of election of the President and the Vice-President of the Central Council;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-33.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the management of the property of the Central Council and the maintenance and audit of its accounts</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-33.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the resignation of members of the Central Council;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-33.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the powers and duties of the President and Vice-President;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-33.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the summoning and holding of meetings of the Central Council and the committees thereof, the times and places where such meetings are to be held, and the conduct of business thereat and the number of members necessary to constitute a quorum;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-33.1.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the functions of the committees constituted under section 9;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-33.1.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the tenure of office, and the powers and duties of the Registrar and other officers and servants of the Central Council;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-33.1.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the qualifications, appointment, powers and duties of, and procedure to be followed by, inspectors and visitors;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-33.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the courses and period of study of practical training to be undertaken, the subjects of examination and the standards of proficiency therein to be obtained, in any University, Board or medical institution for grant of recognized medical qualification;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-33.1.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>the standards of staff, equipment, accommodation, training and other facilities for education in Homoeopathy;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-33.1.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>the conduct of professional examinations, qualifications of examiners and the conditions of admission to such examinations;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-33.1.list1.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>the standards of professional conduct and etiquette and code of ethics to be observed by practitioners of Homoeopathy;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-33.1.list1.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>the particulars to be stated, and the proof of qualifications to be given in applications for registration under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-33.1.list1.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>the manner in which and the conditions subject to which an appeal under section 25 may be preferred;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-33.1.list1.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>the fees to be paid on applications and appeals under this Act; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-33.1.list1.p">
                <num>(p)</num>
                <p>any matter for which under this Act provision may be made by regulations.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-33.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government shall cause every regulation made under this Act to be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the regulation or both Houses agree that the regulation should not be made, the regulation shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that regulation.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
