<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/65/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/65"/>
          <FRBRalias value="INDUSTRIES (DEVELOPMENT AND REGULATION) ACT, 1951"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/65/eng@1951-10-31/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/65/eng@1951-10-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1951-10-31" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/65/eng@1951-10-31/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/65/eng@1951-10-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-04-22" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>Industries (Development And Regulation) Act, 1951</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act, No. 65 of 1951</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-31st">
        <num>31st.</num>
        <heading>October, 1951</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-31st.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PREAMBLE</p>
            <p>An Act to provide for the development and regulation of certain industries .</p>
            <p>Be it enacted by Parliament as follows:.-</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Industries (Development and Regulation) Act, 1951 .</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Declaration as to expediency of control by the Union</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>It is hereby declared that it is expedient in the public interest that the Union should take under its control the industries specified in the First Schedule.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"Advisory Council" means the Central Advisory Council established under section 5;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.aa">
                <num>(aa)</num>
                <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.aa.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>"ancillary industrial undertaking" means an industrial undertaking which, in accordance with the proviso to sub-section (1) of section 11B and the requirements specified under that sub-section, is entitled to be regarded as an ancillary industrial undertaking for the purposes of this Act:</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.aa.list0.ab">
                    <num>(ab)</num>
                    <p>"current assets" means bank balances and cash and includes such other assets or reserves as are expected to be realised in cash or sold or consumed within a period of not more than twelve months in the ordinary course of business, such as stock-in-trade, amounts due from sundry debtors for sale of goods and for services rendered, advance tax payments and bills receivable, but docs not include sums credited to a provident fund, a pension fund, a gratuity fund or any other fund for the welfare of the employees, maintained by a company owning an industrial undertaking;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.aa.list0.ac">
                    <num>(ac)</num>
                    <p>"current liabilities" means liabilities which must be met on demand or within a period of twelve months from the date they are incurred: and includes any current liability which is suspended under section 18FB:</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"Development Council" means a Development Council established under section 6;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.bb">
                <num>(bb)</num>
                <p>"existing industrial undertaking" means--</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in the case of an industrial undertaking pertaining to any of the industries specified in the First Schedule as originally enacted, an industrial undertaking which was in existence on the commencement of this Act or for the establishment of which effective steps had been taken before such commencement, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in the case of an industrial undertaking pertaining to any of the industries added to the First Schedule by an amendment thereof, an industrial undertaking which is in existence on the coming into force of such amendment or for the establishment of which effective steps had been taken before the coming into force of such amendment:</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>"factory" means any premises, including the precincts thereof, in any part of which a manufacturing process is being carried on or is ordinarily so carried on--</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>with the aid of power, provided that fifty or more workers arc working or were working thereon on any day of the preceding twelve months, or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>without the aid of power, provided that one hundred or more workers are working or were working thereon any day of the preceding twelve months and provided further that in no part of such premises any manufacturing process is being carried on with the aid of power:</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.cc">
                    <num>(cc)</num>
                    <p>"High Court" means the High Court having jurisdiction in relation to the place at which the registered office of a company is situate;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.d">
                    <num>(d)</num>
                    <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.d.list0">
                      <listIntroduction>"industrial undertaking" means any undertaking pertaining to a scheduled industry carried on in one or more factories by any person or authority including Government:</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.d.list0.dd">
                        <num>(dd)</num>
                        <p>"new article", in relation to an industrial undertaking which is registered or in respect of which a licence or permission has been issued under this Act means -</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>any article which falls under an item in the First Schedule other that the item under which articles ordinarily manufactured or produced in the industrial undertaking at the date of registration or issue of the licence or permission, as the case may be, fall;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>any article which bears a mark as defined in the Trade Marks Act, 1940 (5 of 1940) , or which is the subject of a patent, if at the dale of registration or issue of the licence or permission, as the case may be the industrial undertaking was not manufacturing or producing such article bearing that mark or which is the subject of that patent;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.e">
                    <num>(e)</num>
                    <p>"notified order" means an order notified in the Official Gazette;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.f">
                    <num>(f)</num>
                    <p>"owner", in relation to an industrial undertaking, means the person who. or the authority which, has the ultimate control over the affairs of the undertaking, and, where the said affairs are entrusted to a manager, managing director or managing agent, such manager, managing director or managing agent shall be deemed to be the owner of the undertaking:</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.g">
                    <num>(g)</num>
                    <p>"prescribed' means prescribed by rules made under this Act:</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.h">
                    <num>(h)</num>
                    <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.h.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>"schedule" means a Schedule to this Act:</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.h.list1.i">
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <p>"schedule industry" means any of the industries specified in the First Schedule;</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.j">
                    <num>(j)</num>
                    <p>"small scale industrial undertaking" means an industrial undertaking which, in accordance with the requirements specified under sub-section (1) of section 11B, is entitled to be regarded as a small scale industrial undertaking for the purposes of this Act;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c.list1.k">
                    <num>(k)</num>
                    <p>words and expressions used herein but not defined in this Act and defined in the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), have the meanings respectively assigned to them in that Act.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Saving Repealed</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Rep. by the Industries (Development and Regulation) Amendment Act, 1953 (26 of 1953), Section 3 (w.e.f. 1st October, 1953).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Establishment and constitution of Central Advisory Council and its functions</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of advising it on matters concerning the development and regulation of scheduled industries, the Central Government may, by notified order, establish a Council to be called the Central Advisory Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Advisory Council shall consist of a Chairman and such other members, not exceeding thirty in number, all of whom shall be appointed by the Central Government from among persons who are in its opinion capable of representing the interests of:</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>owners of industrial undertakings in scheduled industries ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>persons employed in industrial undertakings in scheduled industries ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>consumers of goods manufactured or produced by scheduled industries;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>such other class of persons including primary producers, as in the opinion of the Central Government, ought to be represented on the Advisory Council.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The term of office of, the procedure to be followed in the discharge of their functions by, and the manner of filling casual vacancies among, members of the Advisory Council, shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government shall consult the Advisory Council in regard to--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the making of any rules, other than the first rules to be made under sub-section (3);</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>and may consult the Advisory Council in regard to any other matter connected with the administration of this Act in respect of which the Central Government may consider it necessary to obtain the advice of the Advisory Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Establishment and constitution of Development Councils and their functions</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government may, by notified order, establish for any scheduled industry or group of scheduled industries, a body of persons to be called a Development Council which shall consist of members who in the opinion of the Central Government are--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>persons capable of representing the interests of owners of industrial undertakings in the scheduled industry or group of scheduled industries;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>persons having special knowledge of matters relating to the technical or other aspects of the scheduled industry or group of scheduled industries ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>persons capable of representing the interests of persons employed in industrial undertakings in the scheduled industry or group of scheduled industries;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>persons not belonging to any of the aforesaid categories, who are capable of representing the interests of consumers of goods manufactured or produced by the scheduled industry or group of scheduled industries.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The number and the term of office of, and the procedure to be followed in the discharge of their functions by, and the manner of filling casual vacancies among members of a Development Council shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Development Council shall be, by virtue of this Act, a body corporate by such name as may be specified in the notified order establishing it and may hold and transfer property and shall by the said name sue and be sued.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A Development Council shall perform such functions of a kind specified in the Second Schedule as may be assigned to it by the Central Government and for whose exercise by the Development Council it appears to the Central Government expedient to provide in order to increase the efficiency or productivity in the scheduled industry or group of scheduled industries for which the Development Council is established, to improve or develop the service that such industry or group of industries renders or could render to the community, or to enable such industry or group of industries to render such service more economically.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A Development Council shall also perform such other functions as it may be required to perform by or under any other provision of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Reports and accounts of Development Councils</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A Development Council shall prepare and transmit to the Central Government and the Advisory Council, annually, a report setting out what has been done in the discharge of its functions during the financial year last completed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The report shall include a statement of the accounts of the Development Council for that year, and shall be transmitted as soon as accounts therefore have been audited, together with a copy of any report made by the auditors on the accounts.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The statement of account shall be in such form as may be prescribed, being a form which shall conform to the best commercial standards, and the statement shall show the total of remuneration and allowances paid during the year to members and officers of the Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A copy of each such report of a Development Council, or made by the auditors on its accounts, shall be laid before Parliament by the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Dissolution of Development Councils</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, if it is satisfied that a Development Council should cease to continue in being, by notified order, dissolve that Development Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On the dissolution of a Development Council under sub-section (1), the assets of the Development Council, after its liabilities, if any, are met therefrom, shall vest in the Central Government for the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Imposition of cess on scheduled industries in certain cases</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There may be levied and collected as a cess for the purposes of this Act on all goods manufactured or produced in any such scheduled industry as may be specified in this behalf by the Central Government by notified order a duly of excise at such rate as may be specified in the notified order, and different rates may be specified for different goods or different classes of goods:</p>
            <p>Provided that no such rate shall in any case exceed two annas per cent of the value of the goods.</p>
            <p>Explanation.—In this sub-section the expression "value" in relation to any goods shall be deemed to be the wholesale cash price for which such goods of the like kind and quality arc sold or arc capable of being sold for delivery at the place of manufacture and at the time of their removal therefrom, without any abatement or deduction whatever except trade discount and the amount of duty then payable.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The cess shall be payable at such intervals, within such time and in such manner as may be prescribed, and any rules made in this behalf may provide for the grant of a rebate for prompt payment of the cess.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The said cess may be recovered in the same manner as an arrear of land revenue.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government may hand over the proceeds of the cess collected under this section in respect of the goods manufactured or produced by any scheduled industry or group of scheduled industries to the Development Council established for that industry or group of industries, and where it does so, the Development Council shall utilise the said proceeds--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to promote scientific and industrial research with reference to the scheduled industry or group of scheduled industries in respect of which the Development Council is established;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.4.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to promote improvements in design and quality with reference to the products of such industry or group of industries;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.4.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to provide for the training of technicians and labour in such industry or group of industries;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.4.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>to meet such expenses in the exercise of its functions and its administrative expenses as may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Registration of existing industrial undertakings</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The owner of every existing industrial undertaking, not being the Central Government, shall, within such period as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, fix in this behalf with respect to industrial undertakings generally or with respect to any class of them, register the undertaking in the prescribed manner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government shall also cause to be registered in the same manner every existing industrial undertaking of which it is the owner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an industrial undertaking is registered under this section, there shall be issued to the owner of the undertaking or the Central Government, as the case may be, a certificate of registration containing the productive capacity of the industrial undertaking and such other particulars as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The owner of every industrial undertaking to whom a certificate of registration has been issued under this section before the commencement of the Industries (Development and Regulation) Amendment Act, 1973 (67 of 1973), shall, if the undertaking falls within such class of undertakings as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf, produce, within such period as may be specified in such notification, the certificate of registration for entering therein the productive capacity of the industrial undertaking and other prescribed particulars.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In specifying the productive capacity in any certificate of registration issued under sub-section (3), the Central Government shall take into consideration the productive or installed capacity of the industrial undertaking as specified in the application for registration made under sub-section (1), the level of production immediately before the date on which the application for registration was made under sub-section (1), the level of the highest annual production during the three years immediately preceding the introduction in Parliament of the Industries (Development and Regulation) amendment Bill, 1973, the extent to which production during the said period was utilised for export and such other factors as the Central Government may consider relevant including the extent of underutilisation of capacity, if any, during the relevant period due to any cause.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10A">
        <num>10A.</num>
        <heading>Revocation of registration in certain cases</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If the Central Government is satisfied that the registration of any industrial undertaking has been obtained by misrepresentation as to an essential fact or that any industrial undertaking has ceased to be registrable under this Act by reason of any exemption granted under this Act becoming applicable thereto or that for any other reason the registration has become useless or ineffective and therefore requires to be revoked the Central Government may after giving an opportunity to the owner of the undertaking to be heard revoke the registration.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Licensing of new industrial undertakings</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No person or authority other than the Central Government, shall, after the commencement of this Act, establish any new industrial undertaking, except under and in accordance with a licence issued in that behalf by the Central Government:</p>
            <p>Provided that a Government other than the Central Government may, with the previous permission of the Central Government, establish a new industrial undertaking.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A licence or permission under sub-section (1) may contain such conditions, including, in particular, conditions as to the location of the undertaking and the minimum standards in respect of size to be provided therein as the Central Government may deem fit to impose in accordance with the rules, if any, made under Section 30.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11A">
        <num>11A.</num>
        <heading>Licence for producing or manufacturing new articles</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11A.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The owner of an industrial undertaking not being the Central Government which is registered under Section 10 or in respect of which a licence or permission has been issued under Section 11 shall not produce or manufacture any new article unless--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11A.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in the case of an industrial undertaking registered under Section 10, he has obtained a licence for producing or manufacturing such new article ; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11A.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in the case of an industrial undertaking in respect of which a licence or permission has been issued under Section 11, he has had the existing licence or permission amended in the prescribed manner.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11B">
        <num>11B.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to specify the requirements which shall be complied with by small scale industrial undertakings</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11B.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Power of Central Government to specify the requirements which shall be complied with by small scale industrial undertakings</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-11B.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11B.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government may, with a view to ascertaining which ancillary and small scale industrial undertakings need supportive measures, exemptions or other favourable treatment under this Act to enable them to maintain their viability and strength so as to be effective in--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11B.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>promoting in a harmonious manner the industrial economy of the country and easing the problem of unemployment, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11B.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>securing that the ownership and control of the material resources of the community are so distributed as best to sub serve the common good,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>specify, having regard to the factors mentioned in sub-section (2), by notified order, the requirements which shall be complied with by an industrial undertaking to enable it to be regarded, for the purposes of this Act, as an ancillary, or a small scale, industrial undertaking and different requirements may be so specified for different purposes or with respect to industrial undertakings engaged in the manufacture or production of different articles :</p>
            <blockList id="section-11B.1.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that no industrial undertaking shall be regarded as an ancillary industrial undertaking unless it is, proposed to be, engaged in--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11B.1.list4.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the manufacture of parts, components, sub-assemblies, toolings or intermediates; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11B.1.list4.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>rendering of services, or supplying or rendering, not more than fifty per cent, of its production or its total services, as the case may be, to other units for production of other articles.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11B.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11B.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The factors referred to in sub-section (1) are the following, namely:</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11B.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-11B.2.list1.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>the investment by the industrial undertaking in--</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-11B.2.list1.a.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>plant and machinery, or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-11B.2.list1.a.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>land, buildings, plant and machinery ;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11B.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the nature of ownership of the industrial undertakings;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11B.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the smallness of the number of the workers employed in the industrial undertaking ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11B.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the nature, cost and quality of the product of the industrial undertaking;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11B.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>foreign exchange, if any, required for the import of any plant or machinery by the industrial undertaking ; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11B.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>such other relevant factors as may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11B.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A copy of every notified order proposed to be made under subsection (1) shall be laid in draft before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in disapproving the issue of the proposed notified order or both Houses agree in making any modification in the proposed notified order, the notified order shall not be made, or, as the case may be, shall be made only in such modified form as may be agreed upon by both the Houses.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11B.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), an industrial undertaking which, according to the law for the time being in force, fell, immediately before the commencement of the Industries (Development and Regulation) Amendment Act, 1984 (4 of 1984), under the definition of an ancillary or small scale industrial undertaking, shall, after such commencement, continue to be regarded as an ancillary, or small scale, industrial undertaking for the purposes of this Act until the definition aforesaid is altered or superseded by any notified order made under sub-section (1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Revocation and amendment of licences in certain cases</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the Central Government is satisfied, either on a reference made to it in this behalf or otherwise, that any person or authority, to whom or to which, a licence has been issued under Sec 11, has, without reasonable cause, failed to establish or to take effective steps to establish the new industrial undertaking in respect of which the licence has been issued within the time specified therefore or within such extended time as the Central Government may think fit to grant in any case, it may revoke the licence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to any rules that may be made in this behalf, the Central Government may also vary or amend any licence issued under Section 11:</p>
            <p>Provided that no such power shall be exercised after effective steps have been taken to establish the new industrial undertaking in accordance with the licence issued in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of this section shall apply in relation to a licence issued under Section 11-A or where a licence has been amended under that section, to the amendment thereof, as they apply in relation to a licence issued under Section 11.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Further provision for licensing of industrial undertakings in special cases</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>No owner of an industrial undertaking, other than the Central Government, shall--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in the case of an industrial undertaking required to be registered under Section 10 but which has not been registered within the time fixed for the purpose under that section, carry on the business of that undertaking after the expiry of such period, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in the case of an industrial undertaking the registration in respect of which has been revoked under Sec 10-A , carry on the business of the undertaking after the revocation, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>in the case of an industrial undertaking to which the provisions of this Act did not originally apply but became applicable after the commencement of this Act for any reason, carry on the business of the undertaking after the expiry of three months from the date on which the provisions of this Act became so applicable, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>effect any substantial expansion of an industrial undertaking which has been registered or in respect of which a licence or permission has been issued, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>change the location of the whole or any part of an industrial undertaking which has been registered, except under, and in accordance with, a licence issued in that behalf by the Central Government, and in the case of a State Government, except under and in accordance with the previous permission of the Central Government.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of sub-section (2) of Section 11 and of Section 12 shall apply, so far as may be, in relation to the issue of licences or permissions to any industrial undertaking referred to in this section as they apply in relation to the issue of licences or permissions to a new industrial undertaking.</p>
            <p>Explanation.--For the purposes of this section, "substantial expansion" means the expansion of an existing industrial undertaking which substantially increases the productive capacity of the undertaking, or which is of such a nature as to amount virtually to a new industrial undertaking, but does not include any such expansion as is normal to the undertaking having regard to its nature and the circumstances relating to such expansion.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Procedure for the grant of licence or permission</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Before granting any licence or permission under Section 11, Section 11-A,Section 13, or Section 29-B, the Central Government may require such officer or authority as it may appoint for the purpose, to make a full and complete investigation in respect of applications received in this behalf and report to it the result of such investigation and in making any such investigation, the officer or authority shall follow such procedure as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Power to cause investigation to be made into scheduled industries or industrial undertakings</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-15.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where the Central Government is of the opinion that--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-15.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>in respect of any scheduled industry or industrial undertaking or undertakings--</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>there has been, or is likely to be, a substantial fall in the volume of production in respect of any article or class of articles relatable to that industry or manufactured or produced in the industrial undertaking or undertakings, as the case may be ; for which, having regard to the economic conditions prevailing, there is no justification ; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>there has been, or is likely to be, a marked deterioration in the quality of any article or class of articles relatable to that industry or manufactured or produced in the industrial undertaking or undertakings, as the case may be, which could have been or can be avoided ; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>there has been or is likely to be a rise in the price of any article or class of articles relatable to that industry or manufactured or produced in the industrial undertaking or undertakings, as the case may be, for which there is no justification; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>it is necessary to take any such action as is provided in this Chapter for the purpose of conserving any resources of national importance which are utilised in the industry or the industrial undertaking or undertakings, as the case may be; or</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any industrial undertaking is being managed in a manner highly detrimental to the scheduled industry concerned or to public interest, the Central Government may make or cause to be made a full and complete investigation into the circumstances of the case by such person or body of persons as it may appoint for the purpose.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15A">
        <num>15A.</num>
        <heading>Power to investigate into the affairs of a company in liquidation</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a company, owning an industrial undertaking, is being wound up by or under the supervision of the High Court, and the business of such company is not being continued, the Central Government may, if it is of opinion that it is necessary, in the interests of the general public and, in particular, in the interests of production, supply or distribution of articles or class of articles relatable to the concerned scheduled industry, to investigate into the possibility of running or re-starting the industrial undertaking, make an application to the High Court praying for permission to make, or cause to be made, an investigation into such possibility by such person or body of persons as that Government may appoint for the purpose.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an application is made by the Central Government under sub-section (1), the High Court shall, notwithstanding anything contained in the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), or in any other law for the time being in force, grant the permission prayed for.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Powers of Central Government on completion of investigation under 15</heading>
        <subsection id="section-16.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-16.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If after making or causing to be made any such investigation as is referred to in Section 15 the Central Government is satisfied that action under this section is desirable, it may issue such directions to the industrial undertaking or undertakings concerned as may be appropriate in the circumstances for all or any of the following purposes, namely:</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-16.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>regulating the production of any article or class of articles by the industrial undertaking or undertakings and fixing the standards of production ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>requiring the industrial undertaking or undertakings to take such steps as the Central Government may consider necessary to stimulate the development of the industry to which the undertaking or undertakings relates or relate ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>prohibiting the industrial undertaking or undertakings from resorting to any act or practice which might reduce its or their production, capacity or economic value ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>controlling the prices, or regulating the distribution, of any article or class of articles which have been the subject-matter of investigation.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a case relating to any industry or industrial undertaking or undertakings is under investigation, the Central Government may issue at any time any direction of the nature referred to in sub-section (1) to the industrial undertaking or undertakings concerned , and any such direction shall have effect until it is varied or revoked by the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Special provisions for direct control by Central Government in certain cases Repealed</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Rep. by the Industries (Development and Regulation) Amendment Act, 1953 (26 of 1953), Section 12 (w.e.f. 1st October, 1953).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Power of person or body of persons appointed under 15 to call for assistance in any investigation</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The person or body of persons appointed to make any investigation under Section 15 or Section 15-A may choose one or more persons possessing special knowledge of any matter relating to the investigation to assist him or it in holding the investigation.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The person or body of persons so appointed shall have all the powers of a Civil Court under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), for the purpose of taking evidence on oath (which he or it is hereby empowered to administer) and of enforcing the attendance of witnesses and compelling the production of documents and material objects, and the person or body of persons shall be deemed to be a Civil Court for all the purposes of Section 195 and Chapter XXXV of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18A">
        <num>18A.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to assume management or control of an industrial undertaking in certain cases</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-18A.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If the Central Government is of opinion that--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18A.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>an industrial undertaking to which directions have been issued in pursuance of Section 16 has failed to comply with such directions, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18A.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>an industrial undertaking in respect of which an investigation has been made under See. 15 (whether or not any directions have been issued to the undertaking in pursuance of Section 16), is being managed in a manner highly detrimental to the scheduled industry concerned or to public interest, the Central Government may, by notified order, authorise any person or body of persons to take over the management of the whole or any part of the undertaking or to exercise in respect of the whole or any part of the undertaking such functions of control as may be specified in the order.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any notified order issued under sub-section (1) shall have effect for such period not exceeding five years as may be specified in the order :</p>
            <p>Provided that if the Central Government is of opinion that it is expedient in the public interest that any such notified order should continue to have effect after the expiry of the period of five years aforesaid, it may from time to time issue directions for such continuance for such period, not exceeding two years at a time, as may be specified in the direction, so however that the total period of such continuance (after the expiry of the said period of five years) does not exceed twelve years; and where any such direction is issued, a copy thereof shall be laid, as soon as may be, before both Houses of Parliament.</p>
            <p>Explanation.--The power to authorise a body of persons under this section to take over the management of an industrial undertaking which is a company includes also a power to appoint any individual, firm or company to be the managing agent of the industrial undertaking on such terms and conditions as the Central Government may think fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18AA">
        <num>18AA.</num>
        <heading>Power to take over industrial undertakings without investigation under certain circumstances</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18AA.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-18AA.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Without prejudice to any other provision of this Act, if, from the documentary or other evidence in its possession, the Central Government is satisfied, in relation to an industrial undertaking, that--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18AA.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the persons in charge of such industrial undertaking have, by reckless investments or creation of encumbrances on the assets of the industrial undertaking, or by diversion of funds, brought about a situation which is likely to affect the production of articles manufactured or produced in the industrial undertaking, and that immediate action is necessary to prevent such a situation; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18AA.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>it has been closed for a period of not less than three months (whether by reason of the voluntary winding-up of the company owning the industrial undertaking or for any other reason) and such closure is prejudicial to the concerned scheduled industry and that the financial condition of the company owning the industrial undertaking and the condition of the plant and machinery of such undertaking are such that it is possible to re-start the undertaking and such re-starting is necessary in the interests of the general public,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>it may, by a notified order, authorise any person or body of persons (hereafter referred to as the "authorised person") to take over the management of the whole or any part of the industrial undertaking or to exercise in respect of the whole or any part of the undertaking such functions of control as may be specified in the order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18AA.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of sub-section (2) of Section 18-A shall, as far as may be, apply to a notified order made under sub-section (1) as they apply to a notified order made under sub-section (1) of Section 18-A.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18AA.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing contained in sub-section (1) and sub-section (2) shall apply to an industrial undertaking owned by a company which is being wound up by or under the supervision of the Court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18AA.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any notified order has been made under sub-section (1), the person or body of persons having for the time being, charge of the management or control of the industrial undertaking, whether by or under the orders of any Court or any contract, instrument or otherwise, shall, notwithstanding anything contained in such order, contract, instrument or other arrangements forthwith make over the charge of management or control, as the case may be, of the industrial undertaking to the authorised person.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18AA.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of Sees. 18-B to 18-E (both inclusive) shall as far as may be, apply to or in relation to, the industrial undertaking, in respect of which a notified order has been made under sub-section (1), as they apply to an industrial undertaking in relation to which a notified order has been issued under Section 18-A.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18B">
        <num>18B.</num>
        <heading>Effect of notified order under 18-A</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18B.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-18B.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>On the issue of a notified order under Section 18-A authorizing the taking over of the management of an industrial undertaking,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18B.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>all persons in charge of the management, including persons holding office as managers or directors of the industrial undertaking immediately before the issue of the notified order, shall be deemed to have vacated their office as such;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18B.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any contract of management between the industrial undertaking and any managing agent or any director thereof holding office as such immediately before the issue of the notified order shall be deemed to have been terminated ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18B.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the managing agent, if any appointed under Section 18-A, shall be deemed to have been duly appointed as the managing agent in pursuance of the Indian Companies Act, 1913 (7 of 1913), and the memorandum and articles of association of the industrial under-taking, and the provisions of the said Act and of the memorandum and articles shall, subject to the other provisions contained in this Act, apply accordingly, but no such managing agent shall be removed from office except with the previous consent of the Central Government,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18B.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the person or body of persons authorised under Section 18-A to take over the management shall take all such steps as may be necessary to take into his or their custody or control all the property, effects and actionable claims to which the industrial undertaking is or appears to be entitled, and all the property and effects of the industrial undertaking shall be deemed to be in the custody of the person or, as the case may be, the body of persons as from the date of the notified order ; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18B.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the persons, if any, authorized under Section 18-A to take over the management of an industrial undertaking which is a company shall be for all purposes the directors of the industrial undertaking duly constituted under the Indian Companies Act, 1913 (7 of 1913), and shall alone be entitled to exercise all the powers of the directors of the industrial undertaking, whether such powers are derived from the said Act or from the memorandum or articles of association of the industrial undertaking or from any other source,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18B.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the other provisions contained in this Act and to the control of the Central Government, the person or body of persons authorized to take over the management of an industrial undertaking, shall take such steps as may be necessary for the purpose of efficiently managing the business of the industrial undertaking and shall exercise such other powers and have such other duties as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18B.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any person or body of persons has been authorized to exercise any functions of control in relation to an industrial undertaking, the undertaking shall be carried on pursuant to any directions given by the authorized person in accordance with the provisions of the notified order, and any person having any functions of management in relation to the undertaking or part thereof shall comply with all such directions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18B.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The person or body of persons authorized under Section 18-A shall, notwithstanding anything contained in the memorandum or articles of association of the industrial undertaking, exercise his or their functions in accordance with such directions as may be given by the Central Government so, however, that he or they shall not have any power to give any other person any directions under this section inconsistent with the provisions of any Act or instrument determining the functions of the authority carrying on the undertaking except in so far as may be specifically provided by the notified order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18C">
        <num>18C.</num>
        <heading>Contracts in bad faith, etc., may be cancelled or varied</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18C.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Without prejudice to the provisions contained in Section 18-B, the person or body of persons authorized under Section 18-A to take over the management of an industrial undertaking may, with the previous approval of the Central Government, make an application to any Court having jurisdiction in this behalf for the purpose of cancelling or varying any contract or agreement entered into, at any time before the issue of the notified order under Section 18-A, between the industrial undertaking and any other person and the Court may, if satisfied after due inquiry that such contract or agreement had been entered into in bad faith and is, detrimental to the interests of the industrial undertaking, make an order cancelling or varying (either unconditionally or subject to such conditions as it may think fit to impose) that contract or agreement, and the contract or agreement shall have effect accordingly.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18D">
        <num>18D.</num>
        <heading>No right to compensation for termination of office or contract</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18D.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time being in force, no person who ceases to hold any office by reason of the provisions contained in Cl. (a) of Section 18-B, or whose contract of management is terminated by reason of the provisions contained in Cl. (b) of that section, shall be entitled to any compensation for the loss of office or for the premature termination of his contract of management :</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing contained in this section shall affect the right of any such person to recover from the industrial undertaking moneys recoverable otherwise than by way of such compensation.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18E">
        <num>18E.</num>
        <heading>Application of Act 7 of 1913</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18E.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-18E.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where the management of an industrial undertaking, being a company as defined in the Indian Companies Act, 19131 is taken over by the Central Government, then, notwithstanding anything contained in the said Act or in the memorandum or articles of association of such undertaking,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18E.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>it shall not be lawful for the shareholders of such undertaking or any other person to nominate or appoint any person to be a director of the undertaking ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18E.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>no resolution passed at any meeting of the shareholders of such undertaking shall be given effect to unless approved by the Central Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18E.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>no proceeding for the winding-up of such undertaking or for the appointment of a Receiver in respect thereof shall lie in any Court except with the consent of the Central Government.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18E.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions contained in sub-section (1), and to the other provisions contained in this Act and subject to such other exceptions, restrictions and limitations, if any, as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf, the Indian Companies Act, 1913, shall continue to apply to such undertaking in the same manner as it applied thereto before the issue of the notified order under Section 18-A.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18F">
        <num>18F.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to cancel notified order under 18-A</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18F.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If at any time it appears to the Central Government on the application of the owner of the industrial undertaking or otherwise that the purpose of the order made under Section 18-A has been fulfilled or that for any other reason it is not necessary that the order should remain in force, the Central Government may, by notified order, cancel such order and on the cancellation of any such order the management or the control, as the case may be, of the industrial undertaking shall vest in the owner of the undertaking.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18FA">
        <num>18FA.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to authorise, with the permission of the High Court, persons to take over management or control of industrial undertakings</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18FA.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the Central Government is of opinion that there are possibilities of running or re-starting an industrial undertaking, in relation to which an investigation has been made under Section 15-A, and that such industrial undertaking should be run or re-started, as the case may be, for maintaining or increasing the production, supply or distribution of articles or class of articles relatable to the scheduled industry, needed by the general public, that Government may make an application to the High Court praying for permission to appoint any person or body of persons to take over the management of the industrial undertaking or to exercise in respect of the whole or any part of the industrial undertaking such functions of control as may be specified in the application.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FA.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an application is made under sub-section (1), the High Court shall make an order empowering the Central Government to authorise any of person or body of persons (hereinafter referred to as the "authorised person" to take over the management of the industrial undertaking or to exercise functions of control in relation to the whole or any part of the industrial undertaking (hereinafter referred to as the "concerned part") for a period not exceeding five years :</p>
            <p>Provided that if the Central Government is- of opinion that it is expedient in the interests of the general public that the authorised person should continue to manage the industrial undertaking or continue to exercise functions of control in relation to the concerned part, as the case may be, after the expiry of the period of five years aforesaid, it may make an application to the High Court for the continuance of such management or functions of control, for such period not exceeding two years at a time, as may be specified in the application and thereupon the High Court may make an order permitting the authorised person to continue to manage the industrial undertaking or to exercise functions of control in relation to the concerned part:</p>
            <p>Provided further that the total period of such continuance (after the expiry of the initial period of five years) shall not, in any case, be permitted to exceed twelve years.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FA.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an order has been made by the High Court under sub-section (2), the High Court shall direct the Official Liquidator or any other person having, for the time being, charge of the management or control of the industrial undertaking, whether by or under the orders of any Court, or any contract or instrument or otherwise, to make over the management of such undertaking or the concerned part, as the case may be, to the authorised person and thereupon the authorised person shall be deemed to be the Official Liquidator in respect of the industrial undertaking or the concerned part, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FA.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Before making over the possession of the industrial undertaking or the concerned part to the authorised person, the Official Liquidator shall make a complete inventory of all the assets and liabilities of the industrial undertaking or the concerned part, as the case may be, in the manner specified in Section 18-FG and deliver a copy of such inventory to the authorised person, who shall, after verifying the correctness thereof, sign on the duplicate copy thereof as evidence of the receipt of the inventory by him.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FA.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On taking over the management of the industrial undertaking, or on the commencement of the exercise of functions of control in relation to the concerned part, the authorised person shall take immediate steps to so run the industrial undertaking or the concerned part as to ensure the maintenance of production.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FA.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The authorised person may, on such terms and conditions and subject to such limitations or restrictions as may be prescribed, raise any loan for the purpose of running the industrial undertaking or the concerned part, and may, for that purpose, create a floating charge on the current assets of the industrial undertaking or the concerned part, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FA.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the authorised person is of opinion that the replacement or repair of any machinery of the industrial undertaking or the concerned part is necessary for the purpose of efficient running of the industrial undertaking or such part, he shall on such terms and conditions and subject to such limitations or restrictions as may be prescribed, make such replacement or repair, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FA.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The loan obtained by the authorised person shall be recovered from the assets of the industrial undertaking or the concerned part, in such manner and subject to such conditions as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FA.9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of running the industrial undertaking, or exercising functions of control in relation to the concerned part, the authorised person may employ such of the former employees of the industrial undertaking whose services became discharged by reason of the winding-up of the company owning such undertaking and every such person employed by the authorised person shall be deemed to have entered into a fresh contract of service with the company.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FA.10">
          <num>(10)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-18FA.10.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The proceedings in the winding-up of the company in so far as they relate to--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18FA.10.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the industrial undertaking, the management of which has been taken over by the authorised person under this section, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18FA.10.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the concerned part in relation to which any function of control is exercised by the authorised person under this section,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall, during the period of such management or control, remain stayed, and, in computing the period of limitation for the enforcement of any right, privilege, obligation or liability in relation to such undertaking or the concerned part, the period during which such proceedings remained stayed shall be excluded.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18FB">
        <num>18FB.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to make certain declarations in relation to industrial undertakings, the management or control of which has been taken over under 18-A, 18-AA or 18-FA</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18FB.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-18FB.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government may, if it is satisfied, in relation to an industrial undertaking or any part thereof, the management or control of which has been taken over under Section 18-A, whether before or after the commencement of the Industries (Development and Regulation) Amendment Act, 1971 (72 of 1971) or under Section 18-AA or Section 18-FA, that it is necessary so to do in the interests of the general public with a view to preventing fall in the volume of production of any scheduled industry, it may, by notified order, declare that--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18FB.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>all or any of the enactments specified in the Third Schedule shall not apply or shall apply with such adaptations whether by way of modification, addition or omission (which does not, however, affect the policy of the said enactments) to such industrial undertaking, as may be specified in such notified order, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18FB.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the operation of all or any, of the contracts, assurances of property, agreements, settlements, awards, standing orders or other instruments in force (to which such industrial undertaking or the company owning such undertaking is a party or which may be applicable to such industrial undertaking or company) immediately before the date of issue of such notified order shall remain suspended or that all or any of the rights, privileges, obligations and liabilities accruing or arising thereunder before the said date, shall remain suspended or shall be enforceable with such adaptations and in such manner as may be specified in the notified order.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FB.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The notified order made under sub-section (1) shall remain in force, in the first instance, for a period of one year, but the duration of such notified order may be extended from time to time by a further notified order by a period not exceeding one year at a time :</p>
            <blockList id="section-18FB.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that no such notified order shall, in any case, remain in force--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18FB.2.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>after the expiry of the period for which the management of the industrial undertaking was taken over under Section 18-A, Section 18-AA or Section 18-FA, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18FB.2.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>for more than eight years in the aggregate from the date of issue of the first notified order, whichever is earlier.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FB.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any notified order made under sub-section (1) shall have effect notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any other law, agreement or instrument or any decree or order of a Court, tribunal, officer or other authority or of any submission, settlement or standing order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FB.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-18FB.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any remedy for the enforcement of any right, privilege, obligation or liability referred to in Cl. (b) of sub-section (1) and suspended or modified by a notified order made under that sub-section shall, in accordance with the terms of the notified order, remain suspended or modified, and all proceedings relating thereto pending before any Court, tribunal, officer or other authority shall accordingly remain stayed or be continued subject to such adaptations, so, however, that on the notified order ceasing to have effect--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18FB.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any right, privilege, obligation or liability so remaining suspended or modified shall become revived and enforceable as if the notified order had never been made ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18FB.4.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any proceeding so remaining stayed shall be proceeded with, subject to the provisions of any law which may then be in force, from the stage which had been reached when the proceedings became stayed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FB.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In computing the period of limitation for the enforcement of any right, privilege, obligation or liability referred to in Cl. (b) of sub-section (1), the period during which it or the remedy for the enforcement thereof remained suspended shall be excluded.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18FC">
        <num>18FC.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to call for report on the affairs and working of managed company</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18FC.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where the management or control of an industrial undertaking has been taken over under Section 18-A, whether before or after the commencement of the Industries (Development and Regulation) Amendment Act, 1971 (72 of 1971), or under Section 18-AA or Section 18-FA, the Central Government may, at any time during the continuance of such management or control, call for a report from the authorised person on the affairs and working of the industrial undertaking and in submitting the report the authorised person shall take into account the inventory and the lists of members and creditors prepared under Section 18-FG.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18FD">
        <num>18FD.</num>
        <heading>Decision of Central Government in relation to managed company</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18FD.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-18FD.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If, on receipt of the report submitted by the authorised person, the Central Government is satisfied,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18FD.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in relation to the company owning the industrial undertaking, which is not being wound up by the High Court, that the financial condition and other circumstances of the company are such that it is not in a position to meet its current liabilities out of its current assets, that Government may, if it considers necessary or expedient in the interests of the general public so to do, by order, decide that the industrial undertaking should be sold as a running concern as provided in Section 18-FE and proceedings should simultaneously be started for the winding-up, by the High Court, of the company ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18FD.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in relation to the company, owning the industrial undertaking, which is being wound up by the High Court, that its assets and liabilities are such that in the interests of its creditors and contributories the industrial undertaking should be sold as a running concern as provided in Section 18-FE, it may, by order decide accordingly.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FD.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-18FD.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), if on receipt of the report submitted by the authorised person, the Central Government is satisfied that--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18FD.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in the interests of the general public, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18FD.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in the interests of the shareholders, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18FD.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to secure the proper management of the company owning the industrial undertaking,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>it is necessary so to do, that Government may, by order, decide to prepare a scheme for the reconstruction of the company owning the industrial undertaking :</p>
            <p>Provided that no such scheme shall be prepared in relation to a company which is being wound up by or under the supervision of the High Court, except with the previous permission of that Court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FD.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The powers exercisable by the Central Government under Section 18-F, in relation to an undertaking taken over under Section 18-A, shall also be exercisable in relation to an undertaking taken over under Section 18-AA or Section 18-FA, but such powers shall not be exercised after the making of an order under sub-section (1) or, as the case may be, under sub-section (2) of this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18FE">
        <num>18FE.</num>
        <heading>Provisions where Government decides to follow the course of action specified in 18-FD (1)</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18FE.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-18FE.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The provisions hereinafter laid down shall apply where the Central Government decides that the course of action specified in sub-section (1) of Section 18-FD should be followed, namely :</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18FE.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the decision of the Central Government that the course of action specified in Cl. (a) of sub-section (1) Section 18-FD should be followed in relation to a company owning an industrial undertaking shall be deemed to be a ground specified in Section 433 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), on which the company may be wound up by the High Court ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18FE.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the authorised person shall, as soon as may be, after the decision specified in Cl. (a) of sub-section (1) of Section 18-FD has been taken by the Central Government, present an application to the High Court for the winding-up of the company owning the industrial undertaking;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18FE.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>when an application is made by the authorised person, under Cl. (b), for the winding-up, by the High Court, of the company owning the industrial undertaking, the High Court shall order the winding-up of the company and shall, notwithstanding anything contained in the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), appoint the authorised person as the Official Liquidator in relation to such undertaking;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18FE.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>whenever the Central Government decides under Cl. (b) of sub-section (1) of Section 18-FD that the industrial undertaking should be sold as a running concern, it shall cause a copy of its decision to be laid before the High Court;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18FE.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>until the industrial undertaking referred to in Cl. (a) or Cl. (b) of sub-section (1) of Section 18-FD is sold or purchased in pursuance undertaking in the winding-up proceedings of the company, and thereafter the Official Liquidator appointed by the Central Government under Section 448 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), shall take over and function as the Official Liquidator in the said proceedings.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FE.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The authorised person shall make a report to the Central Government as to what should be the reserve price for the sale of the industrial undertaking as a running concern.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FE.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-18FE.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In making a report under sub-section (2), the authorised person shall have regard to--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18FE.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-18FE.3.list1.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>the financial condition of the company owning the industrial undertaking on the date on which the order under Section 18-FD is made--</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-18FE.3.list1.a.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>as disclosed in its books of account,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-18FE.3.list1.a.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>as disclosed in its balance-sheet and profit and loss account during a period of five years immediately preceding the said date ;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18FE.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the condition and nature of the plant, machinery, instruments and other equipment from the point of view of their suitability for profitable use in the running of the industrial undertaking;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18FE.3.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the total amount of liability on account of secured and unsecured debts including overdrafts, if any, drawn on banks, liabilities on account of terminal benefits to the employees and other borrowings and liabilities of the company; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18FE.3.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>other relevant factors including the factor that the industrial undertaking will be sold free from all incumbrances.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FE.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notice of the reserve price determined by the authorised person shall be given in such manner as may be prescribed to the members and creditors of the company owning such industrial undertaking to make representations within a specified time to the Central Government through the authorised person and the Central Government shall, after considering the representations received and the report of the authorised person, determine the reserve price.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FE.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The authorised person shall thereafter, with the permission of the High Court, invite tenders from the public in such manner as may be determined by the High Court for the sale of the industrial undertaking as a running concern subject to the condition that it will be sold to the person offering the highest price which shall not be less than the reserve price determined under sub-section (4) :</p>
            <p>Provided that the High Court shall not refuse to grant such permission if it is satisfied that the company is not in a position to meet its current liabilities out of its current assets.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FE.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The industrial undertaking shall be sold to the highest bidder, as a running concern, only if the price offered by him therefore is not less than the reserve price.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FE.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where no offer of price is equal to, or more than, the reserve price, the industrial undertaking shall be purchased by the Central Government at the reserve price.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FE.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-18FE.8.list0">
              <item id="section-18FE.8.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>The amount realised from the sale of the industrial undertaking as a running concern together with any other sum which may be realised from any contributory, purchaser or any other person from whom any money is due to the company shall be utilised in accordance with the provisions of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 to 1956), on discharging the liabilities of the company and distributing the balance, if any, amongst the members of the company.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18FE.8.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>In other respects, the provisions of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), relating to the winding-up of a company by High Court shall, as far as may be, apply.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FE.9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When an industrial undertaking is sold to any person under sub-section (6), or purchased by the Central Government under sub-section (7), there shall be transferred to and vested in the purchaser, free from all incumbrances, all such assets relating to the industrial undertaking as are referred to in sub-clause (i) of Cl. (a) of Section 18-FG and existing at the time of the sale or purchase.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18FF">
        <num>18FF.</num>
        <heading>Provisions where Government decides to follow the course of action specified in 18-FD (2)</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18FF.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where in any case the Central Government decides that the course of action specified in sub-section (2) of Section 18-FD should be followed, it shall, subject to the provisions of that sub-section, cause to be prepared, by the authorised person, a scheme for the reconstruction of the company, owning the industrial undertaking, in accordance with the provisions hereinafter contained and the authorised person shall submit the same for the approval of that Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FF.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-18FF.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The scheme for the reconstruction of the company owning the industrial undertaking may contain provisions for all or any of the following matters, namely :</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18FF.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the constitution, name and registered offices, the capital, assets, powers, rights, interests, authorities and privileges, the liabilities, duties and obligations of the company on its reconstruction;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18FF.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any change in the Board of Directors, or the appointment of a new Board of Directors of the company on its reconstruction and the authority by whom, the manner in which and the other terms, and conditions on which, such change or appointment shall be made and in the case of appointment of a new Board of Directors or of any director, the period for which such appointment shall be made;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18FF.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the vesting of controlling interest, in the reconstructed company, in the Central Government either by the appointment of additional directors or by the allotment of additional shares ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18FF.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the alteration of the memorandum and articles of association of the company, on its reconstruction, to give effect to such reconstruction;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18FF.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>subject to the provisions of the scheme, the continuation by or against the company on its reconstruction, of any action or proceedings pending against the company immediately before the date of its reconstruction;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18FF.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the reduction of the interest or rights which the members and creditors have in or against the company before its reconstruction to such extent as the Central Government may consider necessary in the interests of the general public or in the interests of the members and creditors or for the maintenance of the business of the company :</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-18FF.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that nothing contained in this clause shall be deemed to authorise the reduction of the interest or rights of any creditor (including Government) in respect of any loan or advance made by that creditor to the company after the date on which the management of the industrial undertaking of the company has been taken over under Section 18-A, Section 18-AA, or Section 18-FA ;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18FF.2.list3.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <blockList id="section-18FF.2.list3.g.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>the payment in cash or otherwise to the creditors in full satisfaction of their claim,--</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-18FF.2.list3.g.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>in respect of their interest or rights in or against the company before its reconstruction; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-18FF.2.list3.g.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>where their interest or rights in or against the company has or have been reduced under Cl. (f), in respect of such, interest, or rights as so reduced ;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18FF.2.list3.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the allotment to the members of the company for shares held by them therein before its reconstruction whether their interest in such shares has been reduced under Cl. (f) or not, of shares in the company on its reconstruction and where it is not possible to allot shares to any members, the payment in cash to those members in full satisfaction of their claim--</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FF.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>in respect of their interest in shares in the company before its reconstruction ; or</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FF.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-18FF.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>where such interest has been reduced under Cl. (f), in respect of their interest in shares as so reduced;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18FF.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the offer by the Central Government to acquire by negotiations with the members of the company their respective shares on payment in cash to those members who may volunteer to sell their shares to the Central Government in full satisfaction of their claim--</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FF.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>in respect of their interest in shares in the company before its reconstruction ; or</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FF.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-18FF.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>where such interest has been reduced under Cl. (f), in respect of their interest in shares as so reduced ;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18FF.2.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>the conversion of any debentures issued by the company after the taking over of the management of the company under Section 18-A or Section 18-AA or Section 18-FA or of any loans obtained by the company after that date or of any part of such debentures or loans, into shares in the company and the allotment of those shares to such debenture-holders or creditors, as the case may be ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18FF.2.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>the increase of the capital of the company by the issue of new shares and the allotment of such new shares to the Central Government ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18FF.2.list1.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>the continuance of the services of such of the employees of the company as the Central Government may specify in the scheme in the company itself, on its reconstruction, on such terms and conditions as the Central Government thinks fit ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18FF.2.list1.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>notwithstanding anything contained in Cl. (l), where any employees of the company whose services have been continued under Cl. (l), have, by notice in writing given to the company at any time before the expiry of one month next following the date on which the scheme is sanctioned by the High Court, intimated their intention of not becoming employees of the company, on its reconstruction, the payment to such employees and to other employees whose services have not been continued on the reconstruction of the company, of compensation, if any, to which they are entitled under the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 (14 of 1947), and such pension, gratuity, provident fund and other retirement benefits ordinarily admissible to them under the rules or authorisations of the company immediately before the date of its reconstruction;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18FF.2.list1.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>any other terms and conditions for the reconstruction of the company ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18FF.2.list1.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>such incidental, consequential and supplemental matters as are necessary to secure that the reconstruction of the company shall be fully and effectively carried out.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FF.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-18FF.3.list0">
              <item id="section-18FF.3.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>A copy of the scheme, as approved by the Central Government, shall be sent in draft to the company, to the registered trade unions, if any, of which the employees of the company are members and to the creditors thereof for suggestions and objections, if any, within such period as the Central Government may specify for this purpose.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18FF.3.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>The Central Government may make such modifications, if any, in the draft scheme as it may consider necessary in the light of the suggestions and objections received from the company, from the registered trade unions of which the employees of the company are members and from any members or creditors of the company.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FF.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The scheme shall thereafter be placed before the High Court for its sanction and the High Court, if satisfied that the scheme is in the interests of the general public or in the interests of the shareholders or for securing the proper management of the company and that the scheme is designed to be fair and reasonable to the members and creditors of the company, may, after giving a reasonable opportunity to the company and to its members and creditors of showing cause, sanction the scheme without any modification or with such modifications as it may consider necessary.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FF.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The scheme, as so sanctioned by the High Court shall come into force on such date as that Court may specify in this behalf:</p>
            <p>Provided that different dates may be specified for different provisions of the scheme.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FF.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The sanction accorded by the High Court under sub-section (4) shall be conclusive evidence that all the requirements of this section relating to the reconstruction of the company have been complied with, and a copy of the sanctioned scheme certified by the High Court to be a true copy thereof, shall, in all legal proceedings (whether original or in appeal or otherwise), be admitted as evidence to the same extent as the original scheme.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FF.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On and from the date of the coming into operation of the scheme or any provision thereof, the scheme or such provision shall be binding on the company and also on all the members and other creditors and employees of the company and on any other person having any right or liability in relation to the company.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FF.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On the coming into operation of the scheme or any provision thereof, the authorised person shall cease to function, and the management of the reconstucted company shall be assumed by the Board of Directors as provided in the scheme.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FF.9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Copies of the scheme shall be laid before each House of Parliament, as soon as may be, after the scheme has been sanctioned by the Court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18FF.10">
          <num>(10)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of this section and of any scheme made thereunder shall have the effect notwithstanding anything contained in Secs. 391 to 394-A (both inclusive) of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18FG">
        <num>18FG.</num>
        <heading>Preparation of inventory of assets and liabilities and list of members and creditors of managed company</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18FG.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-18FG.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>For the purposes of this Act, the authorised person shall, as soon as may be, after taking over the management of the industrial undertaking of a company under Section 18-A or Section 18-AA or Section 18-FA,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18FG.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-18FG.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>prepare a complete inventory of--</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-18FG.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>all properties, movable and immovable, including lands, buildings, works, workshops, stores, instruments, plant, machinery, automobiles and other vehicles, stocks of materials in the course of production, storage or transit, raw materials, cash balances, cash in hand, deposits in bank or with any other person or body or on loan, reserve funds, investments and book debts and all other rights and interests arising out of such property as were immediately before the date of taking over of the industrial undertaking, in the ownership, possession, power or control of the company, whether within or without India ; and all books of account, registers, maps, plans, sections, drawings, records, documents or titles of ownership of property and all other documents of whatever nature relating thereto ; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-18FG.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>all borrowings, liabilities and obligations of whatever kind of the company including liability on account of terminal benefits to its employees subsisting immediately before the said date ;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18FG.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>prepare separately a list of members, and a list of creditors, of such company as on the date of taking over of the management of the industrial undertaking showing separately in the list of creditors, the secured creditors and the unsecured creditors :</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that where the management of the industrial undertaking of a company has been taken over under the said Section 18-A before the commencement of the Industries (Development and Regulation) Amendment Act, 1971 (72 of 1971), the aforesaid functions shall be performed by the authorised person within six months from such commencement.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18FH">
        <num>18FH.</num>
        <heading>Stay of suits and other proceedings</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18FH.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In the case of a company in respect of which an order under Section 18-FD has been made, no suit or other legal proceeding shall be instituted or continued against the company except with the previous permission of the Central Government or any officer or authority authorised by that Government in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18G">
        <num>18G.</num>
        <heading>Power to control supply, distribution, price, etc. of certain articles</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18G.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government, so far as it appears to it to be necessary or expedient for securing the equitable distribution and availability at fair prices of any article or class of articles relatable to any scheduled industry, may, notwithstanding anything contained in any other provisions of this Act, by notified order, provide of regulating the supply and distribution thereof and trade and commerce therein.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18G.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-18G.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Without prejudice to the generality of the powers conferred by sub-section (1), a notified order made thereunder may provide--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18G.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for controlling the prices at which any such article or class thereof may be bought or sold ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18G.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>for regulating by licences, permits or otherwise the distribution, transport, disposal, acquisition, possession, use or consumption of any such article or class thereof ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18G.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>for prohibiting the withholding from sale of any such article or class thereof ordinarily kept for sale ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18G.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>for requiring any person manufacturing, producing or holding in stock any such article or class thereof to sell the whole or part of the articles so manufactured or produced during a specified period or to sell the whole or a part of the articles so held in stock to such person or class of persons and in such circumstances as may be specified in the order ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18G.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>for regulating or prohibiting any class of commercial or financial transactions relating to such article or class thereof which in the opinion of the authority making the order are, or if unregulated are likely to be detrimental to public interest ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18G.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>for requiring persons engaged in the distribution and trade and commerce in any such article or class thereof to mark the articles exposed or intended for sale with sale price or to exhibit at some easily accessible place on the premises the price-lists of articles held for sale and also to similarly exhibit on the first clay of every month, or at such other time as may be prescribed, a statement of the total quantities of any such articles in stock ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18G.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>for collecting any information or statistics with a view to regulating or prohibiting any of the aforesaid matters ; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18G.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>for any incidental or supplementary matters, including, in particular, the grant or issue of licences, permits or other documents and the charging of fees therefore.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18G.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-18G.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where, in pursuance of any order made with reference to Cl. (d) of sub-section (2), any person sells any article, there shall be paid to him the price therefore--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18G.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>where the price can consistently with the controlled price, if any, be fixed by agreement, the price so agreed upon ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18G.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>where no such agreement can be reached, the price calculated with reference to the controlled price, if any, fixed under this section ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18G.3.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>where neither Cl. (a) nor Cl. (b) applies, the price calculated at the market rate prevailing in the locality at the date of sale.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18G.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No order made in exercise of any power conferred by this section shall be called in question in any Court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18G.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an order purports to have been made and signed by an authority in exercise of any power conferred by this section, a Court shall, within the meaning of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872), presume that such order was so made by that authority.</p>
            <p>Explanation.---In this section, the expression "article or class of articles" relatable to any scheduled industry includes any article or class of articles imported into India which is of the same nature or description as the article or class of articles manufactured or produced in the scheduled industry.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Powers of inspection</heading>
        <subsection id="section-19.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-19.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>For the purpose of ascertaining the position or working of any industrial undertaking or for any other purpose mentioned in this Act or the rules made thereunder, any person authorised by the Central Government in this behalf shall have the right--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-19.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to enter and inspect any premises ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to order the production of any document, book, register or record in the possession or power of any person having the control of, or employed in connection with, any industrial undertaking ; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to examine any person having the control of, or employed in connection with, any industrial undertaking.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person authorized by the Central Government under sub-section (1) shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of Section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>General prohibition of taking over management or control of industrial undertakings</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>After the commencement of this Act, it shall not be competent for any State Government or a local authority to take over the management or control of any industrial undertaking under any law for the time being in force which authorizes any such Government or local authority so to do.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Certain administrative expenses of Development Councils to be paid from moneys provided by Parliament</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Such administrative expenses as relate to the emoluments of officers of a Development Council who are appointed by or with the approval of the Central Government, shall be defrayed out of moneys provided by Parliament.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Power of the Central Government to issue directions to Development Councils</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In the exercise of its functions under this Act, every Development Council shall be guided by such instructions as may be given to it by the Central Government and such instructions may include directions relating to the manner in which, and the purpose for which, any proceeds of the cess levied under Section 9 which may have been handed over to it, shall be expanded.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Decision of Central Government final respecting certain matters</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-23.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If, for the purposes of this Act, any question arises as to whether--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-23.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>there has been a substantial expansion of an industrial undertaking, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-23.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>an industrial undertaking is producing or manufacturing any new article,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>the decision of the Central Government thereon shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Penalties</heading>
        <subsection id="section-24.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-24.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If any person contravenes or attempts to contravene or abets the contravention of--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-24.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the provisions of sub-section (1),or sub-section (4) of Section 10 or of sub-section (1) of Section 11 or of Section 11-A or of sub-section (1) of Section 13or of sub-sections (2), (2-A), (2-D), (2-F) and (2-G) of Section 29-B, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.1.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>any direction issued under Section 16 or sub-section (3) of Section 18-B, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.1.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>any order made under Section 18-G, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.1.list1.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>any rule, the contravention of which, is made punishable under this section, he shall be punishable with imprisonment which may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees, or with both, and, in the case of a continuing contravention, with an additional fine which may extend to five hundred rupees for every day during which such contravention continues after conviction for the first such contravention.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the person contravening any of the said provisions is a company every person who at the time the offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible to the company, for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the contravention and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly :</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to any punishment provided in this Act, if he proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or that he exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (2), where an offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any director or manager, secretary, or other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary or other officer shall be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.</p>
            <blockList id="section-24.3.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation.--For the purposes of this section,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-24.3.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"company" means any body corporate and includes a firm or other association of individuals; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.3.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"director" in relation to a firm means a partner in the firm.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24A">
        <num>24A.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for false statements</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-24A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-24A.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If any person,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-24A.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>when required by this Act or by any order under this Act to make any statement or furnish any information, makes any statement or furnishes any information which is false in any material particular and which he knows or has reasonable cause to believe to be false or does not believe to be true ; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24A.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>makes any such statement as aforesaid in any book, account, record, declaration, return or other document which he is required by any order made under this Act to maintain or furnish ;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>he shall be punishable with imprisonment which may extend to three months or with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Delegation of powers</heading>
        <subsection id="section-25.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notified order, direct that any power exercisable by it under this Act (other than the power given to it by Secs. 16,18-A, 18-AA and 18-FA) shall, in relation to such matters, and subject; to such conditions, if any, as may be specified in the direction, be exercisable also by such officer or authority (including in the said expressions any Development Council, State Government or officer or authority subordinate to the Central Government) as may be specified in the direction.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any power exercisable by a State Government by virtue of a direction under sub-section (1) may, unless otherwise provided in such direction, be exercised also by such officer or authority subordinate to that State Government as it may, by notified order, specify in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Power to issue directions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may give directions to any State Government as to the carrying into execution in the State of any of the provisions of this Act or of any order or direction made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Cognizance of offences</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No Court shall take cognizance of any offence punishable under this Act except on a report in writing of the facts constituting such offence made by a person who is a public servant as defined in Section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28">
        <num>28.</num>
        <heading>Burden of proof in certain cases</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where any person is prosecuted for contravening any order made under Section 18-G which prohibits him from doing an act or being in possession of a thing without lawful authority or without a permit, licence or other document, the burden of proving that he has such authority, permit, licence or other document shall be on him.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29">
        <num>29.</num>
        <heading>Jurisdiction of Courts</heading>
        <subsection id="section-29.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of subsection (2), no Court inferior to that of a Presidency Magistrate or a Magistrate of the first class shall try any offence punishable under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any Magistrate or bench of Magistrates empowered, for the time being, to try in a summary way the offence specified in sub-section (1) of Section 260 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898),may, on application in this behalf being made by the prosecution, try in accordance with the provisions contained in Sections 262 to 265 of the said Code any offence which consists of a contravention of an order made under Section 18-G.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29A">
        <num>29A.</num>
        <heading>Special provision regarding fines</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-29A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in Section 32 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898), 1 it shall be lawful for any Magistrate of the first class and for any Presidency Magistrate to pass a sentence of fine exceeding one thousand rupees on any person convicted of any offence under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29B">
        <num>29B.</num>
        <heading>Power to exempt in special cases</heading>
        <subsection id="section-29B.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the Central Government is of opinion, having regard to the smallness of the number of workers employed or to the amount invested in any industrial undertaking or to the desirability of encouraging small undertakings generally or to the stage of development of any scheduled industry, that it would not be in public interest to apply all or any of the provisions of this Act thereto, it may, by notification in the Official Gazette, exempt, subject to such conditions as it may think fit to impose, any industrial undertaking or class of industrial undertakings or any scheduled industry or class of scheduled industries as it may specify in the notification from the operation of all or any of the provisions of this Act or of any rule or order made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29B.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any notification under sub-section (1) granting any exemption is cancelled, no owner of any industrial undertaking to which the provisions of Section 10, Section 11, Section 11-A or Cl. (d) of sub-section (1) of Section 13 would have applied, if the notification under sub-section (1), had not been issued, shall carry on the business of the undertaking after the expiry of such period as may be specified in the notification cancelling the exemption except under and in accordance with a licence issued in this behalf by the Central Government and in the case of a State Government, except under and in accordance with the previous permission of the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29B.2A">
          <num>(2A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the provisions of sub-section (1), the Central Government may, if it is satisfied, after considering the recommendations made to it by the Advisory Committee constituted under sub-section (2-B), that it is necessary so to do for the development and expansion of ancillary, or small scale, industrial undertakings, by notified order, direct that any article or class of articles specified in the First Schedule shall, on and from such date as may be specified in the notified order (hereafter in this section referred to as the "date of reservation"), be reserved for exclusive production by the ancillary, or small scale, industrial undertakings (hereafter in this section referred to as "reserved article").</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29B.2B">
          <num>(2B)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government shall, with a view to determining the nature of any article or class of articles that may be reserved for production by the ancillary or small scale, industrial undertaking, constitute an Advisory Committee consisting of such persons as have in the opinion of that Government, the necessary expertise to give advice on the matter.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29B.2C">
          <num>(2C)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-29B.2C.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Advisory Committee shall, after considering the following matters, communicate its recommendations to the Central Government, namely :</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-29B.2C.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the nature of any article or class of articles which may be produced economically by the ancillary, or small scale, industrial undertakings ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-29B.2C.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the level of employment likely to be generated by the production of such article or class of articles by the ancillary, or small scale, industrial undertakings;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-29B.2C.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the possibility of encouraging and diffusing entrepreneurship in industry;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-29B.2C.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the prevention of concentration of economic power to the common detriment; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-29B.2C.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>such other matters as the Advisory Committee may think fit.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29B.2D">
          <num>(2D)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The production of any reserved article or class of reserved articles by any industrial undertaking (not being an ancillary, or small scale, industrial undertaking) which, on the date of reservation, is engaged in, or has taken effective steps for the production of any reserved articles or class of reserved articles, shall, after the commencement of the Industries (Development and Regulation) Amendment Act, 1984 (4 of 1984), or, as the case may be, the date of reservation, whichever is later, be subject to such conditions as the Central Government may, by notified order, specify.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29B.2E">
          <num>(2E)</num>
          <content>
            <p>While specifying any condition under sub-section (2-D), the Central Government may take into consideration the level of production of any reserved article or class of reserved articles achieved, immediately before the date of reservation, by the industrial undertaking referred to in sub-section (2-D), and such other factors as may be relevant.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29B.2F">
          <num>(2F)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every person or authority, not being the Central Government, who or which, is registered under Section 10 or to whom, or to which, a licence has been issued or permission has been granted under Section 11 for the production of any article or class of articles which has, or have, been subsequently reserved for the ancillary, or small scale industrial undertakings, shall produce, such registration certificate, licence or permission, as the case may be, within such period as the Central Government may, by notified order, specify in this behalf, and the Central Government may enter therein all or any of the conditions specified by it under sub-section (2-D), including the productive capacity of the industrial undertakings and other prescribed particulars.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29B.2G">
          <num>(2G)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-29B.2G.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The owner of every industrial undertaking (not being an ancillary or small scale, industrial undertaking) which, immediately before the commencement of the Industries (Development and Regulation) Amendment Act, 1984 (4 of 1984), or the date of reservation, whichever is later,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-29B.2G.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>was engaged in the production of any article or class of articles, which has, or have, been reserved for the ancillary, or small scale, industrial undertakings, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-29B.2G.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>had before such commencement or before the date of such reservation, as the case may be, taken effective steps for commencing the production of such reserved article or class of reserved articles,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>without being registered under Section 10 or in respect of which a licence or permission has not been issued under Section 11, shall refrain from the production of such reserved article or class of reserved articles, on and from the date of expiry of three months from such commencement or from the date of such reservation, whichever is later.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29B.2H">
          <num>(2H)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every notified order made under sub-section (2-A) shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session for a total period of thirty days, which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the notified order or both Houses agree that the notified order should not be made, the notified order shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that notified order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29B.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of this Act shall apply, so far as may be, in relation to the issue of a licence or permission to any industrial undertaking referred to in sub-section (2) as they apply in relation to the issue of a licence or permission to a new industrial undertaking.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29C">
        <num>29C.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken under the Act</heading>
        <subsection id="section-29C.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any person for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or any rule or order made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29C.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Government for any damage caused or likely to be caused by anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any rule or order made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29D">
        <num>29D.</num>
        <heading>Debts incurred by the authorized person to have priority</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-29D.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-29D.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Every debt arising out of any loan obtained by the authorised person for carrying on the management of, or exercising function of control in relation to, an industrial undertaking or part thereof, the management of which has been taken over under Section 18-A or Section 18-AA or Section 18-FA,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-29D.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>shall have priority over all other debts, whether secured or unsecured, incurred before the management of such industrial undertaking was taken over,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-29D.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>shall be a preferential debt within the meaning of Section 530 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956),</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>and such debts shall rank equally among themselves and be paid in full out of the assets of the industrial undertakings unless such assets are insufficient to meet them, in which case they shall abate in equal proportions.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29E">
        <num>29E.</num>
        <heading>Validation</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-29E.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any judgment, decree or order of any court, tribunal or other authority, any power exercised, or action taken or done or purported to have been taken or done, by the Central Government or, as the case may be, the State Government, shall be deemed to be, and shall always deemed to have been, for all purposes, as validly taken or done or omitted to be done, as if the amendment made to the First Schedule by the Industries (Development and Regulation) Amendment Act, 2016 had been in force at all material times and no suit or claim or other proceedings shall be instituted, maintained or continued in any court, tribunal or other authority as such.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-30">
        <num>30.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules</heading>
        <subsection id="section-30.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government, may, subject to the condition of previous publication, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-30.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-30.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely :</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-30.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the constitution of the Advisory Council and Development Councils, the term of office and other conditions of service of, the procedure to be followed by, and the manner of filling casual vacancies among members of the Advisory Council or a Development Council ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-30.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the form of the statement of account to be furnished by a Development Council ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-30.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the intervals at which, the time within which, and the manner in which the cess leviable under Section 9 shall be payable and the rebate for the prompt payment of such cess ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-30.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the expenses which a Development Council may meet from the proceeds of the cess levied under Section 9 which may have been handed over to it ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-30.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the appointment by or with the approval of the Central Government of any officers of a Development Council ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-30.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the facilities to be provided by any industrial undertaking for the training of technicians and labour ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-30.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the collection of any information or statistics in respect of any scheduled industry ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-30.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the manner in which industrial undertakings may be registered under Section 10 and the levy of a fee therefore ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-30.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the procedure for the grant or issue of licences and permissions under Section 11, 11-A,Section 13 or Section 29-B, the time within which such licences or permissions shall be granted or issued including, in particular, the publication of notices calling for applications and the holding of such public inquiry in relation thereto as may be necessary in the circumstances ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-30.2.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>the fees to be levied in respect of licences and permissions issued under this Act ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-30.2.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>the matters which may be taken into account in the granting or issuing of licences and permissions, including in particular, the previous consultation by the Central Government with the Advisory Council or any Development Council or both in regard to the grant or issue of any such licences or permissions ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-30.2.list1.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>the procedure to be followed in making any investigation under this Act ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-30.2.list1.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>the conditions which may be included in any licences and permissions;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-30.2.list1.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>the conditions on which licences and permissions may be varied or amended under Section 12 ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-30.2.list1.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>the maintenance of books, accounts and records relating to an industrial undertaking ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-30.2.list1.p">
                <num>(p)</num>
                <p>the submission of special or periodical returns relating to an industrial undertaking by persons having the control of, or employed in connection with, such undertaking, and the forms in which, and the authorities to which, such returns and reports shall be submitted ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-30.2.list1.pp">
                <num>(pp)</num>
                <p>any matter which is to be or may be prescribed for giving effect to the provisions of Chapter III-AA or Chapter III-AC ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-30.2.list1.q">
                <num>(q)</num>
                <p>any other matter which is to be or may be prescribed under this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-30.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any rule made under this section may provide that a contravention thereof shall be punishable under Section 24.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-30.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-31">
        <num>31.</num>
        <heading>Application of the other laws not barred</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-31.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of this Act shall be in addition to and not, save as otherwise, expressly provided in this Act, in derogation of any other Central Act for the time being in force, relating to any of the scheduled industries.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-32">
        <num>32.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of 2, Act 14 of 1947</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-32.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Rep. by Repealing and Amending Act. 1957 (36 of 1957), Section 2 and Schedule I.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-thefirstschedule">
      <doc name="thefirstschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/65/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/65"/>
              <FRBRalias value="THE FIRST SCHEDULE"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/65/eng@1951-10-31/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/65/eng@1951-10-31"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/65/eng@1951-10-31/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/65/eng@1951-10-31"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-04-22" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="thefirstschedule">
            <heading>See Sections 2 and 3(i)</heading>
            <paragraph id="thefirstschedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>Any industry engaged in the manufacture or production of any of the articles mentioned under each of the following headings or sub-headings, namely :</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <section id="section-1">
              <num>1.</num>
              <heading>METALLURGICAL INDUSTRIES :</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>A. Ferrous :</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <subsection id="section-1.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Iron and steel (metal).</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-1.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Ferro-alloys.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-1.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Iron and steel castings and forgings.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-1.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Iron and steel structurals.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-1.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Iron and steel pipes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-1.6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Special steels</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-1.7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Other products of iron and steel.</p>
                  <p>B. Non-ferrous :</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-1.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Precious metals, including gold and silver and their alloys.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-1.1A">
                <num>(1A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Other non-ferrous metals and their alloys.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-1.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Semi-manufactures and manufactures.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-2">
              <num>2.</num>
              <heading>FUELS :</heading>
              <subsection id="section-2.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Coal, lignite, coke and their derivatives.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-2.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Mineral oil (crude oil), motor and aviation spirit, diesel oil, kerosene oil, fuel oil, diverse hydrocarbon oils and their blends including synthetic fuels, lubricating oils and the like.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-2.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Fuel gases--(coal gas, natural gas and the like.)</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-3">
              <num>3.</num>
              <heading>BOILERS AND STEAM GENERATING PLANTS :</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Boilers and steam generating plants.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-4">
              <num>4.</num>
              <heading>PRIME MOVERS (OTHER THAN ELECTRICAL GENERATORS ) :</heading>
              <subsection id="section-4.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Steam engines and turbines.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-4.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Internal combustion engines.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-5">
              <num>5.</num>
              <heading>ELECTRICAL EQUIPMENT :</heading>
              <subsection id="section-5.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Equipment for generation, transmission and distribution of electricity including transformers.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-5.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Electrical motors.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-5.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Electrical fans.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-5.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Electrical lamps.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-5.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Electrical furnaces.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-5.6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Electrical cables and wires.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-5.7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>X-ray equipment.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-5.8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Electronic equipment.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-5.9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Household appliances such as, electric irons, heaters and the like.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-5.10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Storage batteries.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-5.11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Dry cells.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-6">
              <num>6.</num>
              <heading>TELECOMMUNICATIONS :</heading>
              <subsection id="section-6.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Telephones.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-6.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Telegraph equipment.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-6.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Wireless communication apparatus.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-6.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Radio receivers, including amplifying and public address equipment.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-6.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Television sets.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-6.6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Teleprinters.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-7">
              <num>7.</num>
              <heading>TRANSPORTATION :</heading>
              <subsection id="section-7.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Aircraft.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-7.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Ships and other vessels drawn by power.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-7.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Railway locomotives.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-7.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Railway rolling stock.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-7.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Automobiles (motor cars, buses, trucks, motor cycles, scooters and the like).</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-7.6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Bicycles.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-7.7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Others, such as, fork lift trucks and the like.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-8">
              <num>8.</num>
              <heading>INDUSTRIAL MACHINERY :</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>A. Major items of specialised equipment used in specific industries :</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <subsection id="section-8.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Textile machinery (such as spinning frames, carding machines, power looms and the like) including textile accessories.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Jute machinery.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Rayon machinery.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Sugar machinery.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Tea machinery.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Mining machinery.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Metallurgical machinery.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Cement machinery.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Chemical machinery.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Pharmaceutical machinery.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Paper machinery.</p>
                  <p>B. General items of machinery used in several industries, such as, the equipment required for various "unit processes" :</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Size reduction equipment--crushers, ball mills and the like.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Conveying equipment--bucket elevators, skip hoist, cranes, derrick and the like.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Size separation units--screens, classifiers and the like.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Mixers and reactors--kneading mills, turbo mixers and the like.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Filtration equipment--filter presses, rotary filters and the like.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Centrifugal machine.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Evaporators.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Distillation equipment.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Crystallisers.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Driers.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Power-driven pumps--reciprocating, centrifugal and the like.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Air and gas compressors and vacuum pipes (excluding electrical furnaces).</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.13">
                <num>(13)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Refrigeration plants for industrial use.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.14">
                <num>(14)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Fire-fighting equipment and appliances including fire engines.</p>
                  <p>C. Other items of Industrial Machinery :</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Ball, roller and tapered bearings.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Speed reduction units.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Grinding wheels and abrasives.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-9">
              <num>9.</num>
              <heading>MACHINE TOOLS :</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Machine Tools.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-10">
              <num>10.</num>
              <heading>AGRICULTURAL MACHINERY :</heading>
              <subsection id="section-10.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Tractors, harvesters and the like.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-10.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Agricultural implements.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-11">
              <num>11.</num>
              <heading>EARTH-MOVING MACHINERY :</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Bulldozers, dumpers, scrapers, loaders, shovels, drag lines, bucket wheel excavators, road rollers and the like.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-12">
              <num>12.</num>
              <heading>MISCELLANEOUS MECHANICAL AND ENGINEERING INDUSTRIES :</heading>
              <subsection id="section-12.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Plastic moulded goods.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-12.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Hand tools, small tools and the like.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-12.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Razor blades.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-12.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Pressure cookers.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-12.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Cutlery.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-12.6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Steel furniture.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-13">
              <num>13.</num>
              <heading>COMMERCIAL, OFFICE AND HOUSEHOLD EQUIPMENT :</heading>
              <subsection id="section-13.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Typewriters.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-13.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Calculating machines.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-13.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Air conditioners and refrigerators.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-13.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Vacuum cleaners.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-13.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Sewing and knitting machines.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-13.6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Hurricane lanterns.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-14">
              <num>14.</num>
              <heading>MEDICAL AND SURGICAL APPLIANCES :</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Surgical instruments--sterilisers, incubators and the like.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-15">
              <num>15.</num>
              <heading>INDUSTRIAL INSTRUMENTS :</heading>
              <subsection id="section-15.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Water meters, steam meters, electricity meters and the like.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-15.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Indicating, recording and regulating devices for pressure, temperature, rate of flow, weights, levels and the like.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-15.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Weighing machines.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-16">
              <num>16.</num>
              <heading>SCIENTIFIC INSTRUMENTS :</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Scientific instruments.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-17">
              <num>17.</num>
              <heading>MATHEMATICAL, SURVEYING AND DRAWING INSTRUMENTS :</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Mathematical, surveying and drawing instruments.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-18">
              <num>18.</num>
              <heading>FERTILISERS:</heading>
              <subsection id="section-18.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Inorganic fertilisers.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-18.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Organic fertilisers.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-18.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Mixed fertilisers.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-19">
              <num>19.</num>
              <heading>CHEMICALS (OTHER THAN FERTILISERS) :</heading>
              <subsection id="section-19.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Inorganic heavy chemicals.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-19.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Organic heavy chemicals.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-19.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Fine chemicals including photographic chemicals.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-19.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Synthetic resins and plastics.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-19.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Paints, varnishes and enamels.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-19.6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Synthetic rubbers.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-19.7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Man-made fibers including regenerated cellulose-rayon, nylon and the like.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-19.8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Coke oven by-products.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-19.9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Coal-tar distillation products like naphthalene, anthracene and the like.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-19.10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Explosives including gunpowder and safety fuses.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-19.11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Insecticides, fungicides, weedicides and the like.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-19.12">
                <num>(12)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Textile auxiliaries.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-19.13">
                <num>(13)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Sizing materials including starch.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-19.14">
                <num>(14)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Miscellaneous chemicals.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-20">
              <num>20.</num>
              <heading>PHOTOGRAPHIC RAW FILM AND PAPER :</heading>
              <subsection id="section-20.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Cinema film.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-20.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Photographic amateur film.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-20.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Photographic printing paper.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-21">
              <num>21.</num>
              <heading>DYE-STUFFS :</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Dye-stuffs.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-22">
              <num>22.</num>
              <heading>DRUGS AND PHARMACEUTICALS :</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Drugs and Pharmaceuticals.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-23">
              <num>23.</num>
              <heading>TEXTILES (INCLUDING THOSE DYED, PRINTED OR OTHERWISE PROCESSED) :</heading>
              <subsection id="section-23.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Made wholly or in part of cotton, including cotton yarn, hosiery and rope.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-23.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Made wholly or in part of jute, including jute twine and rope.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-23.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Made wholly or in part of wool, including wool tops, woollen yarn, hosiery, carpets and druggets ;</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-23.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Made wholly or in part of silk, including silk yarn and hosiery ;</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-23.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Made wholly or in part of synthetic, artificial (man-made) fibers, including yarn and hosiery of such fibers.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-24">
              <num>24.</num>
              <heading>PAPER AND PULP INCLUDING PAPER PRODUCTS :</heading>
              <subsection id="section-24.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Paper--writing, printing and wrapping.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-24.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Newsprint.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-24.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Paper board and straw board.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-24.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Paper for packaging (corrugated paper, Kraft paper), bags, paper containers and the like.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-24.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Pulp--wood pulp, mechanical, chemical, including dissolving pulp.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-25">
              <num>25.</num>
              <heading>SUGAR.</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Sugar</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-26">
              <num>26.</num>
              <heading>FERMENTATION INDUSTRIES (OTHER THAN POTABLE ALCOHOL):</heading>
              <subsection id="section-26.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Alcohol.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-26.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Other products of fermentation industries</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-27">
              <num>27.</num>
              <heading>FOOD PROCESSING INDUSTRIES :</heading>
              <subsection id="section-27.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Canned fruits and fruit products.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-27.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Milk foods.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-27.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Malted foods.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-27.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Flour.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-27.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Other processed foods.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-28">
              <num>28.</num>
              <heading>VEGETABLE OILS AND VANASPATI :</heading>
              <subsection id="section-28.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Vegetable oils, including solvent extracted oils.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-28.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Vanaspati.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-29">
              <num>29.</num>
              <heading>SOAPS, COSMETICS AND TOILET PREPARATIONS :</heading>
              <subsection id="section-29.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Soaps.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-29.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Glycerine.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-29.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Cosmetics.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-29.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Perfumery</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-29.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Toilet preparations.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-30">
              <num>30.</num>
              <heading>RUBBER GOODS :</heading>
              <subsection id="section-30.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Tyres and tubes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-30.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Surgical and medical products including prophylactics.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-30.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Footwear.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-30.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Other rubber goods.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-31">
              <num>31.</num>
              <heading>LEATHER, LEATHER GOODS AND PICKERS :</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-31.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Leather, leather goods and pickers.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-32">
              <num>32.</num>
              <heading>GLUE AND GELATIN:</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-32.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Glue and gelatin.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-33">
              <num>33.</num>
              <heading>GLASS :</heading>
              <subsection id="section-33.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Hollow ware.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-33.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Sheet and plate glass.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-33.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Optical glass.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-33.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Glass wool.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-33.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Laboratory ware.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-33.6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Miscellaneous ware.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-34">
              <num>34.</num>
              <heading>CERAMICS :</heading>
              <subsection id="section-34.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Fire bricks.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-34.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Refractories.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-34.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Furnace lining bricks--acidic, basic and neutral.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-34.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Chinaware and pottery.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-34.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Sanitary ware.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-34.6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Insulators.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-34.7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Tiles.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-34.8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Graphite Crucibles.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-35">
              <num>35.</num>
              <heading>CEMENT AND GYPSUM PRODUCTS :</heading>
              <subsection id="section-35.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Portland cement.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-35.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Asbestos cement.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-35.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Insulating boards.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-35.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Gypsum boards, wall boards and the like.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-36">
              <num>36.</num>
              <heading>TIMBER PRODUCTS :</heading>
              <subsection id="section-36.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Plywood.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-36.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Hardboard, including fiber-board, chip-board and the like.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-36.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Matches.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-36.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Miscellaneous (furniture components, bobbins, shutters and the like.)</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-37">
              <num>37.</num>
              <heading>DEFENCE INDUSTRIES :</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-37.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Arms and ammunition.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-38">
              <num>38.</num>
              <heading>MISCELLANEOUS INDUSTRIES :</heading>
              <subsection id="section-38.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Cigarettes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-38.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Linoleums, whether felt based or jute based.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-38.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Zip fasteners (metallic and non-metallic).</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-38.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Oil Stoves.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-38.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Printing, including litho-printing industry.</p>
                  <p>Explanation 1.--The articles specified under each of the headings Nos. 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 10, 11 and 13 shall include their component parts and accessories.</p>
                  <p>Explanation 2.--The articles specified under each of the headings Nos. 18, 19, 21, and 22 shall include the intermediates required for their manufacture.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-thesecondschedule">
      <doc name="thesecondschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/65/thesecondschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/65"/>
              <FRBRalias value="THE SECOND SCHEDULE"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/65/eng@1951-10-31/thesecondschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/65/eng@1951-10-31"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/65/eng@1951-10-31/thesecondschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/65/eng@1951-10-31"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-04-22" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="thesecondschedule">
            <paragraph id="thesecondschedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>See 6(4)</p>
                <p>Functions which may be assigned to Development Councils :</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Recommending targets for production, co-ordinating production programmes and reviewing progress from time to time.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Suggesting norms of efficiency with a view to eliminating waste, obtaining maximum production, improving quality and reducing costs.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Recommending measures for securing the fuller utilisation of the installed capacity and for improving the working of the industry, particularly of the less efficient units.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.4">
              <num>(4)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Promoting arrangements for better marketing and helping in the devising of a system of distribution and sale of the produce of the industry which would be satisfactory to the consumer.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.5">
              <num>(5)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Promoting standardisation of products.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.6">
              <num>(6)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Assisting in the distribution of controlled materials and promoting arrangements for obtaining materials for the industry.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.7">
              <num>(7)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Promoting or undertaking inquiry as to materials and equipment and as to methods of production, management and labour utilisation, including the discovery and development of new materials, equipment and methods and of improvements in those already in use, the assessment of the advantages of different alternatives and the conduct of experimental establishments and of tests on a commercial scale.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.8">
              <num>(8)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Promoting the training of persons engaged or proposing engagement in the industry and their education in technical or artistic subjects relevant thereto.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.9">
              <num>(9)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Promoting the retaining in alternative occupations of personnel engaged in or retrenched from the industry.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.10">
              <num>(10)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Promoting or undertaking scientific and industrial research, research into matters affecting industrial psychology and research into matters relating to production and to the consumption or use of goods and services supplied by the industry.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.11">
              <num>(11)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Promoting, improvements and standardisation of accounting and costing methods and practice.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.12">
              <num>(12)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Promoting or undertaking the collection and formation of statistics.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.13">
              <num>(13)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Investigating possibilities of decentralising stages and processes of production with a view to encouraging the growth of allied small scale and cottage industries.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.14">
              <num>(14)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Promoting the adoption of measures for increasing the productivity of labour, including measures for securing safer and better working conditions and the provision and improvement of amenities and incentives for workers.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.15">
              <num>(15)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Advising on any matters relating to the industry (other than remuneration and conditions of employment) as to which the Central Government may request the Development Council to advise and undertaking inquiries for the purpose of enabling the Development Council so to advise, and</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thesecondschedule.16">
              <num>(16)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Undertaking arrangements for making available to the industry information obtained and for advising on matters with which the Development Councils are concerned in the exercise of any of their functions.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-thethirdschedule">
      <doc name="thethirdschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/65/thethirdschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/65"/>
              <FRBRalias value="THE THIRD SCHEDULE"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/65/eng@1951-10-31/thethirdschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/65/eng@1951-10-31"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/65/eng@1951-10-31/thethirdschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/65/eng@1951-10-31"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-04-22" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="thethirdschedule">
            <paragraph id="thethirdschedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>(See 18-FB)</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <section id="section-1">
              <num>1.</num>
              <heading>The Industrial Employment (Standing Orders) Act, 1946 (20 of 1946).</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-2">
              <num>2.</num>
              <heading>The Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 (14 of 1947).</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-3">
              <num>3.</num>
              <heading>The Minimum Wages Act, 1948 (11 of 1948).</heading>
            </section>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
