<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1827/22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1827/22"/>
          <FRBRalias value="Military Authority (Assistance To Marching Troops), 1827"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1827/22/eng@2017-03-27/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1827/22/eng@2017-03-27"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-27" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1827/22/eng@2017-03-27/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1827/22/eng@2017-03-27"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-27" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>Military Authority (Assistance To Marching Troops), 1827</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Bombay Regulation XXII of 1827.</p>
        <p>A Regulation to declare and define military authority, in its relations to the civil power and to the community at large.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>- 39. Repealed.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-40">
        <num>40.</num>
        <heading>Notice to District Magistrates through whose jurisdiction troops pass</heading>
        <subsection id="section-40.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When military bodies, exceeding in number two hundred (200) of infantry, or one hundred (100) of cavalry, shall have occasion to march through a territory, and also, if the number be smaller, provided they will require aid from the local authority, the commanding officer shall give timely notice to each District Magistrate through whose jurisdiction he will pass, specifying the probable time of his arrival, the extent of the corps, and the nature of the aid (if any) which will be required.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-41">
        <num>41.</num>
        <heading>Aid to be furnished by District Magistrate</heading>
        <subsection id="section-41.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If it be required, the District Magistrate shall direct his establishment to be in readiness to procure guides, and such supplies of provisions as the country may furnish, and such conveyance for passing rivers or Ghats, or any peculiarly difficult places, as is professionally provided by the inhabitants for such purposes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-41.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Provision and conveyance supplied as above mentioned to individuals shall be paid for by them at the time and at the current rate of the place, the guides and conveyance for public property shall be paid for at the same rate by the Collector of the district, according to a certificate which the commanding officer is to grant, denoting the services performed; and the Collector is to insert the amount so disbursed at the foot of his treasury-account, in explanation of his treasury-balance as prescribed for similar case.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-42">
        <num>42.</num>
        <heading>On emergent occasions aid may be procured by impressment</heading>
        <subsection id="section-42.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When emergent occasions require the immediate march of troops and more extensive aid towards it that is allowed by the preceding section, is necessary, the District Magistrate may resort to impressment under the following rules, being careful to define the nature of the employment for which the impressment is made and the period it is to continue.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-42.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The District Magistrate’s authority for acting as in the preceding clause shall be either an order from the Central Government or a letter from the commanding officer declaring his inability to proceed without the District Magistrate’s aid, and full explaining the circumstances which render the movement of paramount importance to the general inconvenience occasioned by impressment, or receipt of which the District Magistrate will act at discretion.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-42.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Remuneration for services or supplies procured by impressment is to be fixed by the District Magistrate on a liberal scale, and paid according to the principles of clause second, section 41, of this Regulation, namely, individuals are to pay for that which is personal accommodation, and the Collector is to defray the charges incurred for the public service under the above-quoted rules.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-42.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whenever impressment shall take place by virtue of this section, the District Magistrate shall, within ten (10) days, report the fact, with the cause and extent of impressment, and the rates of remuneration allowed to the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-43">
        <num>43.</num>
        <heading>Certificate to be furnished to person sustaining injury</heading>
        <subsection id="section-43.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When damage is occasioned to individuals by the march or encampment of troops, the commanding officer shall, on application by the sufferer, furnish him with a certificate of the nature, extent and cause thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-43.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The certificate mentioned in the preceding clause shall, if presented to the collector or any of his officers holding charge of a district within ten (10) days from its date, entitle the sufferer to compensation for loss occasioned by such movements or positions of the troops as are bona fide of a military nature.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-43.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On a demand made by virtue of this section to the collector, he shall inquire into its merits, and, if satisfied that it is just, shall apply to the Central Government for permission to pay it; if the Collector thinks the demand is not just, or if the Central Government withhold permission to pay it, the complainant may bring the case to decision according to the process of civil law by instituting a suit against the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
