<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-pun/act/1918/5/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-pun/act/1918/5"/>
          <FRBRalias value="Restriction of Habitual Offenders (Punjab) Act, 1918"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-pun/act/1918/5/eng@1918-04-26/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-pun/act/1918/5/eng@1918-04-26"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1918-04-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-pun/act/1918/5/eng@1918-04-26/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-pun/act/1918/5/eng@1918-04-26"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-12-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>Restriction Of Habitual Offenders (Punjab) Act, 1918</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[Act No. 5 of 1918]</p>
        <p>[April 26, 1918]</p>
        <p>An act for restricting the movements of habitual offenders in Punjab and for requiring them to report themselves.</p>
        <p>Whereas it is expedient to make provision for restricting the movements of habitual offenders in Punjab and requiring habitual offenders in Punjab to report themselves, and whereas the previous sanction of the Governor-General in Council has been obtained under section 79(2) of the Government of India Act, 1915, to the passing of this Act:</p>
        <p>It is hereby enacted as follows:–</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Title and extent.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-1.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>This Act may be called the Restriction of Habitual Offenders (Punjab) Act, 1918.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>It extends to Punjab.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Scope of order of restriction.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>An “Order of restriction” passed under this Act may restrict a person in his movements to any area prescribed in the order; or it may require a person to report himself at times, and places and in the mode prescribed in the order; or it may do both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Order of restriction against habitual offenders.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>In any case in which a Magistrate may under the provisions of Section 110 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898, as it is at present enacted or as it may from time to time be amended, require a person to show cause why he should not be ordered to execute a bond for his good behavior, the Magistrate may in lieu of or in addition to so doing require such person to show cause why an order of restriction should not be made against him.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>If the Magistrate in addition to requiring such person to show cause why he should not be ordered to execute a bond for his good behavior, requires him to show cause why an order of restriction should not be made against him, the proceedings in respect of the order of restriction may be taken jointly with the proceedings in respect of security and may be entered in and form part of the same record.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Procedure in making order of restriction.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>When a Magistrate deems it necessary to require a person to show cause why an order of restriction should not be made against him, he shall follow as nearly as may be the procedure laid down in sections 112, 113, 114, 115 and 117 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898:</p>
            <p>Provided that –</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the order of writing referred to in section 112 of the said Code shall in addition to setting forth the substance of the information received state the term not exceeding three years during which the order of restriction shall be in force; but it need not state whether the order of restriction shall be an order restricting the person to any area or requiring him to report himself or doing both; and</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>for the purposes of section 117(2) of the said Code an order of restriction shall be deemed to be equivalent to an order requiring security for good behaviour.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Issue of warrant in lieu of or in addition to summons.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of section 90 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898, shall be applicable to proceedings under this Act as if they were proceedings under the said Code.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Discharge of person informed against.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If upon enquiry made in accordance with the preceding sections the Magistrate is of opinion that no order of restriction is necessary, the Magistrate shall make an entry to that effect on the record, and if he does not order the execution of a bond for good behaviour he shall if such person is in custody only for purposes of the enquiry release him or if such person is not in custody discharge him.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Making of order of restriction.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If upon enquiry as aforesaid the Magistrate is of opinion that an order of restriction should be made against the person in respect of whom the enquiry is being made, the Magistrate shall make an order accordingly.</p>
            <p>***</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Order of restriction under section 123(3) of Criminal Procedure Code.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An order passed by a Sessions Judge under section 123(3) of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898, may be in addition to an order of restriction for the same or a less period.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Order of restriction against convicted offender.- In any case in which a Court or Magistrate is empowered to take action against any convicted person under section 565 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898, such Court or Magistrate may if it or he thinks fit at the time of passing sentence on such person and in lieu of passing an order under the said section make an order of restriction against such person for a period not exceeding three years from the date of the expiry of such sentence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If such conviction is set aside on appeal or otherwise, such order shall become void.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Means of livelihood within area of restriction.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No order shall be made restricting any person to any area unless the Court or Magistrate making the order is satisfied that such person has adequate means of earning his livelihood within the area of restriction:</p>
            <p>Provided that before making such order the Court or Magistrate shall record and consider any objection which such person may urge in regard to the area proposed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Change of area where means of livelihood are insufficient.- If at any time any person against whom an order of restriction has been passed under this Act satisfies the Court or Magistrate passing the order or the District Magistrate that he had no sufficient means of earning his livelihood within the area to which he is restricted the Court or Magistrate shall change the area.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Power to cancel order of restriction.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The District Magistrate may at any time for sufficient reasons to be recorded in writing cancel any order of restriction passed by any Court having jurisdiction in his district.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Power to vary area of restriction.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The District Magistrate may at any time change the area to which the movements of any person have been restricted by an order of restriction passed under this Act:</p>
            <p>Provided that such person shall be given an opportunity of showing cause why such change should not be made.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Power to add order of restriction to bond for good behavior.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>When an order requiring security for good behaviour has been made against any person under section 118 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898, by any Court whether before or after this Act comes into force, the District Magistrate may at any time before the period of security has expired make in addition an order of restriction:</p>
            <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that –</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the period of the order of restriction shall not exceed the unexpired period of security; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>no order of restriction shall be passed against any person under this section until he has been given an opportunity of showing cause why such order should not be passed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Appeal.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any person against whom an order of restriction has been passed under this Act, may prefer an appeal –</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to the District Magistrate, if such order has been made by an Executing Magistrate subordinate to him.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to the Chief Judicial Magistrate, if such order has been made by a Judicial Magistrate subordinate to him;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to the court of Session, if such order has been made by the District Magistrate, or the Chief Judicial Magistrate;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>to the High Court, in any other case.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Applicability of the Code of Criminal Procedure to appeals and revisions.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898, shall be applicable to appeals and petitions of revision under this Act as if they were appeals and petitions of revision presented under the said Code.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Arrest of person found beyond prescribed limits.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person against whom an order of restriction under this Act has been passed is found in any place beyond the area to which his movements have been restricted without the pass prescribed by the rules made under this Act, or at a time or in a place not permitted by the conditions of his pass, he may be arrested without warrant by any police officer, zaildar, inamdar, village headman or village watchman.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person, not being a police officer, making an arrest under this section shall without unnecessary delay make over the person so arrested to a police officer, or, in the absence of a police officer, take or send such person to the nearest police station.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The State Government may make rules to provide for and regulate ­</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the areas to which persons may be restricted under this Act and the nature of the restrictions to be observed by them;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>the times and places at which and the mode in which persons shall report themselves when required to do so under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>the conditions as to holding passes under which persons may be permitted to leave the area to which their movements have been restricted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>the conditions to be inserted in any such pass in regard to –</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the places to which the holder of the pass may or may not go;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the persons before whom from time to time he shall be bound to present himself; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the time during which he may be absent.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Penalties.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-17.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Whoever being a person against whom an order of restriction under this Act has been passed violates such order or any rule made under this Act, shall on conviction by a Judicial Magistrate of the first class be punished -</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>on a first conviction with imprisonment of either description for a term which may extend to one year, or with fine, or with both;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>on a second conviction with imprisonment of either description for a term which may extend to two years;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>on any subsequent conviction with imprisonment of either description for a term which may extend to three years.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Period of imprisonment to be excluded from period of order of restriction.- In computing the period for which an order of restriction shall remain in force, any period of imprisonment undergone in execution of a sentence passed under sub-section (1) of this Section shall be excluded.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
