<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-tmn/act/1972/36/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-tmn/act/1972/36"/>
          <FRBRalias value="Tamil Nadu Labour Welfare Fund Act, 1972"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-tmn/act/1972/36/eng@2017-05-04/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-tmn/act/1972/36/eng@2017-05-04"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-05-04" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-tmn/act/1972/36/eng@2017-05-04/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-tmn/act/1972/36/eng@2017-05-04"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-05-04" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Tamil Nadu Labour Welfare Fund Act, 1972</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>(ACT No. 36 OF 1972)</docNumber>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the Constitution of a fund for promoting the welfare of labour and for certain other matters connected therewith in the State of Tamil Nadu.</p>
      </longTitle>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by the Legislature of the State of Tamil Nadu in the Twenty-third Year of the Republic of India as follows:-</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Tamil Nadu Labour Welfare Fund Act, 1972.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Tamil Nadu.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Government may, by notification, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"Board" means the Tamil Nadu Labour Welfare Board established under section 4;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>"employee" means-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>any person who is employed for hire or reward to do any work, skilled or unskilled, manual, supervisory, clerical or technical in an establishment for a period of 30 days during the period of the preceding twelve months whether the terms of employment be express or implied, but does not include any person —</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>who is employed mainly in a managerial capacity ; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>who being employed in a supervisory capacity draws wages exceeding three thousand and five hundred rupees per mensem or exercises either by the nature of the duties attached to the office or by reason of the powers vested in him, functions mainly of a managerial nature; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>who is employed as an apprentice or on part-time basis.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation: An apprentice means a person who according to the Certified Standing Orders applicable to the establishment, is an apprentice or who is declared to be an apprentice by the authority specified in this behalf by the Government; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>any other person employed in any establishment whom the Government may by notification, declare to be an employee for the purposes of this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>"employer" means a person who has the ultimate control over the affairs of the establishment and where the said affairs are entrusted to any other person whether called a manager, managing director, managing agent, superintendent or by any other name, such other person;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>"establishment", means-</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>a factory as defined in clause (m) of section 2 of the Factories Act, 1948 (Central ACT, 1972 Act LXIII of 1948), or any place which is deemed to be a factory under sub-section (2) of section 85 of that Act ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>a motor transport undertaking as defined in clause (g) of section 2 of the Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961 (Central Act 27 of 1961);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>a plantation as defined in clause (f) of section 2 of the Plantations Labour Act, 1951 (Central Act LXIX of 1951);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>a catering establishment as defined in section 2 (1) of the Tamil Nadu Catering Establishments Act, 1958 (Tamil Nadu Act XIII of 1958) which employs, or an any working day during the preceding twelve months employed, five or more than five persons;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>an establishment, including a society registered or deemed to be registered under the Tamil Nadu Societies Registration Act, 1975 (Tamil Nadu Act 27 of 1975) and a charitable or other trust whether registered under any law applicable to such charitable or other trust or not, which carries on any business or trade or any work in connection therewith or ancillary thereto and which employs, or on any working day during the preceding twelve months employed, five or more persons; but does not include an establishment (not being a factory) of the Central or any State Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.vi">
                <num>(vi)</num>
                <p>any other establishment which the Government may, by notification, declare to be an establishment for the purposes of this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>Explanation: For the purposes of this Act, where an establishment consists of different departments or has branches whether situated in the same place or in different places, all such departments or branches shall be treated as parts of the same establishment."Fund" means the Labour Welfare Fund constituted under section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>"Government" means the State Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>"Inspector" means an Inspector referred to in section 22;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>"Secretary" means the Secretary appointed under section 21;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>"unpaid accumulation" means all payments other than gratuity due to an employee but not paid to him with-in a period of three years from the date on which the payments became due whether before or after the commencement of this Act and the gratuity accrued to an employee after the commencement of this Act but not paid within a period of three years from the date of such accrual but does not include the amount of contribution, if any, paid by an employer to a provident fund established under the Employees' Provident Funds Act, 1952 (Central Act XIX of 1952);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>"wages" means all remuneration Capable of being expressed in terms of money which would, if the terms of the contract of employment, expressed or implied, were fulfilled, be payable to an employee in respect of his employment or of work done in such employment, but does not include —</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the value of any house accommodation or of the supply of light, water, medical attendance or other amenity or of any service excluded from the computation of wages by general or special order of the Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>any contribution paid by the employer to any pension or provident fund or under any scheme of social insurance;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>any travelling allowance or the value of any travelling concession;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>any sum paid to the employee to defray special expenses entailed on him by the nature of his employment; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>any gratuity payable on termination of employment.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Labour Welfare Fund</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government shall constitute a fund called the Labour Welfare Fund, and notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being in force or in any contract or instrument, all unpaid accumulations shall be paid, at such intervals as may be prescribed, to the Board, and be credited to the Fund and the Board shall keep a separate account therefor until claims thereto have been decided in the manner provided for in section 13.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>There shall also be credited to the Fund:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>unpaid accumulations paid to the Board under sub-section (2) of section 13;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>all fines including the amount realised under Standing Order 20 of the Model Standing Orders issued under the Tamil Nadu Industrial Employment (Standing Orders) Rules, 1947 and under the certified standing orders of the establishment from the employees by the employers, notwithstanding anything contained in any agreement between the employer and employee;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>deductions made under the proviso to sub-section (2) of section 9 of the Payment of Wages Act, 1936 (Central Act IV of 1936) 1and under the proviso to sub-section (2) of section 36 of the Tamil Nadu Shops and Establishments Act, 1947 (Tamil Nadu Act XXXVI of 1947);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>contribution by employers and employees;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>any interest by way of penalty paid under section 14;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>any voluntary donations;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>any amount raised by the Board am other sources to augment the resources of the Board;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>any fund transferred under sub-section (5) of section 17;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>any sum borrowed under section 18;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>any unclaimed amount credited to the Government in accordance with the rules made under the Payment of Wages Act, 1936 (Central Act TV of 1936) and the Minimum Wages Act, 1948 (Central Act XI of 1948);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>grants or advances made by the Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>all fines imposed and realised from employers by courts for violation-of labour laws less the deduction made by court towards administrative expenses.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The sums specified in sub-section (2) shall be paid to, 'or collected by, such agencies, at such intervals and in such manner, and the accounts of the Fund shall be maintained and audited in such manner, as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Establishment of the Board</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>With effect from such date as the Government may, by notification, appoint in this behalf, there shall be established a Board by the name "Tamil Nadu Labour Welfare Board".</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall be a body corporate having perpetual succession and a common seal, and shall, by the said name, sue and be sued.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of the Board</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Board shall consist of a Chairman who shall be the Minister-in-charge of Labour and of the following members appointed by the Government namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>such number of representatives of employers and employees as may be prescribed:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that both employers and employees shall have equal representation on the Board;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>such number of members of the State Legislature as may be prescribed; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>such number of officials and non-officials as may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Appointment of the Chairman and the members to be notified</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The appointment of the Chairman and the members shall be notified in the Tamil Nadu Government Gazette.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Term of office of the members</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The term of office of the members of the Board other than the official members shall be three years from the date of their appointment and they shall be eligible for reappointment They shall continue as such members until the appointment of the successors:</p>
            <p>Provided that a member of the State Legislature shall cease to be a member of the</p>
            <p>Board from the date on which he ceases to be a member of the State Legislature.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Disqualifications and removal</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>No person shall be chosen as, or continue to be, a member of the Board, if he:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>is an officer or servant under the Board ; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>is an undischarged insolvent ; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>is of unsound mind; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>has been convicted by a criminal court for an offence involving moral turpitude, unless such conviction has been set aside; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>is in arrears of any sum due to the Board.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Government may remove from office any member who:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>is or has become subject to any of the disqualifications mentioned in sub¬section (1); or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>is absent without leave of the Board for more than three consecutive meetings of the Board.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Resignation of office by member and filling up of casual vacancies</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any representative of employer or employee or Member of the State Legislature, or non-official member may resign his office by giving notice thereof in writing, to the Government, and on such resignation being accepted, shall be deemed to have vacated his office.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A casual vacancy in the office of a member may be filled up as soon as may be and a member so appointed to fill such vacancy shall hold office for the remainder of the term.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Power to appoint committees</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of advising the Board in the discharge of its functions and in particular for carrying into effect any of the matters specified in sub-section (2) of section 17, the Board may constitute one or more committees consisting of atleast one member of the Board and equal number of representatives of employees and employers.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Acts of the Board or committee not to be invalidated by informality, vacancy, etc.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>No act done or proceeding taken under this Act by the Board or any committee shall be invalidated merely on the ground —</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>of any vacancy or defect in the constitution of the Board or the committee; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>of any defect or irregularity in the appointment of a person acting as a member there-of; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>of any defect or irregularly in such act or proceeding not affecting the merits of the case.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Functions of the Board</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The functions of the Board shall be the administration of the Fund and such other functions as may be assigned by or under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Unpaid accumulations and claims thereto</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All unpaid accumulations shall be deemed to be abandoned property.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any unpaid accumulation paid to the Board in accordance with the provisions of section 3 shall on such payment, discharge an employer of his liability to make payment to an employee in respect thereof, but to the extent only of the amount paid to the Board, and the liability to make payment to the employee to the extent aforesaid shall, subject to the succeeding provisions of this section, be deemed to be transferred to the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>As soon as possible after the payment of any unpaid accumulation is made to the Board, the Board shall —</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>exhibit on the notice-board of the establishment in which the unpaid accumulation was earned; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>publish in the Tamil Nadu Government Gazette, and in such other manner as may be prescribed, a notice inviting claims by employees, their heirs, legal representatives or assigns for any payment due to them.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any question arises whether the notice referred to in sub-section (3) was given as required by that sub-section, a certificate of the Board that it was so given, shall! he conclusive.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If a claim is received whether in response to the notice or otherwise, within a period of six months from the date of the publication of the notice in the Tamil Nadu Government Gazette, in respect of such claim, the Board shall transfer such claim to the Authority appointed under section 15 of the Payment of Wages Act, 1936 (Central. Act IV of 1936), having jurisdiction over the area in which the establishment is situate and that Authority shall proceed to adjudicate upon and decide such claim. In hearing such claim such Authority shall have the powers conferred by that Act and follow the procedure (in so far as it is applicable), specified therein.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the Authority aforesaid is satisfied that any such claim is valid so that the right to receive payment is established, it shall decide that the unpaid accumulation in relation to which the claim is made shall cease to be deemed to be abandoned property, and shall order the Board to pay the whole of the dues claimed, or such part thereof as the Authority decides are properly due, to the employee; and the Board shall make payment accordingly:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Board shall not be liable to pay any sum in excess of that paid under sub-section (1) of section 3 to the Board as unpaid accumulations, in respect of the claim.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If a claim for payment is refused, the employee or his heirs, legal representatives or assigns, as the case may be, may, within sixty days from the date of receipt of the order of the Authority, prefer an appeal in the City of Madras to the Madras City Civil Court, and elsewhere to the District Court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The decision of the Authority, subject to appeal aforesaid, and the decision in appeal of the Madras City Civil Court, or as the case may be, the District Court, shall be final and conclusive as to the right to receive payment, the liability of the Board to pay and also as to the amount, if any.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If no claim is received within the period specified in subsection (5), or a claim has been refused by the Authority, or on appeal by the Madras City Civil Court or the District Court, then the unpaid accumulations in respect of such claim shall accrue to, and vest in, the State as bona vacantia and thereafter be deemed to have been transferred to, and form part of, the Fund.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Interest on unpaid accumulations, or fines after notice of demand</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>if an employer does not pay to the Board any amount of unpaid accumulations, or fines realised from the employees, within the time specified by or under this Act, the Secretary may serve or cause to be sewed a notice on such employer to pay the amount within the period specified therein which shall not be less than thirty days from the date of service of such notice.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If the employer fails, without sufficient cause, to pay any such amount within the period specified in the notice., he shall, in addition to that amount, pay by way of penalty to the Board simple interest:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for the first three months at one per cent. of the said amount for each complete month or part thereof after the last date by which he should have paid it according to the notice; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>for each complete month or part thereof thereafter at one and a half per cent. of that amount during the time he continues to make default in the payment of that amount:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that, the Secretary may, subject to such conditions as may be prescribed, remit the whole or any part of the penalty in respect of any period.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Contribution to the Fund by employee and employer</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every employee shall contribute a sum not exceeding ten rupees, per year, as may be prescribed, from time to time, to the Fund and every employer shall, in respect of each such employee, contribute a sum not exceeding twenty rupees, per year, as may be prescribed, from time to time, to the Fund and the Government shall, in respect of each such employee, contribute a sum not exceeding ten rupees, per year, as may be prescribed, from time to time, to the Fund.Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being in force the employer shall be entitled to recover from the employee the employee's contribution by deduction from his wages in such manner as May be prescribed and such deduction shall be deemed to be a deduction authorised by or under the Payment of Wages Act, 1936 (Central Act IV of 1936) or the Tamil Nadu Shops and Establishments Act, 1947 (Tamil Nadu Act XXXVI of 1947).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Grants and advances by the Government</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, from time to time, make grants or advance loans to the Board for the purposes of this Act on such terms and conditions as the Government may, in each case, determine.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Vesting and application of Fund</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Fund shall vest in, and be held and applied by, the Board as trustees subject to the provisions, and for the purposes, of this Act. The moneys therein shall be utilised by the Board to defray the cost of carrying out measures which may be specified by the Government from time to time to promote the welfare of employees and of their dependants.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-17.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Without prejudice to the generality of the provisions of sub-section (1), the moneys in the Fund may be utilized by the Board to defray expenditure on the following, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>community and social education centres;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>vocational training;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>community necessities;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>entertainment and other forms of recreation;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>convalescent homes for tuberculosis patients;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>holidays homes in health resorts;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>part-time employment for housewives of employees;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>pre-schools;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>nutritious food to children of employees;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>employment opportunities to the disabled employees or the widows of the deceased employees;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>cost of administering this Act including the salaries and allowances of the staff appointed for the purposes of this Act; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>such other objects as would, in the opinion of the Board, improve the standard of living and education and ameliorate the social conditions of labour:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that the Fund shall not be utilised in financing any measure which the employer is required under any law for the time being in force to carry out:</p>
            <p>Provided further that unpaid accumulations and fines shall be expended by the Board under this Act notwithstanding anything contained in the Payment of Wages Act, 1936</p>
            <p>(Central Act IV of 1936) or any other law or agreement for the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board may, with the approval of the Government, make grants from the Fund to any local authority or any other body in aid of any activity for the welfare of employees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any question arises whether any particular expenditure is or is not debitable to the Fund, the matter shall be referred to the Government whose decision thereon shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board may accept the transfer of any Labour Welfare Fund of any establishment and may continue any activity financed from such Labour Welfare Fund if the said Fund is duly transferred to the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Power of Board to borrow</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Board may from time to time with the previous sanction of the Government and subject to the provisions of this Act and to such conditions as may be prescribed in this behalf borrow any sum required for the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Deposit of Fund and placing of accounts and audit report before the State Legislature</heading>
        <subsection id="section-19.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All moneys and receipts forming part of the Fund shall be deposited in the Reserve Bank of India constituted under the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (Central Act 11 of 1934), or in the State Bank of India constituted under the State Bank of India Act, 1955 (Central Act 13 of 1955), or any corresponding new Bank as defined in the Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings) Act, 1970 (Central Act 5 of 1970), or in the State Co-operative Bank or in an Central Co-operative Bank as defined in section 73-A of the Tamil Nadu Co-operative Societies Act. 1961 (Tamil Nadu Act 53 of 1901) or in any corporation owned or controlled by any State Government or the Central Government and such account shall be operated upon by such officers of the Board as may be authorised by the Board and in such manner, as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the accounts of the Board, as certified by the auditor, to ether with the audit report thereon, shall be forwarded yearly to the Government and the Government may issue such instructions to the Board in respect thereof as they deem fit and the Board shall comply with such instructions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-19.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Government shall —</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-19.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>cause the accounts of the Board together with the audit report thereon forwarded to them under sub-section (2) to be laid yearly before the State Legislature: and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>cause the accounts of the Board to be published in the prescribed manner and make available copies thereof on sale at a reason-able price.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Power of Government to give directions to the board</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Government may give the Board such directions as in their opinion are necessary or expedient in connection with expenditure from the Fund or for carrying out the purposes of the Act and it shall be the duty of the Board to comply with such directions.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Appointment and powers of Secretary</heading>
        <subsection id="section-21.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board may with the previous approval of the Government appoint a Secretary who shall be the Chief Executive Officer of the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-21.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be the duty of the Secretary to ensure that the provisions of this Act and the rules made there-under are duly carried out and for this purpose he shall have the power to issue such orders not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder as he deems fit including any order implementing the decisions taken by the Board under this Act or the rules made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Inspectors</heading>
        <subsection id="section-22.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An Inspector of Factories appointed under sub-section (1) of section 8 of the Factories Act, 1948 (Central Act LXIII of 1948), shall be an Inspector for the</p>
            <p>purposes of this Act in respect of all factories within the local limits assigned to him.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-22.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification, appoint such other persons as they think fit to be Inspectors for the purposes of this Act and may define the local limits within which and the class of establishments in respect of which they shall exercise their functions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-22.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-22.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Subject to any rules made in this behalf, an Inspector shall have power to do all or any of the following matters within the local limits for which he is appointed:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-22.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to make such examination and hold such inquiry as may be necessary for ascertaining whether the provisions of this Act have been and are being complied with;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-22.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>require the production of any prescribed register and any other document in possession of the employer in Connection with the sums payable to the Fund;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-22.3.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to enter at all reasonable times any premises with such assistance as he may think fit;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-22.3.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>to exercise such other powers as may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Allotment of certain officers and staff to the Board</heading>
        <subsection id="section-23.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>As soon as may be after the commencement of this Act, the Government may after consulting the Board direct by general or special order that such of the officers and other servants serving immediately before the notified date in connection with the affairs of the State as are specified in such order shall be allotted to serve in connection with the affairs of the Board with effect on and from such date as may be specified in such order:</p>
            <p>Provided that no such direction shall be issued in respect of such officer or other servant without his consent for such allotment:</p>
            <p>Provided further that the conditions of service applicable immediately before the notified date to any such person shall not be varied to his disadvantage except with the previous approval of the Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>With effect on and from the notified date the officers and other servants specified in such order shall become employees of the Board and shall cease to be officers or servants of the Government.</p>
            <p>Explanation: In this section, 'notified date' means such date as is notified by the Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Transfer of Provident Fund to the Board</heading>
        <subsection id="section-24.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The moneys standing to the credit under the Provident Fund Account of any officer or servant allotted from the service of the Government to the Board’s service, on the date specified in the order under sub-section (1) of section 23 shall stand transferred to and vest in the Board with effect on and from such date.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall, as soon as may be, after such date constitute in respect of the moneys and other assets which are transferred to and vested in it under sub-section (1), a similar fund and may invest the accumulations under the Fund in such securities and subject to such conditions, as may be specified by the Board with the approval of the Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Government to credit the leave salary and pensionary contribution in respect of the officers and servants allotted to Board's service</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Government shall credit to the account of the Board the leave salary and pensionary contributions in respect of the officers and servants allotted to the service of the Board in proportion to the leave at the credit of such officers and servants or in proportion to the length of their service under the Government as the case may be, according to the terms and conditions as are applicable to them under the Government on the date specified in the order under sub-section (1) of section 23.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Appointment of clerical and other staff by Board</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Board may, subject to the provisions of section 23, appoint such other officers and servants as it con-side 3 necessary for the efficient performance of its functions: Provided that the expenses of the staff so appointed and other administrative expenses shall not exceed such n percentage of the annual income of the Fund as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Powers of Government to call for records</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Government or any officer authorised by the Government may call for the records of the Board, inspect the same and may supervise the working of the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28">
        <num>28.</num>
        <heading>Mode of recovery of sums payable to Board</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any sum payable to the Board or into the Fund under this Act shall, without prejudice to any other mode of recovery, be recoverable on behalf of the Board as an arrear of land revenue.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29">
        <num>29.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for obstructing inspection or for failure to produce documents, etc.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-29.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-29.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any person who wilfully obstructs an Inspector in the exercise of his powers of discharge of his duties under this Act or fails to produce for inspection on demand by an Inspector any register, record, or other documents maintained in pursuance of the provisions of this Act or the rules made thereunder or to supply to him on demand true copies of any such document shall, on conviction, be punished:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-29.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for the first offence, with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three months, or with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, or with both; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-29.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>for a second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that, in the absence of special and adequate reasons to the contrary to he mentioned in the judgment of the court, in any case where the offender is sentenced to fine only, the amount of fine shall not be less than fifty rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-30">
        <num>30.</num>
        <heading>Cognizance of offences</heading>
        <subsection id="section-30.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No court shall take cognizance of any offence punishable under this Act except on a complaint by, or with previous sanction in writing of, the Secretary.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-30.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No Court inferior to that of a Presidency Magistrate or a Magistrate of the First Class shall try any offence punishable by or under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-31">
        <num>31.</num>
        <heading>Offences by companies</heading>
        <subsection id="section-31.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the person committing an offence under this Act is a Company, very person, who, at the time the offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible to, the company for the conduct of the business of the company as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence, and shah be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to any punishment provided in this Act, if he proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge, or that he exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of the offence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-31.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1) where an offence under this Act has been com-mitted by a company and it is proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of any director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.</p>
            <blockList id="section-31.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation: For the purposes of this section --corporate and association of</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-31.2.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"company" means a body corporate and includes a firm or other associations of individuals and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-31.2.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"director" in relation to a firm means a partner in the firm.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-32">
        <num>32.</num>
        <heading>Limitation of prosecution</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-32.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No court shall take cognizance of an offence punishable by or under this Act unless a complaint thereof is made within six months of the date on which the offence is alleged to have been committed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-33">
        <num>33.</num>
        <heading>Power to supervise the welfare activities of an establishment</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-33.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-33.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In regard to any money set apart in any establishment specifically for the purpose of promoting the welfare of the employees in such establishment the Board shall have powers:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-33.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>to require the production of any document in possession of the employers of the establishment in connection with such money to satisfy itself as to whether such money is being applied for such purpose;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-33.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>to call for any information from such employers of the establishment as it may deem relevant;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-33.paragraph-0.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>to issue such directions to the employers of such establishment as it may deem fit for the purpose of utilising the Fund for promoting the welfare of the employees.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-34">
        <num>34.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for non-compliance with the direction of the Board</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-34.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-34.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any person who wilfully fails to produce any document required by the Board or to furnish any information called for by the Board or wilfully fails to comply with any directions issued by the Board under section 33 shall on conviction be punished with:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-34.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for the first offence, with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three months, or with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, or with both; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-34.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>for a second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that, in the absence of special and adequate reasons to the contrary to be mentioned in the judgment of the court, in any case where the offender is sentenced to fine only, the amount of fine shall not be less than fifty rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-35">
        <num>35.</num>
        <heading>Annual Report</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-35.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall as soon as may be after the end of each year, prepare and submit to the Government before such date and in such form as may be prescribed a report giving an account of its activities during the previous year and the report shall also give an account of the activities, if any, which are likely to be undertaken by the Board in the next year; and the Government shall cause every such report to be laid before the State Legislature as soon as may be after it is received by the Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-36">
        <num>36.</num>
        <heading>Supersession of the Board</heading>
        <subsection id="section-36.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the Government are of opinion that the Board is unable to perform, or has persistently made default in the performance of the duty imposed on it by or under this Act or has exceeded or L used its powers, they may, by notification, supersede the Board for a period not exceeding six months as may be specified in the notification:</p>
            <p>Provided that before issuing a notification under this sub-section, the Government shall by notice require the Board to show cause within such period as may be specified in the notice why it should not be superseded and shall consider the explanations and objections, if any, of the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-36.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-36.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Upon the publication of a notification under sub-section (1) superseding the Board:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-36.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the Chairman and all the members of the Board shall, as from the date of supersession, vacate their offices as such;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-36.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>all the powers and duties which may, by or under the provisions of this Act, be exercised or performed by or on behalf of the Board and the Chairman shall, during the period of supersession, be exercised and performed by such authority or person as the Government may direct;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-36.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>all funds and other property vested in the Board shall, during the period of supersession, vest in the authority or person referred to in clause (a) ; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-36.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>all liabilities, legally subsisting and enforce-able against the Board shall be enforceable against the authority or person referred to in clause (b) to the extent the funds and proper-ties vested in it or him.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-36.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-36.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>On the expiration of the period of supersession specified in the notification issued under sub-section (1), the Government may,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-36.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>extend the period of supersession for such further period not exceeding six months as they may consider necessary; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-36.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>reconstitute the Board in the manner provided in section 5.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-37">
        <num>37.</num>
        <heading>Delegation of Powers</heading>
        <subsection id="section-37.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification, authorise any authority or officer to exercise any of the powers vested in them by or under this Act except the power to make rules under section 41 and may in like manner withdraw such authority.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-37.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board may, by general or special order in writing, delegate to the Secretary or other officer of the Board such of its powers and functions under this Act except the power to make regulations under section 42 as it may deem necessary and it may in like manner withdraw such authority.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-37.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The exercise of any power delegated under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) shall be subject to such restrictions and conditions as may be specified in the order and also to control and revision by the Government or by such officer as may be empowered by the Government in this behalf or, as the case may be, by the Board or such officer as may be empowered by the Board in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-37.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government or the Board, as the case may be, shall also have the power to control and revise the acts and proceedings of any officer so empowered.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-38">
        <num>38.</num>
        <heading>Members of Board, Secretary, Inspectors and all officers and servants of Board to be</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-38.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>public servants</p>
            <p>The members of the Board, the Secretary, Inspectors and all officers and servants of the Board, and any person entrusted with the execution of any function under this Act, shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (Central Act XLV of 1860).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-39">
        <num>39.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith</heading>
        <subsection id="section-39.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against any person for anything which is, in good faith, done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any rule or order made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-39.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Government or the Board for any damage caused or likely to be caused by anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any rule or order made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-40">
        <num>40.</num>
        <heading>Exemption</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-40.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification, exempt any establishment or class of establishments from all or any of the provisions of this Act or of any rules made thereunder subject to such conditions as may be specified in the notification.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-41">
        <num>41.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules</heading>
        <subsection id="section-41.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may make rules for the purpose of carrying into effect the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-41.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-41.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-41.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>all matters expressly required or allowed by this Act to be prescribed;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-41.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the intervals at which or the period within which any of the sums referred to in section 3 shall be paid to the Board or into the Fund, the manner of making such payment and the agency for, and manner of, collection of any such sum;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-41.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the manner in which the accounts of the Fund shall be maintained and audited;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-41.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the allowances, if any, payable to the members of the Board;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-41.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the manner in which the employee's contribution may be deducted from his wages;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-41.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the form of notice regarding unpaid accumulations;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-41.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the procedure for making grants from the Fund;.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-41.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the procedure for defraying the expenditure incurred in administering the Fund;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-41.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the manner in which the Board shall conduct its business;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-41.2.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>the duties and powers of the Inspectors and the conditions of service of the Secretary and Inspectors and other staff appointed under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-41.2.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>the delegation of the powers and functions of the Board to the Secretary and the conditions and limitations subject to which the powers may be exercised or functions discharged;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-41.2.list1.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>the percentage of the annual income of the Fund beyond which the Board may not spend on the staff and on other administrative expenses;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-41.2.list1.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>the registers and records to be maintained under the Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-41.2.list1.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>the publication of the report of the activities financed from the Fund together with a statement of receipts and expenditures of the Fund and statement of accounts.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-41.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All rules made under this Act shall be published in the Tamil Nadu Government</p>
            <p>Gazette, and unless they are expressed to come into force on a particular day, shall come into force on the day on which they are so, published.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-41.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All notifications issued under this Act shall, unless they are expressed to come into force on a particular day, come into force on the day on which they are published.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-41.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made or notification issued under this Act, shall, as soon as possible after it is made or issued be placed on the table of the Legislative Assembly and if, before the expiry of the session in i which it is so placed or the next session, the Legislative Assembly agrees in making any modification in any such rule or notification or the Legislative Assembly agrees 'that the rule or notification should not be made or issued, the rule or notification shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule or notification.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-42">
        <num>42.</num>
        <heading>Power to make regulations</heading>
        <subsection id="section-42.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board may, by notification issued whether prospectively or retrospectively make regulations not inconsistent with this Act, and the rules made thereunder for the purposes of giving effect to the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-42.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-42.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such regulations may provide for:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-42.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>all matters expressly required or allowed ( by this Act to be prescribed by regulations;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-42.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the terms and the conditions of appointment and service and the scales of pay of officers and servants of the Board including the payment of travelling and daily allowances in respect of journeys undertaken by such officers and servants of the Board;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-42.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the supervision and control over the acts and proceedings of the officers and servants of the Board and the maintenance of discipline and conduct among the officers and servants of the Board;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-42.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the procedure in regard to the transaction of business at the meetings of the Board including the quorum;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-42.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the purposes for which and the manner in which temporary association of persons may be made;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-42.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the duties, the functions, the terms and conditions of service of the members of the committees;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-42.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the manner and the form relating to the maintenance of the accounts of the Board.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-42.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No regulation or its cancellation or modification shall have effect until the same shall have been approved by the Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-42.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification, rescind any regulation made under this section and thereupon, the regulation shall cease to have effect.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-43">
        <num>43.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of section 8, Central Act IV of 1936</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-43.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In section 8 of the Payment of Wages Act, 1936 (Central Act IV of 1936), in sub-section (8), in the last sentence the following shall be added at the end, namely:—</p>
            <p>"but in the case of any establishment to which the Tamil Nadu Labour Welfare Fund Act, 1972 applies all such realisations shall be paid into the Fund constituted under the aforesaid Act."</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
