<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1982/4/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1982/4"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Sugar Development Fund Act, 1982"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1982/4/eng@1982-03-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1982/4/eng@1982-03-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1982-03-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1982/4/eng@1982-03-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1982/4/eng@1982-03-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Sugar Development Fund Act, 1982</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 4 OF 1982</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 19th March, 1982.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty- third Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the financing of activities for development of  sugar industry and for matters connected therewith or incidental  thereto.</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:--</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be  called the Sugar Development Fund Act, 1982.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date  as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" Committee" means the Committee constituted under  section 6;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" Fund" means the Sugar Development Fund formed under  section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>all other words and expressions used in this Act and not  defined, but defined in the Sugar Cess Act, 1982, shall have the  meanings respectively assigned to them in that Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Sugar Development Fund.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be formed a fund to be  called the Sugar Development Fund.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An amount equivalent to the proceeds of the duty of excise  levied and collected under the Sugar Cess Act, 1982, reduced by the  cost of collection as determined by the Central Government, together  with any moneys received by the Central Government for the purposes of  this Act, shall, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law, be  credited to the Fund.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Fund shall consist of the amounts credited under sub-</p>
            <p>section (2) and any income from investment of such amounts.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Application of Fund.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Fund shall be applied by the</p>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Central Government,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for making loans for facilitating the rehabilitation and  modernisation of any sugar factory or any unit thereof or the  undertaking of any scheme for development of sugarcane in the  area in which any sugar factory is situated;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-4.1.list2.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>for making grants for the purpose of any research  project aimed at development of sugar industry;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-4.1.list2.b.list0.bb">
                    <num>(bb)</num>
                    <p>for defraying expenditure for the purpose of  building up and maintenance of buffer stocks of sugar with a view  to establishing price of sugar;]</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>for defraying any other expenditure for the purposes of  this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The manner in which any loans or grants may be made under  this section and the terms and conditions subject to which such loans  or grants may be made shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Applications for loans or grants. Every application for loan  or grant under section 4 shall be made to the Committee in such manner  and in such form as may be prescribed.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Committee.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of securing speedy  consideration and disposal of applications received under section 5  and for considering any problems arising in the course of the  administration of this Act, the Central Government may constitute a  committee of officers of that Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The composition of the Committee and the procedure to be  followed by the Committee in the discharge of its functions under this</p>
            <p>Act shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Annual report of activities financed under the Act. The</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Central Government shall, as soon as may be, after the end of each  financial year, cause to be published in the Official Gazette, a  report giving an account of the activities financed under this Act  during the financial year, together with a statement of accounts.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Power to call for reports and returns. The Central Government  may require an occupier of a sugar factory to furnish, for the  purposes of this Act, such statistical and other information, in such  form and within such period as may be prescribed.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the  provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the manner in which any loans or grants may be made and  the terms and conditions subject to which such loans or grants  may be made under section 4;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the manner and form in which applications may be made  under section 5;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the composition of the Committee under section 6 and the  procedure to be followed by the Committee in the discharge of its  functions under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the form in which and the period within which  statistical and other information may be furnished under section</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>any other matter which is required to be or may be  prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as  may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is  in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised  in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before  the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the  successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not  be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified  form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any  such modification or annulment shall be without pejudice to the  validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
