<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1977/16/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1977/16"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Disputed Elections (Prime Minister Andspeaker) Act, 1977"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1977/16/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1977/16/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1977/16/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1977/16/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Disputed Elections (Prime Minister Andspeaker) Act, 1977</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 16 OF 1977</docNumber>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-18th">
        <num>18th.</num>
        <heading>April., 1977.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18th.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>An Act to provide for Authorities to deal with disputed elections  to Parliament in the case of Prime Minister and Speaker of the House  of the People and for matters connected therewith.</p>
            <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- eighth Year of the</p>
            <p>Republic of India as follows:-</p>
            <p>CHAP</p>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
            <p>Short title and commencement.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the</p>
              <p>Disputed Elections (Prime Minister and Speaker) Act, 1977.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 3rd day of</p>
              <p>February, 1977.</p>
              <p>Definitions.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definition. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" Authority" means an Authority constituted under  section 4 for the trial of a petition;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" candidate" means a person who has been or claims to  have been duly nominated as a candidate at any election;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" costs" means all costs, charges and expenses of, or  incidental to, trial of a petition under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" election" means an election in the case of Prime</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Minister or in the case of Speaker;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>" election in the case of Prime Minister" means an  election to either House of Parliament of a person who holds  the office of Prime Minister at the time of such election or  is appointed as Prime Minister after such election;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>" election in the case of Speaker" means an election to  the House of the People of a person who holds the office of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Speaker at the time of such election or is chosen as the</p>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Speaker for that House after such election;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>" Petition" means a petition calling in question an  election;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list7">
                <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list7.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>" returned candidate" means a candidate whose name has  been published under section 67 of the Representation of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list9">
                <listIntroduction>People Act, 1951, (43 of 1951) as duly elected at an election  in the case of 43 of 1951. Prime Minister or, as the case  may be, an election in the case of Speaker;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list9.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>each of the expressions defined in the Representation of  the People Act, 1951, 43 of 1951. but not defined in this Act  shall have the same meaning as in that Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>AUTHORITIES FOR DISPUTED ELECTIONS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>AUTHORITIES FOR DISPUTED ELECTIONS</p>
            <p>Petitions on respect of disputed elections.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Petitions on respect of disputed elections. No election shall  be called in question except by a petition presented in accordance  with the provisions of this Act.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Authority to try a petition.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Authority to try a petition.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every petition shall be  tried by an Authority, constituted for the purpose by the Central</p>
              <p>Government by notification in the official Gazette.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Authority shall consist of a single member, who is a</p>
              <p>Judge of the Supreme Court, to be nominated in this behalf by the</p>
              <p>Chief Justice of India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If for any reason a vacancy occurs in the office of member  aforesaid, the Chief Justice shall, as soon as practicable, nominate a  person to fill the vacancy, and thereupon the trial of the petition  shall be continued as if that member had been the Authority from the  commencement of the trial of such petition:</p>
              <p>Provided that the Authority may, if it thinks fit, recall and re-</p>
              <p>examine any of the witnesses already examined.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>PRESENTATION Of PETITIONS IN RESPECT OF DISPUTED ELECTIONS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRESENTATION Of PETITIONS IN RESPECT OF DISPUTED ELECTIONS</p>
            <p>Presentation of petition.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Presentation of petition.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A petition palling in question  any election may be presented on one or more of the grounds specified  in sub- section (1) of section 100 and section 101 of the</p>
              <p>Representation of the People Act, 1951, (43 of 1951) to the Election</p>
              <p>Commission by any candidate at such election or any elector within  fortyfive days from, but not earlier than, the date of election of the  returned candidate, or if there ire more returned candidates than one  at the election and the dates of their election are different, the  last of those dates:</p>
              <p>Provided that a petition calling in question the election of a  person who does not hold the office of Prime Minister or, as the case  may be, Speaker of the House of the People at the time of such  election and who is appointed or chosen to that office after such  election but before the expiry of the time for presenting such  election petition, may be presented within forty-</p>
              <p>five days from the date on which such person was appointed as the</p>
              <p>Prime Minister or chosen as the Speaker of the House of the People.</p>
              <p>Explanation.- In this sub- section," elector" means a person who  was entitled to vote at the election to which the petition relates,</p>
              <p>whether he has voted at such election or not.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A petition shall be deemed to have been presented to the</p>
              <blockList id="section-5.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Election Commission when it is delivered to the Election Commission or  to such other officer as may be appointed by it in this behalf-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.2.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>by the person making the petition, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-5.2.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>by a person authorised in writing in this behalf by the  person making the petition.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every petition shall be accompanied by as many copies  thereof as there are respondents mentioned in the petition and one  more copy for the use of the Election Commission, and every such copy  shall be attested by the petitioner under his own signature to be a  true copy of the petition.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>At the time of presenting a petition, the petitioner shall  deposit with the Election Commission in such manner as may be  prescribed a sum of two thousand rupees as security for costs.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Authority trying a petition may at any time during the  course of the trial of the petition call upon petitioner to give such  further security for costs as it may direct.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No person shall be entitled to be joined as a respondent to  a petition under sub- section (3) of section 10 unless he has given  such security for costs as the Authority may direct.</p>
              <p>Parties to the petition.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Parties to the petition. A petitioner shall join as respondents  to his petition-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>where the petitioner, in addition to claiming a  declaration that the election of all or any of the returned  candidates is void, claims a further declaration that he  himself or any other candidate has been duly elected, all the  contesting candidates other than the petitioner, and where no  such further declaration is claimed, all the returned  candidates; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>any other candidate against whom allegations of any  corrupt practice are made in the petition.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Contents of petition.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-7.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Contents of petition. A petition-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>shall contain a concise statement of the material facts  on which the petitioner relies;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>shall set forth full particulars of any corrupt  practice that the petitioner alleges, including as full a  statement as possible of the names of the parties alleged to  have committed such cor-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-7.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>rupt practice and the date and place of the commission of  each such practice; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.1.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>shall be signed by the petitioner and verified in the  manner laid down in the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908, (5   of 1908) for the verification of pleadings:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that where the petitioner alleges any corrupt practice,</p>
              <p>the petition shall also be accompanied by an affidavit in the  prescribed form in support of the allegation of such corrupt practice  and the particulars thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any schedule or annexure to the petition shall also be  signed by the petitioner and verified in the same manner as the  petition.</p>
              <p>Relief that may be claimed by the petitioner.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Relief that may be claimed by the petitioner. A petitioner may,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>in addition to claiming a declaration that the election of all or any  of the returned candidates is void, claim a further declaration that  he himself or any other candidate has been duly elected.</p>
              <p>Procedure on receiving petitions.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Procedure on receiving petitions.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Election Commission  shall, as soon as may be after the receipt of a petition under section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>, forward it to the Authority for trying the petition.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where more petitions than one have been received under  section 5 in respect of the same election, the Election Commission  shall forward them to the Authority and such Authority may, in its  discretion, try them separately or in one or more groups.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>TRIAL OF PETITIONS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>TRIAL OF PETITIONS</p>
            <p>Trial of petitions.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Trial of petitions.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to any rules made in this  behalf, the Authority for the trial of any petition shall hold the  trial at New Delhi.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-10.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Authority shall dismiss the petition-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>if the petition has not been presented within the  period specified in sub- section (1) of section 5;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>if the petition does not comply with the provisions of  sub- section (3) or sub- section (4) of section 5 or section 6.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Explanation.- An order dismissing a petition under this sub-</p>
              <p>section shall be deemed to be an order made under clause (a) of  section 16.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any candidate not already a respondent to a petition shall,</p>
              <p>upon application made by him to the Authority within fourteen days  from the date of commencement of the trial and subject to any order as  to security for costs which may be made by the Authority, be entitled  to be joined as a respondent.</p>
              <p>Explanation.- For the purposes of this sub- section and of section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>the trial of a petition shall be deemed to commence on the date  fixed for the respondents to appear before the Authority and answer  the claim or claims made in the petition.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-15.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Authority may, upon such terms as to costs and otherwise  as it may deem fit, allow the particulars of any corrupt practice  alleged in the petition to be amended or amplified in such manner as  may in its opinion be necessary for ensuring a fair and effective  trial of the petition, but shall not allow any amendment of the  petition which will have the effect of introducing particulars of a  corrupt practice not previously alleged in the petition.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The trial of a petition shall, so far as is practicable  consistently with the interests of justice in respect of the trial, be  continued from day to day until its conclusion, unless the Authority  finds the adjournment of the trial beyond the following day to be  necessary for reasons to be recorded.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every petition shall be tried as expeditiously as possible  and endeavour shall be made to conclude the trial within six months  from the date of commencement of the trial.</p>
              <p>Procedure before the Authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Procedure before the Authority.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions  of this Act and of any rules made thereunder, every petition shall be  tried by the Authority, as nearly as may be, in accordance with the  procedure applicable under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1908">
          <num>1908.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1908.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>) to the trial of suits:</p>
              <p>Provided that the Authority shall have the discretion to refuse,</p>
              <p>for reasons to be recorded in writing, to examine any witness or  witnesses, if it is of the opinion that the evidence of such witness  or witnesses is not material for the decision of the petition or that  the party tendering such witness or witnesses is doing so on frivolous  grounds or with a view to delay the proceedings.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-1908.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purposes of any such trial, the Authority shall have  all the powers of a Civil Court while trying a suit under the Code of</p>
              <blockList id="section-1908.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Civil Procedure, 1908, (5 of 1908) in respect of the following  matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1908.2.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person  and examining him on oath;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1908.2.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>requiring the discovery and production of any document;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1908.2.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>receiving evidence on affidavits;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1908.2.list2.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>requisitioning any public record or copy thereof from  any court or office;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1908.2.list2.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses or  documents;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1908.2.list2.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>such other matters as may be prescribed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1908.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872, (1 of</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1872">
          <num>1872.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1872.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>) shall, subject to the provisions of this Act, be deemed to apply  in all respects to the trial of a petition.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-1872.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any proceeding before the Authority shall be deemed to be a  judicial proceeding within the meaning of section 193 of the Indian</p>
              <p>Penal Code. (45 of 1860)</p>
              <p>Secrecy of voting not to be infringed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Secrecy of voting not to be infringed. No witness or other  person shall be required to state for whom he has voted at an  election.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Answering of criminating questions and certificate of indemnity.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Answering of criminating questions and certificate of  indemnity.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-13.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No witness shall be excused from answering any question  as to any matter relevant to a matter in issue in the trial of a  petition upon the ground that the answer to such question may  criminate or may tend to criminate him, or that it may expose or may  tend to expose him to any penalty or forfeiture:</p>
              <blockList id="section-13.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-13.1.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>a witness, who answers truly all questions which he is  required to answer shall be entitled to receive a certificate  of indemnity from the Authority; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.1.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>an answer given by a witness to a question put by or  before the Authority shall not, except in the case of any  criminal proceeding for perjury in respect of the evidence,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>be admissible in evidence against him in any civil or  criminal proceeding.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When a certificate of indemnity has been granted to any  witness, it may be pleaded by him in any court and shall be a full and  complete defence to or upon any charge under Chapter IXA of the Indian</p>
              <p>Penal Code (45 of 1860) Part VII of the Representation of the People</p>
              <p>Act, 1951, (43 of 1951) arising out of the matter to which such  certificate relates, but it shall not be deemed to relieve him from  any disqualification in connection with an election imposed by this</p>
              <p>Act or any other law.</p>
              <p>Expenses of witnesses.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Expenses of witnesses. The reasonable expenses incurred by any  person in attending to give evidence before the Authority may be  allowed by it to such person, and shall, unless the Authority  otherwise directs, be deemed to be part of the costs.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Recrimination when seat claimed.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Recrimination when seat claimed.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-15.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When in a petition a  declaration that any candidate other than the returned candidate has  been duly elected is claimed, the returned candidate or any other  party may give evidence to prove that the election of such candidate  would have been void if he had been the returned candidate and a  petition had been presented calling in question his election:</p>
              <p>Provided that the returned candidate or such other party, as  aforesaid shall not be entitled to give such evidence unless he his,</p>
              <p>within fourteen</p>
              <p>days from the date of commencement of the trial, given notice to  the. Authority of his intention to do so and has also given the  security and the further security referred to in sub- sections (4), (5)</p>
              <p>and (6) respectively of section 5.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every notice referred to in sub- section (1) shall be</p>
              <p>Accompained by the statement and particulars required by section 7 in  the case of a petition and shall be signed and verified in like  manner.</p>
              <p>Decision of the Authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Decision of the Authority. At the conclusion of the trial of a  petition the Authority shall make an order-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-16.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>dismissing the petition; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>declaring the election of all or any of the returned  candidates to be void; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>declaring the election of all or any of the returned  candidates to be void and the petitioner or any other  candidate to have been duly elected.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Other orders to be made by the Authority.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Other orders to be made by the Authority.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-17.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>At the time of  making an order under section 16, the Authority shall also make an  order-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-17.1.list1.a.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>Where any charge is made in the petition of any corrupt  practice having been committed at the election, recording-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-17.1.list1.a.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>a finding whether any corrupt practice has or has  not been proved to have been committed at the election,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-17.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>and the nature of that corrupt practice; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.1.list3.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>the names of all persons, if any, who have been  proved at the trial to have been guilty of any corrupt  practice and the nature of that practice; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.1.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>fixing the total amount of costs payable and specifying  the persons by and to whom costs shall be paid:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-17.1.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that a person who is not a party to the petition shall  not be named in the order tinder sub- clause (ii) of clause (a) unless-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.1.list5.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>he has been given notice to appear before the Authority  and to show cause why he should not be so named; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.1.list5.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>if he appears in pursuance of the notice, he has been  given an opportunity of cross- examining any witness who has  already been examined by the Authority and has given evidence  against him, of calling evidence in his defence and of being  heard.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In this section and in section 18, the expression" agent"</p>
              <p>has the same meaning as in section 123 of the Representation of the</p>
              <p>People Act, 1951. (43 of 1951)</p>
              <p>Grounds for declaring election to be void.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Grounds for declaring election to be void.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-18.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-18.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Subject to the  provisions of sub- section (2), if the Authority is of opinion-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-18.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>that on the date of his election a returned candidate  was not qualified, or was disqualified, to be chosen to fill  the seat under the Constitution or the Representation of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-18.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>People Act, 1951, (43 of 1951) or this Act or the Government  of Union Territories Act, 1963; 20 of 1963 or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-18.1.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>that any corrupt practice has been committed by a  returned candidate or his election agent or by any other  person with the consent of a returned candidate or his  election agent; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.1.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>that any nomination has been improperly rejected; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.1.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-18.1.list3.d.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>that the result of the election, in so far as it  concerns the returned candidate, has been materially  affected-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-18.1.list3.d.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>by the improper acceptance of any  nomination, or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-18.1.list3.d.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>by any corrupt practice committed in the interests  of the returned candidate by an agent other than his  election agent, or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-18.1.list3.d.list0.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>by the improper reception, refusal or  rejection of any vote or the reception of any vote which  is void, or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-18.1.list3.d.list0.iv">
                      <num>(iv)</num>
                      <p>by any non- compliance with the provisions of  the Constitution or of this Act or of any rules or  orders made under this Act, the Authority shall declare  the election of the returned candidate to be void.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-18.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>If in the opinion of the Authority a returned candidate has  been guilty by an agent, other than his election agent, of any corrupt  practice but the Authority is satisfied-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-18.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>that no such corrupt practice was committed at the  election by the candidate or his election agent, and every  such corrupt practice was committed contrary to the orders,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-18.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>and without the consent, of the candidate or his election  agent;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-18.2.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>that the candidate and his election agent took all  reasonable means for preventing the commission of corrupt  practices at the election; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.2.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>that in all other respects the election was free from  any corrupt practice on the part of the candidate or any of  his agents, then the Authority may decide that the election  of the returned candidate is not void.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Grounds for which a candidate other than the returned candidate may bedeclared  to have been elected.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Grounds for which a candidate other than the returned  candidate may be declared to have been elected. If any person who has  lodged a petition has, in addition to calling in question the election  of the returned candidate, claimed a declaration</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>that he himself or any other candidate has been duly elected and the</p>
              <blockList id="section-19.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Authority is of opinion--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>that in fact the petitioner or such other candidate  received a majority of the valid votes; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>that but for the votes obtained by the returned  candidate by corrupt practices the petitioner or such other  candidate would have obtained a majority of the valid votes,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>the Authority shall after declaring the election of the  returned candidate to be void declare the petitioner or such  other candidate, as the case may be, to have been duly  elected.</p>
              <p>Communication of orders of the Authority.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Communication of orders of the Authority. The Authority shall,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>as soon as may be after the conclusion of the trial of a petition,</p>
              <p>intimate the substance of the decision to the Election Commission and  the Speaker or the Chairman, as the case may be, of the House of</p>
              <p>Parliament and, as soon as may be thereafter, shall send to the</p>
              <p>Election Commission an authenticated copy of the decision.</p>
              <p>Costs.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Costs. Costs shall be in the discretion of the Authority:</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Provided that where a petition is dismissed under clause (a) of  section 16, the returned candidate shall be entitled to the costs  incurred by him in contesting the petition and accordingly the</p>
              <p>Authority shall make an order for costs in favour of the returned  candidate.</p>
              <p>Ordersof Authority to be final. 22. Orders of Authority to be final. No  order made by an Authorityunder this Act shall be called in question in any  court.</p>
              <p>Effect of orders of Authority.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Effect of orders of Authority.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-23.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An order made by an</p>
              <p>Authority under this Act shall take effect as soon as it is pronounced  by the Authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where by an order under section 16 the election of a  returned candidate is declared to be void, acts and proceedings in  which that returned candidate has, before the date thereof,</p>
              <p>participated as a member of Parliament or, as the Prime Minister or as  the Speaker of the House of the People shall not be invalidated by  reason of that order, nor shall such candidate be subjected to any  liability or penalty on the ground of such participation.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-V.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
            <p>Withdrawal and abatement of petitions.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Withdrawal and abatement of petitions. The provisions of  sections 109 to 116 (both inclusive) of the Representation of the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>People Act, 1951, (43 of 1951) relating to withdrawal and abatement  of election petitions shall, so far as may be, apply in relation to</p>
              <p>withdrawal and abatement of petitions under this Act subject to the  modifications that the references therein to an election petition,</p>
              <p>High Court and petitioner shall be construed as references to a  petition under this Act, the Authority for hearing such petition and  the petitioner in respect of such petition respectively.</p>
              <p>Payment of costs out of security deposits and return of such deposits.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Payment of costs out of security deposits and return of  such deposits.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-25.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If in any order as to costs under the provisions  of this Act there is a direction for payment of costs by any party to  any person, such costs shall, if they have not been already paid, be  paid in full, or so far as possible, out of the security deposit and  the further security deposit, if any, made by such party under this</p>
              <p>Act on an application made in writing in that behalf within a period  of one year, from the date of such order to the Election Commission by  the person in whose favour the costs have been awarded.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If there is any balance left of any of the said security  deposits after payment under sub- section (1) of the costs referred to  in that sub- section, such balance, or where no costs have been awarded  or no application as aforesaid has been made within the said period of  one year, the whole of the said security deposits may, on an  application made in that behalf in writing to the Election Commission  by the person by whom the deposits have been made, or if such person  dies after making such deposits, by the legal representative of such  person, be returned to the said person or to his legal representative,</p>
              <p>as the case may be.</p>
              <p>Execution of orders as to costs.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Execution of orders as to costs. Any order as to costs under  the provisions of this Act may be produced before the principal civil  court of original jurisdiction within the local limits of whose  jurisdiction any person directed by such order to pay any sum of money  has a place of residence or business or where such place is within a  presidency- town before the court of small causes having jurisdiction  there, and such court shall execute the order or cause the same to be  executed in the same manner and by the same procedure as if it were a  decree for the payment of money made by itself in a suit:</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Provided that where any such costs or any portion thereof may be  recovered by an application made under sub- section (1) of section 25,</p>
              <p>no application shall lie under this section within a period of one  year from the date of such order unless it is for the recovery of the  balance of any costs which has been left unrealised after an  application has been made under that sub- section owing to the  insufficiency of the amount of the security deposits referred to in  that sub- section.</p>
              <p>Power to make rules.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rule.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-27.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may make  rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-27.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the deposit or further deposit to be made by the  petitioner as security for the costs;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the appointment of officers and other employees for  assisting the Authorities in the discharge of their functions  and the conditions of service of such officers and other  employees;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the custody of deposits made under this Act, the  payment of costs out of such deposits on an application made  under section 25 and other matters relating to the disposal  of such application;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the fees, if any, payable in respect of any petition or  application under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>any other matter which has to be prescribed by or  provided for by rules made under this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act  shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House  of Parliament while it is in session, for a total period of thirty  days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more  successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session  immediately following the session, or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or  both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall  thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</p>
              <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything pre-</p>
              <p>viously done under that rule.</p>
              <p>Repeal and saving.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Repeal and saving.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-28.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Disputed Elections (Prime Minister   and Speaker) Ordinance, 1977, (4 of 1977) is hereby repealed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-28.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action  taken under the provisions of the said Ordinance shall be deemed to  have been done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this</p>
              <p>Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
