<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1918/10/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1918/10"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Usurious Loans Act, 1918"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1918/10/eng@1918-03-22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1918/10/eng@1918-03-22"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1918-03-22" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1918/10/eng@1918-03-22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1918/10/eng@1918-03-22"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Usurious Loans Act, 1918</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 10 OF 1918</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 22nd March, 1918.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to give additional powers to Courts to deal in certain cases  with usurious loans of money or in kind.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to give additional powers to Courts to  deal in certain cases with usurious loans of money or in kind; It is  hereby enacted as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Short title and extent. This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Usurious Loans Act, 1918.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India except  (the territories  which, immediately before the lst November, 1956, were comprised in</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <part id="part-B">
        <num>B</num>
        <heading>States) .</heading>
        <subsection id="part-B.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official</p>
            <p>Gazette, direct that it shall not apply to any area, class of persons,</p>
            <p>or class of transactions which it may specify in its notification.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant  in the subject or context,-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-2.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" Interest" means rate of interest and includes the  return to be made over and above what was actually lent,</p>
              <p>whether the same is charged or sought to be recovered  specifically by way of interest or otherwise.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" Loan" means a loan whether of money or in kind and  includes any transaction which is, in the opinion of the</p>
              <p>Court, in substance a loan.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>" Suit to which this Act applies" means any suit-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>for the recovery of a loan made after the commencement  of this Act; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.3.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>for the enforcement of any security taken or any agreement,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>whether by, way of settlement of account or otherwise, made,</p>
              <p>after the commencement of this Act, in</p>
              <blockList id="section-2.3.list5">
                <listIntroduction>respect of any loan made either before or after the commencement  of this Act;  or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.3.list5.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>for the redemption of any security given after the com-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>mencement of this Act in respect of any loan made either  before or after the commencement of this Act.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Re- opening of transaction. Notwithstanding anything in the</p>
              <blockList id="section-3.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Usury Laws Repeal Act, 1855 (28 of 1855), where, in any suit to which  this Act applies, whether heard ex parte or otherwise, the Court has  reason to believe,</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.1.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>that the interest is excessive; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.1.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>that the transaction was, as between the parties  thereto substantially unfair,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.1.list4">
                <listIntroduction>the Court may exercise all or any of the following powers, namely  may,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.1.list4.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>re- open the transaction, take an account between the  parties and relieve the debtor of all liability in respect of  any excessive interest</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.1.list4.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>notwithstanding any agreement, purporting to close  previous dealings and to create a new obligation, re- open any  account already taken between them and relieve the debtor of  all liability in respect of any- excessive interest, and if  anything has been paid or allowed in account in respect of  such liability, order the creditor to repay any sum which it  considers to be repayable in respect thereof;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.1.list4.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>set aside either wholly or in part or revise or  alter any security given or agreement made in respect of any  loan, and if the creditor has parted with the security, order  him to indemnify the debtor in such manner and to such  extent as it may deem just:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.1.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that, in the exercise of these powers, the Court  shall not-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.1.list6.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>re- open any agreement purporting to close previous  dealings and to create a new obligation which has been  entered into by the parties or any persons from whom they  claim at a date more than  twelve] years from the date of  the transaction;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.1.list6.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>do anything which affects any decree of a Court.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Explanation.- In the case of a suit brought on a series of  transactions the expression" the transaction" means, for the purposes  of proviso (i), the first of such transactions.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.2.list0">
                <item id="section-3.2.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>In this section" excessive" means in excess of that  which the Court deems to be reasonable having regard to the risk  incurred</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>as it appeared, or must be taken to have appeared, to the creditor at  the date of the loan.</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.2.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>In considering whether interest is excessive under this sec-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>tion, the Court shall take into account any amounts charged or paid,</p>
              <p>whether in money or in kind, for expenses, inquiries, fines, bonuses,</p>
              <blockList id="section-3.2.list6">
                <listIntroduction>premia, renewals or any other charges, and if compound interest is  charged, the periods at which it is calculated, and the total  advantage which may reasonably be taken to have been expected from the  transaction.</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.2.list6.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>In considering the question of risk, the Court shall take  into account the presence or absence of security and the value  thereof, the financial condition of the debtor and the result of any  previous transactions of the debtor, by way of loan, so far as the  same were known, or must be taken to have been known, to the creditor.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.2.list6.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>In considering whether a transaction was substantially un-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>fair, the Court shall take into account all circumstances materially  affecting the relations of the parties at the time of the loan or  tending to show that the transaction was unfair, including the  necessities or supposed necessities of the debtor at the time- of the  loan so far as the same were known, or must be taken to have been  known, to the creditor.</p>
              <p>Explanation.- Interest may of itself be sufficient evidence that  the transaction was Substantially unfair.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This section shall apply to any suit, whatever its form may  be, if such suit is substantially one for the recovery of a loan or  for the enforcement of any agreement or security in respect of a loan    or for the redemption of any such security].</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in this section shall affect the rights of any  transferee for value who satisfies the Court that the transfer to him  was bona fide, and that he had at the time of such transfer no notice  of any fact which would have entitled the debtor as against the lender  to relief under this section.</p>
              <p>For the purposes of this sub- section, the word" notice" shall  have the same meaning as is ascribed to it in section 4 of the</p>
              <p>Transfer of Property Act, 1882 (4 of 1882).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in this section shall be construed as derogating  from the existing powers or jurisdiction of any Court.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Insolvency proceedings. On any application relating to the  admission or amount of a proof of a loan in any insolvency  proceedings, the Court may exercise the like powers as may be  exercised under section 3 by a Court in a suit to which this Act  applies.</heading>
        </section>
      </part>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
