<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/25"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Jallianwala Bagh National Memorial Act, 1951"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/25/eng@1951-05-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/25/eng@1951-05-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1951-05-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/25/eng@1951-05-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/25/eng@1951-05-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Jallianwala Bagh National Memorial Act, 1951</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 25 OF 1951</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 1st May, 1951.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the erection and management of a National</p>
        <p>Memorial to perpetuate the memory of those killed or wounded on the</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-13th">
        <num>13th.</num>
        <heading>day of April, 1919, in Jallianwala Bagh.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13th.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>BE it enacted by Parliament as follows:-</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title. This Act may be called the Jallianwala Bagh</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>National Memorial Act, 1951.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" Memorial" means the Jallianwala Bagh National Memorial  to perpetuate the memory of those killed or wounded on the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13th">
        <num>13th.</num>
        <heading>day of April, 1919, on the site known as the Jallianwala</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13th.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13th.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Bagh, Amritsar;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13th.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" Trust" means the Trust for the erection and  management of the Memorial;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13th.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" Trustees" means the Trustees of the Jallianwala Bagh</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>National Memorial.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Objects of the Trust. The objects of the Trust shall be-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to erect and maintain suitable buildings, structures  and parks at or near the site of the Jallianwala Bagh in the  city of Amritsar, to perpetuate the memory of those who were  killed or wounded on the 13th day of April, 1919, on the said  site;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to acquire lands, buildings and other properties for  the purposes of the Trust; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to raise and receive funds for the purposes of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Memorial.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Trustees of the Jallianwala Bagh National Memorial. The</p>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Trustees of the Jallianwala Bagh National Memorial shall be the  following, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>Shri Jawaharlal Nehru,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>Dr. Saifuddin Kitchlew,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>Maulana Abul Kalam Azad,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the President of the Indian National Congress,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list2.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the Governor of the State of Punjab,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list2.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the Chief Minister of the State of Punjab, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list2.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>three persons nominated by the Central Government.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Trustees shall be a body corporate with perpetual  succession by the name of the" Trustees of the Jallianwala Bagh</p>
            <p>National Memorial" and a common seal, and in that name shall sue and  be sued, and shall have power to acquire and hold property, to enter  into contracts and to do all acts necessary for and consistent with,</p>
            <p>the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Term of office of Trustees.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The three Trustees  mentioned in clauses (a), (b) and (c) of sub- section (1) of section 4  shall be Trustees for life.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Trustee nominated under clause (g) of the said  sub- section shall be a Trustee for a period of five years, and shall  be eligible for renomination.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Property vested in Trustees. All the property and funds set  out in the Schedule to this Act and all other property, whether  movable or immovable, which may hereafter be given, bequeathed or  otherwise transferred for this purposes of the Memorial or acquired  for the said purposes shall vest in the Trustees.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Power of Trustees to appoint committee of management.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purposes of managing the affairs of the Trust, the Trustees  may, by resolution passed at a meeting, appoint a committee of  management, and entrust to it such powers, duties and functions, under  such directions and limitations, as may be defined by such resolution.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Trustees may appoint any persons as members of the  committee of management, whether such persons are Trustees or not, and  may, from time to time, vary or rescind any resolution passed by it  under this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Validity of acts of Trustees not to be questioned by reason  of vacancy, etc. No act of the Trustees shall be deemed to be invalid  merely by reason of any vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution  of, the body of Trustees.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules 1 to carry out the  objects of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the manner in which funds belonging to the Memorial  shall be kept, deposited or invested;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the mode of authentication of orders for payment of  money by the Trustees;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the form in which accounts shall be kept by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-9.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Trustees and the audit and publication of such accounts;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.2.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the laying out, erection, improvement, maintenance and  management of the Memorial and the care and custody of the  properties thereof;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the conditions under which the public shall have access  to the Memorial or particular parts thereof and the regula-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>tion of the conduct of persons entering the precincts of the</p>
            <blockList id="section-9.2.list6">
              <listIntroduction>Memorial;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.2.list6.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the preservation of, and the prevention of injury to or  interference with, any property vested in the Trustees and  the prevention of persons from trespassing into any parti-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>cular part of the Memorial.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A rule made under this section may provide that a breach of  any rule made under clauses (e) and (f) of sub- section (2) shall be  punishable with fine which may extend to one hundred rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Power of Trustees to make regulations. The Trustees may make  regulations consistent with this Act for all or any of the following  purposes, namely:-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the manner in which meetings of the Trustees shall be  convened, the quorum for the transaction of any business  thereat and the procedure at such meetings;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the manner in which a majority decision of the Trustees  shall be obtained by circulation to the Trustees of the  matter requiring decision;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the term of office of members of the committee of  management, their powers and duties, and the circumstances in  which and the conditions subject to which such powers and  duties may be exercised;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the appointment of such officers and servants as may be  necessary for the purposes of the Trust, and their terms and  conditions of service.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
