<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-chg/act/2001/27/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-chg/act/2001/27"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Chhattisgarh Shaikshanik Sansthan Me Pratarna Ka Pratishedh Act, 2001"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-chg/act/2001/27/eng@2017-01-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-chg/act/2001/27/eng@2017-01-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-chg/act/2001/27/eng@2017-01-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-chg/act/2001/27/eng@2017-01-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-24" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Chhattisgarh Shaikshanik Sansthan Me Pratarna Ka Pratishedh Act, 2001</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 27 OF 2001</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[17th January, 2002.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to prevent ragging in educational institutions in the State and for matters connected therewith and incidental thereto.</p>
      </longTitle>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by the Chhattisgarh legislature in the Fifty-second Year of the Republic of India as follows:-</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Chhattisgarh Shaikshanik Sansthan Me Pratarna Ka Pratishedh Adhiniyarn, 2001 (No. 27 of 2001).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the Chhattisgarh.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the State Government may, by notification, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires –</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“ragging” means causing, inducing compelling or forcing a student, whether by way of a practical joke or otherwise, to do any act which detracts from human dignity or violates his person or exposes him to ridicule or forbear from doing any unlawful act, by intimidating, wrongfully restraining, wrongfully confining, or injuring him or by using criminal force to him or by holding out to him any threat or such intimidation, wrongful restraint, wrongful confinement, injury or the use of criminal force.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition of ragging.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No student of an educational institution either directly or indirectly or by any other means or any where shall commit or take part in ragging.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Punishment.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any person who contravenes the provisions of Section 3 or attempts to commit or abets the act of ragging or takes part either directly or indirectly in ragging shall be punished with either of the description for imprisonment which may extend upto five years or with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Offence to be cognisable, non-bailable and non-compoundable.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every offence under this Act shall be cognisable, non-bailable and non-compoundable.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Trial of offences.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every offence punishable under this Act shall be tried by a Judicial Magistrate of first class.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of the code of criminal procedure, 1973 (No. 2 of 1974) shall apply for investigation, inquiry and trial of the offences under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Disqualification for remaining as student.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Pending investigation of trial of an offence under this Act, the head of the educational institution shall have the power to suspend a student accused of an offence under this Act and debar him from entry into premises of the educational institution and the hostel.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A student of an educational institution who has been convicted under Section 4 shall be liable to rustication from the educational institution.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A student who has been rusticated or any other person who has been convicted under this Act shall not be admitted to another educational institution within the jurisdiction of the state for a period of three years.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
