<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1957/38/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1957/38"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Inter- State Corporations Act, 1957"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1957/38/eng@1957-09-20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1957/38/eng@1957-09-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1957-09-20" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1957/38/eng@1957-09-20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1957/38/eng@1957-09-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Inter- State Corporations Act, 1957</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 38 OF 1957</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 20th September, 1957.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Eighth Year of the Republic of</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the reorganisation of certain corporations  functioning in two or more States by virtue of section 109 of the</p>
        <p>States Reorganisation Act, 1956  or of any other enactment  relating to reorganisation of States], and for matters connected  therewith.</p>
        <p>India as follows:--</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title. This Act may be called the Inter- State</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Corporations Act, 1957.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definition. In this Act," inter- State corporation" means any  body corporate constituted under any of the Acts specified in the</heading>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-scheduleand">
      <doc name="scheduleand">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1957/38/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1957/38"/>
              <FRBRalias value="functioning in two or more States by virtue of section"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1957/38/eng@1957-09-20/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1957/38/eng@1957-09-20"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1957/38/eng@1957-09-20/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1957/38/eng@1957-09-20"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduleand">
            <heading>109 of the States Reorganisation Act, 1956 (37 of 1956.)  or of any  other enactment relating to reorganisation of States].</heading>
            <section id="section-3">
              <num>3.</num>
              <heading>Power of State Governments to frame schemes. If it appears to  the Government of a State in any part of which an inter- State  corporation is functioning that the inter- State corporation should be  reconstituted and reorganised as one or more intra- State corporations  or that it should be dissolved, the State Government may frame a  scheme for such reconstitution and reorganisation or such dissolution,</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>as the case may be, including proposals regarding the transfer of the  assets, rights and liabilities of the inter- State corporation to any  other corporations or State Governments and the transfer or re-</p>
                  <p>employment of employees of the inter- State corporation and forward the  scheme to the Central Government.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-4">
              <num>4.</num>
              <heading>Reorganisation of certain inter- State corporations.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-4.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>On  receipt of a scheme forwarded to it under section 3 the Central</p>
                  <p>Government may, after consulting the State Governments concerned,</p>
                  <p>approve the scheme with or without modifications and give effect to  the scheme so approved by making such order as it thinks fit.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-4.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-4.2.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>An order made under sub- section (1) may provide for all or  any of the following matters, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-4.2.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the dissolution of the inter- State corporation;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-4.2.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>the reconstitution and reorganisation in any manner  whatsoever of the inter- State corporation including the  constitution, where necessary, of new corporations;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-4.2.list1.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>the area in respect of which the reconstituted  corporation or new corporation shall function and  operate;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-4.2.list1.d">
                      <num>(d)</num>
                      <p>the transfer, in whole or in part, of the assets, rights  and liabilities of the inter- State corporation</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>(including the rights and liabilities under any   contract made by it) to any other corporations or State</p>
                  <blockList id="section-4.2.list4">
                    <listIntroduction>Governments and the terms and conditions of such  transfer;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-4.2.list4.e">
                      <num>(e)</num>
                      <p>the substitution of any such transferee for the inter-</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>State corporation, or the addition of any such  transferee, as a party to any legal proceeding to which  the inter- State corporation is a party; and the  transfer of any proceedings pending before the inter-</p>
                  <blockList id="section-4.2.list7">
                    <listIntroduction>State corporation to any such transferee;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-4.2.list7.f">
                      <num>(f)</num>
                      <p>the transfer or re- employment of any employees of the  inter- State corporation to, or by, any such transferee  and subject to the provisions of section 111 of the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>States Reorganisation Act, 1956 (37 of 1956)  or of  any other enactment relating to reorganisation of</p>
                  <blockList id="section-4.2.list10">
                    <listIntroduction>States], the terms and conditions of service applicable  to such employees after such transfer or re- employment;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-4.2.list10.g">
                      <num>(g)</num>
                      <p>the adaptations or modifications of the Act under which  the inter- State corporation was constituted, whether by  way of repeal or amendment, as may be necessary or  expedient to give effect to the approved scheme;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-4.2.list10.h">
                      <num>(h)</num>
                      <p>such incidental, consequential and supplementary matters  as may be necessary to give effect to the approved  scheme.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-4.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where an order is made under this section transferring the  assets, rights and liabilities of any inter- State corporation, then,</p>
                  <p>by virtue of that order, such assets, rights and liabilities of the  inter- State corporation shall vest in, and be the assets, rights and  liabilities of, the transferee.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-4.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every order made under this section shall be published in the</p>
                  <p>Official Gazette and the Act under which the inter- State corporation  was constituted shall have effect subject to the provisions of the  order and the adaptations and modifications made thereby until  altered, repealed or amended by the competent Legislature of a State.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-4.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every order made under this section shall be laid, as soon  as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it  is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be  comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and  if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session  or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the order or both Houses agree that the order should  not be made, the order shall thereafter have effect only in such  modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however,</p>
                  <p>that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to  the validity of anything previously done under that order.]</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-5">
              <num>5.</num>
              <heading>Power of Central Government to add to the Schedule. The</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette,</p>
                  <p>specify in the Schedule any Act under which a body</p>
                  <p>corporate constituted for a State is functioning in two or more States  by virtue of section 109 of the States Reorganisation Act, 1956 (37 of</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-1956">
              <num>1956.</num>
              <heading/>
              <paragraph id="section-1956.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>)  or of any other enactment relating to reorganisation of</p>
                  <p>States], and on the issue of such notification, the Schedule shall be  deemed to be amended by the inclusion of the said Act therein.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
