<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-tmn/act/1981/46/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-tmn/act/1981/46"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Tamil Nadu Industrial Establishments (Conferment Of Permanent Status To Workmen) Act, 1981"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-tmn/act/1981/46/eng@2017-05-04/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-tmn/act/1981/46/eng@2017-05-04"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-05-04" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-tmn/act/1981/46/eng@2017-05-04/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-tmn/act/1981/46/eng@2017-05-04"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-05-04" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Tamil Nadu Industrial Establishments (Conferment Of Permanent Status To Workmen) Act, 1981</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>(Act No. 46 of 1981)</p>
        <p>(Received the assent of the president on the 5th August, 1981).</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the conferment of permanent status to workmen in the industrial establishments in the State of Tamil Nadu.</p>
        <p>Be it enacted by the Legislature of the State of Tamil Nadu in the Thirty-Second Year of the Republic of India as follows:</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title extent application and commencement</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Tamil Nadu Industrial Establishments (Conferment of permanent Status to Workmen) Act, 1981.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Tamil Nadu.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It applies to every industrial establishment (not being an establishment of a seasonal character or in which work is performed only intermittently) in which not less than twenty workers were employed on any day of the preceding twelve months. If any question arises whether an industrial establishment is of a seasonal character or whether work is performed therein only intermittently the decision of the Government thereon shall be final:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Government may, by notification apply the provisions of this Act to any industrial establishment employing such number of workmen less than twenty as may be specified in the notification.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Government may, by notification, appoint:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing contained in this Act shall apply to any industrial establishment until the expiry of a period of two years from the date of its establishment.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In this Act, unless the context otherwise require;</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>“employer” means the owner of an industrial establishment to which this Act for the time being applies and includes,</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>In a factory, any person named under clause (f) of sub-section (1) of section 7 of the Factories Act, 1948) as manager of the factories;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>In any industrial establishment under the control of any department of any State Government in India, the authority appointed by such State Government in this be. Half, or where no authority is so appointed, the head of the department;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>In any other industrial establishment, any person responsible to the owner for the supervision and control of the industrial establishment;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“Government” means the State Government;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>“industrial establishment” means.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>A factory as defined in clause (m) of section 2 of the factories Act, 1948 (Central Act LXIII of 1948) or any place which is deemed to be a factory under sub-section (2) of section 85 of that Act; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>A plantation as defined in clause (f) of section 2 of the plantations Labour Act, 1951 (Central Act LXIX of 1951); or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.3.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>A motor transport undertaking as defined in clause (g) of section 2 of the Motor Transport Workers Act, 1961 (Central Act 27 of 1961); or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.3.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>A beedi industrial premises as defined in clause (i) of section 2 of the Beedi and Cigar Workers (Conditions of Employment) Act, 1966 (Central Act 32 of 1966); or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.3.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>An establishment as defined in clause (6) of section 2 of the Tamil Nadu Shops and Establishments Act, 1947 (Tamil Nadu Act XXXVI of 1947); or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.3.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>A catering establishment as defined in clause (1) of section 2 of the Tamil Nadu Catering Establishments Act, 1958 (Tamil Nadu Act XIII of 1958); or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.3.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>Any other establishment which the Government may, by notification, declare to be an industrial establishment for the purpose of this Act;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“Workman” means any person employed in any industrial establishment to do any skilled or unskilled, manual, supervisory, technical or clerical work for hire or reward, whether the terms of employment be express or implied and includes a badly workman,</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.4.list2">
              <listIntroduction>But does not include any such person;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.4.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>Who is employed in the police service or as an officer or other employee of a prison; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.4.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>Who is employed mainly in managerial or administrative capacity; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.4.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>Who, being employed in a supervisory capacity, draws wages exceeding three thousand and five hundred rupees per mensem or exercises, either by the nature of the duties attached to the office or by reason of the powers vested in him, functions mainly of a managerial nature.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Explanation: “Badli workman” means a workman who is employed I an industrial establishment in the place of another workman whose name is borne on the muster rolls of the establishment.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Conferment of permanent status to workmen</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time being in force every workman who is in continuous service for a period of four hundred and eighty days in a period of twenty-four calendar months in an industrial establishment shall be made permanent.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A workman shall be said to be in continuous service for a period if he is, for that period, in uninterrupted service, including service which may be interrupted on account of sickness or authorised leave or an accident or a strike, which is not illegal, or a lock-out or a cessation of work which is not due to any fault on the part of the workman.</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation: For the purposes of computing the continuous service referred to in sub-sections (1) and (2), a workman shall be deemed to be in continuous service during the days on which,</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list2.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>He has been laid off under an agreement or as permitted by standing orders made under the Industrial Employment (Standing Orders) Act, 1946 (Central Act XX of 1946) or under any other law applicable to the industrial establishment;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list2.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>He has been on leave with full wages, earned in the previous years;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list2.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>He has been absent due to temporary disablement caused by accident arising out of and in the course of his employment; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list2.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>In the case of a female, she has been on maternity leave; so however, that the total period of such maternity leave does not exceed twelve weeks.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Explanation II: For the purposes of this section ‘law’ includes any award, agreement, settlement, instrument or contract of service whether made before or after the commencement of this Act.4. Appointment of Inspectors</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, be notification, appoint such persons or such class or persons as they think fit to be Inspectors for the purpose of this Act within such local limits as the Government may specify.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Inspector shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian penal Code (Central Act XLV of 1860)</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Powers and duties of Inspectors</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Subject to any rules made by the Government in this behalf, the Inspector ma, within the local limits for which he is appointed,</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>Enter at all reasonable times and with such assistants, if any who are persons in the service of the Government or of any local authority as he thinks fit to take with him, any industrial establishment;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>Make such examination of the industrial establishment and of any registers, records and notices and take on the spot or elsewhere the evidence of such person as he may deem necessary, for carrying out the purposes of this Act; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>Exercise such other powers as may be necessary for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Penalties</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every employer who contravenes the provisions of section 3 shall be punishable with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees and in the case of continuing offence with a further fine which may extend to two hundred rupees for every day after the first during which the offence continues.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every employer who contravenes the provisions of any rule made under section 10 shall be punishable, for a first offence, with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, and for a subsequent offence, with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No prosecution for an offence punishable under the section shall be instituted except with the previous sanction of the prescribed authority.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Act not to apply to workmen employed in certain industrial establishment</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Nothing contained in this Act shall apply to workmen employed in an industrial establishment engaged in the construction of buildings, bridges, roads, canals, dams or other construction work whether structural, mechanical or electrical.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Cognizance of offence</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No court inferior to that of a metropolitan magistrate or a judicial magistrate of the first class shall try any offence under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Power to exempt</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification, exempt conditionally or unconditionally any employer or class of employers or any industrial establishment or class of industrial establishments from the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All rules made under this Act shall be published in the Tamil Nadu Government Gazette, and unless they are expressed to come into force on a particular day, shall come into force on the day on which they are so published.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All notifications issued under this Act shall, unless they are expressed to come into force on a particular day, come into force on the day on which they are published.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made or notification issued under this Act shall, as soon as possible, after it is made or issued, be placed on the table of the Legislative Assembly, and if, before the expiry of the session in which it is so placed or the next session, the Legislative Assembly agree in making any modification in any such rule or notification or the Legislative Assembly agree that the rule or notification should not be made or issued, the rule or notification shall, thereafter should not be made or issued, the rule or notification shall, thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done that rule or notification.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
