<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1950/12/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1950/12"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Emblems And Names (Preventation Of Improper Use) Act, 1950"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1950/12/eng@1950-03-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1950/12/eng@1950-03-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1950-03-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1950/12/eng@1950-03-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1950/12/eng@1950-03-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Emblems And Names (Preventation Of Improper Use) Act, 1950</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 12 OF 1950</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 1st March, 1950.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to prevent the improper use of certain emblems and names for  professional and commercial purposes.</p>
      </longTitle>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament as follows:--</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extend, application and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This</p>
            <p>Act may be called the Emblems and Names (Prevention of Improper Use)</p>
            <p>Act, 1950.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India , and also applies to  citizens of India outside India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date  as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" emblem" means any emblem, seal, flag, insignia, coat-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>of- arms or pictorial representation specified in the</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-">
      <doc name="">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1950/12/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1950/12"/>
              <FRBRalias value=";"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1950/12/eng@1950-03-01/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1950/12/eng@1950-03-01"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1950/12/eng@1950-03-01/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1950/12/eng@1950-03-01"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="">
            <paragraph id=".paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <blockList id=".paragraph-0.list0">
                  <item id=".paragraph-0.list0.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>" competent authority" means any authority competent  under any lay for the time being in force to register  any company, firm or other body of persons or any trade  mark or design or to grant a patent:</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id=".paragraph-0.list0.c">
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <p>" name" includes any abbreviation of a name.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <section id="section-3">
              <num>3.</num>
              <heading>Prohibition of improper use of certain emblems and names.</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time being in  force, no person shall, except in such cases and under such conditions  as may be prescribed by the Central Government, use or continue to  use, for the purpose of any trade, business, calling or profession, or  in the title of any patent, or in any trade mark or design, any name  or emblem specified in the Schedule or any colourable imitation  thereof without the previous permission of the Central Government or  of such officer of Government as may be authorized in this behalf by  the Central Government.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-4">
              <num>4.</num>
              <heading>Prohibition of registration of certain companies etc.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-4.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-4.1.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time being in  force, no competent authority shall,--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-4.1.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>register any company, firm or other body or persons  which bears any name, or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-4.1.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>register a trade mark of design which bears any emblem  or name, or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-4.1.list1.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>grant a patent in respect of an invention which bears a  title containing any emblem or name,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>if the use of such name or emblem is in contravention of section 3.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-4.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>If any question arises before a competent authority whether  any emblem is an emblem specified in the Schedule or a colourable  imitation thereof, the competent authority may refer the question to  the Central Government, and the decision of the Central Government  thereon shall be final.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-5">
              <num>5.</num>
              <heading>Penalty. Any person who contravenes the provisions of section</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-3">
              <num>3.</num>
              <heading>shall be punishable with fine which may extend to five hundred  rupees.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-6">
              <num>6.</num>
              <heading>Previous sanction of prosecution. No prosecution for any  offence punishable under this Act shall be instituted, except with the  previous sanction of the Central Government or of any officer  authorized in this behalf by general or special order of the Central</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Government.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-7">
              <num>7.</num>
              <heading>Savings. Nothing in this Act shall exempt any person from any  suit or other proceeding which might, apart from this Act, be brought  against him.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-8">
              <num>8.</num>
              <heading>Power of the Central Government to amend the Schedule. The</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Central Government may, be notification in the Gazette, add to or  alter the Schedule, and any such addition or alternation shall have  effect as if it had been made by this Act.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-9">
              <num>9.</num>
              <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-9.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>] The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the  purposes of this Act.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as  may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is  in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised  in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before  the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the  successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule or both houses agree that the rule should not  be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified  form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any  such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the  validity of anything previously done under that rule.]</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
