<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1956/79/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1956/79"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The State Bank Of Hyderabad Act, 1956"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1956/79/eng@1956-12-22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1956/79/eng@1956-12-22"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1956-12-22" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1956/79/eng@1956-12-22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1956/79/eng@1956-12-22"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The State Bank Of Hyderabad Act, 1956</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 79 OF 1956</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 22nd December, 1956.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to transfer the share capital of the Hyderabad State Bank to  the Reserve Bank of India and to provide for its proper management and  other matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.</p>
        <p>CHAP</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title and commencement.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the</p>
              <p>State Bank of Hyderabad Act, 1956.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 22nd day of</p>
              <p>October, 1956.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" appointed day" means the 22nd day of October, 1956;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" Hyderabad Bank" means the Hyderabad State Bank renamed  under sub- section (1) of section 3, as the State Bank  of Hyderabad;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" Hyderabad State Bank" means the Hyderabad State Bank  constituted and incorporated under the Hyderabad State</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Bank Act, 1350 F (19 of 1350 F);</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by regulations made under  this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>" Reserve Bank" means the Reserve Bank of India  constituted under the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>(2 of 1934);</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>" State Bank" means the State Bank of India  constituted under the State Bank of India Act, 1955</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>(23 of 1955)]</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>RE- NAMING OF THE HYDERABAD STATE BANK AND TRANSFER OF ITS SHARECAPITAL TO</p>
              <p>THE RESERVE BANK</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>RE- NAMING OF THE HYDERABAD STATE BANK AND TRANSFER OF ITS SHARE</p>
            <p>CAPITAL TO THE RESERVE BANK</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Change of name of Hyderabad State Bank.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On the appointed  day, the body corporate constituted by the Hyderabad State Bank Act,</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1350">
          <num>1350.</num>
          <heading>F (19 of 1350 F), and known as the Hyderabad State Bank shall be  re- named as the State Bank of Hyderabad .</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1350.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The said body corporate shall consist of the State Bank  and other shareholders, if any, for the time being, of the Hyderabad</p>
              <p>Bank.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1350.2A">
            <num>(2A)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Hyderabad Bank shall carry on the business of banking  and other business in accordance with the provisions of the State Bank  of India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, 1959 (38 of 1959), and shall have  power to acquire and hold property, whether movable or immovable, for  the purposes of its business and to dispose of the same.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1350.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The change of name of the Hyderabad State Bank by sub- section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1350.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>shall not affect any rights or obligations of that bank, or render  defective any legal proceedings by or against it; and any legal  proceedings which might have been continued or commenced by or against  the Hyderabad State Bank by its former name may be continued by or  against it by its new name.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Head Office and branches of Hyderabad Bank.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Unless  otherwise directed by the Central Government by notification in the</p>
              <p>Official Gazette, the Head Office of the Hyderabad Bank shall be at</p>
              <p>Hyderabad.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Hyderabad Bank shall continue to maintain every branch  and agency of the Hyderabad State Bank in existence immediately before  the appointed day,  and shall not discontinue any branch or  establish any new branch except in consultation with the State Bank  and with the approval of the Reserve Bank].</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Transfer of share capital of Hyderabad State Bank to Reserve</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Bank.- On the appointed day, all shares in the capital of the Hyderabad</p>
              <p>State Bank shall be transferred to, and shall vest in, the Reserve</p>
              <p>Bank free of all trusts, liabilities and encumbrances.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Compensation to share- holders of Hyderabad State Bank.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The</p>
              <p>Reserve Bank shall pay to the State Government of Hyderabad and every  other person who, immediately before the appointed day, is registered  as a holder of shares in the Hyderabad State Bank, as compensation for  the transfer of such shares to the Reserve Bank under section 5, an  amount calculated at the rate of ninety- four rupees four annas and six  pies in Indian currency for each share of the face value of one  hundred Osmania Sicca rupees.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding the transfer of the shares in the capital of  the Hyderabad State Bank to the Reserve Bank, any shareholder who,</p>
              <p>immediately before the appointed day, was entitled to payment of  dividend on the shares of the Hyderabad State Bank held by him shall  be entitled to receive from the Hyderabad Bank all dividends declared  by the Hyderabad State Bank in respect of his shares for any year  which ended before the appointed day and remaining unpaid.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Hyderabad State</p>
              <p>Bank Act, 1350 F (19 of 1350 F), no such shareholder shall be  entitled as of right to any dividend on the shares of the Hyderabad</p>
              <p>State Bank held by him in respect of any period before the appointed  day for which that bank had not declared a dividend:</p>
              <p>Provided that the Central Government may, in respect of any such  period, authorize the payment of dividend at such rate as it may  specify if it is satisfied that there is sufficient balance of profits  available after such provisions and contributions for the purposes  referred to in section 28 as the Reserve Bank considers necessary have  been made.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing contained in sub- section (1) shall affect the rights  inter se between the holder of any share in the Hyderabad State Bank  and any other person who may have an interest in such share and such  other person shall be entitled to enforce his interest against the  compensation awarded to the holder of such share but not against the</p>
              <p>Reserve Bank.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Certain officers of the Hyderabad State Bank to vacate office.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every person holding office as director (including the President   and the managing director) or as deputy managing director,</p>
              <p>in the Hyderabad State Bank immediately before the appointed day,</p>
              <p>shall be deemed to have vacated that office on the appointed day, and  notwithstanding anything contained in this Act or in any other law for  the time being in force or in any agreement or contract, such person  shall not be entitled to any compensation for the loss of office or  for the premature termination of any agreement or contract relating to  his employment, except such pension, compensation or other benefit, as  the Hyderabad Bank may, with the previous approval of the Reserve</p>
              <p>Bank, grant to him having regard to what he would have received, if  this Act had not been passed and if his employment had ceased on the  appointed day in the ordinary course.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in sub- section (1) shall be deemed to prevent the</p>
              <p>Hyderabad Bank from re- appointing or re- employing with the previous  permission in writing of the Reserve Bank, the managing director or  the deputy managing director of the Hyderabad State Bank on such terms  and conditions as are agreed upon between him and the Hyderabad Bank  and are approved by the Reserve Bank.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Special provisions regarding existing officers and employees.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any law or contract of  service or other document, no appointment made or promotion, increment  in salary, pension or allowance or any other benefit granted to any  person by the Hyderabad State Bank after the 19th day of December,</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1954">
          <num>1954.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1954.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>, and before the appointed day which would not ordinarily have  been made or granted or which would not ordinarily have been  admissible under the rules or authorizations of the Hyderabad State</p>
              <p>Bank, or of any provident, pension, or other fund in force before the</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19th">
          <num>19th.</num>
          <heading>day of December, 1954, shall have effect or be payable or  claimable from the Hyderabad Bank, or from any provident, pension or  other fund or from any authority administering any such fund, unless  the Reserve Bank has, by general or special order, confirmed the  appointment, promotion or increment or has directed the grant of the  pension, allowance or other benefit, as the case may be.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-19th.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where any officer or other employee of the Hyderabad State</p>
              <p>Bank has, whether before or after the appointed day, received any  amount by reason of any such appointment, promotion or increment or  the grant of any such pension, allowance or other benefit, as is  referred to in sub- section (1), which has not been confirmed or  sanctioned by the Reserve Bank in pursuance of the powers conferred</p>
              <p>on it by that sub- section, such officer or other employee shall be  bound to refund such amount to the Hyderabad Bank and that bank shall  be entitled to take all such steps as may be necessary for recovering  such amount.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19th.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where any managing director, deputy managing director or  other employee of the Hyderabad State Bank has, after the 19th day of</p>
              <p>December, 1954, and before the appointed day, been paid any sum be way  of compensation or gratuity, the Hyderabad Bank shall be entitled to  claim refund of any sum so paid if the payment is not confirmed by the</p>
              <p>Reserve Bank by general or special order.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19th.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time  being in force, the re- naming of the Hyderabad State Bank or the  transfer of its share capital to the Reserve Bank shall not entitle  any officer or other employees of that bank to any compensation to  which he may be entitled under any such law, and no such claim shall  be entertained by any Court, tribunal or other authority.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>CAPITAL OF THE HYDERABAD BANK</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>CAPITAL OF THE HYDERABAD BANK</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Authorized capital.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The authorised capital of the</p>
              <p>Hyderabad Bank shall be one crore of rupees, divided into shares of  one hundred rupees each.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, the State</p>
              <p>Bank may, with the approval of the Reserve Bank, authorise the</p>
              <p>Hyderabad Bank to increase or reduce its authorised capital:</p>
              <p>Provided that where the authorised capital is so increased, the  shares issued shall be of the denomination specified in sub- section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Issued capital.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The issued capital of the Hyderabad Bank  shall, on the day on which the amendments to this Act made by the</p>
              <p>State Bank of India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, 1959 (38 of 1959), take  effect, be of such amount as the State Bank, with the approval of  the Reserve Bank, may fix in this behalf, so however that the amount  shall be so fixed as to consist only of fully paid- up shares of one  hundred rupees each.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All shares in the issued capital of the Hyderabad Bank shall,</p>
              <p>on that day, vest in the State Bank.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Without prejudice to the provisions contained in sub- section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, the Hyderabad Bank may, with the approval of the State Bank and  the Reserve Bank, increase, from time to time, its issued capital and  the capital so increased shall consist of fully paid- up shares to be  issued in such manner as the State Bank may, with the approval of the</p>
              <p>Reserve Bank, direct:</p>
              <p>Provided that the issued capital shall be so increased that at no  time shall the State Bank hold less than fifty- five per cent. of the  issued capital of the Hyderabad Bank.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Bank shall, as soon as may be, after the  determination, if any, of the amount of compensation by the Tribunal  under the State Bank of India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, 1959 (38 of</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1959">
          <num>1959.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1959.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>), consider whether any increase or reduction of the issued  capital of the Hyderabad Bank as fixed under sub- section (1) by way of  adjustment by transfer from, or to, the reserves of the Hyderabad Bank  or in any other manner, is necessary, expedient or appropriate and  may, thereafter, with the approval of the Reserve Bank, direct the</p>
              <p>Hyderabad Bank to increase or reduce its issued capital.]</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>MANAGEMENT OF THE HYDERABAD BANK</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MANAGEMENT OF THE HYDERABAD BANK</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Reserve Fund.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-27.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-27.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The reserve fund of the Hyderabad Bank  shall, subject to the provisions of sub- section (4) of section 10, and  sub- section (2) of this section, consist of--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>on the day on which the amendments to this Act made by  the State Bank of India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, 1959</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>(38 of 1959), take</p>
              <blockList id="section-27.1.list4">
                <listIntroduction>effect, such sum as the State Bank, with the approval  of the Reserve Bank, may determine; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.1.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>after that day, the sum aforesaid together with such  further sums as may be transferred to the reserve fund  by the Hyderabad Bank out of its annual net profits  before declaring a dividend.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Bank shall, as soon as may be after the  determination, if any, of the amount of compensation by the Tribunal,</p>
              <p>under the State Bank of India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, 1959 (38 of</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1959">
          <num>1959.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1959.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>) consider whether any increase or reduction of the reserve fund  of the Hyderabad Bank is necessary by way of adjustment by transfer  from or to any account or towards provision for bad and doubtful  debts, depreciation in assets, or contingencies or for any other  purpose and may thereafter, with the approval of the Reserve Bank,</p>
              <p>direct the Hyderabad Bank to so increase or reduce its reserve fund.]</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-41">
          <num>41.</num>
          <heading>Power of Central Government to make rules.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-41.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central</p>
              <p>Government may, in consultation with the Reserve Bank, by notification  in the Official Gazette, make rules to give effect to the provisions  of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-41.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-41.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-41.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the manner of, and the procedure for payment of,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-41.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>compensation under this Act, including the requirements  subject to which the payment shall be made;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-41.2.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the determination of persons to whom the said  compensation shall be payable in all cases including  cases where shares have been held by more than one  person, or where they have been transferred before the  appointed day, but the transfer has not been registered  or where the share holder is dead;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.2.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the circumstances under which claims for payment of the  said compensation from persons claiming through or  under a shareholder may be entertained;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.2.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the requirements to be complied with before receipt of  the said compensation by a shareholder, whose share  certificate has been lost, destroyed, mutilated or  stolen;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.2.list3.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the requirements, subject to which information regarding  the payment of the said compensation may be granted or  refused and the conditions subject to which such  information may be given.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-41.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All rules made under this section shall be laid for not less  than thirty days before both Houses of Parliament as soon as possible  after they are made and shall be subject to such modifications as</p>
              <p>Parliament may make during the session in which they are so laid for  the session immediately following.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-44">
          <num>44.</num>
          <heading>References to Hyderabad State Bank in other laws.- On and from  the appointed day, any reference to the Hyderabad State Bank in any  law (other than this Act) or in any contract or other instrument  shall, except as otherwise provided in any general or special order  made by the Central Government, be deemed to be a reference to the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-44.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Hyderabad Bank.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
