<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1915/7/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1915/7"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Delhi Laws Act, 1915"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1915/7/eng@1915-03-22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1915/7/eng@1915-03-22"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1915-03-22" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1915/7/eng@1915-03-22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1915/7/eng@1915-03-22"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Delhi Laws Act, 1915</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 7 OF 1915</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 22nd March, 1915.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to declare the law in force in certain territory added to  the Province of Delhi.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS by Proclamation published in Notification No. 984-C,</p>
        <p>dated the 22nd day of February, 1915, the Governor- General in Council,</p>
        <p>with the sanction and approbation of the Secretary of State for India,</p>
        <p>has been pleased to take under his immediate authority and management  the territory mentioned in Schedule I, which was formerly included  within the United Provinces of Agra and Oudh, and to include the said  territory in the Province of Delhi with effect from the 1st April,</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1915">
        <num>1915.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1915.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>;</p>
            <p>AND WHEREAS it is expedient to declare the law in force in the  said territory;</p>
            <p>It is hereby enacted as follows:--</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Delhi Laws Act, 1915;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on the first day of April, 1915.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Application to added area of law in force in existing State of</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Delhi. All enactments (except the enactments specified in Schedule II)</p>
            <p>for the time being in force in the territory specified in Schedule A</p>
            <p>to the Delhi Laws Act, 1912 (13 of 1912), and all notifications,</p>
            <p>orders, schemes, rules, forms and by- laws issued, made or prescribed  under such enactments shall be deemed to be in force in the territory  specified in Schedule I in the same manner and subject to the same  modifications as they are for the time being in the territory  specified in the said Schedule to the said Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Continuance in added area of certain laws now in force in the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Uttar Pradesh. The enactments specified in Schedule III, and all  notifications, orders, schemes, rules, forms and by- laws issued, made  or prescribed under those enactments shall continue to be in force in  the territory specified in Schedule I:</p>
            <p>Provided that in the enactments so continued and in all  notifications, orders, schemes, rules, forms and by- laws issued, made  or prescribed thereunder, references to a State Government, the</p>
            <p>State Government] of the United Provinces of Agra and Oudh,  or  the Board of Revenue for the Uttar Pradesh shall be read as referring  to the  State Government] of Delhi; references to a High Court or  the</p>
            <p>High Court of Judicature for the North- Western Provinces as referring  to the  High Court of Punjab]; and references to the Official</p>
            <p>Gazette for the Uttar Pradesh as referring to the Official Gazette.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Provision for facilitating application of certain enactments.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of facilitating the application to the territory  mentioned in Schedule I of the enactments referred to in section 3,</p>
            <p>the powers conferred by sections 4 and 5 of the Delhi Laws Act, 1912,</p>
            <p>(13 of 1912) shall be exercisable in respect thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Exclusion of certain enactments from the added area. Save as  provided in sections 2 and 3 no enactment which is in force in the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>United Provinces of Agra and Oudh or any part thereof shall continue  to be in force in the territory specified in Schedule I.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Pending proceedings. Nothing in this Act shall affect any  proceeding which at the commencement thereof is pending in respect of  any of the territory mentioned in Schedule I or of anything arising in  such territory and every such proceeding shall be continued as if this</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Act had not been passed:</p>
            <p>Provided that the State Government may, by notification in the</p>
            <p>Official Gazette, direct that any proceeding, criminal, civil or  revenue, other than a proceeding pending before the High Court of</p>
            <p>Judicature for the North- Western Provinces, shall be transferred to,</p>
            <p>and disposed of by, the corresponding authority of the Delhi State.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of section 7 of Act 13 of 1912. Rep. by the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Repealing Act, 1938 (1 of 1938), s. 2 and Sch.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Construction. This Act shall be construed with, and deemed to  be part of, the Delhi Laws Act, 1912. (13 of 1912)</heading>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
