<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1873/8/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1873/8"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Northern India Canal And Drainage Act, 1873"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1873/8/eng@1873-02-11/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1873/8/eng@1873-02-11"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1873-02-11" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1873/8/eng@1873-02-11/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1873/8/eng@1873-02-11"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Northern India Canal And Drainage Act, 1873</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 8 OF 1873</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 11th February, 1873.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to regulate irrigation, navigation and drainage in Northern</p>
        <p>India.</p>
        <p>PART</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <part id="part-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="part-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title.-- This Act may be call the Northern India Canal and</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Drainage Act, 1873.</p>
              <p>Local extent.-- It extends to  Uttar Pradesh and the    territories which, immediately before the 1st November, 1956,</p>
              <p>were comprised in the States of Punjab and Delhi]] and applies  to all lands whether permanently settled, temporarily settled, or  free from revenue.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Repeal of Acts. Rep. by the Repealing Act, 1873 (12 of</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1873">
          <num>1873.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1873.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>), s. 1 and Sch., Pt. II.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Interpretation- clause.- In this Act, unless there be something  repugnant in the subject or context:--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>" Canal."- (1)" canal" includes.</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>all canals, channels and reservoirs constructed,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>maintained or controlled by the State Government for  the supply or storage of water;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>all works, embankments, structures, supply and escape  channels connected with such canals, channels or  reservoirs;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>all water- courses as defined in the second clause of  this section;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>any part of a river, stream, lake or natural collection  of water, or natural drainage- channel, to which the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>State Government has applied the provisions of Part II</p>
              <p>of this Act;</p>
              <p>" Water- course."- (2)" water- course" means any channel which  is supplied with water from a canal, but which is not maintained at  the cost of the State Government, and all subsidiary works belonging  to any such channel:</p>
              <p>" Drainage- work."- (3)" drainage- work" includes escape- channels  from a canal, dams, weirs, embankments, sluices, groins and other  works for the protection of lands from flood or from erosion, formed  or maintained by the State Government under the provisions of Part</p>
              <p>VII of this Act, but does not include works for the removal of sewage  from towns;</p>
              <p>" Vessel."-  (4)" vessel" includes boats, rafts, timber and  other floating bodies;</p>
              <p>" Commissioner."- (5)" Commissioner" means a Commissioner of a  division, and includes any officer appointed under this Act to  exercise all or any of the powers of a Commissioner;</p>
              <p>" Collector."-  (6)" Collector" means the head revenue- officer of  a district, and includes a Deputy Commissioner or other officer  appointed under this Act to exercise all or any of the powers of a</p>
              <p>Collector;</p>
              <p>" Canal- officer."- (7)" Canal- officer" means an officer appointed  under this Act to exercise control or jurisdiction over a canal or  any part thereof;</p>
              <p>" Superintending Canal- officer."-" Superintending Canal- officer"</p>
              <p>means an officer exercising general control over a canal or portion  of a canal;</p>
              <p>" Divisional Canal- officer."-" Divisional Canal- officer" means an  officer exercising control over a division of a canal;</p>
              <p>" Sub- divisional Canal- officer."-" Sub- divisional Canal- officer"</p>
              <p>means an officer exercising control over a sub- division of a canal;</p>
              <p>" District."- (8)" district" means a district as fixed for  revenue purposes.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Power to appoint officers.- The State Government may from time  to time declare, by notification in the Official Gazette, the officers  by whom, and the local</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>limits within which, all or any of the powers or duties hereinafter  conferred or imposed shall be exercised or performed.</p>
              <p>All officers mentioned in section 3, clause (7), shall be  respectively subject to the orders of such officers as the State</p>
              <p>Government from time to time directs.</p>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>OF THE APPLICATION OF WATER FOR PUBLIC PURPOSES</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="part-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>OF THE APPLICATION OF WATER FOR PUBLIC PURPOSES</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Notification to issue when water- supply is to be applied for  public purposes. Whenever it appears expedient to the State Government  that the water of any river or stream flowing in a natural channel, or  of any lake or other natural collection of still water, should be  applied or used by the State Government for the purpose of any  existing or projected canal or drainage- work, the State Government  may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare that the said  water will be so applied or used after a day to be named in the said  notifcation, not being earlier than three months from the date  thereof.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Powers of Canal- officer.- At any time after the day so named,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>any Canal- officer, acting under the orders of the State Government in  this behalf, may enter on any land and remove any obstructions, and  may close any channels, and do any other thing necessary for such  application or use of the said water.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Notice as to claims for compensation.- As soon as is  practicable after the issue of such notification, the Collector shall  cause public notice to be given at convenient places, stating that the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>State Government intends to apply or use the said water as aforesaid,</p>
              <p>and that claims for compensation in respect of the matters mentioned  in section 8 may be made before him.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Damage for which compensation shall not be awarded.- No  compensation shall be awarded for any damage caused by--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>stoppage or diminution of percolation or floods;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>deterioration of climate or soil;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>stoppage of navigation, or of the means of drifting  timber or watering cattle;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>displacement of labour.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Matters in respect of which compensation may be awarded.- But  compensation may be awarded in respect of any of the following  matters:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list2.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>stoppage or diminution of supply of water through any  natural channel to any defined artificial channel,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>whether above or under ground, in use at the date of  the said notification;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list4.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>stoppage or diminution of supply of water to any work  erected for purposes of profit on any channel, whether  natural or artificial, in use at the date of the said  notification;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list4.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>stoppage or diminution of supply of water through any  natural channel which has been used for purposes of  irrigation within the five years next before the date  of the said notification;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list4.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>damage done in respect of any right to a water- course or  the use of any water to which any person is entitled  under the  Indian Limitation Act, 1877 (15 of 1877)</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <heading>;</heading>
        <paragraph id="part-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="part-IV.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="part-IV.paragraph-0.list0.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>any other substantial damage, not falling under any of  the above clauses (a), (b), (c) or (d), and caused by  the exercise of the powers conferred by this Act, which  is capable of being ascertained and estimated at the  time of awarding such compensation.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>In determining the amount of such compensation, regard shall be  had to the diminution in the market- value, at the time of awarding  compensation of the property in respect of which compensation is  claimed; and, where such market- value is not ascertainable, the amount  shall be reckoned at twelve times the amount of the diminution of the  annual nett profits of such property caused by the exercise of the  powers conferred by this Act.</p>
            <blockList id="part-IV.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>No right to any such supply of water as is referred to in clauses</listIntroduction>
              <item id="part-IV.paragraph-0.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>, (f) or (g) of this section, in respect of a work or channel not  in use at the date of the notification, shall be acquired as against  the State Government, except by grant or under the  Indian</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Limitation Act, 1877 (15 of 1877), Part IV;</p>
            <blockList id="part-IV.paragraph-0.list6">
              <listIntroduction>and no right to any of the advantages referred to in clauses (a),</listIntroduction>
              <item id="part-IV.paragraph-0.list6.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>and (c) of this section shall be acquired, as against the State</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Government, under the same Part.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Limitation of claims.- No claim for compensation for any such  stoppage, diminution or damage shall be made after the expiration of  one year from such stoppage, diminution or damage, unless the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Collector is satisfied that the claimant had sufficient cause for not  making the claim within such period.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Enquiry into claims and amount of compensation.- The Collector  shall proceed to enquire into any such claim, and to determine the  amount of compensation, if any, which should be given to the claimant;</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>and sections 9 to 12 (inclusive), 14 and 15, 18 to 23 (inclusive), 26  to 40 (inclusive), 51, 57, 58 and 59 of the  Land Acquisition Act,</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1870">
          <num>1870.</num>
          <heading>(10 of 1870), shall apply to such inquiries:</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-1870.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Provided that, instead of the last clause of the said section 26,</p>
              <p>the following shall be read:--" The provisions of this section and of  section 8 of the Northern India Canal and Drainage Act, 1873, shall be  read to every assessor in a language which he understands, before he  gives his opinion as to the amount of compensation to be awarded."</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Abatement of rent on interruption of water- supply. Every  tenant holding under an unexpired lease, or having a right of  occupancy, who is in occupation of any land at the time</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>when any stoppage or diminution of water- supply, in respect of which  compensation is allowed under section 8, takes place, may claim an  abatement of the rent previously payable by him for the said land, on  the ground that the interruption reduces the value of the holding.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Enhancement of rent on restoration of water- supply.- If a  water- supply increasing the value of such holding is after- wards  restored to the said land, the rent of the tenant may be enhanced in  respect of the increased value of such land due to the restored water-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>supply, to an amount not exceeding that at which it stood immediately  before the abatement.</p>
              <p>Such enhancement shall be on account only of the restored water-</p>
              <p>supply, and shall not affect the liability of the tenant to  enhancement of rent on any other grounds.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Compensation when due.- All sums of money payable for  compensation under this Part shall become due three months after the  claim for such compensation is made in respect of the stoppage,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>diminution or damage complained of,</p>
              <p>Interest.</p>
              <p>" Interest"- and simple interest at the rate of six per cent. per  annum shall be allowed on any such sum remaining unpaid after the  said three months, except where the non- payment of such sum is  caused by the wilful neglect or refusal of the claimant to receive  the same.</p>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>OF THE CONSTRUCTION AND MAINTENANCE OF WORKS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="part-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>OF THE CONSTRUCTION AND MAINTENANCE OF WORKS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Power to enter and survey, etc.- Any Canal- officer, or other  person acting under the general or special order of a Canal- officer,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>may enter upon any lands adjacent to any canal, or through which  any canal is proposed to be made, and undertake surveys or levels  thereon;</p>
              <p>and dig and bore into the sub- soil;</p>
              <p>and make and set up suitable land- marks, level- marks and water-</p>
              <p>gauges;</p>
              <p>and do all other acts necessary for the proper prosecution of any  enquiry relating to any existing or projected canal under the charge  of the said Canal- officer;</p>
              <p>Power to clear land.</p>
              <p>Power to clear land.- and, where otherwise such enquiry cannot be  completed, such officer or other person may cut down and clear away  any part of any standing crop, fence or jungle;</p>
              <p>Power to inspect and regulate water- supply.</p>
              <p>Power to inspect and regulate water- supply.- and may also enter  upon any land, building or water- course on account of which any  water- rate is chargeable, for the purpose of inspecting or regulating  the use of the water supplied, or of measuring the lands irrigated  thereby or chargeable with a water- rate, and of doing all things  necessary for the proper regulation and management of such canal:</p>
              <p>Notice of intended entry into houses.</p>
              <p>Notice of intended entry into houses.- Provided that, if such</p>
              <p>Canal- officer or person proposes to enter into any building or  enclosed court or garden attached to a dwelling- house not supplied with  water flowing from any canal, he shall previously give the occupier of  such building, court or garden at least seven days' notice in writing  of his intention to do so.</p>
              <p>Compensation for damage caused by entry.</p>
              <p>Compensation for damage caused by entry.- In every case of entry  under this section, the Canal- officer shall, at the time of such  entry, tender compensation for any damage which may be occasioned by  any proceeding under this section; and, in case of dispute as to the  sufficiency of the amount so tendered, he shall forthwith refer the  same for decision by the Collector, and such decision shall be final.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Power to enter for repairs and to prevent accidents. In case  of any accident happening or being apprehended to a canal any</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Divisional Canal- officer or any person acting under his general or  special orders in this behalf may enter upon any lands adjacent to  such canal, and may execute all works which may be necessary for the  purpose of repairing or preventing such accident.</p>
              <p>Compensation for damage to land.</p>
              <p>In every such case such Canal- officer or person shall tender  compensation to the proprietors or occupiers of the said lands for all  damage done to the same. If such tender is not accepted, the Canal-</p>
              <p>officer shall refer the matter to the Collector, who shall proceed to  award compensation for the damage as though the State Government had  directed the occupation of the lands under section 43 of the Land</p>
              <p>Acquisition Act, 1870  (10 of 1870).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Application by persons desiring to use canal- water. Any  persons desiring to use the water of any canal may apply in writing to  the Divisional or Sub- divisional Canal- officer of the division or sub-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>division of the canal from which the water- course is to be supplied,</p>
              <p>requesting such officer to construct or improve a water- course at the  cost of the applicants.</p>
              <p>Contents of application.</p>
              <p>The application shall state the works to be undertaken, their  approximate estimated cost, or the amount which the applicants are  willing to pay for the same, or whether they engage to pay the actual  cost as settled by the Divisional Canal- officer, and how the payment  is to be made.</p>
              <p>Liability of applicants for cost of works.</p>
              <p>When the assent of the Superintending Canal- officer is given to  such application, all the applicants shall, after the application has</p>
              <p>been duly attested before the Collector, be jointly and severally  liable for the cost of such works to the extent mentioned therein.</p>
              <p>Recovery of amount due.</p>
              <p>Any amount becoming due under the terms of such application, and  not paid to the Divisional Canal- officer, or the person authorised by  him to receive the same, on or before the date on which it becomes  due, shall, on the demand of such officer, be recoverable by the</p>
              <p>Collector as if it were an arrear of land- revenue.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Government to provide means of crossing canals.- There shall  be provided, at the cost of the State Government, suitable means of  crossing canals constructed or maintained at the cost of the State</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government, at such places as the State Government thinks necessary  for the reasonable convenience of the inhabitants of the adjacent  lands.</p>
              <p>On receiving a statement in writing, signed by not less than five  of the owners of such lands, to the effect that suitable crossings  have not been provided on any canal, the Collector shall cause enquiry  to be made into the circumstances of the case, and if he thinks that  the statement is established, he shall report his opinion thereon for  the consideration of the State Government, and the State Government  shall cause such measures in reference thereto to be taken as it  thinks proper.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Persons using water- course to construct works for passing  water across roads, etc.- The Divisional Canal- officer may issue an  order to the persons using any water- course to construct suitable  bridges, culverts or other works for the passage of the water of such  water- course across any public road, canal or drainage- channel in use  before the said water- course was made, or to repair any such works.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Such order shall specify a reasonable period within which such  construction or repairs shall be completed;</p>
              <p>If they fail, Canal- officer may construct,</p>
              <p>and if, after the receipt of such order, the persons to whom it  is addressed do not, within the said period, construct or repair such  works to the satisfaction of the said Canal- officer, he may, with the  previous approval of the Superintending Canal- officer, himself  construct or repair the same;</p>
              <p>and recover cost.</p>
              <p>and if the said persons do not, when so required, pay the cost of  such construction or repairs as declared by the Divisional Canal-</p>
              <p>officer, the amount shall, on the demand of the Divisional Canal-</p>
              <p>officer, be recoverable from them by the Collector as if it were an  arrear of land- revenue.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Adjustment of claims between persons jointly using water-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>course.- If any person, jointly responsible with others for the  construction or maintenance of a water- course, or jointly making use  of a water- course with others, neglects or refuses to pay his share of  the cost of such construction or maintenance, or to execute his share  of</p>
              <p>any work necessary for such construction or maintenance, the</p>
              <p>Divisional or Sub- divisional Canal- officer, on receiving an  application in writing from any person injured by such neglect or  refusal, shall serve notice on all the parties concerned that, on the  expiration of a fortnight from the service, he will investigate the  case; and shall, on the expiration of that period, investigate the  case accordingly, and make such order thereon as to him seems fit.</p>
              <p>Such order shall be appealable to the Commissioner, whose order  thereon shall be final.</p>
              <p>Recovery of amount found due.</p>
              <p>Any sum directed by such order to be paid within a specified  period may, if not paid within such period, and if the order remains  in force, be recovered by the Collector, from the person directed to  pay the same, as if it were an arrear of land- revenue.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Supply of water through intervening water- course.- Whenever  application is made to a Divisional Canal- officer for a supply of  water from a canal, and it appears to him expedient that such supply  should be given and that it should be conveyed through some existing  water- course, he shall give notice to the persons responsible for the  maintenance of such water- course to show cause, on a day not less than  fourteen days from the date of such notice, why the said supply should  not be so conveyed: and, after making enquiry on such day, the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Divisional Canal- officer shall determine whether and on what  conditions the said supply shall be conveyed through such water-</p>
              <p>course.</p>
              <p>When such officer determines that a supply of canal- water may be  conveyed through any water- course as aforesaid, his decision shall,</p>
              <p>when confirmed or modified by the superintending Canal- officer, be  binding on the applicant and also on the persons responsible for the  maintenance of the said water- course.</p>
              <p>Such applicant shall not be entitled to use such water- course  until he has paid the expense of any alteration of such water- course  necessary in order to his being supplied through it, and also such  share of the first cost of such water- course as the Divisional or</p>
              <p>Superintending Canal- officer may determine.</p>
              <p>Such applicant shall also be liable for his share of the cost of  maintenance of such water- course so long as he uses it.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Application for construction of new water- course.- Any person  desiring the construction of a new water- course may apply in writing  to the Divisional Canal- officer, stating--</heading>
          <subsection id="section-21.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>that he has endeavoured unsuccessfully to acquire, from  the owners of the land through which he desires such  water- course to pass, a right to occupy so much of the  land as will be needed for such water- course;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-21.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>that he desires the said Canal- officer, in his behalf  and at his cost, to do all things necessary for  acquiring such right;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-21.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>that he is able to defray all costs involved in  acquiring such right and constructing such water-</p>
              <p>course.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Procedure of Canal- officer thereupon. If the Divisional</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Canal- officer considers--</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-22.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>that the construction of such water- course is expedient,</p>
              <p>and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>that the statements in the application are true,</p>
              <p>he shall call upon the applicant to make such deposit as the</p>
              <p>Divisional Canal- officer considers necessary to defray the cost of the  preliminary proceedings, and the amount of any compensation which he  considers likely to become due under section 28;</p>
              <p>and, upon such deposit being made, he shall cause enquiry to be  made into the most suitable alignment for the said water- course, and  shall mark out the land which, in his opinion, it will be necessary to  occupy for the construction thereof, and shall forthwith publish a  notice in every village through which the water- course is proposed to  be taken, that so much of such land as belongs to such village has  been so marked out, and shall send a copy of such notice to the</p>
              <p>Collector of every district in which any part of such land is situate.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Application for transfer of existing water- course.- Any person  desiring that an existing water- course should be transferred from its  present owner to himself may apply in writing to the Divisional Canal-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>officer, stating--</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-23.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>that he has endeavoured unsuccessfully to procure such  transfer from the owner of such water- course;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>that he desires the said Canal- officer, in his behalf  and at his cost, to do all things necessary for  procuring such transfer;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>that he is able to defray the cost of such transfer.</p>
              <p>Procedure thereupon.</p>
              <blockList id="section-23.3.list3">
                <listIntroduction>If the Divisional Canal- officer considers--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-23.3.list3.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>that the said transfer is necessary for the better  management of the irrigation from such water- course,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-23.3.list5">
                <listIntroduction>and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-23.3.list5.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>that the statements in the application are true,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>he shall call upon the applicant to make such deposit as the</p>
              <p>Divisional Canal- officer considers necessary to defray the cost of the  preliminary proceedings, and the amount of any compensation that may  become due under the provisions of section 28 in respect of such  transfer;</p>
              <p>and upon such deposit being made, he shall publish a notice of  the application in every village, and shall send a copy of the notice  to the Collector of every district, through which such water- course  passes.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Objections to construction or transfer applied for.- Within  thirty days from the publication of a notice under section 22 or  section 23, as the case may be, and person interested in the land or  water- course to which the notice refers may apply to the Collector by  petition, stating his objection to the construction or transfer for  which application has been made.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Collector may either reject the petition or may proceed to  inquire into the validity of the objection, giving previous notice to  the Divisional Canal- officer of the place and time at which such  inquiry will be held.</p>
              <p>The Collector shall record in writing all orders passed by him  under this section and the grounds thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>When applicant may be placed in occupation.- If no such  objection is made, or (Where such objection is made) if the Collector  over- rules it, he shall give notice to the Divisional Canal- officer to  that effect, and shall proceed forthwith to place the said applicant  in occupation of the land marked out or of the water- course to be  transferred, as the case may be.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Procedure when objection is held valid.- If the Collector  considers any objection made as aforesaid to be valid he shall inform  the Divisional Canal- officer accordingly; and, if such officer sees  fit, he may, in the case of an application under section 21, alter the  boundaries of the land so marked out, and may give fresh notice under  section 22; and the procedure hereinbefore provided shall be  applicable to such notice, and the Collector shall thereupon proceed  as before provided.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Procedure when Canal- officer disagrees with Collector.- If the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Canal- officer disagrees with the Collector, the matter shall be  referred for decision to the Commissioner.</p>
              <p>Such decision shall be final, and the Collector, if he is so  directed by such decision, shall, subject to the provisions of section</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>, cause the said applicant to be placed in occupation of the land so  marked out or of the water- course to be transferred, as the case may  be.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Expenses to be paid by applicant before receiving occupation.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No such applicant shall be placed in occupation of such land or water-</p>
              <p>course until he has paid to the person named by the Collector such  amount as the Collector determines to be due as compensation for the  land or water- course so occupied or transferred, and for any damage  caused by the marking out or occupation of such land, together with  all expenses incidental to such occupation or transfer.</p>
              <p>Procedure in fixing compensation.</p>
              <p>In determining the compensation to be made under this section the</p>
              <p>Collector shall proceed under the provisions of the Land Acquisition</p>
              <p>Act, 1870  (10 of 1870); but he may, if the person to be  compensated so desires, award such compensation in the form of a rent-</p>
              <p>charge payable in respect of the land or water- course occupied or  transferred.</p>
              <p>Recovery of compensation and expenses.</p>
              <p>If such compensation and expenses are not paid when demanded by  the person entitled to receive the same, the amount may be recovered  by the Collector as if it were an arrear of land- revenue, and shall,</p>
              <p>when recovered, be paid by him to the person entitled to receive the  same.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Conditions binding on applicant placed in occupation.- When  any such applicant is placed in occupation of land or of a water-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-29.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>course as aforesaid, the following rules and conditions shall be  binding on him and his representative in interest:--</p>
              <p>First,-- All works necessary for the passage across such water-</p>
              <p>course, of water- courses existing previous to its construction and of  the drainage intercepted by it, and for affording proper  communications across it for the convenience of the neighbouring  lands, shall be constructed by the applicant, and be maintained by him  or his representative in interest to the satisfaction of the</p>
              <p>Divisional Canal- officer.</p>
              <p>Second.-- Land occupied for a water- course under the provisions of  section 22 shall be used only for the purpose of such water- course.</p>
              <p>Third.-- The proposed water- course shall be completed to the  satisfaction of the Divisional Canal- officer within one year after the  applicant is placed in occupation of the land.</p>
              <p>In cases in which land is occupied or a water- course is  transferred on the terms of a rent- charge.</p>
              <p>Fourth.-- The applicant or his representative in interest shall,</p>
              <p>so long as he occupies such land or water- course, pay rent for the  same at such rate and on such days as are determined by the Collector  when the applicant is placed in occupation.</p>
              <p>Fifth.-- If the right to occupy the land cease owing to a breach  of any of these rules, the liability to pay the said rent shall  continue until the applicant or his representative in interest has  restored the land to its original condition, or until he has paid, by  way of compensation for any injury done to the said land, such amount  and to such persons as the Collector determines.</p>
              <p>Sixth.-- The Collector may, on the application of the person  entitled to receive such rent or compensation, determine the amount of  rent due or assess the amount of such compensation; and, if any such  rent or compensation be not paid by the applicant or his  representative in interest, the Collector may recover the amount, with  interest thereon at the rate of six per cent. per annum from the date  on which it became due, as if it were an arrear of land- revenue, and  shall pay the same, when recovered, to the person to whom it is due.</p>
              <p>If any of the rules and conditions prescribed by this section are  not complied with,</p>
              <p>or if any water- course constructed or transferred under this Act  is disused for three years continuously,</p>
              <p>the right of the applicant, or of his representative in interest,</p>
              <p>to occupy such land or water- course shall cease absolutely.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading>Procedure applicable to occupation for extensions and  alterations.- The procedure hereinbefore provided for the occupation of  land for the construction of a water- course shall be applicable to the  occupation of land for any extension or alteration of a water- course,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-30.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>and for the deposit of soil from water- course clearances.</p>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>OF THE SUPPLY OF WATER</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="part-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>OF THE SUPPLY OF WATER</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading>In absence of written contract, water- supply to be subject to  rules.- In the absence of a written contract, or so far as any such  contract does not extend, every supply of canal- water shall be deemed  to be given at the rates and subject to the conditions prescribed by  the rules to be made by the State Government in respect thereof.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>Conditions as to-- Such contracts and rules must be consistent  with the following conditions:--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-32.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-32.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>power to stop water- supply;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>The Divisional Canal- officer may not stop the supply of  water to any water- course, or to any person, except in  the following cases:--</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-32.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>whenever and so long as it is necessary to  stop such supply for the purpose of executing any work  ordered by competent authority and with the previous  sanction of the State Government;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>whenever and so long as any water- course is  not maintained in such proper customary repair as to  prevent the wasteful escape of water therefrom;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>within periods fixed from time to time by the</p>
              <p>Divisional Canal- officer;</p>
              <blockList id="section-32.3.list3">
                <listIntroduction>claims to compensation in case or failure of stoppage of supply;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.3.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>No claim shall be made against the State Government for  compensation in respect of loss caused by the failure  or stoppage of the water in a canal, by reason of any  cause beyond the control of the State Government or of  any repairs, alterations or additions to the canal, or  of any measures taken for regulating the proper flow of  water therein, or for maintaining the established</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>course of irrigation which the Divisional Canal- officer  considers necessary; but the person suffering such loss  may claim such remission of the ordinary charges  payable for the use of the water as is authorised by  the State Government:</p>
              <blockList id="section-32.3.list6">
                <listIntroduction>claims on account of interruption from other causes;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.3.list6.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>If the supply of water to any land irrigated from a  canal be interrupted otherwise than in the manner  described in the last preceding clause, the occupier or  owner of such land may present a petition for  compensation to the Collector for any loss arising from  such interruption, and the Collector may award to the  petitioner reasonable compensation for such loss:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-32.3.list8">
                <listIntroduction>duration of supply;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.3.list8.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>When the water of a canal is supplied for the irrigation  of a single crop, the permission to use such water  shall be held to continue only until that crop comes to  maturity, and to apply only to that crop; but, if it be  supplied for irrigating two or more crops to be raised  on the same land within the year, such permission shall  be held to continue for one year from the commencement  of the irrigation, and to apply to such crops only as  are matured within that year:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-32.3.list10">
                <listIntroduction>sale or subletting of right to use canal- water;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.3.list10.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>Unless with the permission of the Superintending Canal-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>officer, no person entitled to use the water of any  canal, or any work, building or land appertaining to  any canal, shall sell or sublet or otherwise transfer  his right to such use:</p>
              <p>Provided that the former part of this clause shall  not apply to the use by a cultivating tenant of water  supplied by the owner of a water- course for the  irrigation of the land held by such tenant:</p>
              <p>transfer, with land, of contracts for water.</p>
              <p>But all contracts made between the State</p>
              <p>Government and the owner or occupier of any immovable  property, as to the supply of canal- water to such  property, shall be transferable therewith, and shall be  presumed to have been so transferred whenever a  transfer of such property takes place:</p>
              <blockList id="section-32.3.list17">
                <listIntroduction>No right acquired by user.</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.3.list17.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>No right acquired by user. No right to the use of the  water of a canal shall be, or be deemed to have been,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>acquired under the  Indian Limitation Act, 1877 (15   of 1877) Part IV, nor shall the State Government be  bound to supply any person with water except in  accordance with the terms of a contract in writing.</p>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>OF WATER- RATES</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <paragraph id="part-V.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>OF WATER- RATES</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading>Liability when person using un- authorisedly cannot be  identified. If water supplied through a water- course be used in an un-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-33.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>authorised manner, and if the person by whose act or neglect such use  has occurred cannot be identified,</p>
              <p>the person on whose land such water has flowed if such land has  derived benefit therefrom,</p>
              <p>or if such person cannot be identified or if such land has not  derived benefit therefrom, all the persons chargeable in respect of  the water supplied through such water- course, shall be liable, or  jointly liable, as the case may be, to the charges made for such use.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-34">
          <num>34.</num>
          <heading>Liability when water runs to waste. If water supplied through  a water- course be suffered to run to waste, and if, after enquiry by  the Divisional Canal- officer, the person through whose act or neglect  such water was suffered to run to waste cannot be discovered, all the  persons chargeable in respect of the water supplied through such  water- course shall be jointly liable for the charges made in respect  of the water so wasted.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading>Charges recoverable in addition to penalties.- All charges for  the unauthorised use or for waste of water may be recovered in  addition to any penalties incurred on account of such use or waste.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-35.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Decision of questions under sections 33 and 34.</p>
              <p>All questions under section 33 or section 34 shall be decided by  the Divisional Canal- officer, subject to an appeal to the Head Revenue  officer of the district, or such other appeal as may be provided under  section 75.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-36">
          <num>36.</num>
          <heading>Charge on occupier for water, how determined.- The rates to be  charged for canal- water supplied for purposes of irrigation to the  occupiers of land shall be determined by the rules to be made by the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-36.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>State Government, and such occupiers as accept the water shall pay for  it accordingly.</p>
              <p>" Occupier' s rate."</p>
              <p>A rate so charged shall be called the" occupier' s rate".</p>
              <p>The rules hereinbefore referred to may prescribe and determine  what persons or classes of persons are to be deemed to be occupiers  for the purposes of this section, and may also determine the several  liabilities, in respect of the payment of the occupier' s rate, of  tenants and of persons to whom tenants may have sublet their lands or  of proprietors and of persons to whom proprietors may have let the  lands held by them in cultivating occupancy.]</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-37">
          <num>37.</num>
          <heading>" Owner' s rate."- In addition to the occupier' s rate, a rate to  be called the" owner' s rate" may be imposed, according to rules to be  made by</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-37.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>the State Government, on the owners of canal- irrigated lands, in  respect of the benefit which they derive from such irrigation.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-38">
          <num>38.</num>
          <heading>Amount of owner' s rate.- The owner' s rate shall not exceed the  sum which, under the rules for the time being in force for the  assessment of land- revenue, might be assessed on such land on account  of the increase in the annual value or produce thereof caused by the  canal- irrigation. And, for the purpose of this section only, land  which is permanently settled or held free of revenue shall be  considered as though it were temporarily settled and liable to payment  of revenue.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-39">
          <num>39.</num>
          <heading>Owner' s rate, when not chargeable.- No owner' s rate shall be  chargeable either on the owner or occupier of land temporarily  assessed to pay land- revenue at irrigation- rates, during the currency  of such assessment.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-40">
          <num>40.</num>
          <heading>When occupier is to pay both owner' s rate and occupier' s  rate.- If such land is occupied by the owner,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-40.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>or if it is occupied by a tenant whose rent is not liable to  enhancement on the ground that the value of the produce of the land or  the productive powers of the land has or have been increased by  irrigation,</p>
              <p>such owner or tenant shall pay the owner' s rate as well as the  occupier' s rate.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-41">
          <num>41.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules for apportioning owner' s rate.- In the  case of a tenant with a right of occupancy, the State Government shall  have power to make rules for dividing the owner' s rate between such  tenant and his landlord, proportionately to the extent of the  beneficial interest of each in the land.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-42">
          <num>42.</num>
          <heading>When owner is to pay owner' s rate.- If the owner of the land  is not the occupier, but has power to enhance the rent of the occupier  on the ground that the value of the produce or the productive powers  of the land has or have been increased by irrigation,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-42.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>or if, when the amount of a rent was fixed, the land was  irrigated from the canal,</p>
              <p>the owner shall pay the owner' s rate.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-43">
          <num>43.</num>
          <heading>Effect of introduction of canal- irrigation on landlord' s  right to enhance.- If a revision of settlement is a ground for  entertaining a suit for the enhancement of rent, the introduction of  canal irrigation into any land shall have the same effect on the  landlord' s right to re- enhance the rent of a tenant with a right of  occupancy of such land, as if a revision of settlement had taken  place, under which the revenue payable in respect of such land had  been increased.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-44">
          <num>44.</num>
          <heading>Water- rate by whom payable, when charged on land held by  several owners.- Where a water- rate is charged on land held by several  joint owners, it shall be payable by the manager or other person who  receives the rents or profits of such land, and may be deducted</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-44.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>by him from such rents or profits before division, or may be recovered  by him from the persons liable to such rate in the manner customary in  the recovery of other charges on such rents or profits.</p>
              <p>Recovery of charges</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-45">
          <num>45.</num>
          <heading>Certified dues recoverable as land- revenue.- Any sum lawfully  due under this Part, and certified by the Divisional Canal- officer to  be so due, which remains unpaid after the day on which it becomes due,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-45.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>shall be recoverable by the Collector from the person liable for the  same as if it were an arrear of landrevenue.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-46">
          <num>46.</num>
          <heading>Power to contract for collection of canal- dues.- The</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-46.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Divisional Canal- officer or the Collector may enter into an agreement  with any person for the collection and payment to the State Government  by such person of any sum payable under this Act by a third party.</p>
              <p>When such agreement has been made, such person may recover such  sum by suit as though it were a debt due to him, or an arrear of rent  due to him on account of the land, work or building in respect of  which such sum is payable, or for or in which the canal- water shall  have been supplied or used.</p>
              <p>If such person makes default in the payment of any sum collected  by him under this section, such sum may be recovered from him by the</p>
              <p>Collector under section 45; and, if such sum or any part of it be  still due by the said third party, the sum or part so due may be  recovered in like manner by the Collector from such third party.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-47">
          <num>47.</num>
          <heading>Lambardars may be required to collect canal- dues.- The</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-47.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Collector may require the lambardar, or person under engagement to pay  the land- revenue of any estate, to collect and pay any sums payable  under this Act by a third party, in respect of any land or water in  such estate.</p>
              <p>Such sums shall be recoverable by the Collector as if they were  arrears of land- revenue due in respect of the defaulter' s share in  such estate;</p>
              <p>and for the purpose of collecting such sums from the subordinate  zemindars, raiyats,  tenants or sub- tenants], such lambardar or  person may exercise the powers, and shall be subject to the rules,</p>
              <p>laid down in the law for the time being in force in respect to the  collection by him of the rents of land or of shares of land- revenue.</p>
              <blockList id="section-47.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>The State Government shall provide--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-47.paragraph-0.list5.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>for remunerating persons collecting sums under this  section; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-47.paragraph-0.list5.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>for indemnifying them against expenses properly incurred  by them in such collection; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-47.paragraph-0.list5.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>for both such purposes.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-48">
          <num>48.</num>
          <heading>Fines excluded from sections 45, 46, 47. Nothing in section</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-45">
          <num>45.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-45.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>, 46 or 47 applies to fines.</p>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>OF CANAL- NAVIGATION</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-VI">
        <num>VI</num>
        <paragraph id="part-VI.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>OF CANAL- NAVIGATION</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-49">
          <num>49.</num>
          <heading>Detainer of vessels violating rules.- Any vessel entering or  navigating any canal contrary to the rules made in that behalf by the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-49.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>State Government, or so as to cause danger to the canal or the other  vessels therein, may be removed or detained, or both removed and  detained, by the Divisional Canal- officer, or by any other person duly  authorised in this behalf.</p>
              <p>Liability of owners of vessels causing damage.</p>
              <p>The owner of any vessel causing damage to a canal, or removed or  detained under this section, shall be liable to pay to the State</p>
              <p>Government such sum as the Divisional Canal- officer, with the approval  of the Superintending Canal- officer, determines to be necessary to  defray the expenses of repairing such damage or of such removal or  detention, as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-50">
          <num>50.</num>
          <heading>Recovery of fines for offences in navigating canals.- Any fine  imposed under this Act upon the owner of any vessel, or the servant or  agent of such owner or other person in charge of any vessel, for any  offence in respect of the navigation of such vessel, may be recovered  either in the manner prescribed by the Code of Criminal Procedure   or, if the Magistrate imposing the fine so directs, as though it were  a charge due in respect of such vessel.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-51">
          <num>51.</num>
          <heading>Power to seize and detain vessel on failure to pay charges.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-51.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>If any charge due under the provisions of this Part in respect of any  vessel is not paid on demand to the person authorised to collect the  same, the Divisional Canal- officer may seize and detain such vessel  and the furniture thereof, until the charge so due, together with all  expenses and additional charges arising from such seizure and  detention, is paid in full.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-52">
          <num>52.</num>
          <heading>Power to seize cargo or goods, if charges due thereon are not  paid.- If any charge due under the provisions of this Part in respect  of any cargo or goods carried in a Government vessel on a canal, or  stored on or in lands or warehouses occupied for the purposes of a  canal is not paid on demand to the person authorised to collect the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-52.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>same, the Divisional Canal- officer may seize such cargo or goods and  detain them until the charge so due, together with all expenses and  additional charges arising from such seizure and detention, is paid in  full.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-53">
          <num>53.</num>
          <heading>Procedure for recovery of such charges after seizure.- Within  a reasonable time after any seizure under section 51 or section 52,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-53.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>the said Canal- officer shall give notice to the owner or person in  charge of the property seized that it, or such portion of it as may be  necessary, will, on a day to be named in the notice, but not sooner  than fifteen days from the date of the notice, be sold in satisfaction  of the claim on account of which such property was seized, unless the  claim be discharged before the day so named.</p>
              <p>And, if such claim be not so discharged, the said Canal- officer  may, on such day, sell the property seized or such part thereof as may  be necessary to yield the amount due, together with the expenses of  such seizure and sale:</p>
              <p>Provided that no greater part of the furniture of any vessel or  of any cargo or goods shall be so sold than shall, as nearly as may  be, suffice to cover the amount due in respect of such vessel, cargo  or goods.</p>
              <p>The residue of such furniture, cargo or goods, and of the  proceeds of the sale, shall be made over to the owner or person in  charge of the property seized.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-54">
          <num>54.</num>
          <heading>Procedure in respect of vessels abandoned and goods  unclaimed.- If any vessel be found abandoned in a canal, or any cargo  or goods carried in a Government vessel on a canal, or stored on or in  lands or warehouses occupied for the purposes of a canal, be left  unclaimed for a period of two months, the Divisional Canal- officer may  take possession of the same.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-54.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The officer so taking possession may publish a notice that, if  such vessel and its contents, or such cargo or goods, are not claimed  previously to a day to be named in the notice, not sooner than thirty  days from the date of such notice, he will sell the same; and, if such  vessel, contents, cargo or goods be not so claimed, he may, at any  time after the day named in the notice, proceed to sell the same.</p>
              <p>Disposal of proceeds of sale.</p>
              <p>The said vessel and its contents, and the said cargo or goods if  unsold, or, if a sale has taken place, the proceeds of the sale, after  paying all tolls, charges and expenses incurred by the Divisional</p>
              <p>Canal- officer on account of the taking possession and sale, shall be  made over to the owner of the same, when his ownership is established  to the satisfaction of the Divisional Canal- officer.</p>
              <p>If the Divisional Canal- officer is doubtful to whom such property  or proceeds should be made over, he may direct the property to be</p>
              <p>sold as aforesaid, and the proceeds to be paid into the district  treasury, there to be held until the right thereto be decided by a</p>
              <p>Court of competent jurisdiction.</p>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>OF DRAINAGE</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-VII">
        <num>VII</num>
        <paragraph id="part-VII.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>OF DRAINAGE</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-55">
          <num>55.</num>
          <heading>Power to prohibit obstructions or order their removal.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-55.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Whenever it appears to the State Government that injury to any land or  the public health or public convenience has arisen or may arise from  the obstruction of any river, stream or drainage- channel, such</p>
              <p>Government may, by notification published in the Official Gazette,</p>
              <p>prohibit, within limits to be defined in such notification, the  formation of any obstruction, or may, within such limits, order the  removal or other modification of such obstruction.</p>
              <p>Thereupon so much of the said river, stream or drainage- channel  as is comprised within such limits shall be held to be a drainage- work  as defined in section 3.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-56">
          <num>56.</num>
          <heading>Power to remove obstructions after prohibition.- The</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-56.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Divisional Canal- officer, or other person authorised by the State</p>
              <p>Government in that behalf, may, after such publication issue an order  to the person causing or having control over any such obstruction to  remove or modify the same within a time to be fixed in the order.</p>
              <p>If, within the time so fixed, such person does not comply with  the order, the said Canal- officer may himself remove or modify the  obstruction; and if the person to whom the order was issued does not,</p>
              <p>when called upon, pay the expenses involved in such removal or  modification, such expenses shall be recoverable by the Collector from  him or his representative in interest as an arrear of land- revenue.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-57">
          <num>57.</num>
          <heading>Preparation of schemes for works of improvement.- Whenever it  appears to the State Government that any drain- age- works are necessary  for the improvement of any lands, or for the proper cultivation or  irrigation thereof,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-57.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>or that protection from floods or other accumulations of water,</p>
              <p>or from erosion by a river, is required for any lands, the State</p>
              <p>Government may cause a scheme for such drainage- works to be drawn up  and published, together with an estimate of its cost and a statement  of the proportion of such cost which the State Government proposes to  defray, and a schedule of the lands which it is proposed to make  chargeable in respect of the scheme.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-58">
          <num>58.</num>
          <heading>Powers of persons employed on such schemes.- The persons  authorised by the State Government to draw up such scheme may exercise  all or any of the powers conferred on the Canal- officers by section</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading/>
        </section>
        <section id="section-59">
          <num>59.</num>
          <heading>Rate on lands benefited by works.- An annual rate, in respect  of such scheme, may be charged, according to rules to be made by the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-59.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>State Government, on the owners of all lands which shall, in the  manner prescribed by such rules, be determined to be so chargeable.</p>
              <p>Such rate shall be fixed, as nearly as possible, so as not to  exceed either of the following limits:--</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-59.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>six per cent. per annum on the first cost of the said  works, adding thereto the estimated yearly cost of the  maintenance and supervision of the same, and deducting  therefrom the estimated income, if any, derived from  the works, excluding the said rate:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>in the case of agricultural land, the sum which under  the rules then in force for the assessment of land-</p>
              <p>revenue, might be assessed on such land on account of  the increase of the annual value or produce thereof  caused by the drainage- work.</p>
              <p>Such rate may be varied from time to time, within such maximum,</p>
              <p>by the State Government.</p>
              <p>So far as any defect to be remedied is due to any canal, water-</p>
              <p>course, road or other work or obstruction, constructed or caused by  the State Government or by any person, a proportionate share of the  cost of the drainage- works required for the remedy of the said defect  shall be borne by such Government or such person, as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-60">
          <num>60.</num>
          <heading>Recovery of rate.- Any such drainage- rate may be collected  and recovered in manner provided by sections 45, 46 and 47 for the  collection and recovery of water- rates.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-61">
          <num>61.</num>
          <heading>Disposal of claims to compensation.- Whenever, in pursuance of  a notification made under section 55, any obstruction is removed or  modified.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-61.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>or whenever any drainage- work is carried under section 57,</p>
              <p>all claims for compensation on account of any loss consequent on  the removal or modification of the said obstruction or the  construction of such work may be made before the Collector, and he  shall deal with the same in the manner provided in section 10.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-62">
          <num>62.</num>
          <heading>Limitation of such claims.- No such claim shall be entertained  after the expiration of one year from the occurrence of the loss  complained of, unless the Collector is satisfied that the claimant had  sufficient cause for not making the claim within such period.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-62.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>OF OBTAINING LABOUR FOR CANALS AND DRAINAGE- WORKS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-VIII">
        <num>VIII</num>
        <paragraph id="part-VIII.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>OF OBTAINING LABOUR FOR CANALS AND DRAINAGE- WORKS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-63">
          <num>63.</num>
          <heading>" Definition of" labourer".- For the purposes referred to in  this Part, the word" labourer" includes persons who exercise any  handicraft specified in rules to be made in that behalf by the State</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-63.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-64">
          <num>64.</num>
          <heading>Power to prescribe number of labourers to be supplied by  persons benefited by canal.- In any district in which a canal or  drainage- work is constructed, maintained or projected by the State</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-64.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government, the State Government may, if it thinks fit, direct the</p>
              <blockList id="section-64.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Collector--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-64.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to ascertain the proprietors, sub- proprietors or farmers  whose villages or estates are or will be in the  judgment of the Collector, benefited by such canal or  drainage- work, and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-64.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>to set down in a list, having due regard to the  circumstances of the districts and of the several  proprietors, sub- proprietors or farmers, the number of  labourers which shall be furnished by any of the said  persons, jointly or severally, from any such village or  estate, for employment on any such canal or drainage-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>work when required as hereinafter provided.</p>
              <p>The Collector may, from time to time, add to or alter such list  or any part thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-65">
          <num>65.</num>
          <heading>Procedure for obtaining labour for works urgently required.--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-65.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Whenever it appears to a Divisional Canal- officer duly authorised by  the State Government that, unless some work is immediately executed,</p>
              <p>such serious damage will happen to any canal or drainage- work as to  cause sudden and extensive public injury,</p>
              <p>and that the labourers necessary for the proper execution thereof  cannot be obtained in the ordinary manner within the time that can be  allowed for the execution of such work so as to prevent such injury,</p>
              <p>the said officer may require any person named in such list to furnish  as many labourers (not exceeding the number which, according to the   said list he is liable to supply) as to the said officer seems  necessary for the immediate execution of such work.</p>
              <blockList id="section-65.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Every requisition so made shall be in writing, and shall state--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-65.paragraph-0.list5.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the nature and locality of the work to be done;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-65.paragraph-0.list5.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the number of labourers to be supplied by the person  upon whom the requisition is made; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-65.paragraph-0.list5.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the approximate time for which and the day on which the  labourers will be required;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>and a copy thereof shall be immediately sent to the Superintending</p>
              <p>Canal- officer for the information of the State Government.</p>
              <p>The State Government shall fix, and may from time to time alter  the rates to be paid to any such labourers:</p>
              <p>Provided that such rates shall exceed the highest rates for the  time being paid in the neighbourhood for similar work.</p>
              <p>In the case of every such labourer, the payment shall continue  for the whole period during which he is, in consequence of the  provisions of this part, prevented from following his ordinary  occupation.</p>
              <p>The State Government may  direct that the provisions of this  part shall apply, either permanently or temporarily (as the case may   be), to any district or part of a district for the purpose of  effecting necessary annual silt- clearances, or to prevent the proper  operation of a canal or drainage- work being stopped or so much  interfered with as to stop the established course of irrigation or  drainage.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-66">
          <num>66.</num>
          <heading>Liability of labourers under requisition.- When any  requisition has been made on any person named in the said list, every  labourer ordinarily resident within the village or estate of such  person shall be liable to supply, and to continue to supply, his  labour, for the purposes aforesaid.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-66.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>OF JURISDICTION</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-IX">
        <num>IX</num>
        <paragraph id="part-IX.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>OF JURISDICTION</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-67">
          <num>67.</num>
          <heading>Jurisdiction under this Act of Civil Courts.- Except where  herein otherwise provided, all claims against the State Government in  respect of anything done under this Act may be tried by the Civil</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-67.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Courts; but no such Court shall in any case pass an order as to the  supply of canal- water to any crop sown or growing at the time of such  order.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-68">
          <num>68.</num>
          <heading>Settlement of differences as to mutual rights and liabilites  of persons interested in water- course. Whenever a difference arises  between two or more persons in regard to their mutual rights or  liabilities in respect of the use, construction or maintenance of a  water- course, any such person may apply in writing to the Divisional</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-68.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Canal- officer stating the matter in dispute. Such officer shall  thereupon give notice to the other persons interested that, on a day  to be named in such notice, he will proceed</p>
              <p>to inquire into the said matter. And, after such inquiry, he shall  pass his order thereon, unless he transfers (as he is hereby empowered   to do) the matter to the Collector, who shall thereupon inquire into  and pass his order on the said matter.</p>
              <p>Such order shall be final as to the use or distribution of water  for any crop sown or growing at the time when such order is made, and  shall thereafter remain in force until set aside by the decree of a</p>
              <p>Civil Court.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-69">
          <num>69.</num>
          <heading>Power to summon and examine witnesses.- Any officer empowered  under this Act to conduct any inquiry may exercise all such powers  connected with the summoning and examining of witnesses as are  conferred on Civil Courts by the  Code of Civil Procedure, and every  such inquiry shall be deemed a judicial proceeding.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-69.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>OF OFFENCES AND PENALTIES</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-X">
        <num>X</num>
        <paragraph id="part-X.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>OF OFFENCES AND PENALTIES</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-70">
          <num>70.</num>
          <heading>Offences under Act.- Whoever, without proper authority and  voluntarily, does any of the acts following, that is to say:--</heading>
          <subsection id="section-70.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>damages, alters, enlarges or obstructs any canal or  drainage- work;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-70.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>interferes with, increases or diminishes the supply of  water in, or the flow of water from, through, over or  under, any canal or drainage- work;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-70.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>interferes with or alters the flow of water in any river  or stream, so as to endanger, damage or render less  useful any canal or drainage- work;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-70.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>being responsible for the maintenance of a water- course,</p>
              <p>or using a water- course, neglects to take proper  precautions for the prevention of waste of the water  thereof, or interferes with the authorised distribution  of the water therefrom, or uses such water in an  unauthorised manner;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-70.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>corrupts or fouls the water of any canal so as to render  it less fit for the purposes for which it is ordinarily  used</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-70.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>causes any vessel to enter or navigate any canal  contrary to the rules for the time being prescribed by  the State Government for entering or navigating such  canal;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-70.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>while navigating on any canal, neglects to take proper  precautions for the safety of the canal and of vessels  thereon;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-70.8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>being liable to furnish labourers under Part VIII of  this Act, fails without reasonable cause, to supply or  to assist in supplying the labourers required of him;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-70.9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <p>being a labourer liable to supply his labour under Part</p>
              <p>VIII of this Act, neglects, without reasonable cause,</p>
              <p>so to supply, and to continue to supply, his labour;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-70.10">
            <num>(10)</num>
            <content>
              <p>destroys or moves any level- mark or water- gauge fixed  by the authority of a public servant;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-70.11">
            <num>(11)</num>
            <content>
              <p>passes, or causes animals or vehicles to pass, on or  across any of the works, banks or channels of a canal  or drainage- work contrary to rules made under this</p>
              <p>Act, after he has been desired to desist therefrom;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-70.12">
            <num>(12)</num>
            <content>
              <p>violates any rule made under this Act, for breach  whereof a penalty may be incurred;</p>
              <p>Penalty.</p>
              <p>shall be liable, on conviction before a Magistrate of such class as  the State Government directs in this behalf, to a fine not exceeding  fifty rupees, or to imprisonment not exceeding one month, or to both.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-71">
          <num>71.</num>
          <heading>Saving of prosecution under other laws.- Nothing herein  contained shall prevent any person from being prosecuted under any  other law for any offence punishable under this Act:</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-71.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Provided that no person shall be punished twice for the same  offence.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-72">
          <num>72.</num>
          <heading>Compensation to person injured. Whenever any person is fined  for an offence under this Act, the Magistrate may direct that the  whole or any part of such fine may be paid by way of compensation to  the person injured by such offence.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-73">
          <num>73.</num>
          <heading>Power to arrest without warrant.- Any person in charge of or  employed upon any canal or drainage- work may remove from the lands or  buildings belonging thereto, or may take into custody without a  warrant and take forthwith before a Magistrate or to the nearest  police- station, to be dealt with according to law, any person who,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-73.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>within his view, commits any of the following offences:--</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-73.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>wilfully damages or obstructs any canal or drainage-</p>
              <p>work:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-73.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>without proper authority interferes with the supply or  flow of water in or from any canal or drainage- work, or  in any river or stream, so as to endanger, damage or  render less useful any canal or drainage- work.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-74">
          <num>74.</num>
          <heading>Definition of" canal".- In this Part the word" canal" shall</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-74.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>(unless there be something repugnant in the subject or context) be  deemed to include also all lands occupied by the State Government for  the purposes of canals, and all buildings, machinery, fences, gates  and other erections, trees, crops, plantations or other produce  occupied by or belonging to the State Government upon such lands.</p>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>OF SUBSIDIARY RULES</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-XI">
        <num>XI</num>
        <paragraph id="part-XI.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>OF SUBSIDIARY RULES</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-75">
          <num>75.</num>
          <heading>Power to make, alter and cancel rules.- The State Government  may, from time to time  make rules to regulate the following  matters:--</heading>
          <subsection id="section-75.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the proceedings of any officer who, under any provision  of this Act, is required or empowered to take action in  any matter;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-75.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the cases in which, and the officers to whom, and the  conditions subject to which, orders and decisions given  under any provision of this Act, and not expressly  provided for as regards appeal, shall be appealable;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-75.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the persons by whom,  and] the time, place or manner  at or in which anything for the doing of which  provision is made under this Act, shall be done;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-75.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the amount of any charge made under this Act; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-75.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>generally to carry out the provisions of this Act.</p>
              <p>The State Government may from time to time  alter or cancel any  rules so made.</p>
              <p>Publication of rules.</p>
              <p>Such rules, alterations and cancelments shall be published in the</p>
              <p>Official Gazette, and shall thereupon have the force of law.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </part>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
