<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1992/40/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1992/40"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Central Agricultural University Act, 1992"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1992/40/eng@1992-12-26/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1992/40/eng@1992-12-26"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1992-12-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1992/40/eng@1992-12-26/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1992/40/eng@1992-12-26"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Central Agricultural University Act, 1992</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>NO. 40 OF 1992</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 26th December, 1992.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- third Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the establishment and incorporation of a Univer-</p>
        <p>sity for the North- Eastern region for the development of agricu-</p>
        <p>lture and for the furtherance of the advancement of learning and  prosecution of reserch in agriculture and allied sciences in that  region.</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:--</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencemen.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Central Agricultural University Act, 1992.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date 1 as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, and in all Statutes made hereunder,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>unless the context otherwise requires,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" Academic Council" means the Academic Council of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" academic staff" means such categories of staff as are  designated as academic staff by the Ordinances;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" agriculture" means the basic and applied sciences of  the soil and water management, crop production including  production of all garden crops, control of plants, pests and  diseases, horticulture including floriculture, animal husbandry  including veterinary and dairy science, fisheries, forestry  including farm forestry, homescience, agricultural engineering  and technology, marketing and processing of agricultural and  animal husbandry products, land use and management;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>" Board" means the Board of Management of the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>" Board of Studies" means the Board of Studies of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>" Chancellor" means the Chancellor of the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>" college" means a constituent college of the University  whether located at the headquarters, campus or elsewhere;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>" Department" means a Department of Studies of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list7">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list7.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>" employee" means any person appointed by the University  and includes teachers and other staff of the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list7.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>" extension education" means the educational activities  concerned with the training of orchardists, farmers and other  groups serving agriculture, horticulture, fisheries and improved  practices related thereto and the various phases of scientific  technology related to agriculture and agricultural production  including post harvest technology and marketing;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list7.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>" Faculty" means Faculty of the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list7.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>" North- Eastern region" means the North- Eastern region of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>India comprising the States of Arunachal Pradesh, Manipur,</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10">
              <listIntroduction>Meghalaya, Mizoram, Sikkim and Tripura;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>" Ordinances" means the Ordinances of the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>" Regulations" means the Regulations made by any  authority of the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>" Research Advisory Committee" means the Research</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list12">
              <listIntroduction>Advisory Committee of the University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list12.p">
                <num>(p)</num>
                <p>" Statutes" means the Statutes of the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list12.q">
                <num>(q)</num>
                <p>" student" means a person enrolled in the University for  undergoing a course of studies for obtaining a degree, diploma or  other academic distinction duly instituted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list12.r">
                <num>(r)</num>
                <p>" teachers" means Professors, Associate Professors,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list14">
              <listIntroduction>Assistant Professors, Teaching Faculty Members and their  equivalent appointed for imparting instruction or conducting  research or extension education programmes or combination of  these in the University, college or any institute maintained by  the University and designated as teachers by the Ordinances;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list14.s">
                <num>(s)</num>
                <p>" University" means the Central Agricultural University  established under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list14.t">
                <num>(t)</num>
                <p>" Vice- Chancellor" means the Vice- Chancellor of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list16">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list16.u">
                <num>(u)</num>
                <p>" Visitor" means the Visitor of the University.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>The University.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be established a University by  the name of the" Central Agricultural University".</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The headquarters of the University shall be at Imphal in the</p>
            <p>State of Manipur and it may also establish compuses at such other  places within its jurisdiction as it may deem fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The first Chancellor and the first Vice- Chancellor and the  first members of the Board, the Academic Council and all persons who  may hereafter become such officers or members, so long as they  continue to hold such office or membership are hereby constituted a  body corporate by the name of the Central Agricultural University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The University shall have perpetual succession and a common  seal and shall sue and be sued by the said name.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Objects of the University. The objects of the University shall  be--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to impart education in different branches of  agricultural and allied sciences as it may deem fit;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to further the advancement of learning and prosecution  of research in agriculture and allied sciences;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to undertake programmes of extension education in the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>States under its jurisdiction; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>to undertake such other activities as it may, from time  to time, determine.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Powers of the University. The University shall have the  following powers, namely:--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>to make provision for instructions in agricultural and  allied sciences;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>to make provision for conduct of research in  agricultural and allied branches of learning;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>to make provision for dissemination of the findings of  research and technical information through extension programmes;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>to grant, subject to such conditions as it may  determine, diplomas or certificates to, and confer degrees or  other academic distinctions on the basis of examination,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>evaluation or any other method of testing, on persons, and to  withdraw any such diplomas, certificates, degrees or other  academic distinction for good and sufficient cause;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>to confer honorary degrees or other distinctions in the  manner prescribed by the Statutes;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.vi">
                <num>(vi)</num>
                <p>to provide lectures and instructions for field workers,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>village leaders and other persons not enrolled as regular  students of the University and to grant certificates to them as  may be prescribed by the Statutes;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list4.vii">
                <num>(vii)</num>
                <p>to co- operate or collaborate or associate with any  other University or authority or institution of higher learning  in such manner and for such purposes as the University may  determine;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list4.viii">
                <num>(viii)</num>
                <p>to establish and maintain colleges relating to  agriculture, fisheries, dairying, veterinary medicine and animal  science, homescience, agricultural engineering, forestry and  allied sciences;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list4.ix">
                <num>(ix)</num>
                <p>to establish and maintain such campuses, special  centres, specialised laboratories, libraries, museums or other  units for research and instruction as are, in its opinion,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list6">
              <listIntroduction>necessary for the furtherance of its objects;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list6.x">
                <num>(x)</num>
                <p>to create teaching, research and extension education  posts and to make appointments thereto;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list6.xi">
                <num>(xi)</num>
                <p>to create administrative, ministerial and other posts  and to make appointments thereto;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list6.xii">
                <num>(xii)</num>
                <p>to institute and award fellowships, scholarships,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list8">
              <listIntroduction>studentships, medals and prizes;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list8.xiii">
                <num>(xiii)</num>
                <p>to determine standards of admission to the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list10">
              <listIntroduction>University, which may include examination, evaluation or any  other method of testing;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list10.xiv">
                <num>(xiv)</num>
                <p>to provide and maintain residential accommodation for  students and employees;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list10.xv">
                <num>(xv)</num>
                <p>to supervise the residences of the students of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list12">
              <listIntroduction>University and to make arrangements for promoting their health  and general welfare;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list12.xvi">
                <num>(xvi)</num>
                <p>to lay down conditions of service of all categories of  employees, including their code of conduct;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list12.xvii">
                <num>(xvii)</num>
                <p>to regulate and enforce discipline among the students  and the employees, and to take such disciplinary measures in this  regard as it may deem necessary;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list12.xviii">
                <num>(xviii)</num>
                <p>to fix, demand and receive such fees and other  charges as may be prescribed by the Statutes;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list12.xix">
                <num>(xix)</num>
                <p>to borrow, with the approval of the Central Government  on the security of its property, money for the purpose of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list14">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list14.xx">
                <num>(xx)</num>
                <p>to receive benefactions, donations and gifts and to  acquire, hold, manage and dispose of any property, movable or  immovable, including trust and endowment properties for its  purposes;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list14.xxi">
                <num>(xxi)</num>
                <p>to do all such other acts and things as may be  necessary, incidental or conducive to the attainment of all or  any of its objects.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Jurisdiction.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The jurisdiction and responsibility of the</p>
            <p>University with respect to teaching, research and programmes of  extension education at the University level, in the field of  agricultural shall extend to the States of Arunachal Pradesh, Manipur,</p>
            <p>Meghalaya, Mizoram, Sikkim and Tripura.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All colleges, research and experimental stations or other  institutions coming under the jurisdiction and authority of the</p>
            <p>University shall be its constituent units under the full management  and control of its officers and authorities and no such units shall be  recognised as affiliated units.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The University may assume responsibility for the training of  field extension workers and others and may develop such training  centres as may be required in various parts of the States under its  jurisdiction.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>University open to all classes, castes and creed. The</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>University shall be open to persons of either sex and of whatever  caste, creed, race or class, and it shall not be lawful for the</p>
            <p>University to adopt or impose on any person, any test whatsoever of  religious belief or profession in order to entitle him to be appointed  as a teacher of the University or to hold any other office therein or  be admitted as a student in the University or to graduate thereat or  to enjoy or exercise any privilege thereof:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing in this section shall be deemed to prevent  the University from making special provisions for the employment or  admission of women, handicapped or of persons belonging to the weaker  sections of the society and, in particular, of the Scheduled Castes  and the Scheduled Tribes.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>The Visitor.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The President of India shall be the Visitor  of the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of sub- sections (3) and (4), the</p>
            <p>Visitor shall have the right to cause an inspection to be made, by  such person or persons as he may direct, of the University, its  buildings, laboratories, libraries, museums, workshops and equipments,</p>
            <p>and of any institution or college and also of the examination,</p>
            <p>instruction and other work conducted or done by the University, and to  cause an inquiry to be made in like manner in respect of any matter  connected with the administration and finances of the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Visitor shall, in every case, give notice to the</p>
            <p>University of his intention to cause an inspection or inquiry to be  made and the University shall, on receipt of such notice, have the  right to make, within thirty days from the date of receipt of the  notice or such other period as the Visitor may determine, such  representations to him as it may consider necessary.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>After considering the representations, if any, made by the</p>
            <p>University, the Visitor may cause to be made such inspection or  inquiry as is referred to in sub- section (2).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an inspection or inquiry has been caused to be made by  the Visitor, the University shall be entitled to appoint a  representative who shall have the right to appear in person and to be  heard on such inspection or inquiry.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Visitor may address the Vice- Chancellor with reference to  the results of such inspection or inquiry together with such views and  advice with regard to the action to be taken thereon as the Visitor  may be pleased to offer and on receipt of the address made by the</p>
            <p>Visitor, the Vice- Chancellor shall communicate forthwith to the</p>
            <p>Board the results of the inspection or inquiry and the views of the</p>
            <p>Visitor and the advice tendered by him upon the action to be taken  thereon.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall communicate through the Vice- Chancellor to  the Visitor such action, if any, as it proposes to take or has been  taken by it upon the results of such inspection or inquiry.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the Board does not, within a reasonable time, take  action to the satisfaction of the Visitor, the Visitor may, after  considering any explanation furnished or representation made by the</p>
            <p>Board, issue such directions as he may think fit and the Board shall  be bound to comply with such directions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Without prejudice to the foregoing provisions of this  section, the Visitor may, by an order in writing, annul any proceeding  of the University which is not in conformity with this Act, the</p>
            <p>Statutes or the Ordinances:</p>
            <p>Provided that before making any such order, he shall call upon  the University to show cause why such an order should not be made and,</p>
            <p>if any cause is shown within a reasonable time, he shall consider the  same.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.10">
          <num>(10)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Visitor shall have such other powers as may be specified  by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Officers of the University. The following shall be the  officers of the University, namely:--</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the Chancellor;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the Vice- Chancellor;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Deans;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Directors;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the Registrar;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the Comptroller; and</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>such other officers as may be prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>The Chancellor.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chancellor shall be appointed by the</p>
            <p>Visitor in such manner as may be prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chancellor shall, by virtue of his office, be the Head of  the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chancellor shall, if present, preside at the convocations  of the University held for conferring degrees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>The Vice- Chancellor.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Vice- Chancellor shall be  appointed by the Visitor in such manner as may be prescribed by the</p>
            <p>Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Vice- Chancellor shall be the principal executive and  academic officer of the University and shall exercise general  supervision and control over the affairs of the University and give  effect to the decisions of all the authorities of the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Vice- Chancellor may, if he is of opinion that immediate  action is necessary on any matter, exercise any power conferred on any  authority of the University by or under this Act and shall report to  such authority the action taken by him on such matter:</p>
            <p>Provided that if the authority concerned is of opinion that such  action ought not to have been taken, it may refer the matter to the</p>
            <p>Visitor whose decision thereon shall be final:</p>
            <p>Provided further that any person in the service of the University  who is aggrieved by the action taken by the Vice- Chancellor under this  sub- section shall have the right to appeal against such action to the</p>
            <p>Board within three months from the date on which decision on such  action is communicated to him and thereupon the Board may confirm,</p>
            <p>modify or reverse the action taken by the Vice- Chancellor.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Vice- Chancellor, if he is of opinion that any decision of  any authority of the University is beyond the powers of the authority  conferred by the provisions of this Act, the Statutes or the</p>
            <p>Ordinances or that any decision taken is not in the interest of the</p>
            <p>University, may ask the authority concerned to review its decision  within sixty days of such decision and if the authority refuses to  review the decision either in whole or in part or no decision is taken  by it within the said period of sixty days, the matter shall be  referred to the Visitor whose decision thereon shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Vice- Chancellor shall exercise such other powers and  perform such other duties as may be prescribed by the Statutes or the</p>
            <p>Ordinances.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Deans and Directors. Every Dean and every Director shall be  appointed in such manner and shall exercise such powers and perform  such duties as may be prescribed by the Statutes.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>The Registrar.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Registrar shall be appointed in such  manner as may be prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Registrar shall have the power to enter into agreements,</p>
            <p>sign documents and authenticate records on behalf of the University  and shall exercise such powers and perform such duties as may be  prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>The Comptroller. The Comptroller shall be appointed in such  manner and shall exercise such powers and perform such duties as may  be prescribed by the Statutes.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Other officers. The manner of appointment and powers and  duties of the other officers of the University shall be prescribed by  the Statutes.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Authorities of the University. The following shall be the  authorities of the University, namely:--</heading>
        <subsection id="section-16.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the Board;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the Academic Council;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the Finance Committee;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the Research Programme Committee;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the Extension Education Advisory Committee;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the Board of Studies; and</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>such other authorities as may be prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>The Board.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall be the principal executive  body of the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The constitution of the Board, the term of office of its  members and its powers and functions shall be prescribed by the</p>
            <p>Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>The Academic Council.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Academic Council shall be the  principal academic body of the University and shall, subject to the  provisions of this Act, the Statutes and Ordinances, have the control  and general regulation of, and be responsible for, the maintenance of  standards of learning, education, instruction, evaluation and  examination within the University and shall exercise such other powers  and perform such other functions as may be conferred or imposed upon  it by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The constitution of the Academic Council and the term of  office of its members shall be prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>The Finance Committee. The constitution, powers and functions  of the Finance Committee shall be prescribed by the Statutes.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>The Research Programme Committee. The constitution, powers  and functions of the Research Programme Committee shall be prescribed  by the Statutes.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>The Extension Education Advisory Committee. The constitution,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>powers and functions of the Extension Education Advisory Committee  shall be prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>The Board of Studies. The constitution, powers and functions  of the Board of Studies shall be prescribed by the Statutes.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Faculties. The University shall have such Faculties as may be  prescribed by the Statutes.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Other authorities. The constitution, powers and functions of  other authorities of the University referred to in clause (7) of  section 16 shall be such as may be prescribed by the Statutes.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Power to make Statutes. Subject to the provisions of this</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Act, the Statutes may provide for all or any of the following matters,</p>
            <blockList id="section-25.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>namely:--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the constitution, powers and functions of the  authorities of the University, as may be constituted from time to  time;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the appointment and continuance in office of the members  of the said authorities, the filling up of vacancies of members,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-25.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>and all other matters relating to those authorities for which it  may be necessary or desirable to provide;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the appointment, powers and duties of the officers of  the University and their emoluments;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list4.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the appointment of teachers, academic staff and other  employees of the University and their emoluments;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list4.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the appointment of teachers and academic staff working  in any other University or organisation for a specific period for  undertaking a joint project;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list4.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the conditions of service of employees including  provision for pension, insurance and provident fund, the manner  of termination of service and disciplinary action;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list4.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the principles governing the seniority of service of the  employees of the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list4.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the procedure for arbitration in cases of dispute  between employees or students and the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list4.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the procedure for appeal to the Board by any employee or  student against the action of any officer or authority of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-25.paragraph-0.list6">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list6.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>the establishment and abolition of Departments, Centres,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-25.paragraph-0.list8">
              <listIntroduction>colleges and institutions;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list8.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>the conferment of honorary degrees;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list8.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>the withdrawal of degrees, diplomas, certificates and  other academic distinctions;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list8.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>the institution of fellowships, scholarships,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-25.paragraph-0.list10">
              <listIntroduction>studentships, medals and prizes;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list10.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>the delegation of powers vested in the authorities or  officers of the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list10.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>the maintenance of discipline among the employees and  students;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list10.p">
                <num>(p)</num>
                <p>all other matters which by this Act are to be, or may  be, prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Statutes how to be made.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-26.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The first Statutes are those set  out in the Schedule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board may from time to time make Statutes or may amend or  repeal the Statutes referred to in sub- section (1):</p>
            <p>Provided that the Board shall not make, amend or repeal any</p>
            <p>Statute affecting the status, powers or constitution of any authority  of the University until such authority has been given an opportunity  of expressing an opinion in writing on the proposed changes, and any  opinion so expressed shall be considered by the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Statute or any amendment or repeal of a Statute shall  require the assent of the Visitor who may assent thereto or withhold  assent therefrom or remit it to the Board for consideration.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A Statute or a Statute amending or repealing an existing</p>
            <p>Statute shall have no validity unless it has been assented to by the</p>
            <p>Visitor.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing sub-</p>
            <p>sections, the Visitor may amend or repeal the Statutes referred to in  sub- section (1), during the period of three years immediately after  the commencement of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing sub-</p>
            <p>sections, the Visitor may direct the University to make provisions in  the Statutes in respect of any matter specified by him and if the</p>
            <p>Board is unable to implement such direction within sixty days of its  receipt, the Visitor may, after considering the reasons, if any,</p>
            <p>communicated by the Board for its inability to comply with such  direction, make or amend the Statutes suitably.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Power to make Ordinances.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-27.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-27.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Subject to the provisions of  this Act and the Statutes, the Ordinances may provide for all or any  of the following matters, namely:--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-27.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the admission of students to the University and their  enrolment as such;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-27.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the courses of study to be laid down for all degrees,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-27.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>diplomas and certificates of the University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-27.1.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the medium of instruction and examination;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-27.1.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the award of degrees, diplomas, certificates and other  academic distinctions, the qualifications for the same and the  means to be taken relating to the granting and obtaining of the  same;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-27.1.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the fees to be charged for courses of study in the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>University and for admission to the examinations, degrees,</p>
            <blockList id="section-27.1.list6">
              <listIntroduction>diplomas and certificates of the University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-27.1.list6.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the conditions for award of fellowships, scholarships,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-27.1.list8">
              <listIntroduction>studentships, medals and prizes;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-27.1.list8.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the conduct of examinations, including the term of  office and manner of appointment and the duties of examining  bodies, examiners and moderators;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-27.1.list8.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the conditions of residence of the students;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-27.1.list8.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the special arrangements, if any, which may be made for  the residence, discipline and teaching of women students and the  prescribing of special courses of studies for them;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-27.1.list8.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>the appointment and emoluments of employees other than  those for whom provision has been made in the Statutes;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-27.1.list8.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>the establishment of special centres, specialized  laboratories and other committees;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-27.1.list8.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>the manner of co- operation and collaboration with other</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-27.1.list10">
              <listIntroduction>Universities and authorites including learned bodies or  associations;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-27.1.list10.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>the creation, composition and functions of any other  body which is considered necessary for improving the academic  life of the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-27.1.list10.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>such other terms and conditions of service of teachers  and other academic staff as are not prescribed by the Statutes;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-27.1.list10.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>the management of colleges and institutions established  by the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-27.1.list10.p">
                <num>(p)</num>
                <p>the setting up of a machinery for redressal of  grievances of employees; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-27.1.list10.q">
                <num>(q)</num>
                <p>all other matters which by this Act or the Statutes may  be provided for by the Ordinances.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The first Ordinances shall be made by the Vice- Chancellor  with the previous approval of the Central Government and the</p>
            <p>Ordinances so made may be amended or repealed at any time by the Board  in the manner prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28">
        <num>28.</num>
        <heading>Regulations. The authorities of the University may make</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Regulations, consistent with this Act, the Statutes and the Ordinances  for the conduct of their own business and that of the committees  appointed by them and not provided for by this Act, the Statutes or  the Ordinances in the manner prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29">
        <num>29.</num>
        <heading>Annual report.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-29.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The annual report of the University shall  be prepared under the direction of the Board, which shall include,</p>
            <p>among other matters, the steps taken by the University towards the  fulfilment of its objects and shall be submitted to the Board on or  after such date as may be prescribed by the Statutes and the Board  shall consider the report in its annual meeting.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall submit the annual report to the Visitor along  with its comments, if any.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A copy of the annual report as prepared under sub- section</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>, shall also be submitted to the Central Government, which shall,</p>
            <p>as</p>
            <p>soon as may be, cause the same to be laid before both Houses of</p>
            <p>Parliament.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-30">
        <num>30.</num>
        <heading>Annual accounts.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-30.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The annual accounts of the University  shall be prepared under the directions of the Board and shall, once at  least every year and at intervals of not more than fifteen months, be  audited by the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India or by such  persons as he may authorise in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-30.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A copy of the annual accounts together with the audit report  thereon shall be submitted to the Board and the Visitor along with the  observations of the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-30.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any observations made by the Visitor on the annual accounts  shall be brought to the notice of the Board and the observations of  the Board, if any, shall be submitted to the Visitor.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-30.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A copy of the annual accounts together with the audit report  as submitted to the Visitor, shall also be submitted to the Central</p>
            <p>Government, which shall, as soon as may be, cause the same to be laid  before both Houses of Parliament.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-30.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The audited annual accounts after having been laid before  both Houses of Parliament shall be published in the Official Gazette.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-31">
        <num>31.</num>
        <heading>Conditions of service of employees.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-31.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every employee of the</p>
            <p>University shall be appointed under a written contract, which shall be  lodged with the University and a copy of which shall be furnished to  the employee concerned.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-31.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any dispute arising out of the contract between the</p>
            <p>University and any employee shall, at the request of the employee, be  referred to a Tribunal of Arbitration consisting of one member  appointed by the Board, one member nominated by the employee concerned  and an umpire appointed by the Visitor.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-31.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The decision of the Tribunal shall be final, and no suit  shall lie in any civil court in respect of the matters decided by the</p>
            <p>Tribunal.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-31.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every request made by the employee under sub- section (2)</p>
            <p>shall be deemed to be a submission to arbitration upon the terms of  this section within the meaning of the Arbitration Act, 1940 (2 of</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1940">
        <num>1940.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1940.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-1940.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The procedure for regulating the work of the Tribunal shall  be prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-32">
        <num>32.</num>
        <heading>Procedure of appeal and arbitration in disciplinary cases  against students.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-32.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any student or candidate for an examination  whose name has been removed from the rolls of the University by the  orders or resolution of the Vice- Chancellor, Discipline Committee or</p>
            <p>Examination Committee, as the case may be, and who has been debarred  from appearing at the examinations of the University for more than one  year, may, within ten days of the date of receipt of such orders or  copy of such resolution by him, appeal to the Board and the Board may  confirm, modify or reverse the decision of the Vice- Chancellor or the</p>
            <p>Committee, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-32.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any dispute arising out of any disciplinary action taken by  the University against a student shall, at the request of such  student, be referred to a Tribunal of Arbitration and the provisions  of sub- sections (2), (3), (4) and (5) of section 31 shall, as far as  may be, apply to a reference made under this sub- section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-33">
        <num>33.</num>
        <heading>Right to appeal. Every employee or student of the University  or of a college or institution maintained by the University shall,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-33.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, have a right to  appeal, within such time as may be prescribed by the Statutes, to the</p>
            <p>Board against the decision of any officer or authority of the</p>
            <p>University or any college or an institution, as the case may be, and  thereupon the Board may confirm, modify or reverse the decision  appealed against.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-34">
        <num>34.</num>
        <heading>Provident and pension funds.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-34.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The University shall  constitute for the benefit of its employees such provident or pension  fund or provide such insurance schemes as it may deem fit in such  manner and subject to such conditions as may be prescribed by the</p>
            <p>Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-34.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where such provident fund or pension fund has been so  constituted, the Central Government may declare that the provision of  the Provident Funds Act, 1925 (19 of 1925), shall apply to such fund,</p>
            <p>as if it were a Government provident fund.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-35">
        <num>35.</num>
        <heading>Disputes as to constitution of University authorities. If any  question arises as to whether any person has been duly appointed as,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-35.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>or is entitled to be, a member of any authority of the University, the  matter shall be referred to the Visitor whose decision thereon shall  be final.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-36">
        <num>36.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of Committees. Where any authority of the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-36.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>University is given power by this Act or the Statutes to appoint</p>
            <p>Committees, such Committees shall, save as otherwise provided, consist  of the members of the authority concerned and of such other person, if  any, as the authority in each case may think fit.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-37">
        <num>37.</num>
        <heading>Filling of casual vacancies. All casual vacancies among the  members (other than ex officio members) of any authority of the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-37.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>University shall be filled, as soon as may be, by the person who  appointed or co- opted the member whose place has become vacant and  person appointed or co- opted to a casual vacancy shall be a member of  such authority or body for the residue of the term for which the  person whose place he fills would have been a member.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-38">
        <num>38.</num>
        <heading>Proceedings of University authorities not invalidated by  vacancy. No act or proceedings of any authority of the University  shall be invalid merely by reason of the existence of a vacancy or  vacancies among its members.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-39">
        <num>39.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-39.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against the Board,</p>
            <p>any authority or officer or other employee of the University for  anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in  pursuance of any of the provisions of this Act, the Statutes or the</p>
            <p>Ordinances.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-40">
        <num>40.</num>
        <heading>Mode of proof of University records. A copy of any receipt,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-40.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>application, notice, order, proceeding, resolution of any authority or</p>
            <p>Committee of the University, or other documents in possession of the</p>
            <p>University, or any entry in any register duly maintained by the</p>
            <p>University, if verified by the Registrar, shall be received as prima  facie evidence of such receipt, application, notice, order,</p>
            <p>proceeding, resolution or documents or the existence of entry in the  register and shall be admitted as evidence of the matters and  transactions therein where the original thereof would, if produced,</p>
            <p>have been admissible in evidence, notwithstanding anything contained  in the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872.) or in any other law for  the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-41">
        <num>41.</num>
        <heading>Power to remove difficulties.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-41.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any difficulty arises in  giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government  may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions,</p>
            <p>not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as appear to it to  be necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty:</p>
            <p>Provided that no such order shall be made under this section  after the expiry of three years from the commencement of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-41.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every order made under this section shall be laid, as soon as  may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-42">
        <num>42.</num>
        <heading>Transitional provisions. Notwithstanding anything contained  in this Act and the Statutes,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-42.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-42.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-42.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the first Chancellor and the first Vice- Chancellor shall  be appointed by the Visitor and shall hold office for a term of  five years;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-42.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the first Registrar and the first Comptroller shall be  appointed by the Visitor and each of the said officers shall hold  office for a term of three years;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-42.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the first members of the Board shall be nominated by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-42.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Visitor and shall hold office for a term of three years;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-42.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the first members of the Academic Council shall be  nominated by the Visitor and shall hold office for a term of  three years:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that if any vacancy occurs in the above offices or  authorities, the same shall be filled by appointment or nomination, as  the case may be, by the Visitor, and the person so appointed or  nominated shall hold office for so long as the officer or member in  whose place he is appointed or nominated would have held office, if  such vacancy had not occurred.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-43">
        <num>43.</num>
        <heading>Statutes, Ordinances and Regulations to be published in the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-43.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Official Gazette and to be laid before Parliament.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-43.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Statute,</p>
            <p>Ordinance or Regulation made under this Act shall be published in the</p>
            <p>Official Gazette.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-43.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Statute, Ordinance or Regulation made under this Act  shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House  of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty  days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more  successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session  immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the</p>
            <p>Statute, Ordinance or Regulation or both Houses agree that the</p>
            <p>Statute, Ordinance or Regulation should not be made, the Statute,</p>
            <p>Ordinance or Regulation shall thereafter have effect only in such  modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however,</p>
            <p>that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice</p>
            <p>to the validity of anything previously done under that Statute,</p>
            <p>Ordinance or Regulation.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-43.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The power to make Statutes, Ordinances or Regulations shall  include the power to give retrospective effect from a date not earlier  than the date of commencement of this Act, to the Statutes, Ordinances  or Regulations or any of them but no retrospective effect shall be  given to any Statute, Ordinance or Regulation so as to prejudicially  affect the interests of any person to whom such Statutes, Ordinances  or Regulations may be applicable.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
