<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1980/41/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1980/41"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Essential Services Maintenance (Assam) Act, 1980"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1980/41/eng@1980-07-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1980/41/eng@1980-07-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-07-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1980/41/eng@1980-07-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1980/41/eng@1980-07-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Essential Services Maintenance (Assam) Act, 1980</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 41 OF 1980</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 19th July, 1980.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty- first Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the maintenance of certain essential services  and the normal life of the community in Assam.</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:--</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requrires,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.1.list1.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>" essential service" means--</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.1.list1.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>any transport service for the carriage of passengers or  goods, by land or water, with respect to which the Legislative</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Assembly of the State of Assam has power to make laws;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list3.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>any service connected with the production, storage,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list5">
              <listIntroduction>supply or distribution, as the case may be, of gas or water;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list5.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>any service connected with the maintenance of public  health and sanitation, including hospitals and dispensaries;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list5.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>any public services and posts in connection with the  affairs of the State, and also persons appointed to the secre-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list7">
              <listIntroduction>tarial staff of the Legislative Assembly of the State of Assam;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list7.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>any other service or employment or class thereof, conne-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>cted with matters with respect to which the Legislative Assembly  of the State of Assam has power to make laws and which the State</p>
            <p>Government, being of opinion that strikes therein would prejudi-</p>
            <p>cially affect the maintenance of any public utility service, the  public safety of the maintenance of the supplies and services  necessary for the life of the community or would result in the</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list12">
              <listIntroduction>Official Gazette, declare to be an essential service for the  purposes of this Act;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list12.bb">
                <num>(bb)</num>
                <p>" State Government" means the State Government of Assam;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list12.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" strike" means the cessation of work by a body of  persons employed in any essential service acting in combination  or a concerted refusal or a refusal under a common understanding  of any number of persons who are or who have been so employed to  continue to work or to accept employment, and includes--</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list12.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>refusal to work overtime where such work is  necessary for the maintenance of any essential service;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list12.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>any other conduct which is likely to result in, or  results in, cessation or substantial retardation of work in  any essential service.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Every notification issued  under sub- clause (v)] of clause</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>of sub- section (1) shall be laid before each House of Parliament  immediately after it is made if it is in session and on the first day  of the commencement of the next session of the House if it is not in  session, and shall cease to operate at the expiration of forty days  from the date of its being so laid or from the re- assembly of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Parliament, as the case may be, unless before the expiration of that  period a resolution approving the issue of the notification is passed  by both Houses of Parliament.</p>
            <p>Explanation.-- Where the Houses of Parliament are summoned to  reassemble on different dates, the period of forty days shall be  reckoned from the later of those dates.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any reference in this Act to any law which is not in force in  any area of the State of Assam and to any authority under such law  shall, in relation to that area, be construed as a reference to the  corresponding law in force in that area and to the corresponding  authority under such corresponding law.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Power to prohibit strikes in certain employments.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the</p>
            <p>State Government] is satisfied that in the public interest it is  necessary or expedient so to do, it may, by general or special Order,</p>
            <p>prohibit strikes in the State of Assam in any essential service  specified in the Order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An Order made under sub- section (1) shall be published in  such manner as the  State Government] considers best calculated to  bring it to the notice of the persons affected by the Order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An Order made under sub- section (1) shall be in force for six  months only, but the  State Government] may, by a like Order, extend  it for any period not exceeding six months if it is satisfied that  in the public interest it is necessary or expedient so to do.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Upon the issue of an Order under sub- section (1),--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>no person employed in any essential service to which the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.4.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Order relates shall go or remain on strike;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.4.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any strike declared or commenced, whether before or  after the issue of the Order, by persons employed in any such  service shall be illegal.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Dismissal of employees participating in illegal strikes. Any  person who commences a strike which is illegal under this Act, or goes  or remains on, or otherwise takes part in, any such strike, shall be  liable to disciplinary action (including dismissal) in accordance with  the same provisions as are applicable for the purpose of taking such  disciplinary action (including dismissal) on any other ground under  the terms and conditions of service applicable to him in relation to  his employment.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for illegal strikes. Any person who commences a strike  which is illegal under this Act, or goes or remains on, or otherwise  takes part in, any such strike shall be punishable with imprisonment  for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine which may  extend to one thousand rupees, or with both.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for instigation, etc. Any person who instigates or  incites other persons to take part in, or otherwise acts in  furtherance of, a strike which is illegal under this Act shall be  punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>or with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Subs. by Act 40 of 1981, s. 13 (w. e. f. 26- 7- 1981).</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>It shall cease to have effect on the expiry of nine years from  the date of assent to the Act 40 of 1981, i. e. 23- 9- 1981.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for giving financial aid to illegal strikes. Any  person who knowingly expends or supplies any money in furtherance or  support of a strike which is illegal under this Act shall be  punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>or with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Power to arrest without warrant. Notwithstanding anything  contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), any  police officer may arrest without warrant any person who is reasonably  suspected of having committed any offence under this Act.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Offences to be tried summarily. Notwithstanding anything  contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), all  offences under this Act shall be tried in a summary way by a Judicial</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Magistrate of the first class specially empowered in this behalf by  the  State Government] and the provisions of sections 262 to 265</p>
            <p>(both inclusive) of the said Code shall, as far as may be, apply to  such trial:</p>
            <p>Provided that in a case of conviction for any offence in a  summary trial under this section, it shall be lawful for the</p>
            <p>Magistrate to pass a sentence of imprisonment for any term for which  such offence is punishable under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Act to override other laws. The provisions of this Act and of  any Order issued thereunder shall have effect notwithstanding anything  inconsistent therewith contained in the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>(14 of 1947), or in any other law for the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Repeal and saving.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Essential Services Maintenance</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.Assam">
                <num>(Assam)</num>
                <p>Ordinance, 1980 (2 of 1980), is hereby repealed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action  taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or  taken under this Act, as if this Act had come into force on the 6th  day of April, 1980.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Subs. by Act 40 of 1981, s. 13 (w. e. f. 26- 7- 1981),</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>It shall cease to have effect on the existing of 0nine years from  the date of assent to the Act 40 of 1981, i. e. 23- 9- 1981.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
