<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1923/42/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1923/42"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Mussalman Wakf Act, 1923"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1923/42/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1923/42/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1923/42/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1923/42/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Mussalman Wakf Act, 1923</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short tittle extent and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Mussalman Wakf Act, 1923.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India except [the territories which, immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised in Part B States.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This section shall come into force at once; and</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that the remaining provisions of this Act, or any of them which it may specify, shall come into force in the State, or any specified part thereof, on such date as it may appoint in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“benefit” does not include any benefit which a mutwalli is entitled to claim solely by reason of his being such mutwalli;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“Court” means the Court of the District Judge or, within the limits of the ordinary original civil jurisdiction of a High Court, such Court, subordinate to the High Court, as the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, designate in this behalf;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“mutwalli” means any person appointed either verbally or under any deed or instrument by which a wakf has been created or by a Court of competent jurisdiction to be the mutwalli of a wakf, and includes a naib-mutwalli or other person appointed by a mutwalli to perform the duties of the mutwalli, and, save as otherwise provided in this Act, any person who is for the time being administrating any wakf property;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>“wakf” means the permanent dedication by a person professing the Mussalman faith of any property for any purpose recognised by the Mussalman law as religious, pious or charitable, but does not include any wakf, such as is described in section 3 of the Mussalman Wakf Validating Act, 1913, under which any benefit is for the time being claimable for himself by the person by whom the wakf was created or by any of his family or descendants.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>State Amendment</p>
            <p>Maharashtra: Gujarat.—</p>
            <p>In its application to Bombay area of the State of Maharashtra/Gujarat,—</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>in section 2—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>after clause (b), insert the following clause, namely:—</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>“(bb)</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list4">
              <listIntroduction>“Distirct” means a district constituted under section 3 of the Bombay Civil Courts Act, 1869, and includes the Greater Bombay.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list4.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>after clause (e), insert the following clause namely:—</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>“(ee)</p>
            <p>“Wakf Committee” means a committee constituted under section 6L.”</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>after section 2 insert the heading “Part II”.</p>
            <p>Vide Bombay Act 18 of 1935, secs. 3 and 4 (w.e.f. 23-9-1935) and 17 of 1945, sec. 9 Sch. E, Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87 (w.e.f. 1-5-1960).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Obligation to furnish particulars relating to wakf.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Within six months from the commencement of this Act every mutwalli shall furnish to the Court within the local limits of whose jurisdiction the property of the wakf of which he is the mutwalli is situated or to any one of two or more such Courts, a statement containing the following particulars, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>a description of the wakf property sufficient for the identification thereof;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the gross annual income from such property;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the gross amount of such income which has been collected during the five years preceding the date on which the statement is furnished, or of the period which has elapsed since the creation of the wakf, whichever period is shorter;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the amount of the Government revenue and cesses, and of all rents, annually payable in respect of the wakf property;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>an estimate of the expenses annually incurred in the realisation of the income of the wakf property, based on such details as are available of any such expenses incurred within the period to which the particulars under clause (c) relate;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <blockList id="section-3.1.list1.f.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>the amount set apart under the wakf for—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-3.1.list1.f.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>the salary of the mutwalli and allowances to individuals;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.1.list1.f.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>purely religious purposes;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.1.list1.f.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>charitable purposes;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.1.list1.f.list0.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>any other purposes; and</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>any other particulars which may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every such statement shall be accompanied by a copy of the deed or instrument creating the wakf or, if no such deed or instrument has been executed or a copy thereof cannot be obtained shall contain full particulars, as far as they are known to the mutwalli, of the origin, nature and objects of the wakf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>a wakf is created after the commencement of this Act, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in the case of a wakf such as is described in section 3 of the Wakf Validating Act, 1913, the person creating the wakf or any member of his family or any of his descendants is at the commencement of this Act alive and entitled to claim any benefit thereunder,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>the statement referred to in sub-section (1) shall be furnished, in the case referred to in clause (a), within six months of the date on which the wakf is created or, if it has been created by a written document, of the date on which such document is executed, or, in the case referred to in clause (b), within six months of the date of the death of the person entitled to such benefit as aforesaid, or of the last survivor of any such persons, as the case may be.</p>
            <p>State Amendment</p>
            <p>Uttar Pradesh.—</p>
            <p>Omit section 3.</p>
            <p>Vide Uttar Pradesh Act 13 of 1936, sec. 70 (w.e.f. 1-7-1941).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Publication of particulars and requisition of further particulars.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When any statement has been furnished under section 3 the Court shall cause notice of the furnishing thereof to be affixed in some conspicuous place in the Court-house and to be published in such other manner, if any, as may be prescribed, and thereafter any person may apply to the Court by a petition in writing, accompanied by the prescribed fee, for the issue of an order requiring the mutwalli to furnish further particulars or documents.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On such application being made, the Court may, after making such inquiry, if any, as it thinks fit, if it is of opinion that any further particulars or documents are necessary in order that full information may be obtained regarding the origin, nature or objects of the wakf or the condition or management of the wakf property, cause to be served on the mutwalli an order requiring him to furnish such particulars or documents within such time as the Court may direct in the order.</p>
            <p>State Amendment</p>
            <p>Uttar Pradesh.—</p>
            <p>Omit section 4.</p>
            <p>Vide Uttar Pradesh Act, 13 of 1936, sec. 70 (w.e.f. 1-7-1941).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Statement of accounts.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Within three months after the thirty-first day of March next following the date on which the statement referred to in section 3 has been furnished and thereafter within three months of the thirty-first day of March in every year, every mutwalli shall prepare and furnish to the Court to which such statement was furnished a full and true statement of accounts, in such form and containing such particulars as may be prescribed, of all moneys received or expended by him on behalf of the wakf of which he is the mutwalli during the period of twelve months ending on such thirty-first day of March or, as the case may be, during that portion of the said period during which the provisions of this Act have been applicable to the wakf:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Court may, if it is satisfied that there is sufficient cause for so doing, extend the time allowed for the furnishing of any statement of accounts under this section.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Audit of account.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Every statement of accounts shall, before it is furnished to the Court under section 5, be audited—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in the case of a wakf the gross income of which during the year in question, after deduction of the land-revenue and cesses, if any, payable to the Government exceeds two thousand rupees, by a person who is the holder of a certificate granted by the Central Government under section 144 of the Indian Companies Act, 1913, or is a member of any institution or association the members of which have been declared under that section to be entitled to act as auditors of companies throughout the territories to which this Act applies; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in the case of any other wakf, by any person authorised in this behalf by general or special order of the said Court.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>State Amendment</p>
            <p>Maharashtra: Gujarat.—</p>
            <p>In its appliction to Bombay area of the State of Maharashtra/Gujarat,—</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>after section 6, insert the following parts, namely:—</p>
            <p>“Part III</p>
            <p>Powers of the Court to Call for Particulars and Statement of Accounts</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6A">
        <num>6A.</num>
        <heading>Power of Court to call upon the mutwalli to submit statement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in section 3, it shall be competent to the Court on failure of a mutwalli to furnish a statement as required under the said section to require the mutwalli to furnish, within such time as the Court shall fix, a statement containing all or any of the particulars referred to in the said section, including a copy of the deed or instrument, if any, creating the wakf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The provision of section 4 shall apply to a statement furnished under this section as if such statement had been furnished under section 3.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6B">
        <num>6B.</num>
        <heading>Power of Court to require statement of accounts at any time.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6B.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in section 5, it shall be competent to the Court, on failure of a mutwalli to furnish a statement of accounts as required under the said section, to require the mutwalli to prepare and furnish, within such time as the Court may fix, a statement of accounts of the nature described in the said section and for such period as the Court may think fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6B.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of section 6 shall apply to any statement of accounts required to be furnished under this section as if such statement of accounts were a statement of accounts furnished under section 5.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <part id="part-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="part-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Powers of the Court to Enquire</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-6C">
          <num>6C.</num>
          <heading>Power of Court to Enquire.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6C.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-6C.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Court may, either on its own motion or upon the application of any person claiming to have an interest in a wakf, hold an inquiry in the prescribed manner at any time to ascertain—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6C.1.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>whether a wakf exists;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6C.1.list1.ia">
                  <num>(ia)</num>
                  <p>whether such wakf is a wakf to which this Act applies;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6C.1.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>whether any property is the property of such wakf and whether the whole or any substantial portion of the subject-matter of such wakf is situate within the local limits of the jurisdiction of the Court; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6C.1.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>who is the mutwalli of such wakf.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6C.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If it comes to the knowledge of the Court that a suit has been instituted in any Civil Court in regard to any of the matters mentioned in sub-section (1), it shall stay the inquiry so far as it relates to, or is likely to be affected by, the Court’s findings or order in regard to such matters, until the suit is finally decided in that Court.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6C.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Court shall from time to time ascertain whether such suit has been finally decided and after the final decision of the suit, it shall proceed with the enquiry in regard to such matters, if any, as may not have been decided in such suit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6C.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On completion of the enquiry provided for in sub-sections (1) and (3) the Court shall record its findings as to the matters mentioned in the said sub-sections, except such matters as may have been decided in the aforesaid suit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6C.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Save as provided in this section, the Court shall not, when acting under this section, try or determine any question of the title of any person claiming adversely to the wakf.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <paragraph id="part-V.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Registration of Wakfs, Wakf Accounts and Wakf Administration Funds</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-6D">
          <num>6D.</num>
          <heading>Registration of Wakfs.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6D.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-6D.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Court shall, after the submission of a statement under section 3 or section 4 or section 6A and an enquiry, if necessary, held under section 6C, or merely after an enquiry held under section 6C, record, in such forms as may be prescribed in a register called the Register of Wakfs, the following particulars:—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6D.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>a description of the wakf property sufficient for the identification thereof;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6D.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the gross annual income from such property;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6D.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the gross amount of such income which has been collected during the five years preceding the date on which the statement is furnished, or during the period which has elasped since the creation of the wakf, whichever period is shorter;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6D.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the amount of the Government revenue and cesses and of all rents annually payable in respect of the wakf property;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6D.1.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>an estimate of the expenses annually incurred in the realisation of the income, of the wakf property, based on such details as are available of any such expenses incureed within the period to which the particulars under clause (c) relate;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6D.1.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-6D.1.list1.f.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>the amount set apart under the wakf for—</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-6D.1.list1.f.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>the salary of the mutwalli and allowances to individuals.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-6D.1.list1.f.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>purely religous purposes;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-6D.1.list1.f.list0.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>charitable purposes;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-6D.1.list1.f.list0.iv">
                      <num>(iv)</num>
                      <p>any other purposes;</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6D.1.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the name of the mutwalli; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6D.1.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>such other particulars as may be prescribed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6D.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Statements, if any, furnished under sections 3, 4 and 6A shall be filed with the Register of Wakfs.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6E">
          <num>6E.</num>
          <heading>Amendment of entries in Register of Wakfs.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6E.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When any change occurs in any of the particulars recorded in the Register of Wakfs, the mutwalli shall, within three months of the occurrence of succh change, report to the Court such, change in the prescribed form, accompanied by the prescribed fee. The provisions of sections 3 and 4 shall, so far as may be, apply to any such statement.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6E.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purpose of verifying the correctness of the entries in the Register of Wakfs or ascertaining any change which may have occurred in such register, the Court may hold an enquiry in the prescribed manner. The provisions of section 6C shall, so far as may be, apply to any such inquiry.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6E.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the Court, after receiving a report under sub-section (1) and holding an enquiry, if necessary, under sub-section (2), or merely after an enquiry held under sub-section (2), is satisfied that a change has occurred in any of the particulars recorded in the Register of Wakfs with regard to wakf, it shall amend in the prescribed manner the entry or entries affected by such change and shall file the report furnished under sub-section (1) along with the statement, if any, relating to the said wakf filed under section 3.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6F">
          <num>6F.</num>
          <heading>Entries in the Register of Wakfs and findings recorded under section 6C to be final subject to section 6G.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6F.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The entries made by the Court in the Register of Wakfs and the findings recorded under section 6C shall, subject to the provision of section 6G, be final for the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6G">
          <num>6G.</num>
          <heading>Making or amendment of entries in Register of Wakfs by order of Court.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6G.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>A Civil Court of competent jurisdiction deciding any question relating to any wakf may direct that the Court shall make such entries or amendments of entries in the Register of Wakfs relating to the said wakf as are consequential upon its decision, and the Court shall make such entries or amendments of such entries accordingly.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6H">
          <num>6H.</num>
          <heading>Maintenance of account and their audit.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6H.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every mutwalli of a wakf in respect of which an entry has been recorded in the Register of Wakfs shall keep regular accounts of all movable and immovable property received, and of all payments and alienations made and incumbrances created by him on behalf of the wakf of which he is the mutwall. such accounts shall be kept in such form and shall contain such particulars as amy be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6H.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The account shall be balanced on the thirty-first day of March in each year and shall be examined and audited annually or at such other intervals, and in such manner as may be prescribed and by the persons referred to in section 6.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6H.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every auditor acting under sub-section (2) shall have access to the accounts and to all books, vouchers and other documents and records in the possession and under the control of the mutwalli:</p>
              <p>Provided that, if it is proved to the satisfaction of the Court that the gross annual income of any particular wakf is less than two hundred rupees, the Court may by order in writing exempt such wakf from the provisions of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>-I.  Annual contribution from wakfs.—</p>
              <p>Every wakf shall, for the purpose of meeting the charges and expenses incidental to the registration, superintendence, administration and control of wakfs, the maintenance of the Registers of wakfs, the scrutiny and audit of accounts of wakfs, the institution and defence of suits and proceedings relating to wakfs, and generally carrying into effect the purposes of this Act, be liable to pay to the Wakf Administration Fund of the district concerned annually such contribution, on such date and in such manner as may be prescribed:</p>
              <p>Provided that the (Provincial Government) may, by rules made in this behalf, exempt from the provisions of this section any particular wakf or class of wakfs.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6J">
          <num>6J.</num>
          <heading>Wakf Administration Fund.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6J.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-6J.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>For each distirct there shall be created a fund to be called the Wakf Administration Fund of the district concerned, and there shall be placed to the credit thereof the following sums, namely:—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6J.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>any fee which may be levied under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6J.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>contributions under section 6-I;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6J.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>any sums received by the Wakf Administration Fund from private sources;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6J.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>any sums alloted by (any Government) or by any local authority to the Wakf Administration Fund.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6K">
          <num>6K.</num>
          <heading>Application of Wakf Administration Fund.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6K.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Wakf Administration Fund of a district shall be under the control and management of the Court and shall be applicable to the payment of charges for and expenses incidental to the registration, superintendence, administration and control of wakfs, the maintenance of the Register of Wakfs, the scrutiny and audit of accounts of wakfs, the institution and defence of suits and proceedings relating to wakfs, and generally carrying into effect the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-VI">
        <num>VI</num>
        <paragraph id="part-VI.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Supervision and Control</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-6L">
          <num>6L.</num>
          <heading>Constitution and appointment of Wakf Committee.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6L.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>There shall be constituted in each district a Wakf Committee to advise and assist the Court in all matters relating to the registration, superintendence, administration and control of wakfs.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6L.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-6L.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Committee shall consist of:—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6L.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the members of the Indian and State Legislatures.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6L.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>two members elected in the prescribed manner by the mutwallis of all wakfs in the district registered under the Act,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6L.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>two members elected in the prescribed manner by the members of each District Local Board in the district professing the Mussalman faith from among their number,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6L.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>one member elected in the prescribed manner by the members professing Mussalman faith of each municipality in the district constituted under the Bombay District Municipal Act, 1991,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6L.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>two members elected in the prescribed manner by the members professing Mussalman faith of each municipality in the district constituted under the City of Bombay Municipal Act, 1888, the City of Karachi Municpal Act, 1933, or the Bombay Municipal Buroughs Act, 1925, and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6L.2.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>such other members not exceeding one-fourth of the total number of the members of the Committee as the State Government may nominate:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that no person who does not ordinarily reside in the district or does not profess the Mussalman faith shall be eligible to be a member of the Committee.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6M">
          <num>6M.</num>
          <heading>Functions of Wakf Committee.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6M.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-6M.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>It shall be competent to the Court to refer at any time to the Wakf Committee or any three or more members thereof, for advice, opinion, enquiry report or recommendation, within such time as the Court may direct, any matter relating to the registration, superintendence, administration, and control of wakfs, and in particular any matter relating to—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6M.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the conduct of a mutwalli or a trustee in the administration of a wakf or his fitness to continue as a mutwalli or a trustee.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6M.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the settlement, cancellation or alteration of a scheme for the administration of a wakf, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6M.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the application of the funds of a wakf or any surplus thereof.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6M.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-6M.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>When the Court has referred any of the matters mentioned in sub-section (1) to a wakf committee or any members thereof for advice, opinion, enquiry report or recommendation, and the committee or the members thereof, as the case may be, have, either unanimously or by a majority, made their recommendation in relation to the matter referred to them, the Court may pass orders as it thinks fit after giving due consideration to such recommendation—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6M.2.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>suspending, removing or dismissing a mutwalli or trustee;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6M.2.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>appointing a new mutwalli or trustee; t</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6M.2.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>settling, cancelling or altering a scheme for the administration of wakf;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6M.2.list1.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>directing the application, investment or deposit of the funds of a wakf for any surplus thereof in a particular manner or to a particular purpose;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6M.2.list1.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>generally for carrying out the purposes of the Act:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that nothing in this section shall be deemed to authorise the Court to pass any order which is inconsistent with the objects and purposes of the wakf:</p>
              <p>Provided further that no order under this section shall be passed to the prejudice of any mutwalli or trustee without giving such mutwalli or trustee an opportunity to be heard.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6M.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-6M.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>For the performance of any of the duties under sub-section (2) the Wakf Committee or any members thereof to whom the Court has referred any matter for advice, opinion, enquiry, report, or recommendation, the committee or such members thereof may by order in writing require—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6M.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the production of any document necessary for the purpose;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6M.3.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the attendance of any person for the purpose of giving evidence or for the production of any document referred to in clause (a).</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6M.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of sub-sections (2) and (3) of section 6C shall, so far as may be, apply to any inquiry under sub-section (1) or (2).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6N">
          <num>6N.</num>
          <heading>Court’s power to authorise members of Wakf Committee to institute suits, etc.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6N.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-6N.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in section 92 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908, it shall be competent to the Court, after such inquiry as it may think fit,</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6N.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to authorise any one or more of the members of a Wakf Committee to institute or defend any suit or preceding for the purposes of the protection or recovery of the property of a wakf or for the application of the property of a wakf to any public, charitable or religious purpose and (b) to allocate from the Wakf Administration Fund such sums as may, in the opinion of the Court, be necessary for the aforesaid purpose.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>-O.  Inspection of wakf property, records and accounts.—</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall be competent to the Court to direct one or more members of the Wakf Committee to undertake the inspection, in the prescribed manner, of the property, records and accounts of any wakf and to report to the Court, within such time as the Court may direct, the result of such inspection.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall be competent to the Court to employ upon such terms and conditions as may be prescribed such persons as may in the opinion of the Court be necessary for carrying out the purposes of this Act and to pay them such remuneration from the Wakf Administration Fund as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6P">
          <num>6P.</num>
          <heading>Court’s power to order special audit.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6P.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>It shall be competent to the Court at any time to order a special audit of the accounts of a wakf by an accountant possessing the prescribed qualifications and to order the cost of such audit to be paid by the mutwalli from the income of property of the wakf or out of the Wakf Administration Fund.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6Q">
          <num>6Q.</num>
          <heading>Publication of lists of wakfs.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6Q.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>There shall be published annually on such date as the State Government may determine in the (Official Gazette) and if the State Government so directs in the principle vernacular of the district in a newspaper circulating therein a list of wakf and a statement of the sums standing to the credit of the Wakf Administration Fund under the signature of the Court and in such form as the State Government may prescribe.</p>
              <p>Vide Bombay Act 18 of 1935, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 23-9-1935) as amended by Bombay Acts 10 of 1944 and 15 of 1945, Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87 (w.e.f. 5-5-1960).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-6Q.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>after section 6Q inserted by Bombay Act 18 of 1935 insert the heading “Part VII”.</p>
              <p>Vide Bombay Act 18 of 1935, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 23-9-1935); Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87 (w.e.f. 1-5-1960).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Mutwalli entitled to pay cost of audit, etc., from wakf funds.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the deed or instrument creating any wakf, every Mutwalli may pay from the income of the wakf property any expenses properly incurred by him for the purpose of enabling him to furnish any particulars, documents or copies under section 3 or section 4 or in respect of the preparation or audit of the annual accounts for the purposes of this Act.</p>
              <p>State Amendment</p>
              <p>Maharashtra: Gujarat.—</p>
              <p>In its application to Bombay area of the State of Maharashtra/Gujarat, in section 7 after the word and figure ‘section 4’, insert the words and figures “section 6A or section 6B or section 6C or section 6E”.</p>
              <p>Vide Bomabay Act 18 of 1935, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 23-9-1935); Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87 (w.e.f. 1-5-1960).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Verification.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every statement of particulars furnished under section 3 or section 4, and every statement of accounts furnished under section 5, shall be written in the language of the Court to which it is furnished, and shall be verified in the manner provided in the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), for the signing and verification of pleadings.</p>
              <p>State Amendments</p>
              <p>Maharashtra: Gujarat.—</p>
              <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>In its application to Bombay area of the State of Maharashra/Gujarat, in section 8,—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list4.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>after the word and figure ‘section 4’ insert the words and figures “or section 6A or secion 6C or section 6E”; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>after the word and figure ‘section 5’ insert the words and figures “or section 6B or section 6C”.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Vide Bombay Act 18 of 1935, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 23-9-1935); Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87 (w.e.f. 1-5-1960).</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list6.Orissa">
                  <num>(Orissa)</num>
                  <p>—In section 8, after the word “written”, insert the words “in Urdu or”.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Vide Bihar and Orissa Act 1 of 1926, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 15-5-1926).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Inspection and copies.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Any person shall, with the permission of the Court and on payment of the prescribed fee, at any time at which the Court is open, be entitled to inspect in the prescribed manner, or to obtain a copy of, any statement of particulars or any document furnished to the Court under section 3 or section 4, or any statement of accounts furnished to it under section 5, or any audit report made on an audit under section 6.</p>
              <p>State Amendment</p>
              <p>Maharashtra: Gujarat.—</p>
              <blockList id="section-9.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>In its application to Bombay area of the State of Maharashtra/Gujarat,—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list4.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>in section 9,—</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list4.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>after the word and figure ‘section 4’, insert the words and figures “or section 6A or section 6C or section 6E”;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>after the word and figure ‘section 5’, insert the words and figures “or section 6B or section 6C”;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list4.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>after the word and figure ‘section 6’, insert the words and figures “or section 6H or section 6P or any entry in the Register of Wakfs or any statement, notice, intimation, report, accounts or any document filed under this Act”.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-9.paragraph-0.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Vide Bombay Act 18 of 1935, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 23-9-1935); Act 11 of 1960 sec. 87 (w.e.f. 1-5-1960).</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list6.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>after section 9, insert the following section,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>namely:—</p>
              <p>“9A. Provisions of Code of Civil Procedure to apply.—</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-9.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Provisions of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908, relating to—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-9.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the proof of facts by affidavits;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the enforcing of the attendance of any person and his examination on oath;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the enforcing of the profuction of documents; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the issuing of commissions.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>shall apply to all proceedings held by the Court under this Act and provisions relating to the service of summons shall apply to the service of notices thereunder.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of the said Code relating to the execution of decrees shall, so far as they are applicable, apply to the execution of orders passed by the Court under this Act.</p>
              <blockList id="section-9.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Vide Bombay Act 18 of 1935, sec. 10 (w.e.f. 23-9-1935); Act 11 of 1960 sec. 87 (w.e.f. 1-5-1960).</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-9.2.list2.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>after section 9A inserted by Bombay Act 18 of 1935, insert the heading “Part III”.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Vide Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87 (w.e.f. 1-5-1960).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Penalties.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Any person who is required by or under section 3 or section 4 to furnish a statement of particulars or any document relating to a wakf, or who is required by section 5 to furnish a statement of accounts, shall, if he, without reasonable cause the burden of proving which shall be upon him fails to furnish such statement or document, as the case may be, in due time, or furnishes a statement which he knows or has reason to believe to be false, misleading or untrue in any material particular, or, in the case of a statement of accounts furnishes a statement which has not been audited in the manner required by section 6, be punishable with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, or, in the case of a second or subsequent offence, with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees.</p>
              <p>State Amendment</p>
              <p>Maharashtra: Gujarat.—</p>
              <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>In its application to Bombay area of the State of Maharashtra/Gujarat,—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list4.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>in section 10,—</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list4.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>after the word and figure ‘section 4’, insert the words and figures “or section 6A or section 6C or section 6E”;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>after the word and figure ‘section 5’, insert the words and figures “or section 6B or section 6C”;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list4.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>after the word ‘accounts’ where it occurs for the the first time insert, the words, figure and letter “or who is required by section 6H to keep regular accounts”;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list4.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>after the word “document” where it occurs for the second time, insert the words “or to keep regular accounts”;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list4.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>after the word ‘statement’ where it occurs for the fourth time, insert the words “or keeps accounts”.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Vide Bombay Act 18 of 1935, sec. 12 (w.e.f. 23-9-1935); Act 11 of 1960 sec. 87 (w.e.f. 1-5-1960).</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list6.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>after section 10, insert the following sections, namely:—</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>“10A. Penalty for non-compliance with any other order.—</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>if any person fails to comply with any order passed by the Court or by the Wakf Committee or any member thereof under or in pursuance of the provisions of this Act, such person shall, if such failure to comply is not punishable under any of the sections of this Act, be, on conviction, punishable with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A Criminal Court may, in passing an order of conviction, for an offence under sub-section (1), specify the period within which the person convicted shall comply with the provisions of this Act which may be found to have been contravened by him, and may also prescribe a daily fine not exceeding Rs. 50 for every day for the period during which the default continues after the expiry of the period so specified:</p>
              <p>Provided that, if the person failing to comply with any direction issued by such Court satisfies such Court that there is good reason for his failure to do so and applies for an extension of the period specified under this section, such Court may, if it thinks fit, extend the period and may remit the whole or any part of the fine paid or due.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10B">
          <num>10B.</num>
          <heading>Cognizance of offences.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-10B.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No prosecution under this Act shall be instituted except by or with the previous sanction of the Court given in the prescribed manner.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10B.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No Criminal Court inferior to that of a Presidency Magistrate or of a Magistrate of the First Class shall try an offence under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10C">
          <num>10C.</num>
          <heading>Prosecution of, and suits against, persons acting in good faith.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10C.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No suit or prosecution or other proceeding shall be instituted against any person for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10D">
          <num>10D.</num>
          <heading>Recovery of sums due under this Act.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10D.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>All sums due under this Act shall be recoverable as arrears of land revenue.”</p>
              <p>Vide Bombay Act 18 of 1935, sec. 13 (w.e.f. 23-9-1935); Act 11 of 1960 sec. 87 (w.e.f. 1-5-1960).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, after previous publication, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry into effect the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-11.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the additional particulars to be furnished by mutwallis under clause (g) of sub-section (1) of section 3;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the fees to be charged upon applications made to a Court under sub-section (1) of section 4;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the form in which the statement of accounts referred to in section 5 shall be furnished, and the particulars which shall be contained therein;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the powers which may be exercised by auditors for the purposes of any audit referred to in section 6, and the particulars to be contained in the reports of such auditors;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the fees respectively chargeable on account of the allowing of inspections and of the supply of copies under section 9;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the safe custody of statements, audit reports and copies of deeds or instruments furnished to Courts under this Act; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>any other matter which is to be or may be prescribed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made by the State Government under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before the State Legislature.</p>
              <p>State Amendment</p>
              <p>Maharashtra: Gujarat.—</p>
              <p>In section 11,—</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-11.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>in sub-section (2),—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>in clause (a), after the word and figure “section 3”, insert the words and figures “or under section 6A or section 6C”;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>for clause (b), substitute the following clause, namely:—</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>“(b)</p>
              <blockList id="section-11.1.list4">
                <listIntroduction>the manner in which notice to be published under section 4 and the fees to be charged upon application made to the Court under sub-section (1) of section 4 or under section 6A or section 6B or section 6C;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.1.list4.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>in clause (c), after the word and figure “section 5”, insert the words and figures “or section 6B or section 6C”;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.1.list4.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>in clause (d), after the word and figure “section 6”, insert the words and figures “or section 6H or section 6P”;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.1.list4.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>in clause (e), after the brackets and letter “(e)”, insert the words “the manner of inspection and”;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.1.list4.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>after clause (f), insert the following clauses, namely:—</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>“(f1)</p>
              <blockList id="section-11.1.list7">
                <listIntroduction>the manner in which subject to the provisions of section 9A an inquiry shall be held by the Court and the Wakf Committee under section 6C or 6M and the manner in which the parties shall be represented in such inquiry and the costs of such inquiry shall be borne;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.1.list7.f2">
                  <num>(f2)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which the Register of Wakfs shall be prepared and maintained under section 6D;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.1.list7.f3">
                  <num>(f3)</num>
                  <p>the form in which a change in any of the particulars recorded in the Register of Wakfs shall be reported and the amount of fee to accompany such report and the manner in which the inquiry shall be held and the entries in the Register of Wakfs shall be amended under section 6E;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.1.list7.f4">
                  <num>(f4)</num>
                  <p>the form in which the accounts shall be prepared, kept and furnished, the particulars to be entered therein, and the manner in which, and interval at which such accounts shall be audited under section 6H;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.1.list7.f5">
                  <num>(f5)</num>
                  <p>the amount of contribution, and the date on which and the manner in which it shall be paid and exemptions granted under section 6-I;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.1.list7.f6">
                  <num>(f6)</num>
                  <p>the appointment and remuneration of auditors appointed under the Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.1.list7.f7">
                  <num>(f7)</num>
                  <p>the management, custody, investment and disbursement of the Wakf Administration Fund;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.1.list7.f8">
                  <num>(f8)</num>
                  <p>the purpose for which a Wakf Administration Fund shall be applied under section 6K;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.1.list7.f9">
                  <num>(f9)</num>
                  <p>the number of members who shall constitute a Wakf Committee, the period of office of a Wakf Committee and the manner in which such committee shall hold its meetings and the procedure to be followed at their meetings;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.1.list7.f10">
                  <num>(f10)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which the inspection of the property, records and accounts of a wakf shall be carried out, the sum which shall be paid in respect of the costs of the members of the Wakf Committee undertaking such insepction, the terms and conditions on which persons shall be employed and the remuneration which shall be paid to such persons, under secion 6-O;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.1.list7.f11">
                  <num>(f11)</num>
                  <p>the qualifications of an accountant appointed under section 6P;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.1.list7.f12">
                  <num>(f12)</num>
                  <p>the form in which a list of Wakfs shall be published under section 6Q.”</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>after sub-section (2), insert the following sub-section, namely:—</p>
              <p>“(3) Rules made under this section shall be laid before each of the Chambers of the State Legislature at the session thereof next following and shall be liable to be modified or rescinded by a resolution in which both the Chambers concur and such rule shall after notification in the Official Gazette be deemed to have been modified or rescinded accordingly:</p>
              <p>Provided that when in the option of the State Government such modification or rescission is likely to defeat or frustrate any of the purposes of this Act, the State Government may by notification, in the Official Gazette, declare that the modification or rescission shall have no effect and thereupon the rules shall remain in force as if they had not been modified or rescinded.”</p>
              <p>Vide Bombay Act 18 of 1935, sec. 14 (w.e.f. 23-9-1935); Act 11 of 1960 sec. 87 (w.e.f. 1-5-1960).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Saving.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Nothing in this Act shall—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>affect any other enactment for the time being in force in the territories to which this Act applies providing for the control or supervision of religious or charitable endowments; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>apply in the case of any wakf the property of which—</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>is being administered by the Treasurer of Charitable Endowments, the Administrator General, or the Official Trustee; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>is being administered either by a receiver appointed by any Court of competent jurisdiction, or under a scheme for the administration of the wakf which has been settled or approved by any Court of competent jurisdiction or by any other authority acting under the provisions of any enactment.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Exemption.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official</p>
              <p>Gazette, exempt from the operation of this Act or of any specified provision thereof any wakf or wakfs created or administered for the benefit of any specified section of the Mussalman community.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
