<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-raj/act/1961/40/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-raj/act/1961/40"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Rajasthan Sagri System Abolition Act, 1961"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-raj/act/1961/40/eng@2017-04-06/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-raj/act/1961/40/eng@2017-04-06"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-04-06" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-raj/act/1961/40/eng@2017-04-06/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-raj/act/1961/40/eng@2017-04-06"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-04-06" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Rajasthan Sagri System Abolition Act, 1961</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[Act No. 40 of 1961]</p>
      </longTitle>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[21st November, 1961]</docDate>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>An Act to provide for the abolition, of the Sagri system in the State pf Rajasthan.</p>
      <p>Be it enacted by the Rajasthan State Legislature in the Twelfth Year of the Republic of India as follows:--</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Rajasthan Sagri System Abolition Act, 1961.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Rajasthan.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force at once.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Sagri system defined</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Sagri system consists in the advance of a loan by one person (hereinafter called the creditor) to another person (hereinafter called the debtor), whether evidenced by a writing or otherwise on any one or more of the following terms, namely:--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>that the principal amount of such loan, whether with or without interest accrued due thereon at the stipulated rate, shall be treated as repaid in full by the debtor rendering, to or for the benefit of the creditor or to or for the benefit of any person named in this behalf by the creditor, labour or personal service by himself or by any member or members of his family or by his hired servant or labourer or by any of his relations for a specific period of time either without wages or on payment of merely nominal wages;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>that, upon the expiration of such period, the security, if any, furnished for the repayment of the said loan shall automatically stead discharged;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>that only the interest on such loan shall be treated as paid up by such labour or service and the principal amount of the loan shall be repaid in addition before such security is discharged;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>that the wages for such labour or service, whether substantial or nominal, shall not be actually paid to the person rendering the same but shall be credited to the debtor in his loan account, appropriating the same towards interest till then due on the loan and the surplus towards the principal amount of the loan.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Sagri system, as defined above, includes any other like system of advance of loans prevailing in any part of the State, by whatsoever name it may, locally be called, of which the rendering of labour or personal service is an ingredient.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Sagri system abolished</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>On and from the date of the commencement of this Act,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the Sagri system shall stand abolished,, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>no creditor shall advance a loan to his debtor on the Sagri system.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If on or after the said date any loan is advanced on the Sagri system, it shall not be recoverable by suit or other proceeding in any court and the debtor shall not be bound or compelled to under the labour or personal service stipulated for.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Penalties</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Whoever---</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>advances a loan on the, Sagri system on or after the date of commencement of this Act, or.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>compels his debtor to render labour or persona service in fulfillment of the terms on which a loan was advanced to him, shall, on conviction before a Magistrate of the first class-, be punishable, for every such advance or compulsion, with imprisonment of either description for a term which may extend to one year or with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees or with both.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Presumption as to Sagri character of loan</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In relation to every transaction made after the date of the commencement of this Act whereby a creditor advances a loan to a debtor and also engages him or any member or member of his family or his hired servant or labourer or his relations to render any labour or personal service to or for the benefit of himself (the creditor) or any person named by him in this behalf, it shall be presumed that the loan, was advanced on the Sagri system unless it is satisfactorily proved that such engagement on labour or personal service was altogether independent of the advance of the loan.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Provision for Sagri system loans remaining partly or wholly un-repaid at commencement of Act</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any loan advanced on the Sagri system before the commencement of this Act shall not have been repaid in whole or in part at such commencement, the provisions of the Rajasthan Relief of Agricultural Indebtedness Act, 1957 (Rajasthan Act 28 of 1957) shall apply to the recovery of such whole or part as if the debtor were an agriculturist within the meaning of that Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in that Act--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any suit or other proceeding pending before a court at the commencement of this Act for the recovery of, the whole or a part of any loan advanced before such commencement on the Sagri system shall forthwith be transferred by such court to the Debt Relief Court having jurisdiction, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any creditor claiming recovery of the whole or a part of such loan may, within six months from the date of the commencement of this Act, present to the Debt Relief Court having jurisdiction an application in this behalf, as nearly as may be, in the manner laid down in section 6 of that Act and thereupon such court shall proceed as if it were an application from an agriculturist debtor in accordance with the provisions contained in sections 6 to 11 of that Act in so far as they may be made applicable:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that, in acting under section 10 of that Act, Debt Relief Court shall also take into consideration the labour or personal service rendered as aforesaid and determine the money value thereof at the rate of wages which the court considers to be reasonable and in consonance with the rate of wages current for like labour or service at the time when it was rendered.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No loan advanced on the Sagri system before the commencement of this Act nor any part thereof shall after such commencement be recoverable from the debtor otherwise than as provided in sub-section (2).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>All such loans, as are referred to in sub-section (3), shall be deemed to have been wiped off and repaid in full--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.4.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>if no such suit or other proceeding for the recovery thereof as is referred to in clause (a) of sub-section (2) shall have been pending at the commencement of this Act, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.4.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>if no such proceeding as is referred to in clause (b) of sub-section (2) shall have been initiated by the creditor within the time specified in that clause.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the removal of doubt it is hereby declared that, as from the date of the commencement of this Act, no labour or personal service shall be rendered by any debtor or shall be taken or enforced by any creditor, after such date, in relation to any loan advanced on the Sagri system before such date.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Savings</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of this Act shall be in addition to and not in derogation of any law providing for the regulation and control of transactions of money lending for the time being in force in the whole or any part of the State.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
