<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-bih/act/2002/18/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-bih/act/2002/18"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Bihar Protection Of Interest Of Depositors (In Financial Establishments) Act, 2002"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-bih/act/2002/18/eng@2017-01-21/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-bih/act/2002/18/eng@2017-01-21"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-bih/act/2002/18/eng@2017-01-21/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-bih/act/2002/18/eng@2017-01-21"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Bihar Protection Of Interest Of Depositors (In Financial Establishments) Act, 2002</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[Act No. 18 of 2002]</p>
        <p>An Act to protect the interest of Depositors of the Financial Establishments and matters relating thereto.</p>
        <p>Be it enacted by the Legislature of the State of Bihar in the Fifty Third Year of the Republic of India as follows namely</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and Commencement.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Bihar Protection of Interests of Depositors (in Financial Establishments) Act. 2002.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall extend to whole of the State of Bihar</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force at once.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act unless the context otherwise requires:</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"Competent Authority" means any officer notified by the State Government or the Collector of the district or any officer, not below the rank of Additional Collector or equivalent in the district;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"Designated Court" means the Designated Court Constituted under section 7;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>"deposit" includes and shall be deeMed always to have included any receipt of money or acceptance of any valuable commodity by any Financial Establishment to be returned after a specified period or otherwise, either in cash or in kind or in the form of specified service with or without any benefit in the form of interest, bonus, profit or in any other form, but does not include —</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>amount raised by way of share capital or by way of debenture, bond or any other instrument covered under the guidelines given, and regulations made, by the "SEBI", established under the Securities and Exchange Board of India Act, 1992 (15 of 1992);</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>amount contributed as capital by partners of a firm;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>amounts received from a scheduled bank or a co-operative bank or any other banking company as defined in clause (c) of section 5 of the Banking Regulation Act, 1949: (10 of 1949);</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>Any amount received from —</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the Industrial Development Bank of India</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>a State Financial Corporation,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any financial institution specified in or under section 6A of the industrial Development Bank of India Act. 1964:</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>amount received in the ordinary course of business by way of —</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>security deposit</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>dealership deposit</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>earnest money</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>advance against order for goods or services;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d.list1.vi">
                    <num>(vi)</num>
                    <p>any amount received fro m an individual or a firm or an association of individuals nor being a body corporate, registered under any enactment relating to money lending which is for time being in force in the State; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d.list1.vii">
                    <num>(vii)</num>
                    <p>any amount received by way of subscriptions in respect of Chit.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Explanation — I-</p>
            <p>"Chit" has the meaning as assigned to it in clause (b) of section 2 of the Chit Funds Act. 1982:</p>
            <p>Explanation — II-</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6">
              <listIntroduction>Any credit given by a seller to a buyer on the sale of any property (whether moveable or immovable) shall not be deemed to be deposit for the purpose of this clause.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>"Financial Establishment" means any person including association of persons in whatever form it operates, a firm or a company accepting deposit under any scheme or arrangement or in any other manner but does not include a corporation or a co-operative society owned or controlled by any State Government or the Central Government or a banking company as defined under clause (c) of section 5 of the Banking Regulation Act, 1949.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Explanation–</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list9">
              <listIntroduction>It shall also include deposit taking business in disguised form like the business of real-estate, plantation, tours and travels, cattle rearing, hotels, resorts , amusement parks, supply of any valuable goods or service or gift thereof etc.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list9.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>"Government" means the Government of Bihar</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list9.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>"prescribed" means prescribed under the Rules.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2A">
        <num>2A.</num>
        <heading>Mandatory Intimation, Power to call for information and punishment for non compliance.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2A.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any Financial Establishment intending to establish an office and operate in the State of Bihar or any part thereof shall furnish information in writing to the Competent Authority about the details of its activities, areas of operation and/or business, supported by all necessary papers. This information shall also include its registration by the Registrar of Companies of the State Concerned as also about the registration and the license obtained from the Reserve Bank of India, Securities and Exchange Board of India or any other regulatory authority for the purpose aforesaid with details of its office structure and specific location/address-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2A.1.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>Provided that the Financial Establishment operating before the commencement of this Act shall furnish the requisite information to the Collector of the district/Competent Authority within 30 days of the commencement of this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Competent Authority shall have the power to call for or require any information about the Financial Establishment or its office bearers including the promoter, director, partner or manager or members of such Financial Establishment or direct any office or authority of the Government or a local authority or any other person, to furnish such information as may be required, and such Financial Establishment or its office bearer or promoter, director, partner or manager or members of such Financial Establishment or officer or authority of the Government or local authority or any other person, shall forth with furnish such information to the Competent Authority.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Failure to furnish the requisite information to the Competent Authority as under sub-section (1) of section 2A or furnishing wrong or misleading statement, or refuse to produce or to permit inspection of records/documents etc, as required under section 3A, the Collector of the District under whose local jurisdiction the Financial Establishment conducting its business operation, if satisfied, may after giving reasonable opportunity to the Financial Establishment in accordance with law, impose a fine of up to Rs. 100000/- (Rupee one Lakh) for every such default.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Fraudulent default by Financial Establishment.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any Financial Establishment, having fraudulently or dishonestly, defaults in repayment of any deposit on maturity along with any benefit in the form of interest, bonus or profit, or in any other form as promised or fraudulently or dishonestly fails to render service as assured against the deposit, the Financial Establishment and every person including the promoter, partner. director. manager or any other person or any employee responsible for the management of or conducting the business or affairs of such Financial Establishment shall, on convention, be punished with imprisonment for term up to ten years and with fine up to one lakh of rupees or where such default relates to a quantifiable sum of money twice amount of such sum, whichever is more:</p>
            <p>Provided that in absence of special and adequate reasons to be recorded in the judgment of the Court, the imprisonment shall not be for less than three years and the fine shall not be less than fifty thousand rupees.</p>
            <p>Explanation — I-</p>
            <p>For the purpose of this section, a Financial Establishment, which commits default in repayment of any deposit with such benefits in the term of interest, bonus, profit or in any other term as promised or falls to render any specified service agreed against the deposit with an intention of causing wrongful gain to one person on wrongful loss to another person or commits such defaults due to its inability arising out of impracticable of commercially not viable promises made while accepting such deposit or arising out of deployment of money or assets acquired out of the deposits in such a manner as it involves inherent risk in recovering the same when needed, shall be deemed to have committed a default or failed to render the specific service, fraudulently.</p>
            <p>Explanation — II-</p>
            <p>When a question arises whether any Financial Establishment has committed fraudulent default within the meaning of this section, the Court shall presume that such Financial Establishment has committed the default fraudulently.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No police official below the rank of Deputy Superintendent of police or equivalent, having jurisdiction, shall investigate an offence under this Act-</p>
            <p>Provided that if a police officer not below the rank of an Inspector of police is authorized by the State Government in this behalf by general or special order, he may also investigate any such offence without the order of Metropolitan Magistrate or a Magistrate of the first class, as the case may be, or make arrest thereof without warrant.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3A">
        <num>3A.</num>
        <heading>Power to enter premises and inspect certain documents.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Competent Authority or any other authority not below the rank of the Sub divisional - Officer under him, for the furtherance of the purposes of this Act may enter and inspect any premises, where any register, book, record, paper, application, information in electronic storage and retrieval device or medium, instrument or proceedings are kept and to inspect them and to take such notes and extracts as it may deem necessary.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every person having in his custody or maintaining such register, book, record, paper, application, instrument or proceedings shall at all reasonable times produce or permit the Competent Authority or any other authority authorized by the Competent Authority to inspect them to take notes and extracts as it may deem necessary and if necessary seize and impound them :</p>
            <p>Provided that no residential accommodation (not being a place of business cum residence) shall be so entered into and searched except on the authority of a search warrant issued by a Magistrate having jurisdiction over the area, and all searches under this section shall, so far as may be, be made in accordance with the provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3B">
        <num>3B.</num>
        <heading>Search, Seizure and confiscation of property and its management.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3B.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3B.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>where the Competent Authority, upon information and after such enquiry as he thinks fit and necessary, has reason to believe that any financial establishment or the promoter, partner, director, manager, member, employee or any other person responsible for the management of, or for conducting the business or affairs of such financial establishment—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3B.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>has committed any act which constitutes an offence under sub-section (1) of section 3; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3B.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>is in possession of any material of crime involved in an offence under sub¬section (1) of section-3; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3B.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>is in possession of any records relating to an office under sub-section (1) of section-3; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3B.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <blockList id="section-3B.1.list1.d.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>is in possession of any property relating to an office under sub- section (1) of section 3; such Competent Authority may, subject to the rules made in this behalf, authorize any officers---</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-3B.1.list1.d.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>to enter, with such assistance as may be required, and search any building, place, vessel, vehicle or aircraft where he has reason to suspect that such records or proceeds of crime are kept;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3B.1.list1.d.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>to break /open the lock of any door, box, locker, safe, almirah etc;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3B.1.list1.d.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>where such officer has reason to believe that any property found in such search is likely to be concealed, transferred or dealt with any manner which will result in disposal of such property, he may make order for seizure of such record or property;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3B.1.list1.d.list0.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>to place marks of identification on such records or make or cause to be made extracts or copies there from;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3B.1.list1.d.list0.v">
                    <num>(v)</num>
                    <p>to prepare a statement or an inventory of such records or property;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3B.1.list1.d.list0.vi">
                    <num>(vi)</num>
                    <p>to examine on oath any person who is found to be in possession or control of any record or property, in respect of all or any of the matters relevant for the purpose of any investigation under the Act.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3B.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where it is not practicable to seize such record or property of any financial establishment or the promoter, partner, director, manager, member, employee or any other person responsible for the management of, or for conducting the business or affairs of such financial establishment, the officer authorized under sub-section (1), shall report the same to the Competent Authority who may, in such manner as may be prescribed, make an order to freeze/attach such property whereupon the property shall not be transferred or otherwise dealt with, except with the prior permission of the officer making such order, and a copy of the order shall be served on the person concerned.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3B.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the Competent Authority has made an order under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2), it shall, within thirty days from the date of the publication of an order under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2), as the case may be, make an application supported by an affidavit stating the grounds on which such Competent Authority has issued the said order under that sub-section, to the Designated Court and the Designated Court shall, after giving an opportunity of being heard to the person concerned, make an order of confiscating such seized or freezed property of the financial establishment or the property of every person including the promoter, partner, director, manager, member, employee or any other person responsible for the management of, or for conducting the business or affairs of such financial establishment in the same manner as mentioned in section 4.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3B.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an order of confiscation of seized or freezed property of the financial establishment or the property of every person including the promoter, partner, director, manager, member, employee or any other person responsible for the management of, or for conducting the business or affairs of such financial establishment has been made under sub-section (3), all right and title in such property shall vest to the Competent Authority free from all encumbrances.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3B.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Competent Authority may, in writing, appoint as many officers as it thinks fit, to perform the functions as an Administrator.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3B.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Administrator appointed under sub -section (5), shall receive and manage the property in such manner, and subject to such conditions, as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3B.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Administrator shall, in such manner as may be prescribed, take such measures to dispose of the property which is vested in the Competent Authority appointed by the State Government, to protect the interest of the depositors."</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Attachment of properties on default of return of deposits.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding any thing contained in any other law for the time being in force.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>where upon complaints received from the depositors or otherwise the Government is satisfied that any Financial Establishment has failed:</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to return the deposit after maturity on demand by the depositor; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to pay interest or other assured benefits; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to provide the service promised against such deposit: or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>where the Government has reason to believe that any Financial Establishment is acting in a manner detrimental to the interest of the depositors with an intention to defraud them and if the Government is satisfied that such Financial Establishment is not likely to return the deposits or make payment of interest or other benefits assured or to provide the services against the deposit is received. the Government may, in order to protect the interest of the depositors of such Financial Establishments, after recording reasons, in writing, issue an order b) publishing it in the Official Gazette. attaching the money or other property believed to have been acquired by such Financial Establishment either it its own name or in the name any other person</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>from out of the deposits collected by the Financial Establishment, or if it transpired that such money or other property is not available for attachment or not sufficient for repayment of the deposits, such other property of the said Financial Establishment or the promoter, director, partner or manager or member of the said Financial Establishment as the Government may deem fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On the publication of the order under sub-section (i) all the properties and assets of the Financial Establishment and the persons mentioned therein shall forthwith vest in the Competent Authority appointed by the Government. pending further order from the Designated Court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Save and otherwise specially provided in any other law the attachment shall be made in the manner provided for attachment of property in execution of a decree under order 21 Rules 43, 43A, 46, 47, 49, 50, 51 and 54 of the Code of Civil Procedure.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Appointment, Duties and Power of Competent Authority.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Competent Authority shall exercise control over the money and the properties attached, by the Government order under section 4 of a Financial Establishment.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Competent Authority shall take such necessary actions as are necessary or expedient for taking physical possession of all the moneys and assets of the concerned financial establishment expeditiously and the Competent Authority shall have all the power which are necessary for the aforesaid purpose.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Competent Authority shall apply within thirty days from the date of the publication of the said Order, to the Designated Court, supported by one or more affidavits stating the grounds on which the Government has issued the said order under section 4 and the amount of money or other property believed to have been acquired out of the deposits and the details, if any, of persons in whose name such property is believed to have been invested or acquired or any other property attached under section 4, for such further orders as found necessary.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Competent Authority may also make an application to any Designated Court or any other judicial forum/ authority constituted or entrusted with the powers under any other State Government Law for adjudicating any issue or subject matter pertaining to any money or property of a Financial Establishment under similar enactment in respect of money and property belonging to Financial Establishment or person notified under this Act situated within the territorial jurisdiction of that authority for appropriate orders to give effect to be provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.5.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Without prejudice to the generality of the powers vested under sub-section (i) the Competent Authority shall be entitled to;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.5.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>require assistance of any police authority or any other authority or person and on such requisition it shall be the duty of the police authority or such other authority or person to extend necessary assistance;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.5.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>open bank accounts in any scheduled commercial bank and credit all moneys realised and operate the bank accounts while dealing with the money received in his capacity as Competent Authority;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.5.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>require any person believed to be in possession or control over any money or assets of the financial establishment, to furnish necessary information, to hand over possession of such assets to the Competent Authority and such person shall comply with the requisition without any loss of time;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.5.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>appoint legal practitioner or Chartered Accountant or any other person whose services are necessary for taking possession of assets and realisation of the assets of the financial establishment:</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.5.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>sell, receive, transfer, endorse, negotiate or otherwise deal with any marketable security or negotiable instrument belonging to or in the control of the financial establishment and give proper discharge for the same:</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.5.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>sell, transfer or otherwise realize any movable or immovable property belonging to or in the control of the financial establishment either by public auction or with the private arrangements;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.5.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>make payment as per the orders passed by the Designated Court from out of the bank accounts, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.5.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>do all and every acts and deeds which would be necessary for the speedy realisation of the assets of the financial establishment</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that the sales and transfers of movable properties should not be done before the Designated Court has passed made the order of attachment issued by the Government absolute or has issued a revised attachment order under Section-S.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Competent Authority shall make applications from time to time to the Designated Court seeking permission to make payments to the depositors from out of the money realised. While making such applications, the Competent Authority shall assess the liability to the depositors and the other liabilities and in case the money realized or realizable is not sufficient to meet the entire liability, make a submission to the Designated Court seeking permission for making part payment to the depositors and to other creditors and disburse the money as per the order of the Designated Court.</p>
            <p>Explanation-</p>
            <p>For the purpose of this section. the expression "financial establishment" includes the directors, promoters, managers or member of said establishment or any other person whose property or assets have been attached urder section 3</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Assessment of assets and deposit liabilities.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Competent Authority shall assess to deposit liabilities and the assets of the financial establishment and submit the statement thereof to the Designated Court, within 30 days of the order under section 4(1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Competent Authority, thereafter, shall issue notice either individually or by means of effective media publication, inviting the claims by secured creditors, if any. and also the depositors of the financial establishment to submit their claims with proper proof to establish the same.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every notice under sub section (2) sent to or deemed to have been sent to claimants shall state that if the statement or claim is not sent to the Competent Authority before the expiry of the period of one month from the date of notice the claims shall not be treated as claim entitled to be paid under the provision of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every notice sent to a secured creditor shall require him to value the security before the expiry of the period of one month from the date of the notice and such</p>
            <p>notice shall also state that if the statement of the claim together with the valuation of the security is not sent to the Competent Authority, the Competent Authority himself shall value the security and his valuation shall be binding on such secured creditors.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the claimant fails to comply with the notice as per the sub section (4), such security shall be valued by the Competent Authority in his best judgment.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Designated Court.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of this Act, the Government may, with the concurrence of the Chief Justice of the Patna High, Court, by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute one or more Designated Courts in the cadre of Subordinate Judge including Assistant sessions Judge for such area or areas or for such case or class or group of cases, as maybe specified in the notification.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No court, including the court constituted under the Presidency Towns Insolvency Act, 1909 and the Provincial Insolvency Act. 1920, other than the Designated Court, shall have jurisdiction in respect of any matter to which the provisions of this Act are invoked.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any pending case in any other court to which the provisions of this Act apply shall, on the date of publication of this Act, stand transferred to the Designated Court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Powers of Designated Court regarding attachment.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon receipt of an application under section 5, the Designated Court shall issue to the Financial Establishment or to any other person whose property is attached and vested in the Competent Authority by the Government under section 4, a notice accompanied by copy of the application arid of affidavits and the evidence, if any recorded, calling upon the said Establishment and the said person to show cause on a date to be specified in the notice, why the order of attachment should not be made absolute.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Designated Court shall also issue such notice to all other persons represented to it as having or being likely to claim any Interest or title in the property of the Financial Establishment of the person to whom the notice is issued under sub-section (i), calling upon all such persons to appear on the same date as that specified in the notice and make objection if they so desire to the attachment of the property or any portion thereof, on the ground that they have interest in such property of portion thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person claiming an interest in the property attached or any portion thereof may, notwithstanding that no notice has been served upon him under this section, make an objection as aforesaid to the Designated Court at any time before an order is passed under sub-section(4) or sub-section (6).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Designated Court shall, if no cause is shown and no objection is received under sub-section (3). forthwith pass an order making the order of attachment absolute, and issue any direction as may be necessary for realisation of the assets attached and for the equitable distribution among the depositors of the money realized from out of the property attached.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If cause is shown or any objection is made as aforesaid. the Designated Court shall proceed to investigate the, same and in so doing, as regards the examination of the parties and in all other respect, the Designated Court shall, subject to the provisions of this Act, follow the summary procedure as contemplated under order 37 of the Civil Procedure Code, 1908 and exercise all the powers of a court in hearing a suit under the said Code and any person making on objection shall be required to adduce evidence to show that at the date of the attachment he had some interest in the property attached.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>After investigation under sub-section (5). the Designated Court shall pass an order either making the order of attachment passed under sub-section (1) of section 4 absolute or varying it by releasing a portion of the property from attachment or cancelling the order of attachment:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Designated Court shall not release from attachment any interest, which it is satisfied that the Financial Establishment or the person referred to in</p>
            <p>sub-section (1) has in the property, unless it is also satisfied that there will remain under attachment an amount or property of value not less than the value that is required for repayment of the deposits of the Financial Establishment.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an application is made by any person duly authorised or constituted or specified by any other State Government under similar enactment empowering him to exercise control over any money or the property attached by that Government, the Designated Court shall exercise all its powers as if application is made under this Act and pass appropriate orders or directions on such application.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Powers of the Designated Court regarding realisation or assets and payment to depositors.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Designated Court shall have all the powers for giving effect to the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Without prejudice to the generality of sub section (1). the Designated Court may-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>give any direction to the Competent Authority as it deems fit, for effective implementation of the provisions of this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>approve the statement of dues of the financial establishment due from various debtors, assessment of the value of the assets of the financial establishment, finalise the list of the depositors and their respective dues.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>direct the Competent Authority to take possession of any assets belonging to or in the control of the financial establishment and sell, transfer or realise the attached assets either public auction or by private sale as he deems fit depending upon the nature of assets and credit the sale proceeds' thereof to the bank accounts;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>approve the necessary expenditure to be incurred by the Competent Authority for taking possession and realisation of the assets of financial establishment;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>order for payment to the depositors by the Competent Authority or order for proportionate payment to the depositors in the event of the money so realised is not sufficient to meet the entire deposit liability; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>pass any order which the Designated Court deems</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>fit for realisation of the assets of the company and repayment to the depositors of the financial establishment or on any matter or issue incidental thereof.</p>
            <p>Explanation-</p>
            <p>For the purpose of this section, the expression "financial-establishment" includes the directors, promoters, managers or member of said establishment or any other person whose property or assets have been attached urder section 3.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Attachment of property of malafide transferees.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the assets available for attachment of a Financial Establishment-or other person referred to in section 4 are found to be less than the amount or value which such Financial Establishment Is required to re-pay to the depositor and where the Designated Court is satisfied by affidavit or otherwise, that there is reasonable cause for believing that the said Financial Establishment has transferred (whether after the commencement of this Act or not) any of the property otherwise than in good faith and for adequate consideration the Designated Court may by notice require any transferee of such property (whether or not he received the property directly from the said Financial Establishment) to appear on a date to be specified in the notice and show cause why so much of the transferee's property as is equivalent to the proper value of the property transferred should not be attached.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the said transferee does not appear and show cause on the specified date. or where after investigation in the manner provided in sub-section (5) of section 7, the Designated Court is satisfied that the transfer of the property to the said transferee was not in good faith and for adequate consideration. the Designated Court shall order the attachment of so much of the said transferee's property as is in the opinion of the Designated Court equivalent to the proper value of the property transferred.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Security in lieu of attachment.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any Financial Establishment or person whcse property has been or is proposed to be attached under this Act may, at any time, apply to the Designated Court for permission to give security in lieu of such attachment and where the security offered and given is, in the opinion of the Designated Court, satisfactory and sufficient, it may cancel the order of attachment or, as the case may be, refrain from passing an order of attachment.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Administration of property attached.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-12.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Designated Court may, on the application of any person interested in any property attached and vested in the Competent Authority, give an opportunity to the person concerned of being heard and make such order as the Designated Court considers just and reasonable for--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>Providing from such of the property attached and vested in the Competent Authority as the applicant claims an interest in, such as may be reasonably necessary for the maintenance of the applicant and of his family, and for the expenses connected with the defence of the applicant where criminal proceedings have been instituted against him in the Designated Court under section 3: and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>Safeguarding so far as may be practicable the interests of any business affected by the attachment, and in particular, the interests of any partners in such business.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Appeal.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An appeal shall lie against the final order passed by the Designated Court in connection with and relation to the attachment before the High Court of the area concerned within 60 days from the date of the final order</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person convicted on a trial held by the Designated Court may appeal to the High Court of the area concerned.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Special Public Prosecutor and Special Government Pleaders.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by order appoint one or more Advocates of not having less than 7 years practice as Special Public Prosecutor/Special Government Pleader in consultation with the District and Sessions Judge of the concerned District for the purpose of conduction the cases in the Designated Court.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Procedure and powers of designated Court regarding offences.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Designated Court may, on perusal of the police report of the facts constituting an offence under this Act 01 upon a complaint made by an officer authorized in this behalf by the State Government, take cognizance of the offence without the accused being committed to it for trial.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>White trying the accused person the Designated Court shall follow the procedure prescribed in the Code of Criminal Procedure 1973 for the trial of the warrant cases.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Designated Court will exercise the power of remand with regard to person forwarded to it as provided under Sections 167 and 309 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Designated Court, while trying the offence under this Act, may also try an offence other than the offence under this Act with which, the accused may be charged at the same trial under Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-15.5.list0">
              <item id="section-15.5.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>The offence punishable under this Act shall be cognizable.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.5.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>Subject to the provision contained under this Act the provision with regard to bail as provided under Chapter XXXIII of the Code of Criminal Procedure shall apply except the provision of grant of anticipatory bail as provided under Section 438 of the Code of Criminal Procedure.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Act to override other laws.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Save as otherwise provided in this Act. the provisions of this Act shall have effect not withstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained in any other law for the time being in force or any custom or usage.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit or other proceedings shall lie against the Government or the competent authority or an officer or employee of the Government for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the purpose of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be, after it is made, before each House of the State Legislature, while it is in session for a total period of thirty days, which may be comprised in one session or in two successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session in which it is so laid or the session immediately following, both Houses agree in making any modification in the Rules or both Houses agree that the Rules should not be made, and notify their decision to that effect in the Official Gazette. the rule shall from the date of publication of such decision in the Official Gazette, have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done or omitted to be done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Power to remove difficulties.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Government may, as occasion arises, by order, do anything, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, which appears to it to be necessary to remove the difficulty.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
