<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/41/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/41"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Rajghat Samadhi Act, 1951"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/41/eng@1951-06-29/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/41/eng@1951-06-29"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1951-06-29" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/41/eng@1951-06-29/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/41/eng@1951-06-29"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Rajghat Samadhi Act, 1951</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 41 OF 1951</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 29th June, 1951.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the administration and control of the Rajghat</p>
        <p>Samadhi in Delhi.</p>
      </longTitle>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament as follows:-</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Short title and commencement. This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Rajghat Samadhi Act, 1951.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date 1 as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act,-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" Committee" means the Rajghat Samadhi Committee  constituted under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" Samadhi" means the structure built in token of  reverence for Mahatma Gandhi at Rajghat on the Western bank  of the Jamuna in Delhi, and includes the premises described  in the Schedule with all buildings contained therein,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>together with all additions thereto or alterations thereof  which may be made after the commencement of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Rajghat Samadhi Committee. The administration and  control of the Samadhi shall be vested in a Committee constituted in  the manner hereinafter provided.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Committee shall by the name of" the Rajghat Samadhi</p>
            <p>Committee", be a body corporate and shall have perpetual succession  and a common seal and shall by the said name sue and be sued through  its Chairman.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Composition of the Committee. The Committee shall consist of  the following members, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the Mayor of the Municipal Corporation of Delhi, ex-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>fficio;]</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>three officials nominated by the Central Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>four non- officials nominated by the Central Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>three members of Parliament of whom two shall be  elected from among themselves by members of the House of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>People and one from among themselves by members of the</p>
            <p>Council of States.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may appoint any person referred to in  sub- section (1) or any other person to be the Chairman of the</p>
            <p>Committee, and if any other person is so appointed, he shall be deemed  to be a member of the Committee within the meaning of sub- section (1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All persons nominated by the Central Government to be members  of the Committee shall hold office during the pleasure of the Central</p>
            <p>Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The term of office of a member elected under clause (d) of  sub- section (1) shall come to an end as soon as he ceases to be a  member of the House from which he was elected.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Powers and duties of the Committee. Subject to such rules as  may be made under this Act, the powers and duties of the Committee  shall be--</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to make rules. The Central</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules 3  to carry out the objects of this Act, and to regulate access to the</p>
            <p>Samadhi or to any portion thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Power of Committee to make bye- laws. The Committee may , by  notification in the Official Gazette,] make byelaws consistent with  this Act and the rules made thereunder for all or any of the following  purposes, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the manner in which meetings of the Committee shall be  convened, the quorum for the transaction of any business  thereat and the procedure at such meetings;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the appointment of such persons as may be necessary to  assist the Committee in the efficient performance of its  duties and the terms and conditions of service of such  employees;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the duties and powers of the employees of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-7.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Committee;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.1.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the submission of accounts, returns and reports to the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Committee by any of its employees.</p>
            <p>(The Schedule.)</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All bye- laws made under this section shall be subject to the  condition of previous publication and shall not have effect until they  are approved by the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7A">
        <num>7A.</num>
        <heading>Rule and bye- laws to be laid before Parliament. Every rule  and every bye- law made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be  after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in  session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in  one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the  expiry of the session immediately following the session or the  successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule or the bye- law or both Houses agree that the  rule or bye- law should not be made, the rule or bye- law shall  thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that rule or bye- law.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Validity of acts of Committee not to be questioned by reason  of vacancy, etc. No act or proceeding of the Committee shall be deemed  to be invalid merely by reason of any vacancy in, or any defect in the  constitution of, the Committee.</heading>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
