<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-tmn/act/1948/06/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-tmn/act/1948/06"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Tamil Nadu Restriction Of Habitual Offenders Act, 1948"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-tmn/act/1948/06/eng@2016-12-21/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-tmn/act/1948/06/eng@2016-12-21"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-12-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-tmn/act/1948/06/eng@2016-12-21/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-tmn/act/1948/06/eng@2016-12-21"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-12-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Tamil Nadu Restriction Of Habitual Offenders Act, 1948</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[Act No. 06 of 1948]</p>
        <p>An Act for imposing certain restrictions on habitual offenders in the State of Tamil Nadu.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to impose certain restrictions on habitual offenders in the State of Tamil Nadu;</p>
        <p>It is hereby enacted as follows .—</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called The Tamil Nadu Restriction Of Habitual Offenders Act, 1948</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Tamil Nadu.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on the 29th day of April 1948.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,-</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>"district" includes the" presidency-town;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>"District Magistrate" means in the case of the presidency-town, the Commissioner of Police;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>"Government" means the State Government;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>"habitual offender" means a person who, before or after the commencement of this Act, has been sentenced to a substantive term of imprisonment, such sentence not having boon set aside in appeal or revision, on not loss than three occasions, for one or another of the offences under the Indian Penal Code (Central Act XLV of 1860) set forth in the Schedule, each of the subsequent sentences having been passed in respect of an offence committed after the passing of the sentence on the previous occasion;</p>
            <p>Explanation.—The passing of an order requiring a person to give security for good behaviour with reference to section 110 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (Central Act V of 1898), shall be deemed to amount to the passing of a sentence of substantive imprisonment within the meaning of this clause.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>"notification" means a notification published in the Fort St. George Gazette;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>"notified offender" means a habitual offender in respect of whom a notification has been issued under section 3 and is in force;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>"prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act:</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>"settlement" means a settlement established or deemed to be established under section 8.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Power of Government to notify habitual offenders.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification if they are satisfied that any person is a habitual offender declare that he shall be subject to the provisions of this Act to such extent and subject to such restrictions, if any, as may be specified in the notification.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every notification issued under sub-section (1) shall be in force for a period of five years from the date of publication of such notification, but the Government may, by notification, at any time before the expiry of the said period, cancel or modify any notification issued under sub-section (1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The cancellation of a notification or the expiry of the period of five years, under the subsection (2) shall not be deemed to affect the power of the Government under sub-section (1) to issue a notification in respect of a habitual offender as often as he is sentenced to a substantive terms of imprisonment, such sentence not having been set aside in appeal or revision, for any one or more of the scheduled offences at any time after such cancellation or expiry.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (2), where a notified offender is sentenced to a substantive term of imprisonment, such sentence not having been set aside in appeal or revision, for any one or more of the scheduled offences, the Government may direct that the notification issued under sub-section (1) in respect of such notified offender shall be in force for a further period of five years from the date of his release from such imprisonment.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Before any notification is issued in respect of any person under sub-section (1), or modified to his disadvantage under sub-section (2), or before any direction is issued in respect of any notified offender under sub-section (4), a reasonable opportunity shall be given to him to show cause against such issue, modification or direction, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Delegation of powers to District Magistrate.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification, delegate their powers under Section 3 to a District Magistrate, in respect of person ordinarily residing in his district, subject to such restrictions and conditions as may be specified in the notification and subject also to control and revision by them.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Notified offenders to intimate residence and change of residence.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every notified offenders shall intimate to such authority and in such manner as may be prescribed, his place of residence, every change or intended change thereof, and every absence or intended absence therefrom:</p>
            <p>Provided that the District Magistrate or any officer authorised by him may exempt any such offender from reporting any temporary absence or intended absence from his residence, not exceeding such limit as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Power to restrict movements of notified offenders.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If in the opinion of the Government, it is necessary or expedient in the interests of the general public so to do, they may, by notification, declare that any notified offender shall be restricted in his movements to a specified area.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Before making any such declaration, the Government shall consider-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the nature of the offences, if any, of which the offender has been convicted and the circumstances in which they were committed;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>whether the offender follows any lawful occupation, and whether such occupation is a real one or merely a pretence for facilitating the commission of offences;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>the suitability of the area to which his movements are to be restricted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>the manner in which it is proposed that he should earn his living in such area, and the adequacy of the arrangements therefor.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Power to cancel or alter such restrictions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification, cancel any declaration made under Section 6 or alter any area notified under that Section or this Section; and the District Magistrate may, by order in writing, alter any area notified under Section 6 or this Section into any other area situated in his district:</p>
            <p>Provided that before issuing any such notification or order, the Government or the District Magistrate shall consider the matters referred to in Section 6 , sub-section (2), in so far as they may be applicable.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Power to place notified offenders in settlements.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Government may establish industrial, agricultural or reformatory settlements and may order any notified offender to be placed in any such settlement.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Power to discharge or transfer persons from settlements.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Government or any officer authorized by them may at any time, by order, direct any notified offender, who may be in a settlement to be discharged or transferred to any other settlement.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Power to subject voluntary residents in settlements to restrictions and penalties.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by order, direct that any person voluntarily residing in any settlement shall be subject to all or any of the restrictions and penalties imposed by or under this Act on a notified offender placed in such settlement.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Power to make Rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may make Rules to carry out the purpose of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generally of the foregoing power, such Rules may provide for or regulate-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>all matters required or allowed by this Act to be prescribed;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.2.list1.aa">
                <num>(aa)</num>
                <p>the manner and method of service of notification on the notified offender concerned;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the restrictions to be observed by notified offenders in respect of whom notification or orders have been issued under Section 6 or Section 7 ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the grant of certificates of identity to notified offenders, and the inspection of such certificates;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the conditions under which notified offenders may be permitted to leave the area to which their movement are restricted or the places in which they are settled;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the inspection of the residence of notified offenders;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the term upon which notified offenders may be discharged from the operation of this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the management and supervision of settlements including the discipline and conduct of the persons placed in them;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the periodical review of the cases of all persons who have been placed in any settlement under this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All Rules made under this Act shall be published in the Tamil Nadu Government Gazette and, unless they are expressed to come into force on a particular day, shall come into force on the day on which they are so published.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All notifications issued under this Act shall, unless they are expressed to come into force on a particular day, come into force on the day on which they are published.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Rule made or notification issued as soon as possible after it is made, or issued, be placed on the table of both Houses of the Legislature, and if, before the expiry of the session, in which it is so placed or the next session, both Houses agree in making any modification in any such Rule or notification or Both Houses agree that the Rule or notification should not be made or issued, the Rule or notification shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that Rule or notification.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Penalties.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any notified offender who contravenes, any of the provisions of this Act or any notification, Rule or order made thereunder shall be punishable-</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Arrest of notified offender.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If a notified offender-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>is found outside the area to which his movements have been restricted, in contravention of the conditions under which he is permitted to leave such area, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>escapes from any settlement in which ho has been placed,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>he may be arrested without warrant by any police officer, village headman or village watchman. 1[If the offender is arrested, he shall be informed as soon as may be, of the grounds for such arrest and shall be produced before the nearest Magistrate within a period of twenty-four hours of such arrest, excluding the time necessary for the journey from the place of arrest to the Court of the Magistrate and the offender shall not be detained beyond the said period without the authority of the Magistrate. The Magistrate shall, on production of the offender and on proof of the facts, order him to be removed] to such area or to such settlement, there to be dealt with in accordance with this Act and any rules made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Rules for the removal of prisoners to apply in certain cases.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every law or Rule for the time being in force governing the removal of prisoners shall apply to all persons ordered to be placed in a settlement under Section 8 or to be removed under Section 13 ;</p>
            <p>Provided that no order from the Government or Inspector-General of Prisons shall be necessary for the removal of such persons.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Bar of jurisdiction.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No Court shall question the validity of any notification (other than one under Section 3 ), or order, issued under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15A">
        <num>15A.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any person for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any Rule made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Government for any damage caused or likely to be caused by anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any Rule made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15B">
        <num>15B.</num>
        <heading>Power to amend Schedule.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15B.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification, amend the Schedule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15B.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any reference made in this Act to the Schedule shall be considered as relating to the Schedule as for the time being amended in exercise of the powers conferred by sub-section (1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Effect of certain orders passed under Criminal Tribes Act , 1924.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-16.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In respect of every person who stood registered under the Criminal Tribes Act, 1974 (Central Act 6 of 1924) (thereafter in this Section referred to as the said Act) at the commencement of this Act and who, within a period of five years immediately preceding such commencement, had been either ordered to give security for good behaviour with reference to Section 110 of 15 [ Code of Criminal Procedure , 1973 (Central Act 2 of 1974), or convicted of an offence under Section 24 of the said Act or of a non-bailable offence under any other law, a notification shall be deemed to have been issued under Section 3 , sub-section (1) of this Act, declaring him to be subject to all the provisions of this Act; and this Act shall apply to every such person accordingly.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every notification issued in respect of any person under Section 3 of the Tamil Nadu Restriction of Habitual Offenders Act, 1943 ( Tamil Nadu Act 19 of 1943) and in force at the commencement of this Act, shall be deemed to have been issued under Section 3 , sub-section (1) of this Act, all references in that notification to the provisions of the said Act and the Rules made under it being construed as references to the corresponding provisions of this Act and the Rules made under it.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any notification or order issued or made under the said Act in respect of any person referred to in sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) and in force at the commencement of this Act, restricting the movements of such person or placing him in a settlement shall be deemed to have been issued or made under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All settlements established under Section 16 of the said Act and existing at the commencement of this Act shall be deemed to have been established under Section 8 of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Omitted</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Omitted</heading>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-theschedule">
      <doc name="theschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-tmn/act/1948/06/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-tmn/act/1948/06"/>
              <FRBRalias value="THE SCHEDULE"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-tmn/act/1948/06/eng@2016-12-21/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-tmn/act/1948/06/eng@2016-12-21"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-tmn/act/1948/06/eng@2016-12-21/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-tmn/act/1948/06/eng@2016-12-21"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-12-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="theschedule">
            <heading>[See section 2(4)]</heading>
            <paragraph id="theschedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>[Chapter XII]</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <subsection id="theschedule.231">
              <num>(231)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Counterfeiting coin.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.232">
              <num>(232)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Counterfeiting Indian coin.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.233">
              <num>(233)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Making or selling instrument for counterfeiting coin.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.234">
              <num>(234)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Making or selling instrument for counterfeiting Indian coin.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.235">
              <num>(235)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Possession of instrument or material for the purpose of using the same for counterfeiting coin.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.239">
              <num>(239)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Delivery of coin, possessed with the knowledge that it is counterfeit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.240">
              <num>(240)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Delivery of Indian coin possessed with the knowledge that it is counterfeit.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.242">
              <num>(242)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Possession of counterfeit coin by a person who knew it to be counterfeit when he became possessed thereof.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.243">
              <num>(243)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Possession of Indian coin by a person who knew it to be counterfeit when he became possessed thereof.</p>
                <p>[Chapter XVI]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.299">
              <num>(299)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Culpable homicide.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.307">
              <num>(307)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Attempt to murder.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.308">
              <num>(308)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Attempt to commit culpable homicide.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.310">
              <num>(310)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Being a thug.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.322">
              <num>(322)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Voluntarily causing grievous hurt.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.326">
              <num>(326)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Voluntarily causing grievous hurt by dangerous weapons or means.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.327">
              <num>(327)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Voluntarily causing hurt to extort property or to constrain to an illegal act.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.328">
              <num>(328)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Causing hurt by means of poison, etc., with intent to commit an offence.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.329">
              <num>(329)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Voluntarily causing grievous hurt to extort property or to constrain to an illegal act.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.332">
              <num>(332)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Voluntarily causing hurt to deter public servant from his duty.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.333">
              <num>(333)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Voluntarily causing grievous hurt to deter public servant from his duty.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.369">
              <num>(369)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Kidnapping child under ten years with intent to steal from its person.</p>
                <p>[Chapter XVII]</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.382">
              <num>(382)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Theft after preparation made for causing death, hurt or restraint, in order to the committing of the theft.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.383">
              <num>(383)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Extortion.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.385">
              <num>(385)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Putting person in fear of injury in order to commit extortion.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.386">
              <num>(386)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Extortion by putting a person in fear of death or grievous hurt.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.387">
              <num>(387)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Putting person in fear of death or of grievous hurt in order to commit extortion.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.390">
              <num>(390)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Robbery.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.391">
              <num>(391)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Dacoity.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.393">
              <num>(393)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Attempt to commit robbery.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.394">
              <num>(394)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Voluntarily causing hurt in committing robbery.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.397">
              <num>(397)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Robbery or dacoity, with attempt to cause death or grievous hurt.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.398">
              <num>(398)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Attempt to commit robbery or dacoity when armed with deadly weapon.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.399">
              <num>(399)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Making preparation to commit dacoity.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.402">
              <num>(402)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Assembling for purpose of committing dacoity.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.457">
              <num>(457)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Lurking house-trespass or house-breaking by night in order to the commission of an offence punishable with imprisonment.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.458">
              <num>(458)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Lurking house-trespass or house-breaking by night after preparation for hurt, assault or wrongful restraint.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.459">
              <num>(459)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Grievous hurt caused whilst committing lurking house-trespass or house-breaking.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.460">
              <num>(460)</num>
              <content>
                <p>All persons jointly concerned in lurking house-trespass or house-breaking by night punishable where death or grievous hurt caused by one of them.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
