<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1976/63/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1976/63"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Betwa River Board Act, 1976"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1976/63/eng@1976-04-10/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1976/63/eng@1976-04-10"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1976-04-10" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1976/63/eng@1976-04-10/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1976/63/eng@1976-04-10"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Betwa River Board Act, 1976</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 63 OF 1976</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 10th April, 1976.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the establishment of a Board for the creation of  a reservoir at Rajghat by construction, on behalf of the Governments  of Madhya Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh, of a dam on the Betwa river at</p>
        <p>Rajghat and for the regulation of such reservoir.</p>
        <p>Be it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- seventh Year of the</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:-</p>
        <p>CHAP</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the</p>
              <p>Betwa River Board Act, 1976.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on such date  as the Central</p>
              <p>Government may, after consultation with the Governments of Madhya</p>
              <p>Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh, by notification in the Official Gazette,</p>
              <p>appoint.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Declaration as to expediency of control by the Union. It is  hereby declared that it is expedient in the public interest that the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Central Government should take under its control the regulation and  development of the inter- State Betwa River and River Valley to the  extent hereinafter provided.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" Board" means the Betwa River Board established under  section 4;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" Chairman" means the Chairman of the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" Executive Committee" means the Executive Committee  constituted under section 5;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" member" means a member of the Board and includes the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Chairman;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made by the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Central Government under section 22;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list4.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>" Rajghat Dam" means the Dam described in the Schedule;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list4.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>Rani Laxmibai Sagar] means the reservoir created by  the construction of the Rajghat Dam;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list4.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>" regulations" means regulations made by the Board under  section 23;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list4.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>" rules" means rules made by the Central Government  under section 22.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>ESTABLISHMENT OF THE BOARD</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>ESTABLISHMENT OF THE BOARD</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Establishment and incorporation of the Betwa River Board.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>With effect from such date as the Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, appoint in this behalf, there  shall be established for the purposes of this Act, a board to be  called the Betwa River Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall be a body corporate by the name aforesaid  having perpetual succession and a common seal with power, subject to  the provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of property,</p>
              <p>both movable and immovable, and to contract and shall by the said name  sue and be sued.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Union Minister in charge of Irrigation shall be the</p>
              <blockList id="section-4.3.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Chairman of the Board and the other members of the Board shall be the  following, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.3.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>where the same Union Minister is not in charge of both</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Irrigation and Power, the Union Minister in charge of</p>
              <p>Power or such Minister or Deputy Minister in the Union</p>
              <blockList id="section-4.3.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Ministry or Department in charge of Power as may be  specified in this behalf by the Union Minister in  charge of Power;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.3.list6.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the Chief Ministers of Madhya Pradesh and Uttar</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-4.3.list8">
                <listIntroduction>Pradesh; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.3.list8.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the Ministers of Madhya Pradesh and Uttar pradesh in  charge of Finance, Irrigation and Power]:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that when a proclamation made under article 356 of the</p>
              <p>Constitution is in force in relation to the State of Madhya Pradesh or</p>
              <p>Uttar Pradesh, the Central Government may appoint three persons to  represent such State on the Board and the persons so appointed shall  vacate their offices upon the revocation or cesser of operation of  such proclamation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board may permit any officer of the Central Government or  the Government of Madhya Pradesh or Uttar Pradesh to attend any of its  meetings and take part in the proceedings but such officer shall not  be entitled to vote.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board may associate with itself, in such manner and for  such purposes as may be determined by regulations, any person whose  assistance or advice it may desire in complying with any of the  provisions of this Act and a person so associated shall have the right  to take part in the discussions of the Board relevant to the purpose  for which he has been associated, but shall not be entitled to vote.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Executive committee.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, constitute an Executive</p>
              <p>Committee consisting of officers of that government and officers of  the Governments of Madhya Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The composition of the Executive Committee shall be such as  may be prescribed:</p>
              <blockList id="section-5.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.2.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>an officer of the Central government shall be the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-5.2.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Chairman of the Committee;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.2.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the Governments of Madhya Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh  shall have equal representation.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the general superintendence and control of the</p>
              <p>Board, the management of the affairs of the Board shall vest in the</p>
              <p>Executive Committee and the Chairman and other members of the</p>
              <p>Committee shall assist the Board in such manner as the Board may  require.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the rules, and to the directions of the Board, the</p>
              <p>Executive Committee may exercise any power and do any act or thing  which may be exercised or done by the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The procedure to be followed by the Executive committee and  all other matters relating to the Executive Committee shall be as such  as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Vacancies, etc., not to invalidate proceedings of the Board or  the Executive Committee. No act or proceeding of the Board or the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Executive Committee shall be invalidated by reason of-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>any vacancy in the Board or the Executive Committee;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>any defect in the composition of, or in any appointment  to, the Board or the Executive Committee;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>any irregularity in the procedure of the Board or the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Executive Committee not affecting the merits of the  case.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Chief Engineer and Financial Adviser.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central</p>
              <p>Government may, after consultation with the Governments of Madhya</p>
              <p>Pradesh, and Uttar Pradesh, appoint an Engineer (to be the Chief</p>
              <p>Engineer of the Board and to be known as the Chief Engineer, Rajghat</p>
              <p>Dam Project), and a Financial Adviser, and a Secretary, to the Board  from amongst the officers of the Government of Madhya Pradesh and</p>
              <p>Uttar Pradesh:</p>
              <p>Provided that the Central Government shall, so far as  practicable, ensure that officers from the same State do not hold the  posts of Chief Engineer and Secretary at the same time:</p>
              <p>Provided further that the Central Government may, with the  concurrence of the Governments of Madhya Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh,</p>
              <p>appoint an officer of the Central government as the Financial</p>
              <p>Adviser].</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the general superintendence and control of the</p>
              <blockList id="section-7.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Board and the Executive Committee, the Chief Engineer of the Board  appointed under sub- section (1) shall be the Chief Executive Officer  of the Board and shall exercise and discharge-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.2.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>such powers and duties as may be prescribed or as may  be delegated to him by the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.2.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>such other powers and duties as may be determined by  regulations.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Financial Adviser appointed under sub- section (1) shall  be the Chief Accounts Officer of the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The terms and conditions of service of the Chief Engineer of  the Board, and of the Financial Adviser, and the Secretary, to the</p>
              <p>Board shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Other officers and employees of the Board.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the  rules, the Board may appoint such officers and employees as it may  deem necessary for the efficient discharge of its functions:</p>
              <p>Provided that the Board shall, as far as practicable, utilise the  services of the officers and employees offered by the Governments of</p>
              <p>Madhya Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh in such a manner that equal  representation is given to the two States.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The terms and conditions of service of the officers and  employees of the Board shall be such as may be determined by  regulations.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Advisory Committees. Subject to the rules, the Board may from  time to time, constitute one or more Advisory Committees to assist the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Board and the Executive Committee in the efficient discharge of their  functions.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>FUNCTIONS AND POWERS OF THE BOARD</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>FUNCTIONS AND POWERS OF THE BOARD</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Functions of the Board. Subject to the other provisions of  this Act and the rules, the Board may, if satisfied that the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Governments of Madhya Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh have complied with or  arranged to comply with the conditions specified in section 11,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>carry out surveys and investigations in the Betwa</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Inter- State river valley and prepare a comprehensive  project report for the construction of Rajghat Dam and  appurtenant works  and for the generation of power at</p>
              <p>Rajghat Dam, including the construction of a power  house (hereinafter referred to as the Rajghat Power</p>
              <p>House) near the dam and appurtenant works] and finalise  the same after consulting the Governments of Madhya</p>
              <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh and taking into account the  suggestions if any made by those Governments;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list6.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>prepare detailed reports and estimates in respect of  the Project and allocate the cost among the Governments  of Madhya Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list6.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>draw up standards and specifications for implementation  of the project and for the maintenance thereof;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list6.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>construct the Rajghat Dam  and the Rajghat Power</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list8">
                <listIntroduction>House] and the common carrier from the dam to irrigate  areas in Madhya Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list8.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>lay down rules of operation and management of Rajghat</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list10">
                <listIntroduction>Dam;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list10.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>perform any other function which is supplemental,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>incidental, or consequential to all or any of the  functions specified in clauses (a) to (e).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Conditions subject to which the Board may exercise its  functions.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-11.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The exercise by the Board of the functions specified in  section 10 shall be subject to the following conditions, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.1.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>that the Governments of Madhya Pradesh and Uttar</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-11.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Pradesh shall at all times make, to the satisfaction of  the Board, suitable provisions as to the moneys, land  facilities and electrical power for construction and  all other things required by the Board;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.1.list3.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>that the liability for the entire expenditure on the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Rajghat Dam and Rajghat Power House including  appurtenant works and on the generation of power at</p>
              <p>Rajghat Dam] and all other expenditure incurred by the</p>
              <p>Board in the discharge of its functions shall be shared  by the Governments of Madhya Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh  in such proportion as may be specified by the Board:</p>
              <blockList id="section-11.1.list8">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that the Board may specify different proportions  for different works or matters having regard to the benefits  which may accrue to the States and other relevant factors;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.1.list8.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>that the Governments of Madhya Pradesh and Uttar</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Pradesh shall extend full co- operation to the Board and  shall in particular make available to the Board the  land and electric power required by it for construction  purposes as expeditiously as possible.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purposes of clause (ii) of sub- section (1), the  expenditure on the Rajghat Dam shall include the expenditure incurred  by the Government of Uttar Pradesh on the Rajghat Dam Project before  the establishment of the Board and the Board shall determine the  amount of expenditure so incurred by the Government of Uttar Pradesh  and the extent to which it shall be reimbursed by the Government of</p>
              <p>Madhya Pradesh.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Powers of the Board.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-12.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of this</p>
              <p>Act and the rules, the Board shall have the power to do anything which  may be necessary or expedient for the purpose of carrying out its  functions under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-12.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing  provision, such power shall include the powers-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to acquire, hold and dispose of such properties both  movable and immovable as the Board deems necessary;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>to publish statistics or other information relating to  the various aspects of flood control and drainage in  the Betwa River Valley , the regulation of Rani</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Laxmibai Sagar  and the generation of power at</p>
              <blockList id="section-12.2.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Rajghat Dam];</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12.2.list4.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>to require the Governments of Uttar Pradesh and Madhya</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Pradesh to furnish such information as the Board may  require in the discharge of its functions.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Betwa River Board Fund.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-13.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>There shall be constituted a Fund  to be called the Betwa River Board Fund and there shall be credited  thereto the sums paid to the Board by the Governments of Madhya</p>
              <p>Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh and all other sums received by the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-13.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Fund shall be applied-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-13.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>for meeting the salaries, allowances and other  remuneration of the officers and other employees of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-13.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Board and other administrative expenses of the Board;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-13.2.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>for meeting the expenditure on surveys and  investigations undertaken by the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.2.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>for meeting the cost of construction of the  Rajghat</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-13.2.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Dam, the Rajghat Power House and appurtenant works];</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-13.2.list5.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>for meeting the other expenses of the Board in the  discharge of its functions under this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Budget. The Board shall prepare in such form and at such time  each year as may be prescribed its budget for the next financial year  showing the estimated expenditure, the amount of expenditure which the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>State Governments of Madhya Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh have</p>
              <p>undertaken to provide for and forward the same to the Central</p>
              <p>Government and the said State Governments.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Annual report.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-15.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall prepare in such form and  at such time each year as may be prescribed its annual report giving a  full account of its activities during the previous year and forward  copies thereof to the Central Government and that Government shall  cause the same to be laid before each House of Parliament.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall forward copies of its annual reports to the</p>
              <p>Governments of Madhya Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Accounts and audit. The accounts of the Board shall be  maintained and audited in such manner as may, in consultation with the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Comptroller and Auditor- General of India, be prescribed.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-V.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Directions by Central Government. In the discharge of its  functions, the Board shall be guided by such directions and  instructions on questions of policy as may be given to it by the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Disputes between the Board and the State Governments. If any  dispute arises between the Board and the Government of Madhya Pradesh  or Uttar Pradesh or both regarding any matter covered by this Act or  touching or arising out of it, it shall be referred to the Central  government and the decision of the Central Government shall be final  and binding on the Board and the said Governments.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Power to enter. Subject to any rules made in this behalf, any  officer of the Board generally or specially authorised by the Board in  this behalf may, at all reasonable times, enter upon any land or  premises and there do such things as may be reasonably necessary for  the purpose of lawfully carrying out any works or of making any  surveys, examination or investigation, preliminary or incidental to  the exercise of any power or the performance of any function by the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Board under this Act:</p>
              <p>Provided that no person shall enter into any building or upon any  enclosed court or garden attached to a dwelling house, unless with the  consent of the occupier thereof, without previously giving such  occupier at least seven days' notice in writing of his intention to do  so.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Members. officers and employees of the Board to be public  servants. All members of the Board and the Executive Committee and all  officers and employees of the Board shall be deemed, when acting or  purporting to act in pursuance of any of the provisions of this Act to  be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Penal Code (45 of 1860).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-21.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No suit,</p>
              <p>prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against the Central</p>
              <p>Government or the government of Madhya Pradesh or Uttar Pradesh or any  members of the Board or the Executive Committee or any officer or  employee of the Board for anything which is in good faith done or  intended to be done under this Act or the rules or regulations.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-21.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No suit or other legal proceedings shall lie against the</p>
              <p>Board for any damage caused or likely to be caused by anything in good  faith done or purported to be done under this Act or the rules or  regulations and, in particular, it shall not be the responsibility of  the Board to provide for relief measures necessitated by floods or by  breaches and failure of works.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-22.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the  purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-22.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-22.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the composition of, and the procedure to be followed,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>by the Executive Committee and all other matters  relating to the Executive Committee under sub- sections</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-22.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>and (5) of section 5;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-22.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the powers and duties which may be exercised or  discharged by the Chief Engineer of the Board, under  clause (a) of sub- section (2) of section 7;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-22.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the terms and conditions of service of the Chief</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Engineer of, and the financial Adviser and the</p>
              <blockList id="section-22.2.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Secretary to, the Board, under sub- section (4) of  section 7;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-22.2.list4.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>appointment of officers and employees of the Board,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-22.2.list6">
                <listIntroduction>under sub- section (1) of section 8;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-22.2.list6.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the form in which and the time at which the budget and  annual report of the board shall be prepared, under  section 14, and sub- section (1) of section 15;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-22.2.list6.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which the accounts of the Board shall be  maintained and audited, under section 16;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-22.2.list6.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the form and manner in which disputes may be referred  under section 18 to the Central Government and the  procedure to be followed by the Central Government for  the settlement of such disputes.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Power to make regulations.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-23.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board may, with the  previous approval of the Central Government, by notification in the</p>
              <p>Official Gazette, make regulations not inconsistent with this Act and  the rules, for enabling it to discharge its functions under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power,</p>
              <p>such regulations may provide for all or any of the following matters,</p>
              <blockList id="section-23.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-23.2.list3.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which and the purposes for which the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Board may associate with itself any persons, under sub-</p>
              <blockList id="section-23.2.list6">
                <listIntroduction>section (5) of section 4;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-23.2.list6.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the powers which may be exercised and the duties which  may be discharged by the Chief Engineer of the Board,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-23.2.list8">
                <listIntroduction>under sub- section (2) (b) of section 7;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-23.2.list8.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the terms and conditions of service of the officers</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>(other than the Chief Engineer of the Board, Financial</p>
              <p>Adviser and Secretary to the Board) and other employees  of the Board, under sub- section (2) of section 8.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Rules and regulations to be laid before Parliament. Every  rule and every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon  as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it  is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised  in one session or in two or more successive session and if, before the  expiry of the session immediately following the session or successive  sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree that the rule or regulation, as  the case may be, should not be made, the rule or regulation shall  thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that rule or regulation.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
