<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/39/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/39"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Marking Of Heavy Packages Act, 1951"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/39/eng@1951-06-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/39/eng@1951-06-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1951-06-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/39/eng@1951-06-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/39/eng@1951-06-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Marking Of Heavy Packages Act, 1951</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 39 OF 1951</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 25th June, 1951.] BE</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to give effect to the International Convention drawn up in</p>
        <p>Geneva on the 30th day of May, 1929, for the marking of weight on  heavy packages transported by sea or inland waterways.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be  called the Marking of Heavy Packages Act, 1951.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such  date as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" heavy package" means a package or other object weighing  not less than one metric ton, which is equal to one  thousand kilogrammes or 2204. 6 standard pounds or 26. 8  standard maunds;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" inland waterway" means any canal, river, lake or other  navigable water in India.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Obligation to mark weight on heavy packages. Every person  consigning a heavy package for transport by sea or inland water- way  from any place in India shall have marked thereon plainly, durably and  conspicuously the gross weight of the packages:</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Provided that in cases or circumstances specified by rules made  under this Act where it is difficult to determine the correct weight,</p>
            <p>only the approximate weight may be so marked.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Inspectors.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification  in the Official Gazette, appoint such persons as it thinks fit to be  inspectors for the purposes of this Act and assign to each of them one  or more areas to be specified in the notification, or to two or more  of them the same area to be so specified.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every inspector shall be deemed to be a public servant within  the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Powers of inspectors. Subject to any rules made by the Central</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Government in this behalf, an inspector appointed under sub- section</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>of section 4 may-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>enter, with such assistants as he considers necessary,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>and inspect any place or vessel and examine any  packages found therein;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.1.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>if, on such examination, any heavy package is found not  to have been marked in accordance with the provisions  of section 3, direct that the package shall not be  transported by sea or inland waterway until it has been  marked in accordance with those provisions:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that, instead of issuing any direction as aforesaid, the  inspector may himself cause the package to be marked in accordance  with the provisions of section 3; and in any such case, the expenses  incurred by him for such marking shall be recoverable as an arrear of  land revenue from the person consigning the package for transport.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Penalties.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If any person contravenes--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the provisions of section 3, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any direction given by an inspector under clause (b) of  section 5,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to five hundred  rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person wilfully obstructs an inspector in the exercise  of his powers under this Act, he shall be punishable with fine which  may extend to two hundred rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Offences by companies.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the person committing an  offence under this Act is a company, the company as well as every  person in charge of, and responsible to, the company for the conduct  of its business at the time of the commission of the offence shall be  deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded  against and punished accordingly:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render  any such person liable to any punishment if he proves that the offence  was committed without his knowledge or that he exercised all due  diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where  an offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is  proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or  connivance of, or that the commission of the offence is attributable  to any neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary or  other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary or  other officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of that offence and  shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.</p>
            <blockList id="section-7.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.2.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm  or other association of individuals, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner in  the firm.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Cognizance of offences.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No court inferior to that of a</p>
            <p>Presidency Magistrate or a Magistrate of the first class shall try any  offence under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No court shall take cognizance of any offence under this Act  except on a complaint in writing made by an inspector within six  months of the date on which the offence is alleged to have been  committed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit, prosecution  or other legal proceeding shall lie against any person for anything  which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules providing for--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the conditions as to the manner of marking of heavy  packages, the manner of their packing and the type of  covering to be used;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the cases or circumstances in which the approximate  weight of heavy packages instead of their correct  weight may be marked;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any other matter which has to be, or may be, provided  for by rules.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as  may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is in  session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in  one session or in two successive sessions, and if, before the expiry  of the session in which it is so laid or the session immediately  follow-</p>
            <p>ing, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both</p>
            <p>Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall  thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</p>
            <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that rule.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
