<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1973/56/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1973/56"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Alcock Ashdown Company Limited (Acquisition Of Undertakings) Act, 1973"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1973/56/eng@1973-12-14/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1973/56/eng@1973-12-14"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1973-12-14" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1973/56/eng@1973-12-14/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1973/56/eng@1973-12-14"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Alcock Ashdown Company Limited (Acquisition Of Undertakings) Act, 1973</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 56 OF 1973</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 14th December, 1973.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the acquisition of the undertakings of the</p>
        <p>Alcock Ashdown Company Limited for the purpose of ensuring rational  and co- ordinated development and production of goods essential to the  needs of the country in general, and defence department in particular  and for maters connected therewith or incidental thereto.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title. This Act may be called the Alcock Ashdown Company</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Limited (Acquisition of Undertakings) Act, 1973.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" appointed day" means the date on which this Act comes  into force;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" company" means the Alcock Ashdown Company Limited,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>being a company as defined in the Companies Act, 1956</p>
            <p>(1 of 1956), and having its registered office in the</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>State of Maharashtra;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.c.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>" Court" means the High Court at Bombay;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.c.list0.ca">
                    <num>(ca)</num>
                    <p>" notification" means a notification published in the</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6">
              <listIntroduction>Official Gazette;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6.cb">
                <num>(cb)</num>
                <p>" undertakings of the company" means--</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the industrial unit owned by the company and located at</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list8">
              <listIntroduction>Bhavnagar in the State of Gujarat (hereinafter referred   to as the Bhavnagar unit); and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list8.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>the industrial unit owned by the company and located at</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10">
              <listIntroduction>Bombay in the State of Maharashtra (hereinafter   referred to as the Bombay unit);]</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>words and expressions used herein and not defined but  defined in the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), have  the meanings respectively assigned to them in that Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Undertakings of the company to vest in the Central Government.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>On and from the appointed day, the undertakings of the company shall,</p>
            <p>by virtue of this Act, be transferred to, and shall vest in, the</p>
            <p>Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>General effect of vesting.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The undertakings of the company  shall be deemed to include all assets, rights, powers, authorities and  privileges and all property, movable and immovable, cash balances,</p>
            <p>reserve funds, investments and all other rights and interests in, or  arising out of, such property as were immediately before the appointed  day in the ownership, possession, power or control of the company,</p>
            <p>in relation to the undertakings] whether within or outside India,</p>
            <p>and all books of account, registers and all other documents of  whatever nature relating thereto.</p>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation.-- For the avoidance of doubts, it is hereby  declared that the expression" undertakings of the company" does not  include--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list5.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any debts due to the company; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list5.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any amounts recoverable by the company from its  shareholders or directors.]</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All property included as aforesaid in the undertakings which  have vested in the Central Government under section 3 shall, by force  of such vesting, be freed and discharged from any trusts, obligations,</p>
            <p>mortgages, charges, liens and other incumbrances affecting it, and any  attachment, injunction or any decree or order of any court restricting  the use of such property in any manner shall be deemed to have been  withdrawn.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If, on the appointed day, any suit, appeal or other  proceeding of whatever nature in relation to any business of the  undertakings of the company is pending by or against the company, the  same shall not abate, be discontinued or be, in any way, prejudicially  affected by reason of the transfer of the undertakings of the company  or of any</p>
            <p>thing contained in this Act but the suit, appeal or other proceeding  may be continued, prosecuted and enforced by or against the company.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Duty to deliver possession of the undertaking and documents  relating thereto.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding any decree, judgment or order of  any court or anything contained in any other law for the time being in  force, the Receiver, Official Liquidator of the company or any other  person, in whose possession or custody or under whose control the  undertakings of the company or any part thereof may be, shall deliver  possession of the undertakings of the company or such part thereof as  may be in his possession, custody or control to the Central Government  forthwith.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Receiver, Official Liquidator or any other person who  has, on the appointed day, in his possession or under his custody or  control any books, documents or other papers relating to the  undertakings of the company which have vested, under section 3, in the</p>
            <p>Central Government, shall be liable to account for the said books,</p>
            <p>document or other papers to the Central Government or to such person  as the Central Government may specify in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may take, or cause to be taken, all  necessary steps for securing possession of the undertakings which have  vested in it under section 3.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Duty to furnish particulars.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The company shall, within  such period as the Central Government may allow in this behalf,</p>
            <p>furnish to that Government a complete inventory of all the properties  and assets of the company, as on the appointed day, pertaining to the  undertakings which have vested in the Central Government under section</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>So much of the obligation of the company under sub- section</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>as relates to the properties and assets of the company in the  possession, custody or control of the Receiver shall be discharged by  him and so much of that obligation as relates to the properties and  assets in the possession, custody or control of the Official</p>
            <p>Liquidator shall be discharged by the Official Liquidator.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Payment of amount.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government shall deposit,</p>
            <p>in cash, in Court, to the credit of the company, an amount equal to  the sum of rupees one crore for the transfer to, and vesting in, the</p>
            <p>Central Government, under section 3, of the undertakings of the  company.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the avoidance of doubts, it is hereby declared that the  liabilities of the company in relation to the undertakings which have  vested in the Central Government under section 3, shall be met from  the amount referred to in sub- section (1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In meeting the liabilities of the company in relation to the  undertakings which have vested in the Central Government under section</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>, the Court shall distribute the amount referred to in sub- section</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>amongst the creditors of the company, whether secured or  unsecured, in accordance with their rights and interests, and if there  is any surplus left after such distribution, amongst the  contributories of the company in accordance with the rights and  interests of such contributories.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Management and administration of the undertakings. The  undertakings, which have vested in the Central Government under  section 3, shall be managed on behalf of the Central Government by  such person or body of persons (including one or more Government  companies, whether in existence at the commencement of this Act or   incorporated thereafter) as may be nominated by the Central Government  in this behalf, and such person or body of persons shall carry on the  management in accordance with such regulations as may be made by the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Central Government in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8A">
        <num>8A.</num>
        <heading>Vesting of the Bhavnagar unit in the State Government.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sections 3 and 4 the Central</p>
            <p>Government shall direct by notification that all assets, rights,</p>
            <p>powers, authorities and privileges and all property, movable and  immovable, cash balances, reserve funds, investments and all other  rights and interests in, or arising out of, such property of the</p>
            <p>Bhavnagar unit which have vested in the Central Government under  section 3, shall, instead of continuing to vest in the Central</p>
            <p>Government, vest in the State Government of Gujarat (hereinafter   referred to as the State Government), either on the date of  publication of the notification or on such later date as may be  specified in the notification.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the assets, rights, powers, authorities and privileges  and all property, movable and immovable, cash balances, reserve funds,</p>
            <p>investments and all other rights and interests in, or arising out of,</p>
            <p>such property of the Bhavnagar unit vest, under sub- section (1), in  the State Government that Government shall, on and from the date of  such vesting, be deemed to have become the owner of such unit and  rights and liabilities of the Central Government in relation to that  unit shall, on and from the date of such vesting, be deemed to have  become the rights and liabilities of the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8B">
        <num>8B.</num>
        <heading>Vesting of Bombay unit in Government company.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8B.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sections 3 and 4, the Central</p>
            <p>Government shall direct by notification that all assets, rights,</p>
            <p>powers, authorities and privileges and all property, movable and  immovable, cash balances, reserve funds, investments and all other  rights and interests in, or arising out of, such property of the</p>
            <p>Bombay unit which have vested in the Central Government under section</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>, shall, instead of continuing to vest in the Central Government,</p>
            <p>vest in the Mazagon Dock Limited, a Government company having its  registered office in the State of Maharashtra (hereinafter referred to   as the Government company), either on the date of publication of the  notification or on such later date as may be specified in the  notification.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the assets, rights, powers, authorities and privileges  and all property, movable and immovable, cash balances, reserve funds,</p>
            <p>investments and all other rights and interests in, or arising out of,</p>
            <p>such property of the Bombay unit vest, under sub- section (1), the</p>
            <p>Government company, that company shall, on and from the date of such  vesting, be deemed to have become the owner of such unit and the  rights and liabilities of the Central Government in relation to that  unit shall, on and from the date of such vesting, be deemed to have  become the rights and liabilities of the Government company.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8C">
        <num>8C.</num>
        <heading>Employment of certain employees to continue when Bhavnagar  unit vests under section 8A.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8C.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the assets, rights, powers,</p>
            <p>authorities and privileges and all property, movable and immovable,</p>
            <p>cash balances, reserve funds, investments and other rights and  interests in, or arising out of such property of the Bhavnagar unit  vest, under section 8A in the State Government, every person who has  been, immediately before the date of such vesting, employed in that  unit shall become, on and from the date of such vesting, an employee  of the State Government, and shall hold office or service under that</p>
            <p>State Government with the same rights and privileges as to pension,</p>
            <p>gratuity and other matters as would have been admissible to him if  there had been no such vesting and shall continue to do so unless and  until his employment under the State Government is duly terminated or  until his remuneration and other conditions of service are duly  altered by the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8C.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial Disputes</p>
            <p>Act, 1947 (14 of 1947) or in any other law for the time being in  force, the transfer of the services of any officer or other person  employed in the Bhavnagar unit to the State Government, shall not  entitle such officer or other employee to any compensation under this</p>
            <p>Act or under any other law for the time being in force and no such  claim shall be entertained by any court, tribunal or other authority.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8C.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where under the terms of any contract of service otherwise,</p>
            <p>any person, whose services become transferred to the State Government  by reason of the provisions of this Act, is entitled to any arrears of  salary or wages or any payments for any leave not availed of or any  other payment, not being payment by way of gratuity or pension, such  person may enforce his claim against the Central Government, but not  against the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8D">
        <num>8D.</num>
        <heading>Transfer of provident fund and other fund when undertakings  vest under section 8A.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8D.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a provident fund, superannuation  fund, welfare fund or any other fund has been established for the  benefit of the persons employed in the Bhavnagar unit, the monies  relatable to the officers or other employees, whose services have  become transferred by or under this Act to the State Government shall  stand transferred to, and vest in, the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8D.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The monies which stand transferred under sub- section (1) to  the State Government shall be dealt with by that Government for the  benefit of the officers and employees so transferred in such manner as  the State Government may decide from time to time.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8E">
        <num>8E.</num>
        <heading>Saving of contracts, etc. All contracts, deeds, bonds,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8E.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>agreements and other instruments of whatever nature to which the</p>
            <p>Central Government is a party in relation to the Bhavnagar unit vested  in the State Government under section 8A subsisting or having effect  immediately before the date of vesting of the said unit in the State</p>
            <p>Government shall, as from that day, be of full force and effect  against, or in the State Government and may be enforced fully and  effectual if, instead of the Central Government, the State Government  been a party thereto.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8F">
        <num>8F.</num>
        <heading>Power to remove difficulties.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8F.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any difficulty arises in  giving effect to the provisions of sections 8A, 8B, 8C, 8D and 8E, the</p>
            <p>Central Government may, by the order published in the Official</p>
            <p>Gazette, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, remove the  difficulty:</p>
            <p>Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a  period of two years from the coming into force of the Alcock Ashdown</p>
            <p>Company Limited (Acquisition of Undertakings) Amendment Act, 1988.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8F.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every order made under sub- section (1) shall be laid before  each House of Parliament.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Penalties.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any person who--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>having in his possession, custody or control any  property forming part of the undertakings of the  company, wrongfully withholds such property from the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-9.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Central Government; or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.1.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>wrongfully obtains possession of any property forming  part of the undertakings of the company which have  vested in the Central Government under this Act; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.1.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>wilfully withholds or fails to furnish to the Central</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-9.1.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Government as required by sub- section (2) of section 5  any document which may be in his possession, custody or  control; or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.1.list5.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>wilfully fails to furnish an inventory as required under  section 6; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.1.list5.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>when required to furnish such inventory, furnishes any  particulars therein which are false and which he either  knows or believes to be false or does not believe to be  true,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to  two years, or with fine, or with both:</p>
            <p>Provided that the court trying any offence under clause (a) or  clause (b) or clause (c) of this sub- section may, at the time of  convicting the accused person, order him to deliver up or refund  within a time to be fixed by the court any property wrongfully  withheld</p>
            <p>or wrongfully obtained or any document wilfully withheld or not  furnished.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No court shall take cognizance of any offence punishable  under this section except with the previous sanction of the Central</p>
            <p>Government or of an officer authorised by that Government in this  behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Offences by companies.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an offence under this Act  has been committed by a company, every person who at the time the  offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible to, the  company for the conduct of the business of the company as well as the  company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be  liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render  any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the  offence was committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised  all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where  any offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is  proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or  connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of any  director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such  director, manager, secretary or other officer shall be deemed to be  guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and  punished accordingly.</p>
            <blockList id="section-10.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.2.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm  or other association of individuals; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner in  the firm.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central</p>
            <p>Government or an officer or other employee serving in connection with  the affairs of the undertakings of the company for anything which is  in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Power to make regulations.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make regulations with regard to  the matters specified in section 8.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every regulation made by the Central Government under this</p>
            <p>Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each</p>
            <p>House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of  thirty</p>
            <p>days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more  successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session  immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the  regulation or both Houses agree that the regulation should not be  made, the regulation shall thereafter have effect only in such  modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however,</p>
            <p>that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to  the validity of anything previously done under that regulation.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
