<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-tri/act/1976/14/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-tri/act/1976/14"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Tripura Prevention Of Defacement Of Property Act, 1976"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-tri/act/1976/14/eng@2017-01-23/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-tri/act/1976/14/eng@2017-01-23"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-23" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-tri/act/1976/14/eng@2017-01-23/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-tri/act/1976/14/eng@2017-01-23"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-23" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Tripura Prevention Of Defacement Of Property Act, 1976</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No. 14 of 1976.</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the prevention of defacement of property.</p>
        <p>Where it is expedient in the public interest to provide for the prevention of defacement of property and matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.</p>
        <p>It is hereby enacted in the Twenty-seventh Year of the Republic of India, by the Legislature of Tripura, as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and application</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Tripura Prevention of Defacement of Property Act, 1976.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of Tripura.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall apply in the first instance to Municipal limits of Agartala town, but the State Government may, from time to time by notification in the Official Gazette, apply it to such other local area or areas as may be specified in the notification.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act. unless the context otherwise requires—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>'Beautification' includes the qualities that arouse aesthetic pleasure or make a thing good looking and also includes painting, writing, hoarding and construction work having educational and cultural value excluding and political messages.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.aa">
                <num>(aa)</num>
                <p>'Defacement' includes impairing or interfering with the appearance or beauty, damaging, disfiguring, spoiling or injuring in any other way whatsoever and the word 'deface'; shall be construed accordingly;.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>'Private property' includes any lands, road, building, hut structure, wall, tree, fence, post, pole or any other erection, owned or hired by any private individual solely or jointly, private bodies, organisations. companies officers or institutions.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>'Public property' includes any land, road, building, hut structure, wall, tree, fence, post, pole or any other erection, owned or hired by the Government, Government Undertakings or Autonomous bodies.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>'Sub-Divisional Officer' means Sub-Divisional Officer of a Revenue Sub-Division under District Administration.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for defacement of public property</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever defaces any public property in public view by writing or marking with ink, chalk, paint or any other material, except for the purpose of indicating the name and address of the owner or occupier of such public property, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees or with both.</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list2.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the work done by any Government Department or owner or occupier of the public property as a part of beautification or for advertisement or to welcome dignitories. will not be construed as defacement;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list2.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>putting flags over small pieces of bamboo. hanging of festoons and flags by the side of public road as a part of publicity or propaganda during election or for organising conference, seminars, meetings etc. by political parties or private organisations, shall not be construed as defacement if such Act (s) do not create any public annoyance or obstruction.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list2.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>for raising any temporary gate or hanging of festoons or flags on or across the public road prior permission from the concerned Sub-Divisional Officer shall be obtained subject to the condition that raising of such structure does not create any public annoyance or obstruction;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list2.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>the concerned Government Department or owner or occupier of the public property or candidate or private organisation or political party shall ensure removal, demolition or erasing of any or all the Acts stated in the preceding provisos at its own cost within 7 (seven) days of completion of the conference, meeting, seminar, election as the case may be.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.1A">
          <num>(1A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever defaces any private property in public view by writing or marking with ink, chalk, paint or any other materials without obtaining prior written permission from the owner or occupier of such private property, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months or with fine which may extend to Rs. 1000 or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any offence committed under sub-section (1) is for the benefit of some other person or a company or other body corporate or an association of persons (whether incorporated or not), then, such other person and every president, chairman, director, partner, manager, secretary, agent or any other officer or person concerned with the management thereof, as the case may be, shall, unless he proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or consent, be deemed to be guilty of such offence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Offence to be cognizable.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>An offence punishable under this Act shall be cognizable.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Power of State Government to erase writing, etc.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Without prejudice to the provisions of Section 3, Sub-Divisional Officer of the respective Sub-Division or any other officer authorised by the State Government shall be competent to take such steps as may be necessary for erasing any writing freeing any defacement or removing any mark from any property or to demolish or remove temporary gates. structure, poles. flags festoons at the cost of the concerned person, party or organisation."</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Act to override other laws.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any other law for the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may. if necessary, make rules by notifications published in the Tripura Gazette, for carrying out the purposes of the Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
