<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1899/4/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1899/4"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Government Buildings Act, 1899"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1899/4/eng@1899-02-03/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1899/4/eng@1899-02-03"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1899-02-03" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1899/4/eng@1899-02-03/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1899/4/eng@1899-02-03"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Government Buildings Act, 1899</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 4 OF 1899</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 3rd February, 1899.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the exemption from the operation of municipal  building laws of certain buildings and lands which are the property,</p>
        <p>or in the occupation, of the Government and situate within the limits  of a municipality.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the exemption from the  operation of municipal building laws of certain buildings and lands  which are the property, or in the occupation, of the Government and  situate within the limits of a municipality;</p>
        <p>It is hereby enacted as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and extent.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Government Buildings Act, 1899.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India except  the territories  which, immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised in</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <part id="part-B">
        <num>B</num>
        <heading>States] .</heading>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>" Municipal authority" defined. In this Act the expression</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>" municipal authority" includes a municipal corporation or a body of  municipal commissioners constituted by, or under the provisions of,</p>
              <p>any law or enactment for the time being in force.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Exemption of certain Government buildings from municipal laws  to regulate the erection, etc., of buildings within municipalities.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Nothing contained in any law or enactment for the time being in force  to regulate the erection, re- erection, construction, alteration or  maintenance of buildings within the limits of any municipality shall  apply to any building used or required for the public service or for  any public purpose, which is the property, or in the occupation, of  the Government, or which is to be erected on land which is the  property, or in the occupation, of the Government:</p>
              <p>Provided that, where the erection, re- erection, construction or  material structural alteration of any such building as aforesaid (not  being a building connected with  defence, or a building the</p>
              <p>plan or construction of which ought, in the opinion of  the</p>
              <p>Government concerned], to be treated as confidential or secret) is  contemplated, reasonable notice of the proposed work shall be given to  the municipal authority before it is commenced.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Objections or suggestions as to erection, etc., of certain</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government buildings within municipalities, how to be made and dealt  with.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the case of any such building as is mentioned in the last  preceding section (not being a building connected with  defence or  a building the plan or construction of which ought, in the opinion of    the Government concerned], to be treated as confidential or   secret), the municipal authority, or any person authorized by it in  this behalf, may, with the permission of the State Government  previously obtained, but not otherwise, and subject to any  restrictions or conditions which may, by general or special order, be  imposed by the State Government, inspect the land and building and all  plans connected with its erection, re- erection, construction or  material structural alteration, as the case may be, and may submit to  the State Government a statement in writing of any objections or  suggestions which such municipal authority may deem fit to make with  reference to such erection, re- erection, construction or material  structural alteration.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every objection or suggestion submitted as aforesaid shall be  considered by the State Government, which shall, after such  investigation (if any) as it shall think advisable, pass orders  thereon, and the building referred to therein shall be erected, re-</p>
              <p>erected, constructed or altered, as the case may be, in accordance  with such orders:</p>
              <p>Provided that, if the State Government overrules or disregards  any such objection or suggestion as aforesaid, it shall give its  reasons for so doing in writing.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </part>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
