<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1972/59/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1972/59"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Former Secretary Of State Service Officers (Conditions Of Service) Act, 1972."/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1972/59/eng@1972-09-21/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1972/59/eng@1972-09-21"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1972-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1972/59/eng@1972-09-21/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1972/59/eng@1972-09-21"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Former Secretary Of State Service Officers (Conditions Of Service) Act, 1972.</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 59 OF 1972</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 21st September, 1972.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- third Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the variation or revocation of the  conditions of service of former Secretary of State Service officers in  respect of certain matters and for matters connected therewith or  incidental thereto.</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Former Secretary of State Service Officers (Conditions of Service)</p>
            <p>Act, 1972.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such  date as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" appointed day" means the date on which this Act comes  into force;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" former Secretary of State Service officer" means a  person referred to in sub- clause (a) or sub- clause (b) of  clause (1) of article 312A of the Constitution;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" I. C. S. member of the Indian Administrative Service"</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>means a person who was appointed to the Civil Service of the</p>
            <p>Crown in India known as the Indian Civil Service and who on  the appointed day is a member of the Indian Administrative</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Service;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>" I. P. member of the Indian Police Service" means a  person who was appointed to the Police Service of the Crown  in India known as the Indian Police and who on the appointed  day is a member of the Indian Police Service;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>" pension" has the meaning assigned to it in clause</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-2.17">
          <num>(17)</num>
          <content>
            <p>, of article 366 of the Constitution.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Conditions of service of I. C. S. members of the Indian</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Administrative Service. Subject to the other provisions of this Act,</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>on and from the appointed day,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>the conditions of service as respects,-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2.a.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>remuneration,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2.a.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>leave, and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2.a.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>pension;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the rights as respects disciplinary matters; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the conditions of service and the rights as respects  all other matters,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>of the I. CS. members of the Indian Administrative Service shall be the  same as those of the other members of that Service and accordingly and  subject as aforesaid, the provisions of the All- India Services Act,</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1951">
        <num>1951.</num>
        <heading>(61 of 1951) and the rules and regulations made or deemed to have  been made thereunder, as in force from time to time, shall apply to  and in relation to the I. C. S. members of the Indian Administrative</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1951.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Service as they apply to and in relation to the other members of that</p>
            <p>Service.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Conditions of service of I. P. members of the Indian Police</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Service. Subject to the other provisions of this Act, on and from the  appointed day,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>the conditions of service as respects,-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>remuneration,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>leave, and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>pension;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the rights as respects disciplinary matters; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the conditions of service and the rights as respects  all other matters,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>of the I. P. members of the Indian Police Service shall be the same as  those of the other members of that Service and accordingly and subject  as aforesaid, the provisions of the All- India Services Act, 1951 and  the 61 rules and regulations made or deemed to have been made  thereunder, as in force from time to time, shall apply to and in  relation to the I. P. members of the Indian Police Service as they  apply to and in relation to the other members of that Service.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Pay of I. C. S. members of Indian Administrative Services and</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>I. P. members of Indian Police Service. Notwithstanding anything  contained in section 3 or section 4, an I. C. S. member of the Indian</p>
            <p>Administrative Service or an I. P. member of the Indian Police Service,</p>
            <p>as the case may be, holding a post specified- in the Schedule or a  post declared by the Central Government to be equivalent to such post  shall, for so long as he holds that post, be entitled to draw pay as  indicated against the post in the Schedule.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Retirement of I. C. S. of members of Indian Administrative</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Service and I. P. members of Indian Police Service. Notwithstanding  anything contained in section 3 or section 4,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>an I. C. S. member of the Indian Administrative Service,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>unless his service has been extended before the appointed day  in</p>
            <p>accordance with the rules and regulations then applicable or  is extended on or after that day in accordance with the rules  and regulations applicable to the other members of the Indian</p>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Administrative Service, shall retire compulsorily,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list5.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>where he attains the age of fifty- eight years before  the expiry of six months from the appointed day, on the date  of expiry of the said period of six months or on the date on  which he shall retire compulsorily in accordance with the  rules applicable to him immediately before the appointed day,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list7">
              <listIntroduction>whichever date is earlier;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list7.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>in any other case, on his attaining the age of fifty-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list9">
              <listIntroduction>eight years;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list9.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the Central Government shall have and shall be deemed  always to have had the power to require an I. C. S. member of  the Indian Administrative Service or an I. P. member of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list11">
              <listIntroduction>Indian Police Service, in consultation with the Government of  the State on whose cadre he is borne and after giving to such  member at least three months' previous notice in writing, to  retire in public interest from service on the date on which  such member completes thirty years of qualifying service or  attains fifty years of age or on any date thereafter to be  specified in the notice;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list11.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>an I. C. S. member of the Indian Administrative Service  or an I. P. member of the Indian Police Service may, after  giving at least three months' previous notice in writing to  the Government of the State on whose cadre he is borne,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>retire from service on the date on which such member  completes thirty years of qualifying service or attains fifty  years of age or on any date thereafter to be specified in the  notice:</p>
            <p>Provided that no member under suspension shall retire from  service except with the specific approval of the Government of the</p>
            <p>State on whose cadre he is borne.</p>
            <p>Explanation.- For the purposes of clause (b) and clause (c),</p>
            <p>" qualifying service" means service qualifying for purposes of pension.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Pension of I. C. S. members of Indian Administrative Service.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in section 3,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>an I. C. S. member of the Indian Administrative Service  shall, subject to the provisions of section 8 and subject to  the same provisions in regard to the right of the Central</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Government to withdraw the whole or any part of pension or to  order recovery of pension and the same conditions for grant  of retirement benefits, as are applicable for the time being  in the case</p>
            <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>of other members of the Indian Administrative Service, be  entitled on his retirement from service in accordance with  the provisions of section 6, to receive by way of annuity  rupees thirteen thousand three hundred and thirty- three and  one- third;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>no death- cum- retirement gratuity benefits shall be  available to or in respect of an I. C. S. member of the Indian</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Administrative Service unless such member has exercised his  option for such benefits before the appointed day in  accordance with the orders of the Central Government in that  behalf and the benefits admissible to or in relation to an</p>
            <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list7">
              <listIntroduction>I. C. S. member of the Service who so exercised his option  shall be subject to the conditions specified in the said  orders and to the same conditions for grant of retirement  benefits as are applicable for the time being in the case of  other members of the Indian Administrative Service;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list7.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>no family pension benefits shall be admissible in  relation to an I. C. S. member of the Indian Administrative</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list9">
              <listIntroduction>Service unless such member exercised his option in respect of  such benefits before the appointed day in accordance with the  orders of the Central Government in that behalf and the  benefits admissible in relation to an I. C. S. member of the  service who so exercised his option shall be subject to the  conditions specified in the said orders;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list9.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the Provident Fund account of an I. C. S. member of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Indian Administrative Service shall be credited, on his  retirement or previous death, with the same amount, if any,</p>
            <p>as would have been credited by way of contribution in  accordance with the rules in force immediately before the  appointed day.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Pension payable to former Secretary of State Service officers  in Indian currency only.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>No former Secretary of State Service  officer shall be entitled, or be deemed ever to have been entitled, to  claim,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>pension in sterling; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>that his pension shall be paid outside India; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>where his pension was expressed in sterling or a fixed  sterling minimum was applicable in respect of the pension  payable to him, that his pension shall be computed in the  rupee equivalent of the amount fixed in sterling at a rate of  exchange exceeding the rate of rupees thirteen and one- third  to the pound sterling:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that in relation to every former Secretary of State</p>
            <p>Service officer who, having been in service on the 1st day of</p>
            <p>February, 1921, and</p>
            <p>domiciled in India on that date, is entitled immediately before the  appointed day to claim his pension computed in the rupee equivalent of  the amount fixed in sterling at a rate of exchange of rupees fifteen  to a pound sterling, clause (c) shall have effect as if for the words</p>
            <p>" thirteen and one third", the word" fifteen" were substituted:</p>
            <p>Provided further that every former Secretary of State Service  officer whose pension was expressed in sterling or in respect of whose  pension a fixed sterling minimum was applicable, and who, immediately  before the appointed day, is a foreigner having taken up permanent  residence outside India, shall, so long as he continues to be a  foreigner permanently residing outside India, be allowed to convert  the annuity of rupees thirteen thousand three hundred and thirty- three  and one- third or the annuity actually payable to him in rupees,</p>
            <p>whichever is less, into pound sterling at the rate of rupees thirteen  and one- third to a pound sterling, and the annuity so converted into  pound sterling shall be paid outside India,</p>
            <p>Explanation 1.- Nothing contained in the foregoing proviso shall  be deemed to entitle any former Secretary of State Service officer to  claim conversion of amounts representing the annuity or the commuted  value thereof, already drawn in rupees before the commencement of the</p>
            <p>Former Secretary of State Service Officers (Conditions of Service)</p>
            <p>Amendment Act, 1975, into pound sterling.</p>
            <p>Explanation 2.- In this sub- section, the expression" foreigner"</p>
            <p>means a person who is not a citizen of India.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding any judgment, decree or order of any court,</p>
            <p>every former Secretary of State Service officer not being an  officer to whom the first proviso or the second proviso to sub- section</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>applies who has been paid the rupee equivalent or, as the case  may be, the pound sterling equivalent of his pension by calculating  such pension with reference to a rate of exchange exceeding the rate  of exchange of rupees thirteen and one- third to the pound sterling,</p>
            <p>shall refund to the Central Government or, as the case may be, the</p>
            <p>State Government, the sum by which the amount paid to him exceeds the  amount which would have been payable to him if the calculation had  been made at the rate of exchange of rupees thirteen and one- third to  the pound sterling and the Central Government or the State Government  may set off, in such manner as it may deem fit, the amount required to  be so refunded to it by any such officer against any sum (including   pension) which is or which may become due from that Government to such  officer.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that the  provisions of sub- sections (1) and (2) shall apply to a former</p>
            <p>Secretary of State Service officer who is holding or has held the  office of the Chief Justice</p>
            <p>or other Judge of the Supreme Court or a High Court, the Comptroller  and Auditor- General of India, the Chairman or other member of the</p>
            <p>Union or a State Public Service Commission or the Chief Election</p>
            <p>Commissioner as they apply to other former Secretary of State Service  officers.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to adapt certain rules, regulations  and orders.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of bringing the provisions of any  rules and regulations made or deemed to have been made under the All-</p>
            <p>India Services Act, 1951 (61 of 1951), or any rules, regulations or  orders (including any other instrument having the force of law)</p>
            <p>applicable immediately before the appointed day to or in relation to  former Secretary of State Service officers into accord with the  provisions of this Act, the Central Government may, before the expiry  of two years from the appointed day, by order published in the</p>
            <p>Official Gazette, make such adaptations and modifications of such  rules, regulations or orders, whether by way of repeal or amendment,</p>
            <p>as may be necessary.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of sub- section (1) shall be in addition to  and not in derogation of any power under any other law to amend or  repeal the rules, regulations and orders referred to in that sub-</p>
            <p>section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Power to construe rules, regulations and orders.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding that no provision or insufficient provision has been  made under section 9 for the adaptation of any rule, regulation or  order referred to in that section, any court, tribunal or authority,</p>
            <p>required or empowered to enforce such rule, regulation or order may  construe it with such modifications as may be necessary to bring it  into accord with the provisions of- this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10A">
        <num>10A.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to make orders in certain cases  to ensure parity.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the Central Government is satisfied that the  conditions of service as respects any matter applicable to, or in  relation to, any class or category of former Secretary of State</p>
            <p>Service officers under section 6, 7 or 8 or as respects any benefits  by way of compensation for the increase in cost of living or any other  reason, have become less favourable than those applicable to or in  relation to any corresponding class or category of other officers of  the Indian Administrative Service or the Indian Police Service or, as  the case may be, any comparable service, it may, notwithstanding  anything contained in those sections, by general or special order and  subject to such conditions and restrictions (including conditions as   to refund, adjustment or recovery), as may be specified therein, make  such provisions as it may deem fit for securing, so far as may be,</p>
            <p>parity in such cases.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any order under sub- section (1) may be made so as to have  retrospective effect.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every order made under sub- section (1) shall be laid, as  soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament while  it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be  comprised</p>
            <p>in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before  the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the  successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the order or both Houses agree that the order should  not be made, the order shall thereafter have effect only in such  modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however,</p>
            <p>that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to  the validity of anything previously done under that order.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Power to remove difficulties.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any difficulty arises in  giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government  may, by general or special order published in the Official Gazette,</p>
            <p>for the purpose of removing the difficulty, make such provisions not  inconsistent with the provisions of this Act as appear to it to be  necessary or expedient:</p>
            <p>Provided that no such order shall be made under this sub- section  after the expiry of three years from the appointed day.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every order made under sub- section (1) shall, as soon as may  be after it is made, be laid before each House of Parliament.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Act to have overriding effect. The provisions of this Act or  of any order made thereunder shall have effect notwithstanding  anything inconsistent therewith contained in any law other than this</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Act or in any rule, regulation or order or other instrument having  effect by virtue of any law other than this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Saving of orders in respect of disciplinary matters. Any order  in respect of disciplinary matters in relation to any I. C. S. member of  the Indian Administrative Service or any I. P. member of the Indian</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Police Service in force immediately before the appointed day shall  continue in force as from the appointed day:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing in this section shall derogate from the  powers of the competent authority to vary or rescind such order.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
