<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1959/47/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1959/47"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Rajasthan And Madhya Pradesh (Transfer Of Territories) Act, 1959"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1959/47/eng@1959-09-18/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1959/47/eng@1959-09-18"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1959-09-18" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1959/47/eng@1959-09-18/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1959/47/eng@1959-09-18"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Rajasthan And Madhya Pradesh (Transfer Of Territories) Act, 1959</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 47 OF 1959</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 18th September, 1959.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Tenth Year of the Republic of</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the transfer of certain territories from the</p>
        <p>State of Rajasthan to the State of Madhya Pradesh and for matters  connected therewith.</p>
        <p>India as follows:--</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title. This Act may be called the Rajasthan and Madhya</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Pradesh (Transfer of Territories) Act, 1959.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" appointed day" means the 1st day of October, 1959;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" assembly constituency"," council constituency" and</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>" parliamentary constituency" have the same meanings as  in the Representation of the People Act, 1950 (43 of</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1950">
        <num>1950.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1950.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>).</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" sitting member", in relation to either House of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Parliament or of the Legislature of a State, means a  person who, immediately before the appointed day, is a  member of that House;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>" transferred territories" means the territories  specified in the First Schedule and transferred from  the State of Rajasthan to the State of Madhya Pradesh  by section 3.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Transfer of territories from Rajasthan to Madhya Pradesh.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>As from the appointed day, there shall be added to the State of Madhya</p>
            <p>Pradesh the territories specified in the First Schedule which shall  thereupon cease to form part of the State of Rajasthan.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The transferred territories shall be included in, and form  part of, Bhanpura pargana of Mandsaur district in the State of Madhya</p>
            <p>Pradesh.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in sub- section (2) shall be deemed to affect the  power of the State Government to alter after the appointed day the  name, extent or boundaries of any district in the State of Madhya</p>
            <p>Pradesh.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of the First Schedule to the Constitution. As from  the appointed day, in the First Schedule to the Constitution, under  the heading" I. THE STATES",--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in the entry against" 6. Madhya Pradesh", after the  words and figures" States Reorganisation Act, 1956",</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>the words, brackets and figures" and the First Schedule  to the Rajasthan and Madhya Pradesh (Transfer of</p>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Territories) Act, 1959" shall be inserted;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in the entry against" 11. Rajasthan", after the words  and figures" States Reorganisation Act, 1956", the  words, brackets and figures" but excluding the  territories specified in the First Schedule to the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Rajasthan and Madhya Pradesh (Transfer of Territories)</p>
            <p>Act, 1959" shall be inserted.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Amendments of Delimitation Orders. The Delimitation of</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Parliamentary and Assembly Constituencies Order, 1956, and the</p>
            <p>Delimitation of Council Constituencies (Madhya Pradesh) Order, 1957,</p>
            <p>shall have effect subject to the modifications specified in the Second</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-schedule">
      <doc name="schedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1959/47/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1959/47"/>
              <FRBRalias value="Schedule"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1959/47/eng@1959-09-18/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1959/47/eng@1959-09-18"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1959/47/eng@1959-09-18/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1959/47/eng@1959-09-18"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="schedule">
            <section id="section-6">
              <num>6.</num>
              <heading>Provision as to sitting members.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-6.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The sitting members of  the House of the People representing Mandsaur constituency in the</p>
                  <p>State of Madhya Pradesh and Kotah constituency in the State of</p>
                  <p>Rajasthan shall, notwithstanding the alteration in the extent of those  constituencies by virtue of the provisions of this Act, continue to be  members of the House of the People.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-6.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The sitting members of the Legislative Assemblies of Madhya</p>
                  <p>Pradesh and Rajasthan representing Garoth constituency and begun  constituency respectively shall, notwithstanding the alteration in the  extent of those constituencies by virtue of the provisions of this</p>
                  <p>Act, continue to be members of the said Assemblies.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-7">
              <num>7.</num>
              <heading>Extension of jurisdiction of Madhya Pradesh High Court.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-7.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-7.1.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>As  from the appointed day,--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-7.1.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the jurisdiction of the High Court of Madhya Pradesh  shall extend to the transferred territories; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-7.1.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>the High Court of Rajasthan shall have no jurisdiction  in respect of the said territories.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-7.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>If, immediately before the appointed day, there is any  proceeding relatable to the transferred territories pending in the</p>
                  <p>High Court of Rajasthan, then, notwithstanding anything contained in  sub- section (1), such proceeding shall be heard and disposed of by  that High Court.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-7.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Any order made by the High Court of Rajasthan in any  proceeding with respect to which that High Court exercises juris-</p>
                  <p>diction by virtue of sub- section (2), shall, for all purposes, have  effect, not only as an order of the High Court of Rajasthan, but also  as an order made by the High Court of Madhya Pradesh.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-7.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-7.4.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>For the purposes of this section,--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-7.4.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>proceedings shall be deemed to be pending in the High</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Court of Rajasthan until that Court has disposed of all  issues between the parties, including any issues with  respect to the taxation of the costs of the proceedings  and shall include appeals, applications for leave to  appeal to the Supreme Court, applications for review,</p>
                  <blockList id="section-7.4.list4">
                    <listIntroduction>petitions for revision and petitions for writs;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-7.4.list4.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>references to a High Court shall be construed as  including references to a Judge or Division Court  thereof, and references to an order made by a Court or  a Judge shall be construed as including references to a  sentence, judgment or decree passed or made by that</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Court or Judge.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-8">
              <num>8.</num>
              <heading>Appropriation of moneys for expenditure in transferred  territories under existing Appropriation Acts. As from the appointed  day, any Act passed by the Legislature of Madhya Pradesh before that  day for the appropriation of any money out of the Consolidated Fund of  the State to meet any expenditure in respect of any part of the  financial year 1959- 60 shall have effect also in relation to the  transferred territories, and it shall be lawful for the State</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Government to spend any amount for those territories out of the amount  authorised by such Act to be expended for any services in that State.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-9">
              <num>9.</num>
              <heading>Assets and liabilities.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-9.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>All land and all stores, articles  and other goods in the transferred territories belonging to the State  of Rajasthan shall, as from the appointed day, pass to the State of</p>
                  <p>Madhya Pradesh.</p>
                  <p>Explanation.-- In this sub- section, the expression" land" includes  immovable property of every kind and any rights in or over such  property and the expression" goods" does not include coins, bank notes  and currency notes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>All rights, liabilities and obligations, whether arising out  of a contract or otherwise, of the State of Rajasthan in relation to  the transferred territories shall, as from the appointed day, be the  rights, liabilities and obligations, respectively, of the State of</p>
                  <p>Madhya Pradesh.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-10">
              <num>10.</num>
              <heading>State Financial Corporations and State Electricity Boards. As  from the appointed day,--</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list0">
                    <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the Financial Corporations constituted under the State</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Financial Corporations Act, 1951 (63 of 1951), for the</p>
                  <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>States of Rajasthan and Madhya Pradesh, and</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>the State Electricity Boards constituted under the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Electricity (Supply) Act, 1948 (54 of 1948), for the  said States,</p>
                  <p>shall be deemed to have been constituted for those States with their  areas as altered by the provisions of section 3.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-11">
              <num>11.</num>
              <heading>Extension of laws. All laws which immediately before the  appointed day extend to, or are in force in, the Mandsaur district in  the State of Madhya Pradesh but do not extend to, or are not in force  in, the transferred territories shall, as from that day, extend to, or  as the case may be, come into force in, the transferred territories;</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>and all laws which, immediately before the appointed day, are in force  in the transferred territories, but not in the Mandsaur district in  the State of Madhya Pradesh, shall, on that day, cease to be in force  in the transferred territories, except as respects things done or  omitted to be done before that day.</p>
                  <p>Explanation.-- In this section" law" includes any enactment,</p>
                  <p>ordinance, regulation, order, bye- law, rule, scheme, notification or  other instrument having the force of law in the whole or in any part  of Madhya Pradesh or Rajasthan.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-12">
              <num>12.</num>
              <heading>Power to construe laws. Any court, tribunal or authority  required or empowered to enforce any law extended to the transferred  territories by section 11 may, for the purpose of facilitating its  application in relation to the transferred territories, construe the  law in such manner, without affecting the substance, as may be  necessary or proper in regard to the matter before the court, tribunal  or authority.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-13">
              <num>13.</num>
              <heading>Legal proceedings. Where, immediately before the appointed  day, the State of Rajasthan is a party to any legal proceedings with  respect to any property, rights or liabilities transferred to the</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>State of Madhya Pradesh under this Act, that State shall be deemed to  be substituted for the State of Rajasthan as a party to those  proceedings, or added as a party thereto, as the case may be, and the  proceedings may continue accordingly.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-14">
              <num>14.</num>
              <heading>Transfer of pending proceedings.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-14.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every proceeding pending  immediately before the appointed day before any court (other than a</p>
                  <p>High Court), tribunal, authority or officer in any area which on that  day falls within the State of Rajasthan shall, if it is a proceeding  relating exclusively to any part of the transferred territories, stand  transferred to the corresponding court, tribunal, authority or officer  in the State of Madhya Pradesh.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-14.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>If any question arises as to whether any proceeding should  stand transferred under sub- section (1), it shall be referred to the</p>
                  <p>High Court of Rajasthan and the decision of that High Court shall be  final.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-14.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-14.3.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>In this section,--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-14.3.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>" proceeding" includes any suit, case or appeal; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-14.3.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>" corresponding court, tribunal, authority or officer" in</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-14.3.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>Madhya Pradesh means--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-14.3.list3.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>the court, tribunal, authority or officer  in which, or before whom, the proceeding would  have lain if the proceeding had been instituted  after the appointed day, or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-14.3.list3.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>in case of doubt, such court, tribunal,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>authority or officer in that State as may be  determined after the appointed day by the</p>
                  <p>Government of Madhya Pradesh, or before the  appointed day by the Government of Rajasthan, to  be the corresponding court, tribunal, authority or  officer.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-15">
              <num>15.</num>
              <heading>Effect of provisions inconsistent with other laws. The  provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything  inconsistent therewith contained in any other law.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-16">
              <num>16.</num>
              <heading>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in  giving effect to the provisions of this Act (including any difficulty  in relation to the transition under section 11 from one law to another   law), the President may by order do anything not inconsistent with any  such provision which appears to him to be necessary for the purpose of  removing the difficulty.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-17">
              <num>17.</num>
              <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-17.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to give effect to the  provisions of this Act.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-17.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as  may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is in  session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in  one session or  in two or more successive sessions, and if, before  the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the  successive sessions aforesaid"] both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not  be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified  form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so however that any such  modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity  of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
