<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1936/16/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1936/16"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Bangalore Marriages Validating Act, 1936"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1936/16/eng@1936-10-27/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1936/16/eng@1936-10-27"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1936-10-27" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1936/16/eng@1936-10-27/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1936/16/eng@1936-10-27"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Bangalore Marriages Validating Act, 1936</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 16 OF 1936.</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 27th October, 1936.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to validate certain marriages solemnized in the Civil and</p>
        <p>Military Station of Bangalore.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS Mr. Walter James McDonald Redwood, a Missionary of the</p>
        <p>Plymouth Brethren, was, in the year 1929, granted by the Resident in</p>
        <p>Mysore a licence, under the Indian Christian Marriage Act, 1872 (XV of</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1872">
        <num>1872.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1872.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>), as applied to the Civil and Military Station of Bangalore to  solemnize marriages within the territories included in the Civil and</p>
            <p>Military Station of Bangalore between persons one of whom was a Native</p>
            <p>Christian subject of Mysore, and neither of whom was a Christian  subject of His Majesty;</p>
            <p>AND WHEREAS the said Walter James McDonald Redwood has, in the belief  that he was authorised so to do, solemnized certain marriagaes in the</p>
            <p>Civil and Military Station of Bangalore between certain Christian  subjects of His Majesty;</p>
            <p>AND WHEREAS the parties to the said marriages all believed that the  said Walter James McDonald Redwood was duly authorised to solemnize  the same, and that such marriages were valid in law;</p>
            <p>AND WHEREAS the said parties being Christian subjects of His Majesty,</p>
            <p>the said Walter James McDonald Redwood had not the requisite authority  under the licence held by him to solemnize the said marriages;</p>
            <p>AND WHEREAS it is expedient that the said marriages, having been  solemnized in good faith, should be validated;</p>
            <p>It is hereby enacted as follows:-</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title.- This Act may be called the Bangalore Marriages</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Validating Act, 1936.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Validation of certain irregular marriages.- All marriages between</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Christian subjects of His Majesty which have already been solemnized  in the Civil and Military Station of Bangalore by Mr. Walter James</p>
            <p>McDonald Redwood, a Missionary of the Plymouth Bre hren, shall be, and  shall be deemed to have been with effect from the date of  solemnization of each respectively, as good and valid in law as if  such marriages had been solemnized under a licence authorizing  solemnization of marriages between Christian s bjects of His Majesty  in the Civil and Military Station of Bangalore.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Validation of records of irregular marriages.- Certificates of  marriages which are declared by section 2 to be good and valid in law,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>and register- books and certified copies of true and duly authenticated  extracts therefrom, deposited in compliance wit the provisions of the</p>
            <p>Indian Christian Marriage Act, 1872 (XV of 1872), in so far as the  register- books and extracts relate to such marriages as aforesaid,</p>
            <p>shall be received as evidence of such marriages as if such marriages  had been duly solemnized und r Part I of the said Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
