<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1884/4/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1884/4"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Explosives Act, 1884"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1884/4/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1884/4/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1884/4/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1884/4/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Explosives Act, 1884</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>*** Explosives Act, 1884; and—(1) This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>*** Explosives Act, 1884; and"</p>
            <p>Local extent.—</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India</p>
            <p>***.—</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India</p>
            <p>***."</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act shall come into force on such day1 as the Central Government, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoints.—</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act shall come into force on such day5 as the Central Government, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoints."</p>
            <p>***</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Repeal of portions of Act 12 of 1875.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Rep. by the Indian Ports Act, 1889 (10 of 1889)1, sec. 2 and Sch. II.—</p>
            <p>Rep. by the Indian Ports Act, 1889 (10 of 1889)7, sec. 2 and Sch. II."</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“aircraft” means any machine which can derive support in the atmosphere from the reactions of the air, other than the reactions of the air against the earth’s surface, and includes baloons, whether fixed or free, airships, kites, gliders and flying machines;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“carriage” includes any carriage, wagon, cart, truck, vehicle or other means of conveying goods or passengers by land, in whatever manner the same may be propelled;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“District Magistrate”, in relation to any area for which a Commissioner of Police has been appointed, means the Commissioner of Police thereof and includes—</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any such Deputy Commissioner of Police, exercising jurisdiction over the whole or any part of such area, as may be specified by the State Government in this behalf in relation to such area or part; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>an Additional District Magistrate;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>“explosive” means gunpowder, nitroglycerine, nitroglycol, gun-cotton, di-nitro-toluene, tri-nitro-toluene, picric acid, di-nitro-phenol, tri-nitro-resorcinol (styphnic acid), cyclo-trimethylene-tri-nitramine, penta-erythritol-tetranitrate, tetryl, nitro-guanidine, lead azide, lead styphynate, fulminate of mercury or any other metal, diazo-di-nitro-phenol, coloured fires or any other substance whether a single chemical compound or a mixture of substances, whether solid or liquid or gaseous used or manufactured with a view to produce a practical effect by explosion or pyrotechnic effect; and includes fog-signals, fireworks, fuses, rockets, percussion-caps, detonators, cartridges, ammunition of all descriptions and every adaptation or preparation of an explosive as defined in this clause;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>“export” means taking out of India to a place outside India by land, sea or air;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>“import” means to bring into India from a place outside India by land, sea or air;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>“master”,—</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in relation to any vessel or aircraft means any person, other than a pilot, harbour master, assistant harbour master or berthing master, having for the time being the charge or control of such vessel or aircraft, as the case may be; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in relation to any boat belonging to a ship, means the master of that ship;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>“manufacture” in relation to an explosive includes the process of—</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>dividing the explosive into its component parts or otherwise breaking up or unmaking the explosive, or making fit for use any damaged explosive; and</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>re-making, altering or repairing the explosive;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>“vessel” includes any ship, boat, sailing vessel, or other description of vessel used in navigation whether propelled by oars or otherwise and anything made for the conveyance, mainly by water, of human beings or of goods and a caisson.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules as to licensing of the manufacture, possession, use, sale, transport, import and export of explosives.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, for any part of India 2 *** make rules3 consistent with this Act to regulate or prohibit, except under and in accordance with the conditions of a licence granted as provided by those rules, the manufacture, possession, use, sale, transport, import and export of explosives, or any specified class of explosives.—</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, for any part of</p>
            <p>India</p>
            <p>*** make rules3 consistent with this Act to regulate or prohibit, except under and in accordance with the conditions of a licence granted as provided by those rules, the manufacture, possession, use, sale,</p>
            <p>transport, import and export of explosives, or any specified class of explosives."</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Rules under this section may provide for all or any of the following, among other matters, that is to say:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the authority by which licences may be granted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the fees to be charged for licences, and the other sums (if any) to be paid for expenses by applicants for licences;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the manner in which applications for licenses must be made, and the matters to be specified in such applications;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the form in which, and the conditions on and subject to which, licences must be granted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the period for which licences are to remain in force; ***</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>***"</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.2.list3.ee">
                <num>(ee)</num>
                <p>the authority to which appeals may be preferred under section 6F, the procedure to be followed by such authority and the period within which appeals shall be preferred, the fees to be paid in respect of such appeals and the circumstances under which such fees may be refunded; (ee) the authority to which appeals may be preferred under section 6F, the procedure to be followed by such authority and the period within which appeals shall be preferred, the fees to be paid in respect of such appeals and the circumstances under which such fees may be refunded;"</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list3.eea">
                <num>(eea)</num>
                <p>the total quantity of explosives that a licensee can purchase in a given period of time;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list3.eeb">
                <num>(eeb)</num>
                <p>the fees to be charged by the Chief Controller of Explosives or any officer authorised by him in this behalf, for services rendered in connection with the manufacture, transport, import or export of explosives;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.2.list3.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the exemption absolutely or subject to conditions of any explosives 6or any person or class of persons from the operation of the rules.or any person or class of persons from the operation of the rules."</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>***</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5A">
        <num>5A.</num>
        <heading>Persons already in business in respect of certain explosives to carry on such business without licence for a certain period.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5A.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything in section 5 or in the rules made thereunder where, immediately before the commencement of the Indian Explosives (Amendment) Act, 1978 (32 of 1978), any person was carrying on the business of manufacture, sale, transport, import or export of any explosive [for which no licence was required under this Act before its amendment by the Indian Explosives (Amendment) Act, 1978, then, such person shall be entitled to continue to carry on such business without licence in respect of such explosive—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5A.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for a period of three months from the date of such commencement; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5A.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>if before the expiry of the said period of three months, such person has made an application for grant of licence under this Act for such business in such explosive, until the final disposal of his application,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>whichever is later.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Power for Central Government to prohibit the manufacture, possession or importation of specially dangerous explosives.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything in the rules under the last foregoing section, the Central Government may, from time to time, by notification in the Official Gazette,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>prohibit, either absolutely or subject to conditions, the manufacture, possession or importation of any explosive which is of so dangerous a character that, in the opinion of the Central Government, it is expedient for the public safety to issue the notification; ***</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>***"</p>
            <p>***</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Customs Act, 1962 (52 of 1962) shall have effect in relation to any explosive with regard to the importation of which a notification has been issued under this section and the vessel, carriage or aircraft containing such explosive as that Act has in relation to any article the importation of which is prohibited or regulated thereunder and the vessel, carriage or aircraft containing such article.</p>
            <p>***</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6A">
        <num>6A.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition of manufacture, possession, sale or transport of explosives by young persons and certain other persons.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6A.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything in the foregoing provisions of this Act,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6A.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-6A.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>no person,—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-6A.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>who has not completed the age of eighteen years, or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-6A.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>who has been sentenced on conviction of any offence involving violence or moral turpitude for a term of not less than six months, at any time during a period of five years after the expiration of the sentence, or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-6A.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>who has been ordered to execute under Chapter VIII of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), a bond for keeping the peace or for good behaviour, at any time during the term of the bond, or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-6A.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>whose licence under this Act has been cancelled, whether before or after the commencement of the Indian Explosives (Amendment) Act, 1978 (32 of 1978), for contravention of the provisions of this Act or of the rules made thereunder, at any time during a period of five years from the date of cancellation of such licence,</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall,—</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-6A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>manufacture, sell, transport, import or export any explosive, or</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6A.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>possess any such explosive as the Central Government may, having regard to the nature thereof, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6A.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-6A.2.list1.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>no person shall sell, deliver or despatch any explosive to a person whom he knows or has reason to believe at the time of such sale, delivery or despatch,—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-6A.2.list1.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>to be prohibited under clause (a) to manufacture, sell, transport, import, export or possess such explosive, or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-6A.2.list1.b.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>to be of unsound mind.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6B">
        <num>6B.</num>
        <heading>Grant of licences.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6B.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a person makes an application for licence under section 5, the authority prescribed in the rules made under that section for grant of licences (hereinafter referred to in this Act as the licensing authority), after making such inquiry, if any, as it may consider necessary, shall, subject to the other provisions of this Act, by order in writing either grant the licence or refuse to grant the same.6B. Grant of licences.—</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6B.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a person makes an application for licence under section 5, the authority prescribed in the rules made under that section for grant of licences (hereinafter referred to in this Act as the licensing authority), after making such inquiry, if any, as it may consider necessary, shall, subject to the other provisions of this Act, by order in writing either grant the licence or refuse to grant the same."</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6B.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6B.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The licensing authority shall grant a licence—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6B.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-6B.2.list1.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>where it is required for the purpose of manufacture of explosives if the licensing authority is satisfied that the person by whom licence is required—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-6B.2.list1.a.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>possesses technical know-how and experience in the manufacture of explosives; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-6B.2.list1.a.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>has in his employment or undertakes to employ a person or persons possessing such technical know-how and experience; or</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6B.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>where it is required for any other purpose, if the licensing authority is satisfied that the person by whom licence is required has a good reason for obtaining the same.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6C">
        <num>6C.</num>
        <heading>Refusal of licences.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6C.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in section 6B, the licensing authority shall refuse to grant a licence—16C. Refusal of licences.—</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6C.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6C.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in section 6B, the licensing authority shall refuse to grant a licence—"</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6C.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>where such licence is required in respect of any prohibited explosives; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6C.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-6C.1.list1.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>where such licence is required by a person whom the licensing authority has reason to believe—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-6C.1.list1.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>to be prohibited by this Act or by any other law for the time being in force to manufacture, possess, sell, transport, import or export any explosive, or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-6C.1.list1.b.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>to be of unsound mind, or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-6C.1.list1.b.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>to be for any reason unfit for a licence under this Act; or</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6C.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>where the licensing authority deems it necessary for the security of the public peace or for public safety to refuse to grant such licence.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6C.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the licensing authority refuses to grant a licence to any person it shall record in writing the reasons for such refusal and furnish to that person on demand a brief statement of the same unless in any case the licensing authority is of opinion that it will not be in the public interest to furnish such statement.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6D">
        <num>6D.</num>
        <heading>Licensing authority competent to impose conditions in addition to prescribed conditions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6D.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A licence granted under section 6B may contain in addition to prescribed conditions such other conditions as may be considered necessary by the licensing authority in any particular case.1[6D. Licensing authority competent to impose conditions in addition to prescribed conditions.—</p>
            <p>A licence granted under section 6B may contain in addition to prescribed conditions such other conditions as may be considered necessary by the licensing authority in any particular case."</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6E">
        <num>6E.</num>
        <heading>Variation, suspension and revocation of licences.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6E.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The licensing authority may vary the conditions subject to which a licence has been granted except such of them as have been prescribed and may for that purpose require the holder of licence by notice in writing to deliver-up the licence to it within such time as may be specified in the notice.6E. Variation, suspension and revocation of licences.—</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6E.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The licensing authority may vary the conditions subject to which a licence has been granted except such of them as have been prescribed and may for that purpose require the holder of licence by notice in writing to deliver-up the licence to it within such time as may be specified in the notice."</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6E.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The licensing authority may, on the application of the holder of a licence, also vary the conditions of the licence except such of them as have been prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6E.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6E.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The licensing authority may, by order in writing, suspend a licence for such period as it thinks fit or revoke a licence,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6E.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>if the licensing authority is satisfied that the holder of the licence is prohibited by this Act or by any other law for the time being in force to manufacture, possess, sell, transport, import or export any explosive, or is of unsound mind, or is for any reason unfit for a licence under this Act; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6E.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>if the licensing authority deems it necessary for the security of the public peace or for public safety to suspend or revoke the licence; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6E.3.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>if the licence was obtained by the suppression of material information or on the basis of wrong information provided by the holder of the licence or any other person on his behalf at the time of applying for the licence; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6E.3.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>if any of the conditions of the licence has been contravened; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6E.3.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>if the holder of the licence has failed to comply with a notice under sub-section (1) requiring him to deliver-up the licence.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6E.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The licensing authority may also revoke a licence on the application of the holder thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6E.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the licensing authority makes an order varying the conditions of a licence under sub-section (1) or an order suspending or revoking a licence under sub-section (3), it shall record in writing the reasons therefor and furnish to the holder of the licence on demand a brief statement of the same unless in any case the licensing authority is of the opinion that it will not be in the public interest to furnish such statement.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6E.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A court convicting the holder of a licence of any offence under this Act or the rules made thereunder may also suspend or revoke a licence:</p>
            <p>Provided that if the conviction is set aside on appeal or otherwise, the suspension or revocation shall become void.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6E.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An order of suspension or revocation under sub-section (6) may also be made by an appellate court or by the High Court when exercising its powers of revision.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6E.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by order in the Official Gazette, suspend or revoke, or direct any licensing authority to suspend or revoke, all or any licences granted under this Act throughout India or any part thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6E.9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On the suspension or revocation of a licence under this section the holder thereof shall without delay surrender the licence to the authority by whom it has been suspended or revoked or to such other authority as may be specified in this behalf in the order of suspension or revocation.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6F">
        <num>6F.</num>
        <heading>Appeals.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6F.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person aggrieved by an order of the licensing authority refusing to grant a licence or varying the conditions of a licence or by an order of the licensing authority suspending or revoking a licence may prefer an appeal against that order to such authority (hereinafter referred to as the appellate authority) and within such period as may be prescribed:1[6F. Appeals.—</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6F.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person aggrieved by an order of the licensing authority refusing to grant a licence or varying the conditions of a licence or by an order of the licensing authority suspending or revoking a licence may prefer an appeal against that order to such authority (hereinafter referred to as the appellate authority) and within such period as may be prescribed\:"</p>
            <p>Provided that no appeal shall lie against an order made by, or under the direction of the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6F.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No appeal shall be admitted if it is preferred after the expiry of the period prescribed therefor:</p>
            <p>Provided that an appeal may be admitted after the expiry of the period prescribed therefor if the appellant satisfies the appellate authority that he had sufficient cause for not preferring the appeal within that period.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6F.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The period prescribed for an appeal shall be computed in accordance with the provisions of the Limitation Act, 1963 (36 of 1963), with respect to the computation of periods of limitation thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6F.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every appeal under this section shall be made by a petition in writing and shall be accompanied by a brief statement of the reasons for the order appealed against where such statement has been furnished to the appellant and by such fee as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6F.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In disposing of an appeal the appellate authority shall follow such procedure as may be prescribed:</p>
            <p>Provided that no appeal shall be disposed of unless the appellant has been given a reasonable opportunity of being heard.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6F.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The order appealed against shall, unless the appellate authority conditionally or unconditionally directs otherwise, be in force pending the disposal of the appeal against such order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6F.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every order of the appellate authority confirming, modifying or reversing the order appealed against shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules conferring powers of inspection, search, seizure, detention and removal.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government</p>
            <p>*** may make rules consistent with this Act authorising any officer, either by name or in virtue of his office——(1) The Central Government</p>
            <blockList id="section-7.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>*** may make rules consistent with this Act authorising any officer, either by name or in virtue of his office—"</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.1.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to enter, inspect and examine 2[any place, aircraft, carriage or vessel in which an explosive is being manufactured, possessed, used, sold,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>transported, imported or exported under a licence granted under this Act, or in which he has reason to believe that an explosive has been or is being manufactured, possessed, used, sold,</p>
            <p>transported, imported or exported in contravention of this Act or of the rules made under this Act;any place, aircraft, carriage or vessel in which an explosive is being manufactured, possessed, used, sold,</p>
            <p>transported, imported or exported under a licence granted under this Act, or in which he has reason to believe that an explosive has been or is being manufactured, possessed, used, sold,</p>
            <blockList id="section-7.1.list8">
              <listIntroduction>transported, imported or exported in contravention of this Act or of the rules made under this Act;"</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.1.list8.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to search for explosives therein;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list8.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to make samples of any explosive found therein on payment of the value thereof; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list8.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>to seize, detain and remove any explosive or ingredient thereof found therein and, if necessary, also destroy such explosive or ingredient. (d) to seize, detain and remove any explosive or ingredient thereof found therein and, if necessary, also destroy such explosive or ingredient."</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of the</p>
            <p>Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) relating to searches under that Code shall, so far as the same are applicable, apply to searches by officers authorised by rules under this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Notice of accidents.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whenever there occurs in or about, or in connection with, any place in which an explosive is manufactured, possessed or used, or</p>
            <p>any aircraft, carriage or vessel either conveying an explosive or on or from which an explosive is being loaded or unloaded, any accident by explosion or by fire attended with loss of human life or serious injury to person or property, or of a description usually attended with such loss or injury, the occupier of the place, or</p>
            <p>the master of the aircraft or vessel, or the person in charge of the carriage, as the case may be, shall</p>
            <p>within such time and in such manner as may be by rule prescribed give notice thereof and of the attendant loss of human life or personal injury, if any, to the</p>
            <p>Chief Controller of Explosives and to the officer in charge of the nearest police station.</p>
            <p>***</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Inquiry into accidents.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any accident such as is referred to in section 8 occurs in or about or in connection with</p>
            <p>any place, aircraft, carriage or vessel under the control of any of</p>
            <p>Armed Forces of the Union, an inquiry into the causes of the accident shall be held by the naval, military, or air force authority concerned, and where any such accident occurs in any other circumstances, the District Magistrate</p>
            <p>*** shall, in cases attended by loss of human life, or may, in any other case, hold or direct a Magistrate subordinate to him to hold, such an inquiry.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person holding an inquiry under this section shall have all the powers of a Magistrate in holding an inquiry into an offence under the</p>
            <p>Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) and may exercise such of the powers conferred on any officer by rules under section 7 as he may think it necessary or expedient to exercise for the purposes of the inquiry.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The person holding an inquiry under this section shall make a report to the Central Government stating the causes of the accident and its circumstances.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government may make rules—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to regulate the procedure at inquiries under this section;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.4.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to enable the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Chief Controller of Explosives to be present or represented at any such inquiry;</p>
            <blockList id="section-9.4.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Chief Controller of Explosives to be present or represented at any such inquiry;"</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.4.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to permit the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Chief Controller of Explosives or his representative to examine any witnesses at the inquiry;</p>
            <blockList id="section-9.4.list7">
              <listIntroduction>Chief Controller of Explosives or his representative to examine any witnesses at the inquiry;"</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.4.list7.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>to provide that where the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Chief Controller of Explosives is not present or represented at any such inquiry, a report of the proceedings thereof shall be sent to him;</p>
            <blockList id="section-9.4.list10">
              <listIntroduction>Chief Controller of Explosives is not present or represented at any such inquiry, a report of the proceedings thereof shall be sent to him;"</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.4.list10.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>to prescribe the manner in which and the time within which notices referred to in section 8 shall be given.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>THE EXPLOSIVES ACT, 1884</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9A">
        <num>9A.</num>
        <heading>Inquiry into more serious accidents. —</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, where it is of opinion, whether or not it has received the report of an inquiry under section 9, that an inquiry of more formal character should be held into the causes of an accident such as is referred to in section 8, appoint the 8 [Chief Controller of Explosives or any other competent person to hold such inquiry, and may also appoint one or more persons possessing legal or special knowledge to act as assessors in such inquiry.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the Central Government orders an inquiry under this section, it may also direct that any inquiry under section 9 pending at the time shall be discontinued.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The person appointed to hold an inquiry under this section shall have all the powers of a Civil Court under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), for the purposes of enforcing the attendance of witnesses and compelling the production of documents and material objects; and every person required by such person as aforesaid to furnish any information shall be deemed to be legally bound so to do within the meaning of section 176 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9A.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person holding an inquiry under this section may exercise such of the powers conferred on any officer by rules under section 7 as he may think it necessary or expedient to exercise for the purposes of the inquiry.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9A.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The person holding an inquiry under this section shall make a report to the Central Government stating the causes of the accident and its circumstances, and adding any observations which he or any of the assessors may think fit to make; and the Central Government shall cause every report so made to be published at such time and in such manner as it may think fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9A.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may make rules for regulating the procedure at inquiries under this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9B">
        <num>9B.</num>
        <heading>Punishment for certain offences. — 1) Whoever, in contravention of rules made under section 5 or of the conditions of a licence granted under the said rules—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9B.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9B.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-9B.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>manufactures, imports or exports any explosive shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term, which may extend to three years, or with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees, or with both;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9B.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>possesses, uses, sells or transports any explosive shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years or with fine which may extend to three thousand rupees or with both; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9B.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>in any other case, with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-9B.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever in contravention of a notification issued under section 6 manufactures, possesses or imports any explosive shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years or with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees or with both; and in the case of importation by water, the owner and master of the vessel or in the case of importation by air, the owner and the master of the aircraft, in which the explosive is imported shall, in the absence of reasonable excuse, each be punishable with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9B.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9B.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Whoever,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9B.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>manufactures, sells, transports, imports, exports or possesses any explosive in contravention of the provisions of clause (a) of section 6A; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9B.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>sells, delivers or despatches any explosive in contravention of the provisions of clause (b) of that section,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-9B.3.list3">
              <listIntroduction>shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years or with fine or with both; or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9B.3.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <blockList id="section-9B.3.list3.c.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>in contravention of the provisions of section 8 fails to give notice of any accident shall be punishable,—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-9B.3.list3.c.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-9B.3.list3.c.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>if the accident is attended by loss of human life, with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three months or with fine or with both.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9C">
        <num>9C.</num>
        <heading>Offences by companies. —</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9C.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whenever an offence under this Act has been committed by a company, every person who at the time the offence was committed was in charge of, or was responsible to the company for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to any punishment under this Act if he proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge and that he exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9C.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against the punished accordingly.</p>
            <blockList id="section-9C.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation. —For the purposes of this section,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9C.2.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“company” means any body corporate, and includes a firm or other association of individuals; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9C.2.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“director”, in relation to a firm, means a partner in the firm.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Forfeiture of explosives.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>When a person is convicted of an offence punishable under this Act or the rules made under this Act, the court before which he is convicted may direct that the explosive, or ingredient of the explosive, or the substance (if any) in respect of which the offence has been committed, or any part of that explosive, ingredient or substance, shall, with the receptacles containing the same, be forfeited.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Distress of aircraft or vessel.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where the owner or master of any aircraft or vessel is adjudged under this Act to pay a fine for any offence committed with, or in relation to, that aircraft or vessel, the Court may, in addition to any power it may have for the purpose of compelling payment of the fine, direct it to be levied by distress and sale of,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the aircraft and its furniture or so much of the furniture, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the vessel and the tackle, apparel and furniture of such vessel or so much of the tackle, apparel and furniture thereof,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>as is necessary for the payment of the fine.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Abetment and attempts.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever abets, within the meaning of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860), the commission of an offence punishable under this Act, or the rules made under this Act, attempts to Act, or commit any such offence and in such attempt does any act towards the commission of the same, shall be punished as if he had committed the offence.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Power to arrest without warrant persons committing dangerous offences.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever is found committing any act for which he is punishable under this Act or the rules under this Act, and which tends to cause explosion or fire in or about any place where an explosive is manufactured or stored, or any railway or port, or any carriage,</p>
            <p>aircraft or vessel, may be apprehended without a warrant by a police officer, or by the occupier of, or the agent or servant of, or other person authorised by the occupier of, that place, or by any agent or servant of, or other person authorised by, the railway administration or</p>
            <p>conservator of the port or officer in charge of the airport, and be removed from the place where he is arrested and conveyed as soon as conveniently may be before a Magistrate.—</p>
            <p>Whoever is found committing any act for which he is punishable under this Act or the rules under this Act, and which tends to cause explosion or fire in or about any place where an explosive is manufactured or stored, or any railway or port, or any carriage,</p>
            <p>aircraft or vessel, may be apprehended without a warrant by a police officer, or by the occupier of, or the agent or servant of, or other person authorised by the occupier of, that place, or by any agent or servant of, or other person authorised by, the railway administration or</p>
            <p>conservator of the port or officer in charge of the airport, and be removed from the place where he is arrested and conveyed as soon as conveniently may be before a Magistrate."</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Saving and power to exempt.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Nothing in this Act, except sections 8, 9 and 9A shall apply to the manufacture, possession, use, transport or importation of any explosive—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>by any of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Armed Forces of the Union, and Ordnance factories or other establishments of such Forces in accordance with rules or regulations made by</p>
            <p>*** the Central Government;</p>
            <p>Armed Forces of the Union, and Ordnance factories or other establishments of such Forces in accordance with rules or regulations made by</p>
            <blockList id="section-14.1.list6">
              <listIntroduction>*** the Central Government;"</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.1.list6.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>by any person employed under 4[the Central Government or under a State Government in execution of this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>the Central Government or under a State Government in execution of this Act."</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may by notification in the Official Gazette exempt, absolutely or subject to any such conditions as it may think fit to impose,</p>
            <p>any explosive and any person or class of persons from all or any of the provisions of this Act or the rules made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Saving of Arms Act, 1959.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in this Act shall affect the provisions of the Arms Act, 1959 (54 of 1959):—Nothing in this Act shall affect the provisions of the</p>
            <p>Arms Act, 1959 (54 of 1959)\:"</p>
            <p>Provided that an authority granting a licence under this Act for the manufacture, possession, sale, transport or importation of an explosive may, if empowered in this behalf by the rules under which the licence is granted, direct by an order written on the licence that it shall have the effect of a like licence granted under the said *** Arms Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Saving as to liability under other law.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in this Act or the rules under this Act shall prevent any person from being prosecuted under any other law for any act or omission which constitutes an offence against this Act or those rules, or from being liable under that other law to any other or higher punishment or penalty than that provided by this Act or those rules:</p>
            <p>Provided that a person shall not be punished twice for the same offence.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Extension of definition of “explosive” to other explosive substances.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, from time to time, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare that any substance which appears to the Central Government to be specially dangerous to life or property, by reason either of its explosive properties or of any process in the manufacture thereof being liable to explosion, shall be deemed to be an explosive within the meaning of this Act, and the provisions of this Act (subject to such exceptions, limitations and restrictions as may be specified in the notification) shall accordingly extend to that substance in like manner as if it were included in the definition of the term “explosive” in this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Extension of definition of “explosive” to other explosive substances.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, from time to time, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare that any substance which appears to the Central Government to be specially dangerous to life or property, by reason either of its explosive properties or of any process in the manufacture thereof being liable to explosion, shall be deemed to be an explosive within the meaning of this Act, and the provisions of this Act (subject to such exceptions, limitations and restrictions as may be specified in the notification) shall accordingly extend to that substance in like manner as if it were included in the definition of the term “explosive” in this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17A">
        <num>17A.</num>
        <heading>Power to delegate.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-17A.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that any power or function which may be exercised or performed by it under this Act other than the power under sections 5, 6, 6A, 14 and 17 may, in relation to such matters and subject to such conditions, if any, as it may specify in the notification, be exercised or performed also by—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17A.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>such officer or authority subordinate to the Central Government, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17A.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>such State Government or such officer or authority subordinate to the State Government.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Procedure for making, publication and confirmation of rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An authority making rules under this Act shall, before making the rules, publish a draft of the proposed rules for the information of persons likely to be affected thereby.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The publication shall be made in such manner as the Central Government, from time to time, by notification in the Official Gazette prescribes1.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be published with the draft a notice specifying a date at or after which the draft will be taken into consideration.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The authority making the rules shall receive and consider any objection or suggestion which may be made by any person with respect to the draft before the date so specified.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A rule made under this Act shall not take effect</p>
            <p>*** until it has been published in the Official Gazette</p>
            <p>***.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The publication in the Official Gazette of a rule purporting to be made under this Act shall be conclusive evidence that it has been duly made, and, if it requires sanction, that it has been duly sanctioned.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All powers to make rules conferred by this Act may be exercised from time to time as occasion requires.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
