<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1954/29/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1954/29"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Hyderabad Prisons Act, 1954"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1954/29/eng@2017-01-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1954/29/eng@2017-01-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1954/29/eng@2017-01-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1954/29/eng@2017-01-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Hyderabad Prisons Act, 1954</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[Act No. 29 of 1954]</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the regulation of Prisons in the State of Hyderabad. Whereas it is expedient to provide for the regulation of prisons in the State of Hyderabad;</p>
        <p>Be it enacted in the Fifth Year of our Republic as follows:--</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Hyderabad Prisons Act, 1954.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Hyderabad.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force from the date of its publication in the official Gazette.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Repeal</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Hyderabad Prisons Act (IV of 1317 F.), is hereby repealed:</p>
            <p>Provided that all notifications issued, rules or orders made, and all action taken under the repealed Act shall so far as they are not inconsistent with this Act, be deemed to have been issued, made and taken thereunder:</p>
            <p>Provided further that the provisions of section 3 (v) of the Hyderabad General Clauses Act (III of 1308 F.), shall apply as though the said repealed Act were an enactment repealed by this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context:-</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>'civil prisoner' means any prisoner who is not a criminal prisoner;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>'convicted criminal prisoner' means any criminal prisoner under sentence of a Court or Court-Martial, and includes a person detained in prison under the provisions of Chapter VIII of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (Act V of 1898);</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>'criminal prisoner' means any prisoner duly committed to custody under the writ, warrant or order of any Court or authority exercising criminal jurisdiction, or by order of a Court-Martial;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>'furlough system' means the system of releasing prisoners in jails on furlough in accordance with the rules for the time being in force;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>'history ticket' means the ticket exhibiting such information as is required in respect of each prisoner by this Act or the rules thereunder?;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>'Inspector-General' means the Inspector-General of Prisons;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.7.list1">
              <listIntroduction>'prison' means any jail or place used permanently or temporarily under the general or special orders of Government for the detention of prisoners, and includes all lands and buildings appurtenant thereto, but does not include-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.7.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any place for the confinement of prisoners who are exclusively in the custody of the police;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.7.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any place specially appointed by Government under section 541 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (Act V of 1898);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.7.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any place which has been declared by Government, by general or special order, to be a subsidiary jail;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>'prohibited article' means an article the introduction or removal of which into or out of a prison is prohibited by any rule under this Act;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>'remission system' means the system of regulating the award of marks to, and the consequent shortening of sentences of prisoners in jail in accordance with the rules for the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <heading>Maintenance and officers of prisons</heading>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Accommodation for Prisoners</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Government shall provide, for the prisoners in the State of Hyderabad, accommodation in prisons constructed and regulated in such manner as to comply with the requisitions of this Act in respect of the separation of prisoners.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Inspector-General</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>An Inspector-General shall be appointed by the Government for the State of Hyderabad and shall exercise subject to the orders of the Government, the general control and superintendence of all prisons situated in the whole of the State.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Officers of Prisons</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>For every prison there shall be a Superintendent, a Medical Officer (who may also be the Superintendent), a Jailor or Deputy Jailor and such other officers (including subordinates of the Medical Officer for the purposes of this Act) as the Government thinks necessary.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Temporary accommodation</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Whenever it appears to the Inspector-General that the number of prisoners in any prison is greater than can conveniently or safely be kept therein, and it is not convenient to transfer the excess number to some other prison, or whenever from the outbreak of epidemic disease within any prison, or for any other reason, it is desirable to provide for the temporary shelter and safe custody of any prisoners, provision shall be made, by such officer and in such manner as Government may direct, for the shelter and safe custody in temporary prisons of so many of the prisoners as cannot be conveniently or safely kept in the prison.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <heading>Duties of officers generally</heading>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Control and duties of officers of prisons</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>All Officers of a prison shall obey the directions of the Superintendent; all officers subordinate to the Jailor shall perform such duties as may be imposed on them by the Jailor with the sanction of the Superintendent or be prescribed by rules under section 59.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Officers not to have business dealings with prisoners</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No officer of a prison shall sell or let, nor shall any person in trust for or employed by him sell or let, or derive any benefit from selling or letting, any article to any prisoner or have any money or other business dealings directly or indirectly with any prisoner.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Officers not to be interested in prison contracts</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No officer of a prison shall, nor shall any person in trust for or employed by him, have any interest, direct or indirect, in any contract for the supply of the prison; nor shall he derive any benefit, directly or indirectly, from the sale or purchase of any article on behalf of the prison or belonging to a prisoner.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Superintendent</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the orders of the Inspector-General, the Superintendent shall manage the prison in all matters relating to discipline, labour, expenditure, punishment and control.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to such general or special directions as may be given by the Government, the Superintendent of a prison other than a central prison shall obey all orders not inconsistent with this Act or any rule thereunder which may be given respecting the prison by the Collector, and shall report to the Inspector-General all such orders and the action taken thereon.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Records to be kept by Superintendent</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Superintendent shall keep, or cause to be kept, the following records:-</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-12.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>a register of prisoners admitted</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>a book showing when each prisoner is to be released;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>a punishment book for the entry of the punishments inflicted on prisoners for prison offences;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>a visitors' book for the entry of any observations made by the visitors touching any matters connected with the administration of the prison;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>a record of the money and other articles taken from prisoners; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>all such other records as may be prescribed by rules under section 59. Medical Officer.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Duties of Medical Officer</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the control of the Superintendent, the Medical Officer shall have charge of the sanitary administration of the prison, and shall perform such duties as may be prescribed by rules made by the Government under section 59.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Medical Officer to report in certain cases</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Whenever the Medical Officer has reason to believe that the mind of a prisoner is, or is likely to be, injuriously affected by the discipline or treatment to which he is subjected, the Medical Officer shall report the case in writing to the Superintendent, together with such observations as he may think proper.</p>
              <p>This report, with the orders of the Superintendent thereon, shall forthwith be sent to the Inspector-General for information.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Report on death of Prisoner</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>On the death of any prisoner, the Medical Officer shall forthwith record in a register the following particulars, so far as they can be ascertained, namely :--</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-15.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the day on which the deceased first complained of illness or was observed to be ill,</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the labour, if any, on which he was engaged on that day,</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the scale of his diet on that day,</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the day on which the Medical Officer was first informed of the illness,</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the day on which he was admitted to hospital,</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the nature of the disease,</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>when the deceased was last seen before his death by the Medical Officer or his subordinate,</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>when the prisoner died and reasons therefor, and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <p>(in cases where a post-mortem examination is made) an account of the appearances after death together with any special remarks that appear to the Medical Officer to be required.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Jailor</heading>
          <subsection id="section-16.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Jailor shall reside in the prison, unless the Superintendent permits him in writing to reside elsewhere.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Jailor shall not, without the Inspector-General's sanction in writing, be concerned in any other employment.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Jailor to give notice of death of prisoner</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Upon the death of a prisoner, the Jailor shall give immediate notice thereof to the Superintendent and the Medical Officer,</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Responsibility of Jailor</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Jailor shall be responsible for the safe custody of the records to be kept under section 12 for the commitment warrants and all other documents confided to his care and for the money and other articles taken from prisoners.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Jailor to be present at night</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Jailor shall not be absent from the prison for a night without permission in writing from the Superintendent, but, if absent without leave for a night from unavoidable necessity, he shall</p>
              <p>immediately report the fact and the cause of it to the Superintendent.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Powers of Deputy and Assistant Jailors</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Where a Deputy Jailor or Assistant Jailor is appointed to a prison, he shall, subject to the orders of the Superintendent, be competent to perform any of the duties, and be subject to all the responsibilities, of a Jailor under this Act or any rule thereunder.</p>
              <p>Subordinate Officers.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Duties of gate-keeper</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Officer acting as gate-keeper, or any other officer of the prison, may examine anything carried in or out of the prison, and may stop and search or cause to be searched any person suspected of bringing any prohibited article into or out of the prison, or of carrying out any property belonging to the prison, and, if any such article or property be found, shall give immediate notice thereof to the Jailor.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Subordinate Officers not to be absent without leave</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Officers subordinate to the Jailor shall not be absent from the prison without leave from the Superintendent or from the Jailor.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Convict officers</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Prisoners who have been appointed as officers of prisons shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of the Indian Penal Code (XLV of 1860).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <heading>Admission, removal and discharge of prisoners</heading>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Prisoners to be examined on admission</heading>
          <subsection id="section-24.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Whenever a prisoner is admitted into prison, he shall be searched, and all weapons and prohibited articles shall be taken from him.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-24.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every criminal prisoner shall also, as soon as possible after admission, be examined under the general or special orders of the Medical Officer, who shall enter or cause to be entered in a book, to be kept by the Jailor, a record of the state of the prisoner's health, and of any wounds or marks on his person, the class of labour he is fit for if sentenced to rigorous, imprisonment, and any observations which the Medical Officer thinks fit to add.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-24.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the case of female prisoners, the search and examination shall be carried out by the matron under the general or special orders of the Medical Officer.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Effects of prisoners</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>All money or other articles in respect whereof no order of a competent Court has been made, and which may with proper authority be brought into the prison by any criminal prisoner or sent to the prison for his use, shall be placed in the custody of the Jailor and the prisoner shall be informed with his signature being taken in the prescribed register.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Removal and discharge of prisoners</heading>
          <subsection id="section-26.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All prisoners, previously to being removed to any other prison, shall be examined by the Medical Officer.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-26.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No prisoner shall be removed from one prison to another unless the Medical Officer certifies that the prisoner is free from any illness rendering him unfit for removal.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-26.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No prisoner shall be discharged against his will from prison, if labouring under any acute or dangerous distemper, nor until, in the opinion of the Medical Officer, such discharge is safe.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <heading>Discipline of prisoners</heading>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Separation of prisoners</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The requisitions of this Act with respect to the separation of prisoners are as follows :--</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-27.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>in a prison containing female as well as male prisoners, the females shall be imprisoned in separate buildings, or separate parts of the same building, in such manner as to prevent their seeing, or conversing or holding any intercourse with the male prisoners;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>in a prison where male prisoners under the age of 21 (twenty-one) years are confined, means shall be provided for separating them altogether from the other prisoners and for separating those of them who have arrived at the age of puberty from those who have not;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>unconvicted criminal prisoners shall be kept apart from convicted criminal prisoners; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>civil prisoners shall be kept apart from criminal prisoners.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Association and segregation of prisoners</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the requirements of the last foregoing section, convicted criminal prisoners may be confined either in association or individually in cells or partly in one way and partly in the other.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Solitary confinement</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-29.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No cell shall be used for solitary confinement unless it is furnished with the means of enabling the prisoner to communicate at any time with an officer of the prison, and every prisoner so</p>
              <p>confined in a cell for more than twenty-four hours, whether as a punishment or otherwise, shall be visited at least once a day by the Medical, Officer or his subordinate.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading>Prisoners under sentence of death</heading>
          <subsection id="section-30.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every prisoner under sentence of death shall, immediately on his arrival in the prison after sentence, be searched by, or by order of, the Jailor, and all articles shall be taken from him which the Jailor deems dangerous or inexpedient to leave in his possession.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-30.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every such prisoner shall be confined in a cell apart from all other prisoners, and shall be placed by day and by night under the charge of a guard.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VI">
        <num>VI</num>
        <heading>Food, clothing and betiding of civil and unconvicted criminal prisoners</heading>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading>Maintenance of certain prisoners from private sources</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-31.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>A civil prisoner or an unconvicted criminal prisoner shall be permitted to maintain himself, and to purchase, or receive from private sources at proper hours, food, clothing, bedding or writing material, books, newspapers or other necessaries, but subject to examination and to such rules as may be approved by the Inspector-General.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>Restriction on transfer of food and clothing between certain prisoners</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-32.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No part of any food, clothing, bedding, or other necessaries belonging to any civil or unconvicted criminal prisoner shall be given, hired or sold to any other prisoner; and any prisoner transgressing the provisions of this section shall lose the privilege of purchasing food or receiving it from private sources, for such time as the Superintendent thinks proper.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading>Supply of clothing and bedding to civil and unconvicted criminal prisoners</heading>
          <subsection id="section-33.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every civil prisoner and unconvicted criminal prisoner unable to provide himself with sufficient clothing and bedding shall be supplied by the Superintendent with such clothing and bedding as may be necessary.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-33.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When any civil prisoner has been committed to prison in execution of a decree in favour of a private person, such person, or his representative, shall, within forty-eight hours after the receipt by him of a demand in writing, pay to the Superintendent the cost of clothing and beading so supplied to the prisoner; and in default of such payment the prisoner may be released.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VII">
        <num>VII</num>
        <heading>Employment of prisoners</heading>
        <section id="section-34">
          <num>34.</num>
          <heading>Employment of civil prisoners</heading>
          <subsection id="section-34.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Civil prisoners may, with the Superintendent's permission, work and follow any trade or profession.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-34.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Civil prisoners finding their own implements, and not maintained at the expense of the prison, shall be allowed to receive the whole of their earnings; but the earnings of such as are furnished with implements or are maintained at the expense of the prison shall be subject to a deduction, to be determined by the Superintendent, for use of implements and the cost of maintenance.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading>Employment of criminal prisoners</heading>
          <subsection id="section-35.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No criminal prisoner sentenced to labour or employed on labour at his own desire shall, except on an emergency with the sanction in writing of the Superintendent, be kept to labour for more than eight hours in any one day.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-35.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Medical Officer shall from time to time examine the labouring prisoners while they are employed and shall at least once in every fortnight cause to be recorded upon history ticket of each prisoner employed on labour the weight of such prisoner at the time.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-35.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When the Medical Officer is of opinion that the health of any prisoner suffers from employment on any kind or class of labour, such prisoner shall not be employed on that labour but shall be placed on such other kind or class of labour as the Medical Officer may consider suited for him.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-36">
          <num>36.</num>
          <heading>Employment of criminal prisoners sentenced to simple imprisonment</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-36.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Provision shall be made by the Superintendent for the employments (as long as they so desire) of all criminal prisoners sentenced to simple imprisonment; but no prisoner not sentenced to rigorous imprisonment shall be punished for neglect of work excepting by such alteration in the scale of diet as may be established by the rules of the prison in the case of neglect of work by such a prisoner.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VIII">
        <num>VIII</num>
        <heading>Health of prisoners</heading>
        <section id="section-37">
          <num>37.</num>
          <heading>Sick prisoners</heading>
          <subsection id="section-37.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The names of prisoners desiring to see the Medical Officer or his subordinate or appearing out of health, in mind or body shall, without delay, be reported by the officer in immediate charge of such prisoners to the Jailor.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-37.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Jailor shall, without delay, call the attention of the Medical Officer or his subordinate to any prisoner desiring to see him, or who is ill, or whose state of mind or body appears to require attention, and shall carry into effect all written directions given by the Medical Officer or his subordinate respecting alterations of the discipline or treatment of any such prisoner.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-38">
          <num>38.</num>
          <heading>Record of directions of Medical Officers</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-38.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>All directions given by the Medical Officer or his subordinate in relation to any prisoner, with the exception of orders for the supply of medicines or directions relating to such matters as are carried into effect by the Medical Officer himself or under his superintendence, shall be entered day by day in the prisoner's history ticket or in such other record as the Government may by rule direct, and the Jailor shall make an entry in its proper place stating in respect of each direction the fact or, its having been or not having been complied with, accompanied by such observations, if any, as the Jailor thinks fit to make, and the date of the entry.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-39">
          <num>39.</num>
          <heading>Hospital</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-39.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>In every prison an hospital or proper place for the reception of sick prisoners shall be provided.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IX">
        <num>IX</num>
        <heading>Visits to prisoners</heading>
        <section id="section-40">
          <num>40.</num>
          <heading>Visits to civil and unconvicted criminal prisoners</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-40.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Due provision shall be made for the admission, at proper times and under proper restrictions, into every prison of persons with whom civil or unconvicted criminal prisoners may desire to communicate, care being taken that, so far as may be consistent with the interest of justice, prisoners under trial may see their duly qualified legal advisers without the presence of any other person.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-41">
          <num>41.</num>
          <heading>Search of visitors</heading>
          <subsection id="section-41.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Jailor may demand the name and address of any visitor to a prisoner, and when the Jailor has any ground for suspicion, may search any visitor, or cause him to be searched, but the search shall not be made in the presence of any prisoner or another visitor.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-41.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In case of any such visitor refusing to permit himself to be searched, the Jailor may deny him admission; and the grounds of such proceeding, with the particulars thereof, shall be entered in such record as the Government may direct.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-X">
        <num>X</num>
        <heading>Offences in relation to prisons</heading>
        <section id="section-42">
          <num>42.</num>
          <heading>Penalty for introduction or removal of prohibited articles into or from prison, and communications with prisoners</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-42.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Whoever, contrary to any rule under section 59 introduces or removes, or attempts by any means whatever to introduce or remove, into or from any prison, or supplies or attempts to supply to any prisoner outside the limits of a prison, any prohibited Stick, and every officer of a prison who, contrary to any such rule, knowingly suffers any such article to be introduced into or removed from any prison, to be possessed by any prisoner, or to be supplied to any prisoner outside the limits of a prison, and whoever, contrary to any such rule, communicates or attempts to communicate with any prisoner, and whoever abets any offence made punishable by this section, shall, on conviction before a Magistrate, be liable to imprisonment for a term not exceeding six months, or to fine not exceeding two hundred rupees, or to both.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-43">
          <num>43.</num>
          <heading>Power to arrest for offence under section 42</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-43.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>When any person, in the presence of any officer of a prison, commits any offence specified in the last foregoing section, and refuses on demand of such officer to state his name and residence, or gives a name or residence which such officer knows, or has reason to believe, to be false, such officer, may arrest him and shall without unnecessary delay make him over to a Police Officer, and thereupon such Police Officer shall proceed as if the offence had been committed in his presence.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-44">
          <num>44.</num>
          <heading>Publication of penalties</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-44.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Superintendent shall cause to be affixed, in a conspicuous place outside the prison, a notice in English and the regional language setting forth the acts prohibited under section 42 and the penalties incurred by their commission</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-XI">
        <num>XI</num>
        <heading>Prison offences</heading>
        <section id="section-45">
          <num>45.</num>
          <heading>Prison offences</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-45.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The following acts are declared to be prison offences when committed by a prisoner:-</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-45.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>such wilful disobedience to any regulation of the prison as shall have been declared by rules made under section 59 to be a prison offence;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>any assault or use of criminal force;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the use of insulting or threatening language;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>immoral or indecent or disorderly behaviour;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>wilfully disabling himself from labour;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>contumaciously refusing to work;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>filing, Cutting, altering or removing handcuffs, fetters or bars without due authority;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>wilful idleness or negligence at work by any prisoner sentenced to rigorous imprisonment;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <p>wilful mismanagement of work by any prisoner sentenced to rigorous imprisonment;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.10">
            <num>(10)</num>
            <content>
              <p>wilful damage to prison property;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.11">
            <num>(11)</num>
            <content>
              <p>tampering with or defacing history tickets, records or documents;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.12">
            <num>(12)</num>
            <content>
              <p>receiving; possessing or transferring any prohibited article;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.13">
            <num>(13)</num>
            <content>
              <p>wilfully bringing a false accusation against any prisoner;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.14">
            <num>(14)</num>
            <content>
              <p>omitting or refusing to report, as soon as it comes to his knowledge the occurrence of any fire, any plot or conspiracy, any escape, attempt or preparation to escape, and any attack or preparation for attack upon any prisoner or prison official; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.15">
            <num>(15)</num>
            <content>
              <p>conspiring to escape or to assist in escaping, or to commit any other of the offences aforesaid.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-46">
          <num>46.</num>
          <heading>Punishment of such offences</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-46.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Superintendent may examine any person touching any such offence, and determine thereupon, and punish such offence by-</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-46.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>a formal warning :</p>
              <p>Explanation-A formal warning shall mean a warning personally addressed to a prisoner by the Superintendent and recorded in the punishment book and on the prisoner's history ticket;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-46.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>change of labour to some more irksome or severe form for such period as may be prescribed by rules made by the Government);</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-46.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>hard labour for a period hot exceeding seven days in the case of convicted criminal prisoners not sentenced to rigorous imprisonment;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-46.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>such loss of privileges admissible under the remission or furlough system for the time being in force as may be prescribed by rules made by the Government;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-46.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>separate confinement for any period not exceeding two months :</p>
              <p>Provided that while executing the punishment of a separate confinement, no prisoner shall be kept in separate confinement continuously, for more than a fortnight at one time and the interval between one period of confinement and the next will be at least a week.</p>
              <p>Explanation.- Separate confinement means such confinement with or without labour as secludes a prisoner from communication with, but not from sight of, other prisoners, and allows him not less than one hour's exercise in the open air per diem and to have his meals in association with one or more other prisoners</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-46.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>cellular confinement for any period not exceeding ten days:</p>
              <p>Provided that after each period of cellular confinement an interval of not less duration than such period must elapse before the prisoner is again sentenced to</p>
              <p>cellular or solitary confinement:</p>
              <p>Explanation.- Cellular confinement means such confinement with or without labour as entirely secludes a prisoner from communication with, but not from sight of, other prisoners:</p>
              <p>Provided that nothing in this section shall render any female or civil prisoner liable to the imposition of any form of handcuffs.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-47">
          <num>47.</num>
          <heading>Plurality of punishments under section 46</heading>
          <subsection id="section-47.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-47.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Any two of the punishments enumerated in the last foregoing section may be awarded for any such offence in combination, subject to the following exceptions, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-47.1.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>formal warning shall not he combined with any other punishment except loss of privileges under clause (4) of that section;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-47.1.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>cellular confinement shall pot be combined with separate confinement, so as to prolong the total period of seclusion to which the prisoner shall be liable.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-47.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No punishment will be combined with any other punishment in contravention of rules made by the Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-47.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No punishment shall be awarded for any such offence so as to combine, with the punishment awarded for any other such offence, two of the punishments which may not be awarded in combination for any such offence.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-48">
          <num>48.</num>
          <heading>Award of punishments under sections 46 &amp; 47</heading>
          <subsection id="section-48.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Superintendent shall have power to award any of the punishments enumerated in the two last foregoing sections; subject, in the ease of separate confinement for a period exceeding one month, to the previous confirmation of the Inspector-General.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-48.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No officer subordinate to the Superintendent shall have power to award any punishment whatever.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-49">
          <num>49.</num>
          <heading>Punishment for breach of conditions of suspension of sentence, etc</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-49.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>If any prisoner fails without sufficient cause to observe any of the conditions on which his sentence was suspended or remitted or furlough was granted to him, he shall be deemed to have committed a prison offence and the Superintendent may, after obtaining his explanation, punish such offence by--</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-49.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>a formal warning as provided in clause (1) of section 46;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-49.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>reduction in grade if such prisoner has been appointed an officer of prison;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-49.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>loss of privileges admissible under the remission or furlough system; or</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-49.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>loss of such other privileges as the Government may by a general or special order direct.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-50">
          <num>50.</num>
          <heading>Punishment to be in accordance with foregoing sections</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-50.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Except by order of a Court of Justice, no punishment other than the punishments specified in the foregoing sections shall be inflicted on any prisoner and no punishment shall be inflicted on any prisoner otherwise than in accordance with the provisions of those sections.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-51">
          <num>51.</num>
          <heading>Medical officer to certify to fitness of prisoner for punishment</heading>
          <subsection id="section-51.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No punishment of change of labour under clause (2) of section 46, shall be executed until the prisoner to whom such punishment has been awarded has been examined by the Medical Officer, who, if he considers the prisoner fit to undergo the punishment, shall certify accordingly in the appropriate column of the Punishment Book prescribed in section 12.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-51.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If he considers the prisoner unfit to undergo the punishment, he shall in like manner record his opinion in writing and shall state whether the prisoner is absolutely unfit for punishment of the kind awarded, or whether he considers any modification necessary.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-51.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the latter case he shall state what extent of punishment he thinks the prisoner can undergo without injury to his health.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-52">
          <num>52.</num>
          <heading>Entries in punishment books</heading>
          <subsection id="section-52.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the punishment book prescribed in section 12 there shall be recorded, in respect of every punishment inflicted, the prisoner's name, register number and the class (whether habitual or not) to which he belongs, the prison offence of which he was guilty, the date on which Such prison offence was committed, the number of previous prison offences recorded against the prisoner, and the date of his last prison offence, the punishment awarded, and the date of infliction.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-52.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the case of every serious prison offence, the names of the witnesses proving the offence shall be recorded.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-52.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Against the entries relating to each punishment the Jailor and Superintendent shall affix their initials as evidence of the correctness of the entries.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-53">
          <num>53.</num>
          <heading>Procedure on committal of heinous offence</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-53.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>If any prisoner is guilty of any offence against prison discipline which, by reason of his having frequently committed such offences or otherwise, in the opinion of that Superintendent, is not adequately punishable by the infliction of any punishment which he has power under this Act to award, the Superintendent may forward such prisoner to the Court of the District Magistrate, or any Magistrate of the First Class having jurisdiction, together with a statement of the circumstances, and such Magistrate shall thereupon inquire into and try the charge so brought against the prisoner, and, upon conviction, may sentence him to imprisonment which may extend to one year, such term to be in addition to any term for which such prisoner was undergoing imprisonment when he committed such offence, or may sentence him to any of the punishments enumerated in section 46 :</p>
              <p>Provided that any such case may be transferred for inquiry and trial by the District Magistrate to any Magistrate of the First Class: and</p>
              <p>Provided also that no person shall be punished twice for the same offence.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-54">
          <num>54.</num>
          <heading>Offences by prison subordinates</heading>
          <subsection id="section-54.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every Jailor or officer of a prison subordinate to him who shall be guilty of any violation of duty or wilful breach or neglect of any rule or regulation or lawful order made by competent authority, or who shall withdraw from the duties of his office without permission, or without having given previous notice in writing of his intention for the period of two months, or who shall wilfully overstay any leave granted to him, or who shall engage without authority in any employment other than his prison duty, or who shall be guilty of cowardice, shall be liable, on conviction before a Magistrate, to fine not exceeding two hundred rupees, or to imprisonment for a period not exceeding three months, or to both.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-54.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No person shall under this section be punished twice for the same offence.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-XII">
        <num>XII</num>
        <heading>Miscellaneous</heading>
        <section id="section-55">
          <num>55.</num>
          <heading>Extramural custody, control and employment of prisoners</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-55.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>A prisoner, when being taken to or from any prison in which he may be lawfully confined, or whenever he is working outside or is otherwise beyond the limits of any such prison in or under the lawful custody or control of a prison officer belonging to such prison, shall be deemed to be in prison and shall be subject to all the same incidents as if he were actually in prison.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-56">
          <num>56.</num>
          <heading>Confinement in irons</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-56.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Whenever the Superintendent considers it necessary (with reference either to the state of the prison or the character of the prisoners) for the safe custody of any prisoners that they should be confined in irons, he may, subject to such rules and instructions as may be laid down by the Inspector-General with the sanction of the Government, so confine them.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-57">
          <num>57.</num>
          <heading>Confinement of prisoners under sentence of transportation in irons</heading>
          <subsection id="section-57.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Prisoners under sentence of transportation may, subject to any rules made under section 59 be confined in fetters for the first three months after admission to prison.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-57.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Should the Superintendent consider it necessary, either for the safe custody of the prisoner himself or for any other reason, that fetters should be retained on any such prisoner for more than three months, he shall apply to the Inspector-General for sanction to their retention for the period for which he considers their retention necessary, and the. Inspector-General may sanction such retention accordingly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-58">
          <num>58.</num>
          <heading>Prisoners not to be ironed by Jailor except under necessity</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-58.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No prisoner shall be put in irons or under mechanical restraint by the Jailor of his own authority, except in cases of urgent necessity, in which case notice thereof shall be forthwith given to the Superintendent.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-58A">
          <num>58A.</num>
          <heading>Power to release a prisoner on furlough.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-58A.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Government or any authority empowered by it may release a prisoner on furlough in accordance with the rules for the time being in force.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-59">
          <num>59.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-59.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Government may make rules consistent with this Act:</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-59.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>defining the acts which shall constitute prison offences;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>determining the classification of prison offences into serious and minor offences;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>fixing the punishments admissible under this Act which shall be awardable for commission of prison offences or classes thereof;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>declaring the circumstances in which acts constituting both a prison offence and an offence under the Indian Penal Code (XLV of 1860) may or may not be dealt with as a prison offence;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>for the award of works, granting remission or furlough determining the conditions on which and the authority by which such remission or furlough shall be granted and the consequent shortening of the sentence;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>regulating the use of arms against any prisoner or body of prisoners in the case of an outbreak or attempt to escape;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>defining the circumstances and regulating the conditions under which prisoners in danger of death may be released;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>for the classification of prisons, and description and construction of wards, cells and other places of detention;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <p>for the regulation by numbers, length or character of sentences, or otherwise, of the prisoners to be confined in each class of prisons;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.10">
            <num>(10)</num>
            <content>
              <p>for the government of prisons and for the appointment of all officers appointed under this Act;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.11">
            <num>(11)</num>
            <content>
              <p>as to the food, bedding and clothing of criminal prisoners and of civil prisoners; maintained otherwise than at their own cost;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.12">
            <num>(12)</num>
            <content>
              <p>for the employment, instruction and control of convict within or without prisons;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.13">
            <num>(13)</num>
            <content>
              <p>for defining articles the introduction or removal of which into or out of prisons without due authority is prohibited;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.14">
            <num>(14)</num>
            <content>
              <p>for classifying and prescribing the forms of labour 'and regulating the periods of rest from labour;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.15">
            <num>(15)</num>
            <content>
              <p>for regulating the disposal of the proceeds of the employment of prisoners;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.16">
            <num>(16)</num>
            <content>
              <p>for regulating the confinement in fetters of prisoners sentenced to transportation;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.17">
            <num>(17)</num>
            <content>
              <p>for the classification and the separation of prisoners;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.18">
            <num>(18)</num>
            <content>
              <p>for regulating the confinement of convicted criminal prisoners under section. 28;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.19">
            <num>(19)</num>
            <content>
              <p>for the preparation and maintenance of history tickets;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.20">
            <num>(20)</num>
            <content>
              <p>for the selection and appointment of prisoners as officers of prisons;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.21">
            <num>(21)</num>
            <content>
              <p>for rewards for good conduct;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.22">
            <num>(22)</num>
            <content>
              <p>for regulating the transfer of prisoners whose term of transportation or imprisonment is about to expire; subject, however, to the consent of the Government of any other State to which a prisoner is to be transferred;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.23">
            <num>(23)</num>
            <content>
              <p>for the treatment, transfer and disposal of criminal lunatics or recovered criminal lunatics confined in prisons;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.24">
            <num>(24)</num>
            <content>
              <p>for regulating the transmission of appeals and petitions from prisoners and their communications with their friends;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.25">
            <num>(25)</num>
            <content>
              <p>for the appointment and guidance of visitors of prisons;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.26">
            <num>(26)</num>
            <content>
              <p>for extending any or all of the provisions of this Act and of the rules thereunder to subsidiary jails or special places of confinement appointed under section 541 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898, and to the officers employed, and the prisoners confined, therein;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.27">
            <num>(27)</num>
            <content>
              <p>in regard to the admission, custody, employment, dieting, treatment and release of prisoners; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.28">
            <num>(28)</num>
            <content>
              <p>generally for carrying into effect the purposes of this Act</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-60">
          <num>60.</num>
          <heading>Exhibition of copies of rules</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-60.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Copies of rules, under section 59 so far as they affect the government of prisons, shall be exhibited, both in English and in the regional language, in some place to which all persons employed within a prison have access.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-61">
          <num>61.</num>
          <heading>Exercise of powers of Superintendent and Medical Officers</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-61.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>All or any of the power and duties conferred and imposed by this Act on a Superintendent or Medical Officer may, in his absence, be exercised and performed by such other officer as the Government may appoint in this behalf either by name or by his official designation.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
