<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1943/9/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1943/9"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Reciprocity Act, 1943"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1943/9/eng@1943-03-31/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1943/9/eng@1943-03-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1943-03-31" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1943/9/eng@1943-03-31/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1943/9/eng@1943-03-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Reciprocity Act, 1943</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 9 OF 1943</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 31st March, 1943.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to make provisions on a basis of reciprocity in regard to entry  into, travel, residence, the acquisition, holding or disposal of  property, the enjoyment of educational facilities, the holding of  public office, or the carrying on of any occupation, trade, business  or profession in  India by, and the franchise in  India of,</p>
        <p>persons domiciled in British possessions.</p>
        <p>Preamble. WHEREAS it is expedient to make provisions on a basis  of reciprocity in regard to entry into, travel, residence, the  acquisition, holding or disposal of property, the enjoyment of  educational facilities, the holding of public office, or the carrying  on of any occupation, trade, business or profession in  India by,</p>
        <p>and the franchise in  India of, persons domiciled in British  possessions;</p>
        <p>It is hereby enacted as follows:--</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be  called the Reciprocity Act, 1943.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India .</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on the 1st day of September,</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1943">
        <num>1943.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1943.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant  in the subject or context--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" British possession" means any part of His Majesty' s  dominions  and includes a protectorate or other  territory administered by a British possession as a  mandatory on behalf of the League of Nations; and where  parts of those dominions are under both a central and a  local legislature, the expression shall mean either  each part under a local legislature or all parts under  the central legislature];</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" entry" includes landing at any port in  India]</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>during the stay in  India] of a ship or aircraft on  its way to a destination outside  India];</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to impose reciprocal  disabilities on persons domiciled in British possessions. Where by the  law or practice of any British possession persons of Indian origin are  subject in that British possession to disabilities in respect of entry  into, or travel, residence, the acquisition, holding or disposal of  property, the enjoyment of educational facilities, the holding of  public office, the carrying on of any occupation, trade, business or  profession, or the exercise of the franchise in, that British  possession, to which in respect of the like matters in  India]</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>persons domiciled in that British possession are not subject in</p>
            <p>India], the Central Government may, by  notification in the</p>
            <p>Official Gazette, direct that the same disabilities or disabilities as  similar thereto as may be, shall, notwithstanding anything contained  in any other law for the time being in force, be imposed in  India]</p>
            <p>on persons not being of Indian origin who are domiciled in that</p>
            <p>British possession.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Burden of proof on person claiming exemption. If any person  alleged to be domiciled in any British possession and to be subject to  the provisions of this Act pleads that he is not so domiciled, or that  the provisions of this Act do not apply to him, the onus of proving  the truth of such a plea shall be on him.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Direction imposing disabilities in respect of entry, travel  and residence not to apply to armed forces. Any direction made by the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Central Government under section 3 imposing disabilities in respect of  entry into or travel or residence in  India] upon persons domiciled  in a British possession shall not, until the expiry of six months  after the termination of the present hostilities, apply to any person  domiciled in that British possession who is a member of its armed  forces.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make  rules for carrying out  the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, rules made under this section may provide-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for the setting up of machinery to ascertain the  disabilities in respect of any of the matters specified  in section 3 to which persons of Indian origin are  subject in any British possession;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>for the establishment of a suitable agency to  administer the rules and for defining its functions and  powers;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>for specifying the disabilities that shall, when a  direction has been made under section 3, be imposed in</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-6.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>India] on persons not being of Indian origin who are  domiciled in any British possession and for the  imposition on them of the disabilities so specified;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.2.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>for the enforcement, by the prescription of a penalty  by way of imprisonment or fine or both, of any rule  made under clause (c);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.2.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>for authorizing the arrest of any person contravening  or reasonably suspected of contravening any rule made  under clause (c), and for prescribing the duties of  public servants and others in regard to such arrests.]</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as  may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is  in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised  in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before  the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the  successive sessions aforesaid both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not  be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified  form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any  such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the  validity of anything previously done under that rule.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Repeal of Act 3 of 1924. The Immigration into India Act,</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1924">
        <num>1924.</num>
        <heading>(3 of 1924), is hereby repealed.]</heading>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
