<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2000/54/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2000/54"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Central Road Fund Act, 2000"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2000/54/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2000/54/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2000/54/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2000/54/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Central Road Fund Act, 2000</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Central Road Fund Act, 2000.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Save as otherwise provided in this Act, it shall be deemed to have come into force on the Ist day of November, 2000.</p>
            <p>.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“appointed day” means the date on which the Fund is established under sub‑section (1) of section 6;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“cess” means a duty in the nature of duty of excise and customs, imposed and collected on motor spirit commonly known as petrol and high speed diesel oil for the purposes of this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“Fund” means the Central Road Fund established under sub‑section (1) of section 6;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>“national highways” means the highways specified in the Schedule to the National Highways Act, 1956 (48 of 1956) or any other highway declared as national highway under sub‑section (2) of section 2 of the said Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>“National Highways Authority of India” means an authority constituted under sub‑section (1) of section 3 of the National Highways Authority of India Act, 1988 (68 of 1988);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Levy and collection of cess.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>With effect from such date as the Central Government may, by notification in Official Gazette, specify, there shall be levied and collected, as a cess, a duty of excise and customs for the purposes of this Act, on every item specified in column (2) of the Schedule, which is produced in or imported into India and—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>removed from a refinery or a factory or an outlet; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>transferred by the person, by whom such item is produced or imported, to another person,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>at such rates not exceeding the rate set forth in the corresponding entry in column (3) of the Schedule, as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify:</p>
            <p>Provided that until the Central Government specifies by such notification the rate of the cess in respect of petrol and high speed diesel oil (being items specified in the Schedule), the cess on petrol and high speed diesel oil under this sub‑section shall be levied and collected at the rate of rupee one per litre:</p>
            <p>Provided further that the additional duty of customs and the additional duty of excise on petrol levied under sub‑section (1) of section 103 and sub‑section (1) of section 111, as the case may be, of the Finance (No. 2) Act, 1998 (21 of 1998) and the additional duty of customs and the additional duty of excise on high speed diesel oil levied under sub‑section (1) of section 116 and sub‑section (1) of section 133, as the case may be, of the Finance Act, 1999 (27 of 1999) shall be deemed to be a cess for the purposes of this Act from the date of its levy and the proceeds thereof shall be credited to the Fund.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every cess leviable under sub‑section (1) on any item shall be payable by the person by whom such item is produced, and in the case of imports, the cess shall be imposed and collected on items so imported and specified in the Schedule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The cess leviable under sub‑section (1) on the items specified in the Schedule shall be in addition to any cess or duty leviable on those items under any other law for the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of the Central Excise Act, 1944 (1 of 1944) and the rules made thereunder and the provisions of the Customs Act, 1962 (52 of 1962) and the rules made thereunder, as the case may be, including those relating to refunds and exemptions from duties shall, as far as may be, apply in relation to the levy and collection of cess leviable under this section and for this purpose, the provisions of the Central Excise Act, 1944 and of the Customs Act, 1962, as the case may be, shall have effect as if the aforesaid Acts provided for the levy of cess on all items specified in the Schedule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Crediting of cess to Consolidated Fund of India.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The proceeds of the cess levied under section 3 shall first be credited to the Consolidated Fund of India, and the Central Government may, if Parliament by appropriation made by law in this behalf so provides, credit such proceeds to the Fund from time to time, after deducting the expenses of collection, for being utilised exclusively for the purposes of this Act.</p>
            <p>.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Grants and Loans by the Central Government.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in this behalf, credit by way of grants or loans such sums of money as the Central Government may consider necessary in the Fund.</p>
            <p>.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Establishment of Central Road Fund.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>With effect from such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint in this behalf, there shall be established for the purposes of this Act, a Fund to be called as the “Central Road Fund”.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Fund shall be under the control of the Central Government and there shall be credited thereto—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any sums of money paid under section 4 or section 5;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>unspent part of the cess, being already levied for the purposes of the development and maintenance of national highways;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the sums, if any, realised by the Central Government in carrying out its functions or in the administration of this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>any fund provided by the Central Government for the development and maintenance of State roads;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The balance to the credit of the Fund shall not lapse at the end of the financial year.</p>
            <p>.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Utilisation of the Fund.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Fund shall be utilised for the­—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>development and maintenance of national highways;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>development of the rural roads;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>development and maintenance of other State roads including roads of inter­-State and economic importance;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>construction of roads either under or over the railways by means of a bridge and erection of safety works at unmanned rail‑road crossings; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>disbursement in respect of such projects as may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>COMMENTS</p>
            <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Road Fund is to be utilised for the</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list4.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>development and maintenance of national highways;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>development of rural roads;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>development and maintenance of other State roads including roads of inter-State and economic importance;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list4.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>construction of roads either under or over the railways by means of a bridge and erection of safety works at unmanned rail-road crossings, and (e) disbursement in respect of such projects.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Accounts and audit.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The concerned departments of the Central Government shall maintain proper accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual statement of accounts, including the profit and loss account and the balance‑sheet in respect of allocations of their shares of fund in such form, as may be prescribed by the Central Government in consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor‑General of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The accounts of the Fund shall be audited by the Comptroller and Auditor­ General of India at such intervals as may be specified by him.</p>
            <p>.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Powers of Central Government to administer the Fund:—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government shall have the power to administer the Fund and shall—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>take such decisions regarding investment on projects of national highways and expressways as it considers necessary;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>take such measures as may be necessary to raise funds for the development and maintenance of the national highways and for the development of rural roads;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <blockList id="section-9.1.list1.c.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>allocate and disburse such sums as are considered necessary, to the concerned departments responsible for the development and maintenance of—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-9.1.list1.c.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>national highways;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-9.1.list1.c.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>rural roads;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-9.1.list1.c.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>state roads; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-9.1.list1.c.list0.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>construction of roads either under or over the railways by means of a bridge and erect suitable safety works at unmanned rail-road level crossings.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Functions of the Central Government.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government shall be responsible for the—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>administration and management of the share of Fund allocated to the development and maintenance of the national highways;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>co‑ordination and complete and timely utilization of all sums allocated out of the Fund;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>sanction of schemes for State roads of inter‑State and economic importance in such manner as may be prescribed;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>formulation of criteria on the basis of which the specific projects of State roads of inter‑State and economic importance are to be approved and financed out of share of State roads;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>release of funds to the States for specific projects and monitoring of such projects and expenditure incurred thereon;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.vi">
                <num>(vi)</num>
                <p>formulation of the criteria for allocation of the funds for such projects which are required to be implemented by the National Highways Authority of India and also for other projects for the development and maintenance of the national highways;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.vii">
                <num>(vii)</num>
                <p>allocation of share of funds to each State and Union territory specified in the First Schedule to the Constitution;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.viii">
                <num>(viii)</num>
                <p>allocation of—</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>fifty per cent. of the cess on high speed diesel oil for the development of rural roads in such manner as may be prescribed; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the balance amount of fifty per cent. of cess on high speed diesel oil and the entire cess collected on petrol as follows:­—</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>an amount equal to fifty seven and one‑half per cent. of such sum for the development and maintenance of national highways;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>an amount equal to twelve and one‑half per cent. for the construction of road either under or over the railways by means of a bridge and erection of safety works at unmanned, rail‑road crossings; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>the balance thirty per cent. on development and maintenance of roads other than national highways and out of this amount, ten per cent. that is three per cent. of the total share of State roads shall be kept as reserve by the Central Government for allocation to States for implementation of State road schemes of inter‑State and economic importance to be approved by the Central Government in terms of clauses (iii) and (iv) of this section.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in clause (viii) of sub-section (1), the Central Government shall, with effect from 1st day of March, 2005, allocate fifty paise from the amount of rupee two as amended by sections 119 and 120 of the Finance Act, 2005 as the additional duty of customs and the additional duty of excise on petrol, levied under sub-section (1) of section 103 and sub-section (1) of section 111, as the case may be, of the Finance (No. 2) Act, 1998 (21 of 1998) and the additional duty of customs and the additional duty of excise on high speed diesel oil levied under sub-section (1) of section 116 and sub-section (1) of section 133, as the case may be, of the Finance Act, 1999 (27 of 1999), exclusively for the development and maintenance of national highways.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Administra­tion of States' share of the Fund. —</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The share of the fund to be spent on development and maintenance of roads, other than national highways, as specified under sub-clause (b) of clause (viii) of section 10, after deducting the reserve kept by the Central Government for State road schemes of inter-State and economic importance, shall be allocated to various States and Union territories in such manner as may be decided by the Central Government:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Central Government may use the share of the Fund under sub-clause (a) of clause (viii) of section 10 for the repayment of any loan taken for the purpose of development of rural roads in any State or Union territory.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The portion of the fund allocated for expenditure in the various States and Union territories shall be retained by the Central Government until it is actually required for expenditure.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If in the opinion of the Central Government, the Government of any State or the administration of any Union territory has at any time—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>failed to take such steps as the Central Government may recommend for the regulation and control of motor vehicles within the State or the Union territory; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>delayed without reasonable cause the application of any portion of the fund allocated or re-allocated, as the case may be, for expenditure within the State or Union territory,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>the Central Government may resume the whole or part of any sums which it may have at that time held for expenditure in that State or the Union territory.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All sums resumed by the Central Government from the account of any State Government or Union territory administration as aforesaid shall be re-allocated between the credit accounts of the defaulting and other State Governments and Union territory administrations in the ratio of the main allocation for the financial year preceding the year in which the re-allocation is made.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The balance to the credit of the Fund in respect of any allocation shall not lapse at the end of the financial year.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-12.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing powers, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>specify the projects in respect of which the funds may be disbursed under section 7;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the manner in which the accounts shall be maintained and the annual state­ment of accounts may be prepared including the profit and loss account and the balance‑sheet under sub‑section (1) of section 8;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the manner in which the schemes for development and maintenance of State roads of inter‑State and economic importance are to be formulated and sanctioned under section 10;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>any other matter for which rule is to be made, or may be, prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Rules made under this Act to be laid before Parliament.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such notification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
            <p>.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Provisions relating to existing Central Road Fund.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>With effect from the appointed day the Central Road Fund governed by the Parliamentary Resolution dated the 13th May, 1988 (hereafter referred to in this section as the existing Fund) shall be deemed to be the Fund established under this Act and,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>all schemes relating to development and maintenance of national highways and State roads sanctioned under the existing Fund in so far as such schemes are relatable to the schemes under this Act, shall be deemed to be the schemes sanctioned under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>all funds accrued under the existing Fund including assets and liabilities shall be transferred to the Fund established under this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Repeal and saving.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Road Fund Ordinance, 2000 (Ord. 5 of 2000) is hereby repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.</p>
            <p>.</p>
            <p>The CENTRAL ROAD FUND ACT, 2000</p>
            <p>THE SCHEDULE</p>
            <p>(See section 3)</p>
            <p>Sl. No.</p>
            <p>Name of Item</p>
            <p>Rate of Duty</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content/>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content/>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content/>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Motor spirit commonly known as petrol</p>
            <p>Rupees one per litre</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>High Speed diesel oil</p>
            <p>Rupees one per litre</p>
            <p>.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
