<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1971/84/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1971/84"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The North- Eastern Council Act, 1971"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1971/84/eng@1971-12-30/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1971/84/eng@1971-12-30"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1971-12-30" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1971/84/eng@1971-12-30/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1971/84/eng@1971-12-30"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The North- Eastern Council Act, 1971</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 84 OF 1971</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 30th December, 1971.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- second Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the setting up of a Council for the north-</p>
        <p>eastern areas of India to be called the North- Eastern Council  and for matters connected therewith.</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:--</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>North- Eastern Council Act, 1971.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date , being a date not  earlier than the day appointed under clause (b) of section 2 of the</p>
            <p>North- Eastern Areas (Reorganisation) Act, 1971, as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" Council" means the North- Eastern Council set up under  section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" north- eastern area" means the area comprising the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>States of Arunachal Pradesh, Assam, Manipur, Meghalaya,</p>
            <p>Mizoram, Nagaland and Tripura.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Setting up and composition of the North- Eastern Council.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>There shall be a Council to be called the North- Eastern Council which  shall consist of the following members, namely:--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the person or persons for the time being holding the  office of the Governor of the States or the office of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Administrator of the Union territories in the north-</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list4">
              <listIntroduction>eastern area;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the Chief Ministers of the States of Arunachal</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Pradesh, Assam, Manipur, Meghalaya, Mizoram, Nagaland  and Tripura.]</p>
            <p>Provided that if there is no Council of Ministers  in any State or</p>
            <p>Union territory referred to in clause (b)], the President may nominate  not more than one person to represent such State or Union territory in  the Council for so long as there is no Council of Ministers in such</p>
            <p>State or Union territory.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), the</p>
            <p>President may, if he deems it necessary so to do, nominate a Union</p>
            <p>Minister to be a member of the Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>One of the members of the Council to be nominated by the</p>
            <p>President shall be the Chairman of the Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The President may, if he deems it necessary so to do,</p>
            <p>nominate another member of the Council to act as Vice- Chairman of the</p>
            <p>Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Functions of the Council.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Council shall be an advisory  body and may discuss any matter in which some or all of the States  represented in that Council, or the Union and one or more of the</p>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>States represented in that Council, have a common interest and advise  the Central Government and the Government of each State concerned as  to the action to be taken on any such matter, and, in particular, may  discuss and make recommendations with regard to,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list2.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>any matter of common interest in the field of economic  and social planning;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list2.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>any matter concerning inter- State transport and  communications;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list2.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>any matter relating to power or flood control projects  of common interest.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>For securing the balanced development of the north- eastern  area, the Council shall forward proposals,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>formulating for the States represented in the Council a  unified and co- ordinated regional plan (which will be  in</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-4.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>addition to the State Plan) in regard to matters of  common importance to that area;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.2.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>regarding the priorities of the projects and schemes  included in the regional plan and the stages in which  the regional plan may be implemented; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.2.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>regarding the location of the projects and schemes  included in the regional plan,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>to the Central Government for its consideration.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Council shall--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>review, from time to time, the implementation of the  projects and schemes included in the regional plan and  recommend measures for effecting co- ordination among  the Governments of the States concerned in the matter  of implementation of such projects and schemes;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-4.3.list1.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>where a project or scheme is intended to benefit two or  more States, recommend the manner in which,--</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-4.3.list1.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>such project or scheme may be executed or  implemented and managed or maintained; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-4.3.list1.b.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>the benefits therefrom may be shared; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-4.3.list1.b.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>the expenditure thereon may be incurred;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>on a review of progress of the expenditure, recommend to  the Central Government the quantum of financial  assistance to be given, from time to time, to the State  or States entrusted with the execution or  implementation of any project or scheme included in the  regional plan;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>recommend to the Government of the State concerned or to  the Central Government the undertaking of necessary  surveys and investigation of projects in any State  represented in the Council to facilitate consideration  of the feasibility of including new projects in the  regional plan.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Council shall review from time to time the measures taken  by the States represented in the Council for the maintenance of  security and public order therein and recommend to the Governments of  the States concerned further measures necessary in this regard.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Meetings of the Council.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Council shall meet at such  times as the Chairman of the Council may appoint in this behalf and  shall, subject to the other provisions of this section, observe such  rules of procedure in regard to transaction of business at its  meetings as it may lay down from time to time.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chairman or in his absence the Vice- Chairman, if any, or  in the absence of both the Chairman and the Vice- Chairman, any other  member chosen by the members present from amongst themselves, shall  preside at a meeting of the Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The proceedings of every meeting of the Council shall be  forwarded to the Central Government and also to the Government of each</p>
            <p>State represented on the Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Nomination of certain officers to attend the meetings of the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Council. In order to assist the Council in the discharge of its  functions, each of the Ministries of the Central Government dealing  with matters relating to Defence, Finance, Home Affairs and Planning  shall nominate an officer to attend the meetings of the Council.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Officers and staff of the Council.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Council shall have  a secretarial staff consisting of a Secretary, a Planning Adviser, a</p>
            <p>Financial Adviser and a Security Adviser and such other officers and  employees as the Central Government may, by order, determine.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The secretarial staff of the Council shall function under the  direction, supervision and control of the Chairman of the Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The office of the Council shall be located at such place as  may be determined by the Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The administrative expenses of the said office, including the  salaries and allowances payable to, or in respect of, members of the  secretarial staff of the Council, shall be borne by the Central</p>
            <p>Government out of the moneys provided by Parliament for the purpose.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Repeal. The North- Eastern Council Act, 1970 (26 of 1970) is  hereby repealed.</heading>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
