<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1983/27/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1983/27"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Jute Manufactures Development Council Act, 1983"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1983/27/eng@1983-09-07/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1983/27/eng@1983-09-07"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1983-09-07" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1983/27/eng@1983-09-07/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1983/27/eng@1983-09-07"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Jute Manufactures Development Council Act, 1983</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 27 OF 1983</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 7th September, 1983.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty- fourth Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the establishment of a Council for the  development of production of jute manufactures by increasing the  efficiency and productivity in the jute industry, the financing of  activities for such development and for matters connected therewith.</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:--</p>
        <p>CHAP</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be  called the Jute Manufactures Development Council Act, 1983.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It extends to the whole of India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on such date  as the Central</p>
              <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" Chairman" means the Chairman of the Council;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" Council" means the Jute Manufactures Development</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Council established under section 3;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" jute manufacture" shall have the same meaning as  assigned to it in the Jute Manufactures Cess Act, 1983;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" member" means a member of the Council and includes the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Chairman;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>" year" means the year commencing on the 1st day of July  and ending on the 30th day of June next following.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>THE JUTE MANUFACTURES DEVELOPMENT COUNCIL</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>THE JUTE MANUFACTURES DEVELOPMENT COUNCIL</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Establishment and constitution of the Council.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>With effect  from such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the</p>
              <p>Official Gazette, appoint in this behalf, there shall be established  for the purposes of this Act, a Council to be called the Jute</p>
              <p>Manufactures Development Council.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Council shall be a body corporate by the name aforesaid,</p>
              <p>having perpetual succession and a common seal, with power to acquire,</p>
              <p>hold and dispose of property, both movable and immovable, and to  contract, and shall by the said name sue and be sued.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The head office of the Council shall be at Calcutta in the</p>
              <p>State of West Bengal, and the Council may, with the previous approval  of the Central Government, establish offices or agencies at other  places in or outside India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.4.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Council shall consist of the following members, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.4.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>a Chairman to be appointed by the Central Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.4.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>such number of members not exceeding eight as the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.4.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Central Government may think fit to be appointed by it from among  the Ministries of the Central Government dealing with--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.4.list3.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>agriculture;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.4.list3.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>commerce (textiles);</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.4.list3.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>finance;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.4.list3.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>industry;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.4.list3.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>civil supplies;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.4.list3.vi">
                  <num>(vi)</num>
                  <p>co- operation;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.4.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>six members to be appointed by the Central Government by  rotation in the alphabetical order to represent respectively the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Governments of the States of Andhra Pradesh, Assam, Bihar,</p>
              <p>Meghalaya, Orissa, Tripura and West Bengal in which jute is  cultivated on a large scale:</p>
              <blockList id="section-3.4.list7">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that such appointment shall be made on the  recommendation of the Government of the State concerned;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.4.list7.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>four members to be appointed by the Central Government  to represent the producers of jute manufactures;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.4.list7.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>two members to be appointed by the Central Government to  represent the exporters of jute manufactures;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.4.list7.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>three members to be appointed by the Central Government  to represent the growers of jute;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.4.list7.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>three members to be appointed by the Central Government  to represent the interests of workmen employed in factories  producing jute manufactures;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.4.list7.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>five members to be appointed by the Central Government  from amongst persons who, in the opinion of the Central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Government, are experts in jute technological research, jute  marketing or agricultural economics.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Council shall elect, from amongst its members, a Vice-</p>
              <p>Chairman who shall exercise such of the powers and perform such of the  functions of the Chairman as may be prescribed or as may be delegated  to him by the Chairman.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The term of office and other conditions of service of the  members and the manner of filling vacancies among, and the procedure  to be followed in the discharge of their functions by, the members  shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any officer of the Central Government, not being a member of  the Council, when deputed by that Government in this behalf, shall  have the right to attend the meetings of the Council and take part in  the proceedings thereof, but shall not have the right to vote.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Council may associate with itself, in such manner,</p>
              <p>subject to such conditions and for such purposes as may be prescribed,</p>
              <p>any person whose assistance or advice it may desire in complying with  any of the provisions of this Act and a person so associated shall be  entitled to receive such allowances or fees as may be fixed by the</p>
              <p>Central Government and shall have the right to take part in the  proceedings of the Council relevant to the purpose for which he has  been associated, but shall not have the right to vote.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.9.list1">
                <listIntroduction>No act or proceeding of the Council or any committee  appointed by it under section 5 shall be invalidated merely by reason  of--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.9.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>any vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution of,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.9.list3">
                <listIntroduction>the Council or such committee; or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.9.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>any defect in the appointment of a person acting as a  member of the Council or such committee; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.9.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>any irregularity in the procedure of the Council or such  committee not affecting the merits of the case.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.10">
            <num>(10)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Council shall meet at such times and places and shall  observe such rules of procedure in regard to the transaction of  business at its meetings (including the quorum at meetings) as may be  prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Salary and allowances and other conditions of service of</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Chairman and other members.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chairman shall be entitled to such  salary and allowances and shall be subject to such conditions of  service in respect of leave, pension, provident fund and other matters  as may from time to time be fixed by the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The other members of the Council shall receive such  allowances as may be fixed by the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Committees of the Council.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Council may appoint such  committees as may be necessary for the efficient discharge of its  duties and performance of its functions under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Council shall have the power to co- opt as members of any  committee appointed under sub- section (1) such number of persons who</p>
              <p>are not members of the Council as it may think fit and the persons so  co- opted shall have the right to attend meetings of the committee and  take part in its proceedings but shall not have the right to vote.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The persons co- opted as members of a committee under sub-</p>
              <p>section (2) shall be entitled to receive such allowances or fees for  attending the meetings of the committee as may be fixed by the Central</p>
              <p>Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Officers of the Council and other staff.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the  provisions of this Act, every person employed by the Jute Manufactures</p>
              <p>Development Council established under sub- section (1) of section 6 of  the Industries (Development and Regulation) Act, 1951, (65 of 1951.)</p>
              <p>immediately before the date of establishment of the Council under  section 3 of this Act, shall, on and from such date, become an  employee of the Council with such designation as the Council may  determine and shall hold his office or service therein by the same  tenure, at the same remuneration and upon the same terms and  conditions as he would have held on such date if the Council had not  been established and shall continue to do so unless and until his  employment in the Council is terminated or until such tenure,</p>
              <p>remuneration and terms and conditions are duly altered by the Council:</p>
              <p>Provided that the tenure, remuneration and terms and conditions  of service of any such person shall not be altered to his disadvantage  without the previous approval of the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every employee holding any office under the Central</p>
              <p>Government immediately before the date of establishment of the Council  solely or mainly for or in connection with such matters as are  relevant to the functions of the Council under this Act, shall, on and  from such date, be treated as on deputation with the Council but shall  hold his office in the Council by the same tenure and upon the same  terms and conditions of service as respects remuneration, leave,</p>
              <p>provident fund, retirement or other terminal benefits as he would have  held such office, if the Council had not been established and shall  continue to do so until the Central Government, either on its own  motion or at the request of the Council, recalls such employee to its  service or until the Council, with the concurrence of the Central</p>
              <p>Government, duly absorbs such employee in its regular service,</p>
              <p>whichever is earlier:</p>
              <p>Provided that during the period of deputation of any such  employee with the Council, the Council shall pay to the Central</p>
              <p>Government, in respect of every such employee, such contribution  towards his leave salary, pension and gratuity as the Central</p>
              <p>Government may, by order, determine:</p>
              <p>Provided further that any such employee, who has, in respect of  the proposal of the Council to absorb him in its regular service,</p>
              <p>intimated within such time as may be specified in this behalf by the</p>
              <p>Council his intention of not becoming a regular employee of the</p>
              <p>Council, shall not be absorbed by the Council in its regular service.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any dispute or doubt arises as to which of the employees  serving under the Central Government are to be treated as on  deputation with the Council under this section, such dispute or doubt  shall be decided by the Central Government in consultation with  the Council and the decision of the Central Government thereon shall  be final.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purposes of enabling it efficiently to discharge its  functions under this Act, the Council shall, subject to the other  provisions of this section and to such rules as may be made in this  behalf by the Central Government, appoint (whether on deputation or   otherwise) such number of officers and other employees as it may  consider necessary:</p>
              <p>Provided that the appointment of such category of officers as may  be specified in such rules, shall be subject to the approval of the</p>
              <p>Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the other provisions of this section, every  officer or other employee appointed by the Council shall be subject to  such conditions of service and shall be entitled to such remuneration  as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Functions of the Council.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall be the duty of the</p>
              <p>Council to promote, by such measures as it thinks fit, the development  of production of jute manufactures by increasing the efficiency and  productivity in the jute industry.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Without prejudice to the generality of the provisions of sub-</p>
              <blockList id="section-7.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>section (1), the measures referred to therein may provide for--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.2.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>evolving an integrated approach to jute cultivation in  the matter of formulation of schemes, extension work,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-7.2.list4">
                <listIntroduction>implementation and evaluation of schemes aimed at increasing the  yield of jute and improving the quality thereof;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.2.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>promoting arrangements for better marketing and sale of  jute;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.2.list4.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>recommending targets for production for jute industry,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-7.2.list6">
                <listIntroduction>co- ordinating production programmes and reviewing progress from  time to time;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.2.list6.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>suggesting norms of efficiency for jute industry with a  view to eliminating waste, obtaining optimum production,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-7.2.list8">
                <listIntroduction>improving quality and reducing costs;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.2.list8.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>promoting standardisation of jute manufactures;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.2.list8.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>maintenance and improvement of existing markets and  development of new markets outside India for jute manufactures  and devising marketing strategy in consonance with the demand for  such manufactures outside India;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.2.list8.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>sponsoring, assisting, co- ordinating or encouraging  scientific, technological and economic research into the matters  relating to materials, equipment, methods of production, product  development, including discovery and development of new  materials, equipment and methods and of improvements in those  already in use in the jute industry;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.2.list8.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>ensuring stabilisation of prices of jute manufactures in  and outside India;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.2.list8.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>promoting or undertaking the collection and formulation  of statistics regarding jute industry;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.2.list8.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>propagating information useful to the growers, dealers  and exporters of jute and producers or manufacturers of jute  goods;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.2.list8.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>such other matters as may be prescribed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Council shall perform its functions under this section in  accordance with and subject to such rules as may be made by the</p>
              <p>Central Government and such rules may be in particular make provisions  for ensuring that the Council functions in close liaison with Union  agencies, institutions and authorities concerned with the jute  manufactures (including cultivation of jute) and avoids duplication of  effort.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Dissolution of the Council.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette and for reasons to be specified  therein, direct that the Council shall be dissolved from such date and  for such period as may be specified in the notification:</p>
              <p>Provided that before issuing any such notification, the Central</p>
              <p>Government shall give a reasonable opportunity to the Council to make  representations against the proposed dissolution and shall consider  the representations, if any, of the Council.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When the Council is dissolved under the provisions of sub-</p>
              <blockList id="section-8.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>section (1),--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.2.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>all the members, notwithstanding that their term of  office has not expired, shall, from the date of dissolution,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-8.2.list4">
                <listIntroduction>vacate their offices as such members;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.2.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>all the powers and duties of the Council shall, during  the period of dissolution, be exercised and performed by such  person or persons as the Central Government may appoint in this  behalf and their remuneration shall be such as may be prescribed;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.2.list4.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>all funds and other properties vested in the Council  shall, during the period of dissolution, vest in the Central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-8.2.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Government; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.2.list6.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>as soon as the period of dissolution expires, the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Council shall be reconstituted in accordance with the provisions  of this Act.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Grants and loans by the Central Government Jute Furd. The</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Central Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by  law in this behalf, pay to the Council by way of grants or loans such  sums of money as the Central Government may think fit for being  utilised for the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-10.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>There shall be formed a Fund to be called the Jute Fund  and there shall be credited thereto--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>any fees that may be levied and collected under this Act  or the rules made thereunder;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>any sums of money paid or any grants or loans granted by  the Central Government for the purposes of this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>any grants or loans that may be made by any person for  the purposes of this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-10.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Fund shall be applied--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>for meeting the cost of the measures referred to in  section 7;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>for meeting the salaries, allowances and other  remuneration of the officers and other employees of the Council;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>for meeting the other administrative expenses of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-10.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Council;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.2.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>for repayment of any loans.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Borrowing powers of the Council. Subject to such rules as may  be made in this behalf by the Central Government, the Council shall  have the power to borrow on the security of the Jute Fund or any other  asset for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Accounts and audit.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-12.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Council shall maintain proper  accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual statement of  accounts, including the profit and loss account, and the balance  sheet, in such form and in such manner as may be prescribed by the</p>
              <p>Central Government in consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor-</p>
              <p>General of India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The accounts of the Council shall be audited by the</p>
              <p>Comptroller and Auditor- General of India at such intervals as may be  specified by him and any expenditure incurred in connection with such  audit shall be payable by the Council to the Comptroller and Auditor-</p>
              <p>General.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any other  person appointed by him in connection with the audit of the accounts  of the Council shall have the same rights and privileges and authority  in connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor- General  has in connection with the audit of the Government accounts and, in  particular, shall have the right to demand the production of books,</p>
              <p>accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and to  inspect any of the offices of the Council.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The accounts of the Council as certified by the Comptroller  and Auditor- General of India or any other person appointed by him in  this behalf together with the audit report thereon shall be forwarded  annually to the Central Government and that Government shall cause the  same to be laid before each House of Parliament.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>CONTROL BY CENTRAL GOVERNMENT</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>CONTROL BY CENTRAL GOVERNMENT</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Directions by Central Government. The Council shall carry out  such directions as may be issued to it from time to time by the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Central Government for the efficient administration of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Returns and reports of activities of the Council.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The</p>
              <p>Council shall furnish to the Central Government at such time and in  such form and manner as may be prescribed, such returns and statements  and such particulars in regard to any proposed or existing programme  for the development of jute manufactures, as the Central Government  may, from time to time, require.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Council shall furnish a programme of its activities for  each year to the Central Government for its information and  directions, if any.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Without prejudice to the provisions of sub- section (1), the</p>
              <p>Council shall, as soon as possible, after the end of each year, submit  to the Central Government a report in such form, and before such date,</p>
              <p>as may be prescribed, giving a true and full account of its  activities, policy and programmes during the previous year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A copy of the report received under sub- section (3) shall be  laid, as soon as may be, after it is received, before each House of</p>
              <p>Parliament.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-V.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Power to call for reports and returns. The Council may  require a producer of a jute manufacture to furnish, for the purposes  of this Act, such statistical or other information in such form and  within such period as may be specified by the Council.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Power of inspection. Any person authorised in this behalf by  the Central Government or by the Council or any officer of the Council  authorised by the Chairman in writing, may enter, at all reasonable  times, any place or premises where jute manufactures are stored, kept  or exposed for sale and may require the production for inspection of  any book, register, record or other paper kept therein and ask for any  information relating to the production, storage or keeping for sale of  jute manufactures.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Penalties. Whoever fails to comply with any order or  direction given under this Act, within such time as may be specified  in the said order or direction, or contravene or attempts to  contravene or abets the contravention of any of the provisions of this</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Act or any rules made thereunder, shall be punishable with  imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year or with fine  which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Offences by companies.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-18.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where an offence under this Act  has been committed by a company, every person who at the time the  offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible to, the  company for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as the  company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be  liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:</p>
              <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render  any such person liable to any punishment provided in this Act, if he  proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or that he  had exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such  offence.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where  an offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is  proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or  connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any  director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to  be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against  and punished accordingly.</p>
              <blockList id="section-18.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-18.2.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm  or other association of individuals; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.2.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner in  the firm.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Cognizance of offences. No court inferior to that of a</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Metropolitan Magistrate or a Judicial Magistrate of the first class  shall try any offence punishable under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Sanction for prosecutions. Notwithstanding anything contained  in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973, (2 of 1974.) no court shall  take cognizance of any offence punishable under this Act except with  the previous sanction of the Central Government.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central</p>
              <p>Government, or the Council or any committee appointed by it, or any  member of the Council or such committee, or any officer or other  employee of the Central Government or the Council or any other person  authorised by the Central Government or the council or the Chairman  for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under  this Act or the rules made thereunder.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Members, officers and employees of the Council to be public  servants. All the members and all officers and other employees of the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Council when acting or purporting to act in pursuance of the  provisions of this Act or the rules made thereunder shall be deemed to  be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian</p>
              <p>Penal Code. (45 of 1860.)</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Suspension of operation of Act.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-23.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the Central Government  is satisfied that circumstances have arisen rendering it necessary  that certain of the restrictions imposed by this Act should cease to  be imposed and if it considers it necessary or expedient so to do in  the public interest, the Central Government may, by notification in  the Official Gazette, suspend or relax to a specified extent and for  such period as may be specified in the notification, the operation of  all or any of the provisions of this Act, in all or any of the  territories to which this Act extends.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where the operation of any provision of this Act has, under  sub- section (1), been suspended or relaxed, such suspension or  relaxation may, at any time while this Act remains in force, be  removed by the Central Government by notification in the Official</p>
              <p>Gazette.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every notification issued under this section shall be laid,</p>
              <p>as soon as may be after it is issued, before each House of Parliament,</p>
              <p>while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be  comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and  if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session  or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the notification or both Houses agree that the  notification should not be</p>
              <p>issued, the notification shall thereafter have effect only in such  modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however,</p>
              <p>that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to  the validity of anything previously done under that notification.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Application of other laws not barred. The provisions of this</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Act shall be in addition to, and not in derogation of, the provisions  of any other law for the time being in force.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-25.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the  purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-25.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-25.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the powers and functions of the Vice- Chairman of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-25.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Council under sub- section (5) of section 3;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-25.2.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the term of office and other conditions of service of  members, the manner of filling vacancies among, and the procedure  to be followed in the discharge of their functions by, members,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-25.2.list5">
                <listIntroduction>under sub- section (6) of section 3;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-25.2.list5.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which, the conditions subject to which and  the purposes for which persons may be associated by the Council  under sub- section (8) of section 3;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-25.2.list5.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the times and places at which the Council shall meet,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-25.2.list7">
                <listIntroduction>the rules of procedure to be observed in regard to the  transaction of business at its meetings and the number of members  which shall form a quorum at a meeting under sub- section (10) of  section 3;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-25.2.list7.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the conditions and limitations subject to which the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Council may appoint officers and other employees under sub-</p>
              <blockList id="section-25.2.list10">
                <listIntroduction>section (4) of section 6;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-25.2.list10.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the conditions of service and the remuneration of  officers and other employees appointed by the Council under sub-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-25.2.list12">
                <listIntroduction>section (5) of section 6;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-25.2.list12.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the matters in respect of which the Council may  undertake measures in the discharge of its functions under clause</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-25.2.list12.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>of sub- section (2) of section 7;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-25.2.list12.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>the remuneration payable to the person or persons  referred to in clause (b) of sub- section (2) of section 8;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-25.2.list12.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the conditions subject to which the Council shall borrow  on the security of the Jute Fund or any other asset under section</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>the form and manner in which the accounts of the Council  shall be maintained under sub- section (1) of section 12;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>the time at which and the form and manner in which the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Council shall furnish returns, statements and other particulars  under sub- section (1) of section 14;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list3.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>the form in which and the date before which the Council  shall furnish to the Central Government the report of its  activities, policy and programmes under sub- section (3) of  section 14;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list3.m">
                  <num>(m)</num>
                  <p>any other matter which is to be or may be prescribed or  provided for by rules under this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-11.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may  be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in  session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in  one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the  expiry of the session immediately following the session or the  successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not  be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified  form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any  such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the  validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
