<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1861/16/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1861/16"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Stage- Carriages Act, 1861"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1861/16/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1861/16/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1861/16/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1861/16/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-11-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Stage- Carriages Act, 1861]</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 16 OF 1861</docNumber>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-7the">
        <num>7the.</num>
        <heading>July, 1861.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7the.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>An Act for licensing and regulating Stage- Carriages.</p>
            <p>Preamble.- WHEREAS it is expedient to licence and to regulate  stage- carriages in the Provinces; It is enacted as follows:--</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Definition of stage- carriage.-- Every carriage drawn by one or  more  horses which shall ordinarily be used for the purpose of  conveying passengers for hire to or from any place in the Stats,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>shall, without regard to the form or construction of such carriage, be  deemed to be a stage- carriage within the meaning of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Carriages to be licensed.-- No carriage shall be used as a  stage- carriage unless licensed by a  Magistrate or by the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Commissioner of Police of a Presidency- town.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Power to refuse license.-- The Magistrate or  Commissioner  of Police to whom the application for a license of a stage- carriage is  made may refuse to license the same, if he shall be of opinion that  such stage- carriage is unserviceable or is unsafe or unfit for public  accommodation or use.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Particulars of license.-- If a Magistrate or  Commissioner of</p>
            <p>Police as aforesaid shall grant a license, the license shall set forth  the number thereof, the name and residence of the proprietor of the  stage- carriage, the place at which his head office is held, the  largest number of passengers and the greatest weight of luggage to be  carried in or on such carriage, the number of horses by which such  carriage is to be drawn, and the name of the place at which such  carriage is licensed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Charge for and duration of license.--  For every such  license there shall be paid by the proprietor of the stage- carriage  the sum of five rupees or such less sum as the State Government may  fix, and such license shall be in force for one year from the date  thereof.]</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>When a licensed stage- carriage is transferred to a new proprietor  within the year, the name of such new proprietor shall, on application  to that effect, be substituted in the license for the name of the  former proprietor without any further payment for that year; and every  person who appears by the license to be the proprietor, shall be  deemed to be such proprietor for all the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Particulars to be painted on conspicuous part of carriage.-- On  any stage- carriage being licensed, the proprietor thereof shall cause  the number of the license and all the other particulars of the license  to be distinctly painted in the English language and character upon a  conspicuous part of such stage- carriage.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for letting carriage without having particulars  painted.-- The proprietor of any licensed stage- carriage who shall let  such stage- carriage for hire without the particulars specified in  section 3 being painted on such carriage in the manner directed in the  last preceding section, shall be liable to a fine not exceeding one  hundred rupees.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for letting for hire unlicensed carriage.-- Whoever  lets for hire any stage- carriage without the same being licensed as  provided by this Act, shall be liable, on a first conviction, to a  fine not exceeding one hundred rupees, and on any subsequent  conviction, to a fine which may extend to five hundred rupees.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for allowing carriage to be drawn by fewer animals or  more passengers, etc., to be carried than provided by license.-- Any  proprietor, or agent of a proprietor, or any driver of a licensed  stage- carriage, who, knowingly permits such carriage to be drawn by a  less number of harses or who knowingly permits a larger number of  passengers, or a greater weight of luggage, to be carried by such  stage- carriage than shall be provided by the license, shall be liable  on a first conviction to a fine not exceeding one hundred rupees, and  on any subsequent conviction, to a fine which may extend to five  hundred rupees.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In every case where such stage- carriage shall be proved to have  been drawn by a less number of horses, or to have carried a larger  number of passengers or a greater weight of luggage, than shall be  provided by the license, the proprietor of such carriage shall be held  to have knowingly permitted such offence, unless he shall prove that  the offence was not committed with his connivance, and that he had  taken every reasonable precaution and had made reasonable provision to  prevent the commission of the offence.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for ill- treating animals.-- Any person who shall  cruelly beat, ill- treat, over- drive, abuse, torture or cause or  procure to be cruelly beaten, ill- treated, overdrive, abused or  tortured any horse employed in drawing or harnessed to any stage-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>carriage, or who shall harness to or drive in any stage- carriage any  horse which from sickness, age, wounds or other cause is unfit to be  driven in such stage- carriage, shall for every such offence be liable  to a fine not exceeding one hundred rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Revocation of license.-- Any Magistrate or  Commissioner  of Police within the local limits of whose jurisdiction any stage-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>carriage shall ply, or who has granted the license of any stage-</p>
            <p>carriage, may cancel the license of such stage- carriage if it shall  appear to him that such stage- carriage or any horse or any harness  used with such carriage is unserviceable or unsafe or otherwise unfit  for public accommodation or use.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for not conforming to provisions of section 5.-- In  any station or place in which a Magistrate shall reside and be, any  police- officer may, in any place within two miles of the office of  such Magistrate, seize any stage- carriage with the horse harnessed  thereto, if the full particulars of the license of such stage- carriage  be not distinctly painted on such stage- carriage in the manner  provided in section 5 of this Act.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Such carriage with the horse harnessed thereto shall be taken  without delay by such police- officer before such Magistrate, who shall  forthwith proceed to hear and determine the complaint of such police-</p>
            <p>officer; and, if thereupon any fine is imposed by such Magistrate and  such fine is paid, such stage- carriage and horse shall be immediately  released; and if such fine be not paid, such stage- carriage and horse  may be detained for twenty days as security for the payment thereof;</p>
            <p>and if the fine be not sooner paid, they may be sold and the proceeds  applied (so far as they extend) to the payment of the said fine, and  all costs and charges incurred on account of the detention and sale;</p>
            <p>and the surplus (if any), when claimed, shall be paid to the  proprietor of such carriage and horse; and if such surplus be not  claimed within a further period of two months from such sale, the same  shall be forfeited to the State.</p>
            <p>If the proceeds of such sale do not fully pay the fine and costs  and charges aforesaid, the balance may be recovered as hereinafter  provided.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for misconduct on part of drivers.-- If any driver of  any stage- carriage, or any other person having the care thereof,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>shall, through intoxication, neglect, or by wanton or furious driving,</p>
            <p>or by any other misconduct, endanger the safety of any passenger or  other person, or shall injure or endanger the property of the  proprietor of such stage- carriage or of any other person, every such  person so offending shall be liable to a fine not exceeding one  hundred rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Penalty when recoverable from proprietor.-- Whenever the  driver of any stage- carriage or the owner of any horse employed in  drawing any stage- carriage shall have committed any offence against  this Act for the commission whereof any penalty is by this Act  imposed, other than an offence specified in section 8, and such driver  or owner shall not be known, or being known cannot be found, or if the  penalty cannot be recovered from such driver or owner, the proprietor  of such carriage shall be liable to every such penalty as if he had  been the driver of such carriage or owner of such horse at the time  when such offence was committed:</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Proviso.-- Provided that if any such proprietor shall make out, to  the satisfaction of the Magistrate before whom any complaint or  information shall be heard, by sufficient evidence, that the offence  was committed by such driver or owner without the privity or knowledge  of such proprietor, and that no profit, advantage, or benefit, either  directly or indirectly, has accrued or can accrue to such proprietor  therefrom, and that he has used his endeavour to find out such driver  or owner, and has done all that was in his power to recover the amount  of the penalty from him, the Magistrate may discharge the proprietor  from such penalty, and shall levy the same upon such driver or owner  when found.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Issue of summons.-- Whenever any charge is made before any</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Magistrate of any offence under this Act on which it is necessary to  issue a summons to the proprietor of a stage- carriage, the Magistrate  shall issue such summons directed to such proprietor or his nearest  agent, and may transmit such summons by letter- post, which shall be  deemed to be good service thereof.</p>
            <p>The letter shall be registered at the post- office, and the cost  of the registration shall be born by the Government in the first  instance, but may be charged as costs in the case.</p>
            <p>The summons shall allow a reasonable time, in reference to the  distance to which the summons is sent, for the appearance of such  proprietor or his agent as aforesaid.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Adjudication of penalties.-- All penalties incurred under this</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Act shall be adjudged by a Magistrate or  Commissioner of Police  as aforesaid, and all orders made under this Act by such Magistrate or</p>
            <p>Commissioner of Police shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Recovery of penalties etc.-- All penalties imposed under this</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Act, or any balance of any fine, costs, or charges as mentioned in  section 11 of this Act, may in case of non- payment or non- recovery  thereof be levied by distress and sale of the movable property of the  offender by warrant under the hand of the Magistrate who imposed the  same.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Offender may be apprehended and detained in custody until  return of warrant of distress.-- In case any such penalties shall not  be forthwith paid, such Magistrate may order the offender to be  apprehended and detained in safe custody until the return can be  conveniently made to such warrant of distress, unless the offender  shall give security to the satisfaction of such Magistrate for his  appearance at such place and time as shall be appointed for the return  of the warrant of distress.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Imprisonment of offender if distress not sufficient.-- If upon  the return of such warrant it shall appear that no sufficient distress  can be had whereon to levy such penalty, and the same shall not be  forthwith paid, or in case it shall appear to the satisfaction of such</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Magistrate by the confession of the offender or otherwise that he has  not sufficient goods and chattels whereupon such penalty could be  levied if warrant of distress were issued, such Magistrate may, by  warrant under his hand, commit the offender  to prison, there to  be imprisoned, according to the discretion of such officer, for any  term not exceeding two calender months when the amount of penalty  shall not exceed fifty rupees, and for any term not exceeding four  calendar months when the amount shall not exceed one hundred rupees,</p>
            <p>and for any term not exceeding six calendar months in any other case,</p>
            <p>the commitment to be determinable in each of the cases aforesaid on  payment of the amount.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Recovery of penalty and costs from European British  subjects. Rep. by the A. O. 1950.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Jurisdiction.-- On complaint made before any Magistrate of any  offence committed under this Act, it shall not be necessary to prove  that the offence was committed within the local limits of such</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Magistrate or other officer.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20A">
        <num>20A.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.--</heading>
        <subsection id="section-20A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the  purposes and objects of this Act in the territories under its  administration or any part of the said territories.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-20A.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-20A.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>prescribe forms for licenses under this Act, the sums  payable for the same and the conditions on which they may be  granted, and the cases in which they may be revoked;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-20A.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>provide for the inspection of stage- carriages, and of  the animals employed in drawing them; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-20A.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>regulate the number and length of the stages for which  animals may be driven in stage- carriages, and the manner in which  they shall be harnessed and yoked.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In making any rule under this section the State Government  may direct that a breach thereof shall be punishable with fine which  may extend to one hundred rupees.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Interpretation- clause." Magistrate."-- The term" Magistrate"</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>in this Act shall include all Magistrates and other persons exercising  the powers of a Magistrate:</p>
            <p>Act applicable to all animals used for drawing carriages.-- 2</p>
            <p>All expressions and provisions which in this Act are applied to  horses shall also apply to all other animals employed in drawing any  carriage ordinarily used for the purpose of conveying passengers for  hire to or from any place in the States:</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Extent of Act.-- This Act, as amended by subsequent</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Acts, extends to the whole of India except  the territories  which, immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised in</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <part id="part-B">
        <num>B</num>
        <heading>States]; but it shall not apply to carriages ordinarily plying  for hire within the limits of any municipality or cantonment or other  place in which any law for the regulation of carriages is for the time  being in force.</heading>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Power to State Government to exempt.-- The State Government  may, by notification in the Official Gazette, exempt any carriages or  class of carriages from all or any of the provisions of this Act.]</heading>
        </section>
      </part>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
