<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1944/1/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1944/1"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Central Excises And Salt Act, 1944"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1944/1/eng@1944-02-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1944/1/eng@1944-02-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1944-02-24" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1944/1/eng@1944-02-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1944/1/eng@1944-02-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Central Excises And Salt Act, 1944</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT No. 1 OF 1944</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 24th February, 1944.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to consolidate and amend the law relating to Central duties  of  excise and to salt.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to consolidate and amend the law  relating  to Central duties of excise on goods manufactured or produced  in     certain parts] of India] and to salt;</p>
        <p>It is hereby enacted as follows:-</p>
        <p>CHAP</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title extent and commencement.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called  the Central Excises and Salt Act, 1944;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It extends to the whole of India ;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on such date 5 as the Central</p>
              <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint in  this behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in  the subject or context,-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" adjudicating authority" means any authority competent  to pass any order or decision under this Act, but does not  include the Central Board of Excise and Customs constituted  under the Central Boards of Revenue Act, 1963, (54 of 1963)</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Collector of Central Excise (Appeals) or Appellate Tribunal;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.aa">
                  <num>(aa)</num>
                  <p>" Appellate Tribunal" means the Customs, Excise and Gold</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.Control">
                  <num>(Control)</num>
                  <p>Appellate Tribunal constituted under section 129 of  the Customs Act, 1962;] (52 of 1962)</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.aaa">
                  <num>(aaa)</num>
                  <p>]" broker" or" commission agent" means a person who in  the ordinary course of business makes contracts for the sale  or purchase of excisable goods for others;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" Central Excise Officer" means any officer of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Central Excise Department, or any person (including an   officer of the State Government) invested by the  Central</p>
              <p>Board of Excise and Customs constituted under the Central</p>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Boards of Revenue Act, 1963 (54 of 1963) with any of the  powers of a Central Excise Officer under this Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" curing" includes wilting, drying, fermenting and any  process for rendering an unmanufactured product fit for  marketing or manufacture;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" excisable goods" means goods specified in the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-scheduleto">
      <doc name="scheduleto">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1944/1/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1944/1"/>
              <FRBRalias value="the Central Excise Tariff Act, 1985] as being  subject to a duty of excise and includes salt; (5 of 1986)"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1944/1/eng@1944-02-24/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1944/1/eng@1944-02-24"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1944/1/eng@1944-02-24/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1944/1/eng@1944-02-24"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduleto">
            <paragraph id="scheduleto.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <blockList id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list0">
                  <item id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list0.e">
                    <num>(e)</num>
                    <blockList id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list0.e.list0">
                      <listIntroduction>" factory" means any premises, including the precincts  thereof, wherein or in any part of which excisable goods  other than salt are manufactured, or wherein or in any part  of which any manufacturing process connected with the  production of these goods is being carried on or is  ordinarily carried on;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list0.e.list0.ee">
                        <num>(ee)</num>
                        <p>" Fund" means the Consumer Welfare Fund established  under section 12C;]</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </item>
                  <item id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list0.f">
                    <num>(f)</num>
                    <blockList id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list0.f.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>" manufacture" includes any process,-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list0.f.list1.i">
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <p>incidental or ancillary to the completion of a  manufactured product;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list0.f.list1.ii">
                        <num>(ii)</num>
                        <p>which is specified in relation to any goods in the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <p>Section or Chapter notes of the Schedule to the Central</p>
                <p>Excise Tariff Act, 1985 as amounting to manufacture, (5   of 1986).</p>
                <blockList id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list4">
                  <listIntroduction>and the word" manufacturer" shall be construed accordingly  and shall include not only a person who employs hired labour  in the production or manufacture of excisable, goods, but  also any person who engages in their production or  manufacture on his own account;]</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list4.g">
                    <num>(g)</num>
                    <p>" Prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <blockList id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list6">
                  <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list6.h">
                    <num>(h)</num>
                    <p>" sale" and" purchase", with their grammatical  variations and cognate expressions, mean any transfer of the  possession of goods by one person to another in the ordinary  course of trade or business for cash or deferred payment or  other valuable consideration;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list6.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>" saltpeter" includes rasi, sajji, and all other  substances manufactured from saline earth, and kharinun and  every form of sulphate or carbonate of soda;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list6.j">
                    <num>(j)</num>
                    <blockList id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list6.j.list0">
                      <listIntroduction>" salt factory" includes-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list6.j.list0.i">
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <p>a place used or intended to be used in the  manufacture of salt and all embankments, reservoirs,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <p>condensing and evaporating pans, buildings and waste  places situated within the limits of such place as  defined from time to time by the Collector of Central</p>
                <blockList id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list9">
                  <listIntroduction>Excise;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list9.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>all drying grounds and storage platforms and  storehouses appertaining to any such place;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list9.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>land on which salt is spontaneously produced.;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <blockList id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list11">
                  <listIntroduction>and a" private salt factory" is one not solely owned or not  solely worked by the Central Government;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list11.k">
                    <num>(k)</num>
                    <p>' wholesale dealer" means a person who buys or sells  excisable goods wholesale for the purpose of trade or  manufacture, and includes a broker or commission agent who,</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <p>in addition to making contracts for the sale or purchase of  excisable goods for others, stocks such goods belonging to  others as an agent for the purpose of sale.</p>
                <p>CHAP</p>
                <p>LEVY AND COLLECTION OF DUTY</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <chapter id="chapter-II">
              <num>II</num>
              <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>LEVY AND COLLECTION OF DUTY</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-3">
                <num>3.</num>
                <heading>Duties specified in the Schedule to the Central Excise Tariff</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Act, 1985 to be levied.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-3.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>There shall be levied and collected in  such manner as may be prescribed duties of excise on all excisable  goods other than salt which are produced or manufactured in  India]</p>
                    <p>and a duty on salt manufactured in, or imported by land into, any part  of  India] as, and at the rates, set forth in the  Schedule to the</p>
                    <p>Central Excise Tariff Act, 1985:] (5 of 1986)</p>
                    <blockList id="section-3.1.list4">
                      <listIntroduction>Provided that the duties of excise which shall be levied and  collected on any  excisable goods which are produced or  manufactured,-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-3.1.list4.i">
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <p>in a free trade zone and brought to any other place in</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-3.1.list6">
                      <listIntroduction>India; or</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-3.1.list6.ii">
                        <num>(ii)</num>
                        <p>by a hundred per cent., export- oriented undertaking and  allowed to be sold in India,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>shall be an amount equal to the aggregate of the duties of customs  which would be leviable under section 12 of the Customs Act, 1962 (52   of 1962) on like goods produced or manufactured outside India if  imported into India, and where the said duties of customs are  chargeable by reference to their value, the value of such excisable  goods shall, notwithstanding anything contained in any other provision  of this Act, be determined in accordance with the provisions of the</p>
                    <p>Customs Act, 1962 and the Customs Tariff Act, 1975. (51 of 1975)</p>
                    <p>Explanation 1.- Where in respect of any such like goods, any duty  of customs leviable under the said section 12 is leviable at different  rates, then, such duty shall, for the purposes of this proviso, be  deemed to be leviable under the said section 12 at the highest of  those rates.</p>
                    <blockList id="section-3.1.list11">
                      <listIntroduction>Explanation 2.- In this proviso,-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-3.1.list11.i">
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <p>" free trade zone" means the Kandla Free Trade Zone and  the Santa Cruz Electronics Export Processing Zone and  includes any other free trade zone which the Central</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette,</p>
                    <blockList id="section-3.1.list14">
                      <listIntroduction>specify in this behalf;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-3.1.list14.ii">
                        <num>(ii)</num>
                        <p>" hundred per cent. export- oriented undertaking" means  an undertaking which has been approved as a hundred per cent.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>export- oriented undertaking by the Board appointed in this  behalf by the Central Government in exercise of the powers  conferred by section 14 of the Industries (Development and</p>
                    <p>Regulation) Act, 1951, (65 of 1951) and the rules made under  that Act.]</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-3.1A">
                  <num>(1A)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The provisions of sub- section (1) shall apply in respect  of all excisable goods other than salt which are produced or  manufactured in India by, or on behalf of, Government, as they apply  in respect of goods which are not produced or manufactured by</p>
                    <p>Government.]</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-3.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official</p>
                    <p>Gazette, fix, for the purpose of levying the said duties, tariff  values of any articles enumerated, either specifically or under  general headings, in the  Schedule to the Central Excise Tariff Act,</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-1985">
                <num>1985.</num>
                <heading/>
                <paragraph id="section-1985.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>] (5 of 1986) as chargeable with duty ad valorem and may alter any  tariff values for the time being in force.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-1985.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-1985.3.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>Different tariff values may be fixed-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-1985.3.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>for different classes or descriptions of the same  excisable goods; or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-1985.3.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <blockList id="section-1985.3.list1.b.list0">
                          <listIntroduction>for excisable goods of the same class or description-</listIntroduction>
                          <item id="section-1985.3.list1.b.list0.i">
                            <num>(i)</num>
                            <p>produced or manufactured by different classes of  producers or manufacturers; or</p>
                          </item>
                          <item id="section-1985.3.list1.b.list0.ii">
                            <num>(ii)</num>
                            <p>sold to different classes of buyers:</p>
                          </item>
                        </blockList>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Provided that in fixing different tariff values in respect of  excisable goods falling under sub- clause (i) or sub- clause (ii),</p>
                    <p>regard shall be had to the sale prices charged by the different  classes of producers or manufacturers or, as the case may be, the  normal practice of the wholesale trade in such goods.]</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-2">
                <num>2.</num>
                <heading>3A. Emergency. power of Central Government to increase duties of  excise. Emergency. power of Central Government to increase duties of  excise. Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1960 (58 of 1960), s.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-2">
                <num>2.</num>
                <heading>and Sch. I.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-4">
                <num>4.</num>
                <heading>Valuation of excisable goods for purposes of charging of  duty of excise.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-4.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-4.1.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>Where under this Act, the duty of excise is  chargeable on any excisable goods with reference to value, such value  shall, subject to the other provisions of this section, be deemed to  be-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-4.1.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>the normal price thereof, that is to say, the price at  which such goods are ordinarily sold by the assessee to a  buyer in the course of wholesale trade for delivery at the  time and place of removal, where the buyer is not a related  person and the price is the sole consideration for the sale:</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-4.1.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>Provided that-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-4.1.list3.i">
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <p>where, in accordance with the normal practice of  the wholesale trade in such goods, such goods are  sold by the assessee at different prices to different  classes of buyers (not being related persons) each such  price shall, subject to the existence of the other  circumstances specified in clause (a), be deemed to be  the normal price of such goods in relation to each such  class of buyers;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-4.1.list3.ii">
                        <num>(ii)</num>
                        <p>where such goods are sold by the assessee in the  course of wholesale trade for delivery at the time and  place of removal at a price fixed under any law foe the  time being in force or at a price, being the maximum,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>fixed under any such law, then, notwithstanding anything  contained in clause (ill) of this proviso, the price or  the maximum price, as the case may be, so fixed, shall,</p>
                    <blockList id="section-4.1.list6">
                      <listIntroduction>in relation to the goods so sold, be deemed to be the  normal price thereof;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-4.1.list6.iii">
                        <num>(iii)</num>
                        <p>where the assessee so arranges that the goods are  generally not sold by him in the course of wholesale  trade except to or through a related person, the normal  price of the goods sold by the assessee to or through  such related person shall be deemed to be the price at  which they are ordinarily sold by the related person in  the course of wholesale trade at the time of removal, to  dealers (not being related persons) or where such goods  are not sold to such dealers, to dealers (being related   persons) who sell such goods in retail;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-4.1.list6.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>where the normal price of such goods is not  ascertainable for the reason that such goods are not sold or  for any other reason, the nearest ascertainable equivalent  thereof determined in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-4.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Where, in relation to any excisable goods the price thereof  for delivery at the Place of removal is not known and the value  thereof is determined with reference to the price for delivery at a  place other than the place of removal, the cost of transportation from  the place of removal to the place of delivery shall be excluded from  such price.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-4.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The provisions of this section shall not apply in respect of  any excisable goods for which a tariff value has been fixed under sub-</p>
                    <p>section (2) of section 3.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-4.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-4.4.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>For the purposes of this section,-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-4.4.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>" assessee" means the person who is liable to pay the  duty of excise under this Act and includes his agent;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-4.4.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <blockList id="section-4.4.list1.b.list0">
                          <listIntroduction>" place of removal" means-</listIntroduction>
                          <item id="section-4.4.list1.b.list0.i">
                            <num>(i)</num>
                            <p>a factory or any other place or premises of  production or manufacture of the excisable goods; or</p>
                          </item>
                          <item id="section-4.4.list1.b.list0.ii">
                            <num>(ii)</num>
                            <p>a warehouse or any other place or premises wherein  the excisable goods have been permitted to be deposited  without payment of duty, from where such goods are  removed;</p>
                          </item>
                        </blockList>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-4.4.list1.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>" related person" means a person who is so associated with  the assessee that they have interest, directly or indirectly, in the  business of each other and includes a holding company, a subsidiary  company, a relative and a distributor of the assessee, and any  sub- distributor of such distributor.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Explanation.- In this clause" holding company"," subsidiary  company and" relative" have the same meanings as in the Companies Act,</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-1956">
                <num>1956.</num>
                <heading/>
                <paragraph id="section-1956.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>; (1 of 1956)</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0">
                          <listIntroduction>" value", in relation to any excisable goods,-</listIntroduction>
                          <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0.i">
                            <num>(i)</num>
                            <p>where the goods are delivered at the time of removal in  a packed condition, includes the cost of such packing except  the cost of the packing which is of a durable nature and is  returnable by the buyer to the assessee.</p>
                          </item>
                        </blockList>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>Explanation.- In this sub- clause," packing" means the  wrapper, container, bobbin, pirn, spool, reel or warp beam or  any other thing in which or on which the excisable goods are  wrapped, contained or wound;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list3.ii">
                        <num>(ii)</num>
                        <p>does not include the amount of the duty of excise,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>sales tax and other taxes, if any, payable on such goods and,</p>
                    <p>subject to such rules as may be made, the trade discount</p>
                    <p>(such discount not being refundable on any account   whatsoever) allowed in accordance with the normal practice of  the wholesale trade at the time of removal in respect of such  goods sold or contracted for sale.</p>
                    <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list8">
                      <listIntroduction>Explanation.- For the purposes of this sub- clause, the  amount of the duty of excise payable on any excisable goods  shall be the sum total of-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list8.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>the effective duty of excise payable on such goods  under this Act; and</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list8.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>the aggregate of the effective duties of excise  payable under other Central Acts, if any, providing for  the levy of duties of excise on such goods,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list10">
                      <listIntroduction>and the effective duty of excise on such goods under each Act  referred to in clause (a) or clause (b) shall be,-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list10.i">
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <p>in a case where a notification or order providing for  any exemption (not being an exemption for giving credit with  respect to,  or reduction of duty of excise under such Act  on such goods equal to, any duty of excise under such Act, or  the additional duty under section 3 of the Customs Tariff</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list12">
                      <listIntroduction>Act, 1975, (51 of 1975) already paid] on the raw material or  component parts used in the production or manufacture of   such, goods) from the duty of excise under such Act is for  the time being in force, the duty of excise computed with  reference to the rate specified in such Act in respect of  such goods as reduced so as to give full and complete effect  to such exemption; and</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list12.ii">
                        <num>(ii)</num>
                        <p>in any other case, the duty of excise computed  with reference to the rate specified in such Act in  respect of such goods;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list12.e">
                        <num>(e)</num>
                        <p>" wholesale trade" means sales to dealers, industrial  consumers Government, local authorities and other buyers, who  or which purchase their requirements otherwise than in  retail.]</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-5">
                <num>5.</num>
                <heading>Remission of duty on goods found deficient in quantity.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-5.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Central Government may, by rules made under this section, provide  for remission of duty of excise leviable on any excisable goods which  due to any natural cause are found to be deficient in quantity.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-5.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Any rules made under sub- section (1) may, having regard to  the nature of the excisable goods or of processing or of curing  thereof, the period of their storage or transit and other relevant  considerations, fix the limit or limits of percentage beyond which no  such remission shall be allowed:</p>
                    <p>Provided that different limit or limits of percentage may be  fixed for different varieties of the same excisable goods or for  different areas or for different seasons.]</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-5A">
                <num>5A.</num>
                <heading>Power to grant exemption from duty of excise.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-5A.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>If the</p>
                    <p>Central Government is satisfied that it is necessary in the public  interest so to do, it may, by notification in the Official Gazette,</p>
                    <p>exempt generally either absolutely or subject to such conditions (to   be fulfilled before or after removal) as may be specified in the  notification, excisable goods of any specified description from the  whole or any part of the duty of excise leviable thereon:</p>
                    <p>Provided that, unless specifically provided in such notification,</p>
                    <p>no exemption. therein shall apply to excisable goods which are pro-</p>
                    <blockList id="section-5A.1.list6">
                      <listIntroduction>duced or manufactured-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-5A.1.list6.i">
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <p>in a free trade zone and brought to any other place in</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-5A.1.list8">
                      <listIntroduction>India; or</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-5A.1.list8.ii">
                        <num>(ii)</num>
                        <p>by a hundred per cent. export- oriented undertaking and  allowed to be sold in India.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Explanation.- In this proviso," free trade zone" and" hundred per  cent. export- oriented undertaking" shall have the same meanings as in</p>
                    <p>Explanation 2 to sub- section (1) of section 3.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-5A.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>If the Central Government is satisfied that it is necessary  in the public interest so to do, it may, by special order in each  case, exempt from the payment of duty of' excise, under circumstances  of an exceptional nature to be stated in such order, any excisable.</p>
                    <p>goods on which duty of excise is leviable.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-5A.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>An exemption under sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) in  respect of any excisable goods from any part of the duty of excise  leviable thereon (the duty of excise leviable thereon being herein-</p>
                    <p>after referred to as the statutory duty) may be granted by providing  for the levy of a duty on such goods at a rate expressed in a form or  method' different from the form or method in which the statutory duty  is leviable and any exemption granted in relation to any excisable  goods in th manner provided in this sub- section shall have effect  subject to the condition that the duty of excise chargeable on such  goods shall in no case exceed the statutory duty.</p>
                    <p>Explanation.--" Form or method", in relation to a rate of duty of  excise means. the basis, namely, valuation, weight, number, length,</p>
                    <p>area, volume or other measure with reference to which the duty is  leviable.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-5A.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every notification issued under sub- rule (1), and every  order made under sub- rule (2), of rule 8 of the Central Excise Rules,</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-1944">
                <num>1944.</num>
                <heading/>
                <paragraph id="section-1944.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>, and in force immediately before the commencement of the Customs  and Central Excises Laws (Amendment) Act, 1987 shall be deemed to have  been issued or made under the provisions of this section and shall  continue to have the same force and effect after such commencement  until it is amended, varied rescinded or superseded under the  provisions of this section.]</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-6">
                <num>6.</num>
                <heading>Registration of certain persons. Any prescribed person who  is engaged in-</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list0">
                      <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>the production or manufacture or any process of pro-</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>duction or manufacture of any specified goods included in the</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
            </chapter>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-scheduleto">
      <doc name="scheduleto">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in/act/1980/01/scheduleto"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in/act/1980/01"/>
              <FRBRalias value="the Central Excise Tariff Act, 1985, or"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in/act/1980/01/eng@/scheduleto"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in/act/1980/01/eng@"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in/act/1980/01/eng@/scheduleto"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in/act/1980/01/eng@"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduleto">
            <paragraph id="scheduleto.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <blockList id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list0">
                  <item id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>the wholesale purchase or sale (whether on his own   account or as a broker or commission agent) or the storage of  any specified goods included in the Schedule to the Central</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <p>Excise Tariff Act, 1985,</p>
                <p>shall get himself registered with the proper officer in such manner  as may be prescribed.]</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <section id="section-9">
              <num>9.</num>
              <heading>xxx.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-8">
              <num>8.</num>
              <heading>Restriction on possession of goods specified in the Second</heading>
            </section>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-fromsuchdateasmaybespecifiedinthisbehalfbythe">
      <doc name="fromsuchdateasmaybespecifiedinthisbehalfbythe">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1944/1/fromsuchdateasmaybespecifiedinthisbehalfbythe"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1944/1"/>
              <FRBRalias value="From such date as may be specified in this behalf by the"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1944/1/eng@1944-02-24/fromsuchdateasmaybespecifiedinthisbehalfbythe"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1944/1/eng@1944-02-24"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1944/1/eng@1944-02-24/fromsuchdateasmaybespecifiedinthisbehalfbythe"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1944/1/eng@1944-02-24"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="fromsuchdateasmaybespecifiedinthisbehalfbythe">
            <heading>Central Government by notification in the Official Gazette, no person  shall, except as provided by rules made under this Act, have in his  possession  any goods specified in the Second Schedule] in excess of  such quantity as may be prescribed for the purposes of this section as  the maximum amount of such goods or of any variety of such goods which  may be possessed at any one time by such a person.</heading>
            <section id="section-9">
              <num>9.</num>
              <heading>Offences and penalties.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-9.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-9.1.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>] Whoever commits any of the  following offences, namely.-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-9.1.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>contravenes any of the provisions of section 8 or of  a rule made under clause (iii) or clause (xxvii) of sub-</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-9.1.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>section (2) of section 37;]</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-9.1.list3.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <blockList id="section-9.1.list3.b.list0">
                        <listIntroduction>evades the payment of any duty payable under this Act;</listIntroduction>
                        <item id="section-9.1.list3.b.list0.bb">
                          <num>(bb)</num>
                          <p>removes any excisable goods in contravention of any of  the provisions of this Act or any rule made thereunder or in  any way concerns himself with such removal;</p>
                        </item>
                        <item id="section-9.1.list3.b.list0.bbb">
                          <num>(bbb)</num>
                          <p>acquires possession of, or in any way concerns himself  in transporting, depositing, keeping, concealing, selling or  purchasing, or in any other manner deals with, any excisable  goods which he knows or has reason to believe are liable to  confiscation under this Act or any rule made thereunder;]</p>
                        </item>
                      </blockList>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-9.1.list3.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>fails to supply any information which he is required by  rules made under this Act to supply, or (unless with a  reasonable belief, the burden of proving which shall be upon   him, that the information supplied by him is true) supplies  false information;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-9.1.list3.d">
                      <num>(d)</num>
                      <p>attempts to commit, or abets the commission of, any of  the offences mentioned in clauses (a) and (b) of this  section;</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-9.1.list5">
                    <listIntroduction>shall be punishable,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-9.1.list5.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>in the case of an offence relating to any excisable  goods, the duty leviable thereon under this Act exceeds one  lakh of rupees, with imprisonment for a term which may extend  to seven years and with fine:</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-9.1.list7">
                    <listIntroduction>Provided that in the absence of special and adequate reasons  to the contrary to be recorded in the judgment of the Court  such imprisonment shall not be for a term of less than six  months;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-9.1.list7.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>in any other case, with imprisonment for a term which  may extend to three years or with fine or with both.]</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>If any person convicted of an offence under this section is  again convicted of an offence under this section, then, he shall be  punishable for the second and for every subsequent offence with  imprisonment for a term which may extend to seven years and with fine:</p>
                  <p>Provided that in the absence of special and adequate reasons to  the contrary to be recorded in the judgment of the Court such  imprisonment shall not be for a term of less than six months.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>For the purposes of sub- sections (1) and (2), the following  shall not be considered as special and adequate reasons for awarding  a sentence of imprisonment for a term of less than six months,</p>
                  <blockList id="section-9.3.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>namely:-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-9.3.list2.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>the fact that the accused has been convicted for the  first time for an offence under this Act;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-9.3.list2.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>the fact that in any proceeding under this Act, other  than a prosecution, the accused has been ordered to pay a  penalty or the goods in relation to such proceedings have  been ordered to be confiscated or any other action has been  taken against him for the same act which constitutes the  offence;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-9.3.list2.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>the fact that the accused was not the principal  offender and was acting merely as a carrier of goods or  otherwise was a secondary party in the commission of the  offence;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-9.3.list2.iv">
                      <num>(iv)</num>
                      <p>the age of the accused.]</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-9A">
              <num>9A.</num>
              <heading>Certain offences to be non- cognisable. Notwithstanding  anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 4, (5 of</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-1898">
              <num>1898.</num>
              <heading/>
              <paragraph id="section-1898.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>) offences under section 9 shall be deemed to be non- cognisable  within the meaning of that Code.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-9AA">
              <num>9AA.</num>
              <heading>Offences by companies.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-9AA.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where an offence under this Act  has been committed by a company, every person who at the time the  offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible to, the  company for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as the  company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be  liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:</p>
                  <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render  any such person liable to any punishment provided in this Act, if be  proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or that he  had exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such  offence.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9AA.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where  an offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is  proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or  connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any  director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such  director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to  be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against  and punished accordingly.</p>
                  <blockList id="section-9AA.2.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-9AA.2.list2.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>" company" means any body corporate and' includes a firm or  other association of individuals; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-9AA.2.list2.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>" director" in relation to a firm means a partner in the  firm.]</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-9B">
              <num>9B.</num>
              <heading>Power of Court to publish name, place of business etc., of  persons convicted under the Act.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-9B.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where any person is convicted  under this Act for contravention of any of the provisions thereof, it  shall be competent for the Court convicting- the person to cause the  name and place of business or residence of such person, nature of the  contravention, the fact that the person has been so convicted and such  other particulars as the Court may consider to be appropriate in the  circumstances of the case, to be published at the expense of such  person, in such newspapers or in such manner as the Court may direct.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9B.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>No publication under sub- section (1) shall be made until the  period for preferring an appeal against the orders of the Court has  expired without any appeal having been preferred, or such an appeal,</p>
                  <p>having been preferred, has been disposed of.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9B.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The expenses of any publication under sub- section (1) shall  be recoverable from the convicted person as if it were a fine imposed  by the Court.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-9C">
              <num>9C.</num>
              <heading>Presumption of culpable mental state.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-9C.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>In any prosecution  for an offence under this Act which requires a culpable mental state  on the part of the accused, the Court shall presume the existence of  such mental state but it shall be a defence for the accused to prove  the fact that he had no such mental state with respect to the act  charged as an offence in that prosecution.</p>
                  <p>Explanation.- In this section," culpable mental state" includes  intention motive, knowledge of a fact, and belief in, or reason to  believe, a fact.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9C.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>For the purposes of this section, a fact is said to be  proved only when the Court believes it to exist beyond reasonable  doubt and not merely when its existence is established by a  preponderance of probability.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-9D">
              <num>9D.</num>
              <heading>Relevancy of statements under certain circumstances.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-9D.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A</p>
                  <p>statement made arid signed by a person before any Central Excise</p>
                  <blockList id="section-9D.1.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>Officer of a gazetted rank during the course of any inquiry or  proceeding under this Act shall be relevant, for the purpose of  proving, in any prosecution for an offence under this Act, the truth  of the facts which it contains,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-9D.1.list3.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>when the person who made the statement is dead or  cannot be found, or is incapable of giving evidence, or is  kept out of the way by the adverse party, or whose presence  cannot be obtained without an amount of delay or expense  which, under the circumstances of the case, the Court  considers unreasonable; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-9D.1.list3.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>when the person who made the statement is examined as a  witness in the case before the Court and the Court is of  opinion that, having regard to the circumstances of the case,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>the statement should be admitted in evidence in the interests  of justice.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9D.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The provisions of sub- section (1) shall, so far as may be,</p>
                  <p>apply in relation to- any proceedings under this Act, other than a  proceeding before a Court, as they apply in relation to a proceeding  before a Court.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-9E">
              <num>9E.</num>
              <heading>Application of section 562 of the Code of Criminal Procedure,</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-1898">
              <num>1898.</num>
              <heading/>
              <paragraph id="section-1898.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>, and of the Probation of offenders Act, 1958.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <subsection id="section-1898.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Nothing  contained in section 562 of the Code of Criminal Procedure 1898 1, (5   of 1898) or in the Probation of Offenders Act, 1958, (20 of 1958)</p>
                  <p>shall apply to a person convicted of an offence under this Act unless  that person is under eighteen years of age.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-1898.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The provisions of sub- section (1) shall have effect  notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (3) of section 9.]</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-10">
              <num>10.</num>
              <heading>Power of Courts to order forfeiture. Any Court trying an  offence under this Chapter may order the forfeiture to Government of  any goods in respect of which the Court is satisfied that an offence  under this Chapter has been committed, and may also order the  forfeiture of any receptacles, packages or coverings in which such  goods are contained and the animals, vehicles, vessels or other  conveyances, used in carrying the goods and any implements or  machinery used in the manufacture of the goods.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-11">
              <num>11.</num>
              <heading>Recovery of sums due to Government. In respect of duty and any  other sums of any kind payable to the Central Government under any of  the provisions of this Act or of the rules made thereunder, the  officer empowered by the  Central Board of Excise and Customs  constituted under the Central Boards of Revenue Act, 1963] (54 of</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-1963">
              <num>1963.</num>
              <heading/>
              <paragraph id="section-1963.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>) to levy such duty or require the payment of such sums may deduct  the amount so payable from any money owing to the person from whom  such sums may be recoverable or due which may be in his hands or under  his disposal or control, or may recover the amount by attachment and  sale of excisable goods belonging to such person; and if the amount  payable is not so recovered he may prepare a certificate signed by him  specifying the amount due from the person liable to pay the same and  send it to the Collector of the district in which such person resides  or conducts his business and the said Collector, on receipt of such  certificate, shall proceed to recover from the said person the amount  specified therein as if it were an arrear of land revenue.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-11A">
              <num>11A.</num>
              <heading>Recovery of duties not levied or not paid or short levied  or short paid or erroneously refunded.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-11A.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>When any duty of excise has  not been levied or paid or has been short- levied or short- paid or  erroneously refunded, a Central Excise Officer may, within six months  from the relevant date, serve notice on the person chargeable with the  duty which has not been levied or paid or which has been short- levied  or short- paid or to whom the refund has erroneously been made,</p>
                  <p>requiring him to show cause why he should not pay the amount specified  in the notice: (54 of 1963)</p>
                  <p>Provided that where any duty of excise has not been levied or  paid or has been short- levied or short- paid or erroneously refunded by  reason of fraud, collusion or any wilful misstatement or suppression  of facts, or contravention of any of the provisions of this Act or of  the rules made thereunder with intent to evade payment of duty, by  such person or his agent, the provisions of this sub- section shall  have effect,  as if (5 xxx),] for the words" six months", the words</p>
                  <p>" five years" were substituted.</p>
                  <p>Explanation.- Where the service of the notice is stayed by an  order of a Court, the period of such stay shall be excluded in  computing the aforesaid period of six months or five years, as the  case may be.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-11A.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Central Excise Officer 5 shall, after considering  the representation, if any, made by the person on whom notice is  served under sub- section (1), determine the amount of duty of excise  due from such person (not being in excess of the amount specified in   the notice) and thereupon such person shall pay the amount so  determined.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-11A.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-11A.3.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>For the purposes of this section-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-11A.3.list1.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>" refund" includes rebate of duty of excise on excisable  goods exported out of India or on excisable materials used in  the manufacture of goods which are exported out of India;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-11A.3.list1.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>" relevant date" means,.-</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-11A.3.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>in the case of excisable goods on which duty of excise  has not been levied or paid or has been short- levied or  short- paid-</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-11A.3.list1.A">
                      <num>(A)</num>
                      <p>where under the rules made under this Act a  monthly return, showing particulars of the duty paid  on the excisable goods removed during the month to which  the said return relates, is to be filed by a  manufacturer or producer or a licensee of a warehouse,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-11A.3.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>as the case may be, the date on which such return is so  filed;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-11A.3.list3.B">
                      <num>(B)</num>
                      <p>where no monthly return as aforesaid is filed, the  last date on which such return is to be filed under the  said rules;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-11A.3.list3.C">
                      <num>(C)</num>
                      <p>in any other case, the date on which the duty is  to be paid under this Act or the rules made thereunder;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-11A.3.list3.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>in a case where duty of excise is provisionally  assessed under this Act or the rules made thereunder, the  date of adjustment of- duty after the final assessment thereof</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-11A.3.list5">
                    <listIntroduction>;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-11A.3.list5.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>in the case of excisable goods on which duty of excise  has been erroneously refunded, the date of such refund.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-11B">
              <num>11B.</num>
              <heading>Claim for refund of duty.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-11B.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Any person claiming refund of  any duty of excise may make an application for refund of such duty to  the Assistant Collector of Central Excise before the expiry of six  months  from the relevant date  in such form as may be prescribed  and the application shall be accompanied by such documentary or other  evidence (including the documents referred to in section 12A) as the  applicant may furnish to establish that the amount of duty of excise  in relation to which such refund is claimed was collected from, or  paid by, him and the incidence of such duty had not been passed on by  him to any other person:</p>
                  <blockList id="section-11B.1.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>Provided that where an application for refund has been made  before the commencement of the Central Excises and Customs Laws</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-11B.1.list2.Amendment">
                      <num>(Amendment)</num>
                      <p>Act, 1991, such application shall be deemed to have been  made under this sub- section as amended by the said Act and the same  shall be dealt with in accordance with the provisions of subsection</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-11B.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>as substituted by that Act]:</p>
                  <p>Provided further that] the limitation of six months shall not  apply where any duty has been paid under protest.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-11B.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>if, on receipt of any such application, the Assistant Col-</p>
                  <p>lector of Central Excise is satisfied that the whole or any part of  the duty of excise paid by the applicant is refundable, he may make an  order accordingly and the amount so determined shall be credited to  the Fund:</p>
                  <p>Provided that the amount of duty of excise as determined by the</p>
                  <blockList id="section-11B.2.list4">
                    <listIntroduction>Assistant Collector of Central Excise under the foregoing provisions  of this sub- section shall, instead of being credited to the Fund, be  paid to the applicant, if such amount is, relatable to--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-11B.2.list4.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>rebate of duty of excise on excisable goods exported  out of India or, on excisable materials used in the manufac-</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-11B.2.list6">
                    <listIntroduction>ture of goods which are exported out of India;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-11B.2.list6.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>unspent advance deposits lying in balance in the  applicant' s account current maintained with the Collector of</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-11B.2.list8">
                    <listIntroduction>Central Excise;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-11B.2.list8.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>refund of credit of duty paid on excisable goods used  as inputs in accordance with the rules made, or any notifica-</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-11B.2.list10">
                    <listIntroduction>tion issued, under this Act;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-11B.2.list10.d">
                      <num>(d)</num>
                      <p>the duty of excise paid by the manufacturer, if he had  not passed on the incidence of such duty to any other person;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-11B.2.list10.e">
                      <num>(e)</num>
                      <p>the duty of excise borne by the buyer, if he had not  passed on the incidence of such duty to any other person;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-11B.2.list10.f">
                      <num>(f)</num>
                      <p>the duty of excise borne by any other such class of  applicants as the Central Government may, by notification in  the Official Gazette, specify:</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Provided further that no notification under clause (f) of the  first proviso shall be issued unless in the opinion of the Central</p>
                  <p>Government the incidence of duty has not been passed on by the persons  concerned to any other person.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-11B.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any  judgment, decree, order or direction of the Appellate Tribunal or any</p>
                  <p>Court or in any other provision of this Act or the rules made  thereunder or any other law for the time being in force, no refund  shall be made except as provided in sub- section (2).</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-11B.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every notification under clause (f) of the first proviso to  subsection (2) shall be laid before each House of Parliament, if it is  sitting, as soon as may be after the issue of the notification, and,</p>
                  <p>if it is not sitting, within seven days of its reassembly, and the</p>
                  <p>Central Government shall seek the approval of Parliament to the  notification by a resolution moved within a period of fifteen days  beginning with the day on which the notification is so laid before the</p>
                  <p>House of the People and if Parliament makes any modification in the  notification or directs that the notification should cease to have  effect, the notification shall thereafter have effect only in such  modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be, but without  prejudice to the validity of anything previously done thereunder.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-11B.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that any  notification issued under clause (f) of the first proviso to sub-</p>
                  <p>section (2), including any such notification approved or modified  under sub- section (4), may be rescinded by the Central Government at  any time by notification in the Official Gazette."]</p>
                  <blockList id="section-11B.5.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-11B.5.list3.A">
                      <num>(A)</num>
                      <p>" refund" includes rebate of duty of excise on excisable  goods exported out of India or on excisable materials used  in  the manufacture of goods which are exported out of India;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-11B.5.list3.B">
                      <num>(B)</num>
                      <p>" relevant date" means,-</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-11B.5.list3.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>in the case of goods exported out of India where a  refund of excise duty paid is available in respect of  the goods themselves or, as the case may be, the  excisable materials used in the manufacture of such  goods,-</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-11B.5.list3.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>if the goods are exported by sea or air, the date  on which the ship or the aircraft in which such goods  are loaded, leaves India, or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-11B.5.list3.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>if the goods are exported by land, the date on  which such goods pass the frontier, or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-11B.5.list3.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>if the goals arc exported by post, the date of despatch  of goods by the Post Office concerned to a place outside</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-11B.5.list5">
                    <listIntroduction>India;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-11B.5.list5.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>in the case of goods returned for being remade,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-11B.5.list7">
                    <listIntroduction>refined, reconditioned, or subjected to any other similar  process, in any factory, the date of entry into the factory  for the purposes aforesaid;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-11B.5.list7.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>in the case of goods to which banderols are required to  be affixed if removed for home consumption but not so  required when exported outside India, if returned to a  factory after having been removed from such factory for  export out of India, the date of entry into the factory;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-11B.5.list7.d">
                      <num>(d)</num>
                      <p>in a, case where a manufacturer is required to pay a  sum, for a certain period, on the basis of the rate fixed by  the Central Government by notification in the Official</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-11B.5.list9">
                    <listIntroduction>Gazette in full discharge of his liability for the duty  leviable on his production of certain goods, if after the  manufacturer has made the payment on the basis of such rate  for any period but before the expiry of that period such rate  is reduced, the date of such reduction;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-11B.5.list9.e">
                      <num>(e)</num>
                      <p>in the case of a person, other than the manufacturer,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-11B.5.list11">
                    <listIntroduction>the date of purchase of the goods by such person;"]</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-11B.5.list11.f">
                      <num>(f)</num>
                      <p>in any other case, the date of payment of duty.]</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-11C">
              <num>11C.</num>
              <heading>Power not to recover duty of excise not levied or short-</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-11C.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>levied as a result of general practice.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <subsection id="section-11C.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-11C.1.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding  anything contained in this Act, if the Central Government is  satisfied-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-11C.1.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>that a practice was, or is, generally prevalent  regarding levy of duty of excise (including non- levy thereof)</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-11C.1.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>on any excisable goods; and</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-11C.1.list3.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <blockList id="section-11C.1.list3.b.list0">
                        <listIntroduction>that such goods were, or are, liable-</listIntroduction>
                        <item id="section-11C.1.list3.b.list0.i">
                          <num>(i)</num>
                          <p>to duty of excise, in cases where according to the  said practice the duty was not, or is not being, levied,</p>
                        </item>
                      </blockList>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-11C.1.list5">
                    <listIntroduction>or</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-11C.1.list5.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>to a higher amount of duty of excise than what  was, or is being, levied, according to the said  practice,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>then, the Central Government may, by notification in the Official</p>
                  <p>Gazette, direct that the whole of the duty of excise payable on such  goods, or, as the case may be, the duty of excise in excess of that  payable on such goods, but for the said practice, shall not be  required to be paid in respect of the goods on which the duty of  excise was not, or is not being, levied, or was, or is being, short-</p>
                  <p>levied, in accordance with the said practice.]</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-11C.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where any notification under sub- section (1) in respect of  any goods has been issued, the whole of the duty of excise paid on  such goods or, as the case may be, the duty of excise paid in excess  of that payable on such goods, which would not have been paid if the  said notification had been in force, shall be dealt with in accordance  in force, shall be dealt with in accordance with the provisions of  sub- section (2) of section 11B:</p>
                  <p>Provided that the person claiming the refund of such duty or, as  the case may be, excess duty, makes an application in this behalf to  the Assistant Collector of Central Excise, in expiry of six months in  sub- section (1) Of section 11B, before the expiry of six months from  the date of issue of the said notification."]</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-11D">
              <num>11D.</num>
              <heading>Duties of excise collected from the buyer to be deposited  with the Central Government.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-11D.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Notwithstanding anything to the  contrary contained in any order or direction of the Appellate Tribunal  or any Court or in any other provision of this Act or the rules made  thereunder, every person who has collected any amount from the buyer  of any goods in any manner as representing duty of excise, shall  forthwith pay the amount so collected to the credit of the Central</p>
                  <p>Government.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-11D.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The amount paid to the credit of the Central Government  under sub- section (1) shall be adjusted against the duty of excise  payable by the person on finalisation of assessment and where any  surplus is left after such adjustment, the amount of such surplus  shall either be credited to the Fund or, as the case may be, refunded  to the person who has borne the incidence of such amount, in accord-</p>
                  <p>ance with the provisions of section 11B and the relevant date for  making an application under that section in such cases shall be the  date of the public notice to be issued by the Assistant Collector of</p>
                  <p>Central Excise.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-12">
              <num>12.</num>
              <heading>Application of the provisions of Act 8 of 1878 to Central  excise duties. The Central Government may, by notification in the</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Official Gazette, declare that any of the provisions of the Sea</p>
                  <p>Customs Act, 1878 1, relating to the levy of and exemption from  customs duties, drawback of duty, warehousing, offences and penalties,</p>
                  <p>confiscation, and procedure relating to offences and appeals shall,</p>
                  <p>with such modifications and alterations as it may consider necessary  or desirable to adapt them to the circumstances, be applicable in  regard to like matters in respect of the duties imposed by section 3.</p>
                  <p>CHAP</p>
                  <p>INDICATING AMOUNT OF DUTY IN THE PRICE OF GOODS, ETC., FOR PURPOSEOF REFUND AND</p>
                  <p>CREDITING CERTAIN AMOUNTS TO THE FUND</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <chapter id="chapter-IIA">
              <num>IIA</num>
              <paragraph id="chapter-IIA.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>INDICATING AMOUNT OF DUTY IN THE PRICE OF GOODS, ETC., FOR PURPOSE</p>
                  <p>OF REFUND AND CREDITING CERTAIN AMOUNTS TO THE FUND</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-12A">
                <num>12A.</num>
                <heading>Price of goods to indicate the amount of duty paid thereon.</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-12A.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act or any other law for  the time being in force, every person who is liable to pay duty of  excise on any goods shall, at the time of clearance of the goods,</p>
                    <p>prominently indicate in all the documents relating to assessment,</p>
                    <p>sales invoice, and other like documents, the amount of such duty which  will form part of the price at which such goods are to be sold.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-12B">
                <num>12B.</num>
                <heading>Presumption that incidence of duty has been passed on to the  buyer. Ever person who has paid the duty of excise on any goods under  this Act shall, unless the, contrary is proved by him, be deemed to  have passed on the full incidence of such duty to the buyer of such  goods.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-12C">
                <num>12C.</num>
                <heading>Consumer Welfare Fund.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-12C.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>There shall be established by the</p>
                    <p>Central Government a fund, to be called the Consumer Welfare Fund.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-12C.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-12C.2.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>There shall be credited to the Fund, in such manner as may  be prescribed,--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-12C.2.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>the amount of duty of excise referred to in sub- section</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-12C.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>of section 11B or sub- section (2) of section 11C or sub-</p>
                    <blockList id="section-12C.2.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>section (2) of section 11D;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-12C.2.list2.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>the amount of duty of customs referred to in sub-</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>section (2) of section 27 or sub- section (2) of section 28A,</p>
                    <blockList id="section-12C.2.list5">
                      <listIntroduction>or  sub- section (2) of section 28B of the Customs Act, 1962;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-12C.2.list5.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>any income from investment of the amount credited to  the Fund and any other monies received by the Central Govern-</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>ment for the purposes of this Fund.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-12D">
                <num>12D.</num>
                <heading>Utilisation of the Fund.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-12D.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Any money credited to the Fund  shall be utilised by the Central Government for the welfare of the  consumers in accordance with such rules as that Government may make in  this behalf.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-12D.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Central Government shall maintain or, if it thinks fit,</p>
                    <p>specify the authority which shall maintain, proper and separate ac-</p>
                    <p>count and other relevant records in relation to the Fund in such form  as may be prescribed in consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor-</p>
                    <p>General of India."]</p>
                    <p>CHAP</p>
                    <p>POWERS AND DUTIES OF OFFICERS AND LANDHOLDERS</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
            </chapter>
            <chapter id="chapter-III">
              <num>III</num>
              <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>POWERS AND DUTIES OF OFFICERS AND LANDHOLDERS</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-12E">
                <num>12E.</num>
                <heading>Powers of Central Excise Officers.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-12E.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>A Central Excise</p>
                    <p>Officer may exercise the powers and discharge the duties conferred or  imposed under this Act on any other Central Excise Officer who is  subordinate to him.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-12E.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), the</p>
                    <p>Collector of Central Excise (Appeals) shall not exercise the powers  and discharge the duties conferred or imposed on a Central Excise</p>
                    <p>Officer other than those specified in section 14 or Chapter VIA.]</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-13">
                <num>13.</num>
                <heading>Power to arrest.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-13.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Any Central Excise Officer duly  empowered by the Central Government in this behalf may arrest any  person whom he has reason to believe to be liable to punishment under  this Act.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-13.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Any person accused or reasonably suspected' of committing an  offence under this Act or any rules made thereunder, who on demand of  any officer duly empowered by the, Central Government in this behalf  refuses to give his name and residence, or who gives a name or  residence which such officer has reason to believe to be false, may be  arrested by such officer in order that his name and residence may be  ascertained.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-14">
                <num>14.</num>
                <heading>Power to summon persons to give evidence and produce  documents in inquiries under this Act.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-14.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Any Central Excise Officer  duly empowered by the Central Government in this behalf shall have  power to summon any person whose attendance he considers necessary  either to give evidence or to produce a document or any other thing in  any inquiry which such officer is making for any of the purposes of  this Act. A summons to produce documents or other things may be for  the production of certain specified documents or things or for the  production of all documents or things of a certain description in the  possession or under the control of the person summoned.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-14.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>All persons so summoned shall be bound to attend, either in  person or by an authorised agent, as such officer may, direct; and all  persons so summoned shall be bound to state the truth upon any subject  respecting which they are examined or make statements and to produce  such documents and other things as may be required:</p>
                    <p>Provided that the exemptions under sections 132 and 133 of the</p>
                    <p>Code of Civil Procedure shall be applicable to requisitions for  attendance under this section. (5 of 1980).</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-14.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every such inquiry as aforesaid shall be deemed to be a</p>
                    <p>" judicial proceeding" within the meaning of section 193 and section</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-228">
                <num>228.</num>
                <heading>of the Indian Penal Code. (45 of 1860).</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-15">
                <num>15.</num>
                <heading>Officers required to assist Central Excise Officers. All  officers of Police and Customs and all officers of Government engaged  in the collection of land revenue, and all village officers are hereby  empowered and required to assist the Central Excise Officers in the  execution of this Act.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-16">
                <num>16.</num>
                <heading>Owners or occupiers of land to report manufacture of  contraband excisable goods. Every owner or occupier of land, and the  agent of any such owner or occupier, in charge of the management of-</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>that land, if contraband excisable goods are manufactured thereon,</p>
                    <p>shall in the absence of reasonable excuse be bound to give notice of  such manufacture to a Magistrate, or to an officer of the Central</p>
                    <p>Excise, Customs, Police, or Land Revenue Department, immediately the  fact comes to his knowledge.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-17">
                <num>17.</num>
                <heading>Punishment or connivance at offences. Any owner or occupier  of land, or any agent of such owner or occupier in charge of the  management of that land, who wilfully connives at any offence against  the provisions of this Act or of any rules made thereunder shall for  every Such offence be punishable with imprisonment for a term which  may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to five  hundred rupees, or with both.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-18">
                <num>18.</num>
                <heading>Searches and arrests how to be made. All searches made under  this Act or any rules' made thereunder and all arrests made under this</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Act shall be carried out in accordance with the provisions of the Code  of Criminal Procedure, 18981, relating respectively to' searches and  arrests made under that Code. (5 of 1898).</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-19">
                <num>19.</num>
                <heading>Disposal of persons arrested. Every person arrested under  this Act shall be forwarded without delay to the nearest Central</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Excise Officer empowered to send persons so arrested to a Magistrate,</p>
                    <p>or, if there is no such Central Excise Officer within a reasonable  distance,- to the officer- in- charge of the nearest police- station.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-20">
                <num>20.</num>
                <heading>Procedure to be followed by officer- in- charge of  police station. The officer- in- charge of a police- station to whom any  person is forwarded under section 19 shall either admit him to bail to  appear before the Magistrate having jurisdiction, or in default of  bail forward him in custody to such Magistrate.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-21">
                <num>21.</num>
                <heading>Inquiry how to be made by Central Excise Officers against  arrested persons forwarded to them under section 19.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-21.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>When any  person is forwarded under section 19 to a Central Excise Officer  empowered to send persons so arrested to a Magistrate, the Central</p>
                    <p>Excise Officer shall proceed to inquire into the charge against him.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-21.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>For this purpose the Central Excise Officer may exercise the  same powers and shall be subject to the same provisions as the  officer- in- charge of a police- station may exercise and is subject to  under the Code of Criminal Procedure, 18981, when investigating a  cognizable case: (5 of 1898).</p>
                    <blockList id="section-21.2.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>Provided that-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-21.2.list2.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>if the Central Excise Officer is of opinion that there  is sufficient evidence or reasonable ground of suspicion  against the accused person, he shall either admit him to bail  lo appear before a Magistrate having jurisdiction in the  case, or forward him in custody to such Magistrate;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-21.2.list2.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>if it appears to the Central Excise Officer that there  is not sufficient evidence or reasonable ground of suspicion  against the accused person, he shall release the accused  person on his executing a bond, with or without sureties as  the Central Excise Officer may direct, to appear, if and when  so required before the Magistrate having jurisdiction, and  shall make a full report of all the particulars of the case  to his official superior.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-22">
                <num>22.</num>
                <heading>Vexatious search, seizure, etc., by Central Excise Officer.</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-22.paragraph-0.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>Any Central Excise or other officer exercising powers under this Act  or under the rules made thereunder who-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-22.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>without reasonable ground of suspicion searches or  causes to be searched any house, boat or place;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-22.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>vexatiously and unnecessarily detains, searches or  arrests any person;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-22.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>vexatiously and unnecessarily seizes the moveable  property of any person, on pretence of seizing or searching  for any article liable to confiscation under this Act;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-22.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <p>commits, as such officer, any other act to the injury  of any person, without having reason to believe that such act  is required for the execution of his duty;</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>shall, for every such offence, be punishable with fine which may  extend to two thousand rupees.</p>
                    <p>Any person wilfully and maliciously giving false information and  so causing an arrest or a search to be made under this Act shall be  punishable with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees or with  imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years or with both.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-23">
                <num>23.</num>
                <heading>Failure of Central Excise Officer in duty. Any Central Excise</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Officer who ceases or refuses to perform or withdraws himself from the  duties of his office, unless he has obtained the express written per-</p>
                    <p>mission of the Collector of Central Excise, or has given to his  superior officer two months' notice in writing of his intention or has  other lawful excuse, shall on conviction before a Magistrate be  punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three  months or with fine which may extend to three months' pay, or with  both.</p>
                    <p>CHAP</p>
                    <p>TRANSPORT BY SEA</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
            </chapter>
            <chapter id="chapter-IV">
              <num>IV</num>
              <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>TRANSPORT BY SEA</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-24">
                <num>24.</num>
                <heading>Penalties for carrying excisable goods in certain vessels.</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>When any excisable goods are carried by sea in any vessel other than a  vessel of the burden of three hundred tons and upwards, the owner and  master of such vessel shall each be punishable with imprisonment for a  term which may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to  one thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-25">
                <num>25.</num>
                <heading>Exceptions. Nothing in section 24 applies to-</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-25.paragraph-0.list0">
                      <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>any excisable goods covered by a permit granted under  rules made under this Act;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>any excisable goods covered by a pass granted by any  officer whom the  Central Board of Excise and Customs  constituted under the Central Boards of Revenue Act, 1963]</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-25.paragraph-0.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>may appoint in this behalf; (54 of 1963).</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>such amount of excisable goods carried on board any  vessel for consumption by her crew or by the passengers or  animals (if any) on board as the  Central Board of Excise  and Customs constituted under the Central Boards of Revenue</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Act, 1963] may from time to time exempt from the operation of  section 24. (54 of 1963).</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-26">
                <num>26.</num>
                <heading>Power of stoppage, search and arrest. When any officer-</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>empowered by the  Central Board of Excise and Customs constituted  under the Central Boards of Revenue Act, 1963], (54 of 1963) to act</p>
                    <blockList id="section-26.paragraph-0.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>Under this section has reason to believe, from personal knowledge or  from information taken down in writing, that any excisable goods are  being carried, or have within the previous twenty- four hours been  carried, in any vessel so as to render the owner or master of such  vessel liable to the penalties imposed by section 24, he may require  such vessel to be brought- to and thereupon may-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>enter and search the vessel;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>require the master of the vessel to produce any  documents in his possession relating to the vessel or the  cargo thereof;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>seize the vessel if the officer has reason to believe  it liable to confiscation under this Act, and cause it to be  brought with its crew and cargo into any port in  India];</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-26.paragraph-0.list4">
                      <listIntroduction>and</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list4.d">
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <p>where any excisable goods are found on board the  vessel, search and arrest without a warrant any person on  board the vessel whom he has reason to believe to be  punishable under section 24.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-27">
                <num>27.</num>
                <heading>Penalties for resisting officer. Any master of a vessel  refusing or neglecting to bring- to the vessel or to produce his  papers when required to do so by an officer acting under section 26,</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>and any person obstructing any such officer in the performance of  his duty, may be arrested by such officer without a warrant, and shall  be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six  months or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with  both.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-28">
                <num>28.</num>
                <heading>Confiscation of vessel and cargo.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-28.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every vessel (including   all appurtenances) in which any excisable goods are carried so as to  render the owner or master of such vessel liable to penalties imposed  by section 24, the cargo on board such vessel and the excisable goods  in respect of which an offence under this Act has been committed shall  be liable to confiscation on the orders of the officer empowered in  this behalf by the Central Government.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-28.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Whenever any Customs Officer is satisfied that any article  is liable to confiscation under this section he may seize such  article, and shall at once report the seizure to his superior officer  for the information of the officer empowered to order confiscation  under sub- section (1) and such officer may, if satisfied on such  report or after making such inquiry as he thinks fit, that the article  so seized is liable, to confiscation, either declare it to be  confiscated, or impose a fine in lieu thereof not exceeding the value  of the article.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-29">
                <num>29.</num>
                <heading>Jurisdiction. Any offence punishable under section 24 or  section 27 may be deemed to have been committed within the limits of  the jurisdiction of the Magistrate of any place where the offender is  found, or to which, if arrested under section 26 or section 27, he may  be brought.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-30">
                <num>30.</num>
                <heading>Power to exempt from operation of his Chapter. The Central</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-30.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, exempt the  carriage of excisable goods within any local limits or in any class of  vessels from the operation of this Chapter, and, by like notification,</p>
                    <p>again subject such carriage to the operation of this Chapter.</p>
                    <p>CHAP</p>
                    <p>SPECIAL PROVISIONS RELATING TO SALT</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
            </chapter>
            <chapter id="chapter-V">
              <num>V</num>
              <paragraph id="chapter-V.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>SPECIAL PROVISIONS RELATING TO SALT</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-31">
                <num>31.</num>
                <heading>Special and permanent rights of manufacturing salt to be  recognised. The proprietor of a private salt factory who has by virtue  of a sanad granted by  the Government] or any former Government, a  special and permanent right to manufacture salt, or to excavate or  collect natural salt, shall on application made in accordance with the  rules made under this Act be entitled to a licence for such purpose  and to the annual renewal thereof, unless on a breach of the  provisions of this Act, his licence has been cancelled by an officer  duly empowered by the Central Government in this behalf.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-32">
                <num>32.</num>
                <heading>Rights of ordinary proprietors of existing salt- works. Every  proprietor of a private salt- work, other than a private salt factory,</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-32.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>to which section 31 applies, of which, under the provisions of section</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-17">
                <num>17.</num>
                <heading>of the Bombay Salt Act, 1890, (Bom. Act 11 of 1890) the proprietor  was entitled on application to a licence to manufacture or to excavate  or collect natural salt at such factory, shall continue to be  entitled, on, application made in accordance with the rules made under  this Act, to a licence for such purpose and to the annual renewal  thereof, unless on a breach of the provisions of this Act his licence  has been cancelled by an officer duly empowered by the Central</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Government in this behalf:</p>
                    <p>Provided that the Collector of Central Excise may at any time  withdraw or withhold a licence from the proprietor of any such salt  factory, if no salt' has been manufactured, excavated or collected in  such salt factory for the three years ending on the thirtieth day of</p>
                    <p>June last preceding the date of his order, or, with the previous  sanction of the  Central Board of Excise and Customs constituted  under the Central Boards of Revenue Act, 1963], (54 of 1963) if such  salt factory has not produced, on an average, during the said three  years, at least five thousand maunds. of salt per annum.</p>
                    <p>CHAP</p>
                    <p>ADJUDICATION OF CONFISCATIONS AND PENALTIES</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
            </chapter>
            <chapter id="chapter-VI">
              <num>VI</num>
              <paragraph id="chapter-VI.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>ADJUDICATION OF CONFISCATIONS AND PENALTIES</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-33">
                <num>33.</num>
                <heading>Power of adjudication. Where by the rules made under this Act  anything is liable to confiscation or any person is liable to a  penalty, such confiscation or penalty may be adjudged-</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-33.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-33.paragraph-0.list0">
                      <item id="section-33.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>without limit, by a Collector of Central Excise;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-33.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>up to confiscation of goods not exceeding five hundred  rupees in value and imposition of penalty not exceeding two  hundred and fifty rupees, by an Assistant Collector of</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Central Excise:</p>
                    <p>Provided that the  Central Board of Excise and Customs  constituted under the Central Boards of Revenue Act, 1963] (54 of</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-1963">
                <num>1963.</num>
                <heading/>
                <paragraph id="section-1963.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>) may, in the case of any officer performing the duties of an</p>
                    <p>Assistant Collector of Central Excise, reduce the limits indicated in  clause (b) of this section and may confer on any officer the powers  indicated in clause (a) or (b) of this section.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-34">
                <num>34.</num>
                <heading>Option to pay fine in lieu of confiscation. Wherever  confiscation is adjudged under this Act or the rules made thereunder,</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-34.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>the officer adjudging it shall give the owner of the goods an option  to pay in lieu of confiscation such fine as the officer thinks fit.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-34A">
                <num>34A.</num>
                <heading>Confiscation or penalty not to interfere with other  punishments. No confiscation made or penalty imposed under the  provisions, of this Act or of any rule made thereunder shall prevent  the infliction of any other punishment to which the person affected  thereby is liable under the provisions of this Act or under any other  law.]</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-34A.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>CHAP</p>
                    <p>APPEALS</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
            </chapter>
            <chapter id="chapter-VIA">
              <num>VIA</num>
              <paragraph id="chapter-VIA.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>APPEALS</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-35">
                <num>35.</num>
                <heading>Appeals to Collector (Appeals).</heading>
                <subsection id="section-35.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Any person aggrieved by  any decision or order passed under this Act by a Central Excise</p>
                    <p>Officer lower in rank than a Collector, of Central Excise may appeal  to the Collector of Central, Excise (Appeals) hereafter in this</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
            </chapter>
            <chapter id="chapter-referred">
              <num>referred</num>
              <heading>to as the Collector (Appeals) within three months  from the date of the communication to him of such decision or order:</heading>
              <paragraph id="chapter-referred.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Provided that the Collector (Appeals) may, if he is satisfied  that the appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from presenting  the appeal within the aforesaid period of three months, allow it to be  presented within a further period of three months.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <subsection id="chapter-referred.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every appeal under this section shall be in the prescribed  form and shall be verified in the prescribed manner.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <section id="section-35A">
                <num>35A.</num>
                <heading>Procedure in appeal.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-35A.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Collector (Appeals). shall give  an opportunity to the appellant to be heard, if he so desires.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35A.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Collector (Appeals) may, at the hearing of an appeal,</p>
                    <p>allow an appellant to go into any ground of appeal not specified in  the grounds of appeal, if the Collector (Appeals) is satisfied that  the omission of that ground from the grounds of appeal was not wilful  or unreasonable.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35A.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Collector (Appeals), may, after making such further  inquiry as may be necessary, pass such order as he thinks fit  confirming, modifying or annulling the decision or order appealed  against, or may refer the case back to the adjudicating authority with  such directions as he may think fit for a fresh adjudication or  decision, as the case may be, after taking additional evidence, if  necessary:</p>
                    <p>Provided that an order enhancing any penalty or fine in lieu of  confiscation or confiscating goods of greater value or reducing the  amount of refund shall not be passed unless the appellant has been  given a reasonable opportunity of showing cause against the proposed  order:</p>
                    <p>Provided further that where the Collector (Appeals) is of opinion  that any duty of excise has not been levied or paid or has been short-</p>
                    <p>levied or short- paid or erroneously refunded, no order requiring the  appellant to pay any duty not levied or paid, short- levied or short-</p>
                    <p>paid or erroneously refunded shall be passed unless the appellant is  given notice within the time limit specified in section 11 A to show  cause against the proposed order.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35A.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The order of the Collector (Appeals) disposing of the appeal  shall be in writing and shall state the points for determination the  decision thereon and the reasons for the decision.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35A.5">
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>On the disposal of the appeal, the Collector (Appeals) shall  communicate the order passed by him to the appellant, the adjudicating  authority and the Collector of Central Excise.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-35B">
                <num>35B.</num>
                <heading>Appeals to the Appellate Tribunal.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-35B.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-35B.1.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>Any person aggrieved  by any of the following orders may appeal to the Appellate Tribunal  against such order-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-35B.1.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>a decision or order passed by the Collector of Central</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-35B.1.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>Excise as an adjudicating authority;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-35B.1.list3.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>an order passed by the Collector (Appeals) under  section 35A;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-35B.1.list3.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>an order passed by the Central Board of Excise and</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Customs constituted under the Central Boards of Revenue Act,</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-1963">
                <num>1963.</num>
                <heading>(54 of 1963) (hereafter in this Chapter referred to as   the Board) or the Appellate Collector of Central Excise under  section 35, as it stood immediately before the appointed day;</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-1963.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list0">
                      <item id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <p>an order passed by the Board or the Collector of Central</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Excise, either before or after the appointed day, under  section 35A, as it stood immediately before that day:</p>
                    <blockList id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>Provided that no appeal shall lie to the Appellate Tribunal  and the Appellate Tribunal shall not have jurisdiction to  decide any appeal in respect' of any order referred to in  clause (b) if such order relates to,-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list3.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>a case of loss of goods, where the loss occurs in  transit from a factory to a warehouse or to another  factory, or from one warehouse to another, or during  the course of processing of the goods in a warehouse or  in storage, whether in a factory or in a warehouse;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>a rebate of duty of excise on goods exported to  any country or territory outside India or on excisable  materials used in the manufacture of goods which are  exported to any country or territory outside India;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>goods exported outside India (except to Nepal or</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Bhutan) without payment of duty:</p>
                    <blockList id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list6">
                      <listIntroduction>Provided further that] the Appellate Tribunal may, in its  discretion, refuse, to admit an appeal in respect of an order referred  to in clause (b) or clause (c) or clause (d) where-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list6.i">
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <p>in any disputed case, other than a case where the  determination of any question having a relation to the  rate of duty of excise or to the value, of goods for  purposes of assessment is in issue or is one of the  points in issue, the difference in duty involved or the  duty involved; or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list6.ii">
                        <num>(ii)</num>
                        <p>the amount of fine or penalty determined by such  order,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>does not exceed fifty thousand rupees 4</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-1963.1A">
                  <num>(1A)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every appeal against any order of the nature referred to  in the first proviso to sub- section (1), which is pending immediately  before the commencement of section 47 of the Finance Act, 1984, (21 of</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-1984">
                <num>1984.</num>
                <heading/>
                <paragraph id="section-1984.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>) before the Appellate Tribunal and any matter arising out of, or  connected with, such appeal and which is so pending shall stand  transferred on such commencement to the Central Government, and the</p>
                    <p>Central Government shall deal with such appeal or matter under section</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-35EE">
                <num>35EE.</num>
                <heading>as if such appeal or matter were an application or a matter  arising out of' an application made to it under that section.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-35EE.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Collector of Central Excise may, if he is of opinion  that an order passed by the Appellate Collector of Central Excise  tinder section 35, as it stood immediately before the appointed day,</p>
                    <p>or the Collector (Appeals) under section 35A, is not legal or proper,</p>
                    <p>direct any Central Excise Officer authorised by him in this behalf</p>
                    <p>(hereafter in this Chapter referred to as the authorised officer) to  appeal on his behalf to the Appellate Tribunal against such order.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35EE.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every appeal under this section shall be filed within three  months from the date on which the order sought to be appealed against  is communicate to the Collector of Central Excise, or, as the case may  be, the other party preferring the appeal.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35EE.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>On receipt of notice that an appeal has been preferred under  this section, the party against whom the appeal has been preferred  may, notwithstanding that. he may not have appealed against such order  or any part thereof, file, within forty- five days of the receipt of  the notice, a memorandum of cross objections verified in the  prescribed manner against any part of the order appealed against and  such memorandum shall be disposed of by the Appellate Tribunal as if  it were an appeal, presented within the time specified in sub- section</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35EE.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35EE.5">
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Appellate Tribunal may admit an appeal or permit the  filing of a memorandum of cross- objections after the expiry of the  relevant period referred to in sub- section (3) or sub- section (4), if  it is satisfied that there was sufficient cause for not presenting it  within that period.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35EE.6">
                  <num>(6)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>An appeal to the Appellate Tribunal shall be in the  prescribed form and shall be verified in the prescribed manner and  shall, in the case of an appeal made on or after the 1st day of June,</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-1993">
                <num>1993.</num>
                <heading/>
                <paragraph id="section-1993.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-1993.paragraph-0.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>, irrespective of the date of demand of duty Pr of levy of penalty  in relation to which the appeal is made, be accompanied by a fee of,-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-1993.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>where the amount of duty demanded and penalty levied by  any Central Excise Officer in the case to which the appeal  relates is one lakh rupees or less, two' hundred rupees:</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-1993.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>where the amount of duty demanded and penalty levied by  any Central Excise Officer in the case to which the appeal  relates is more than one lakh rupees, one thousand rupees:</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Provided that no such fee shall be payable in the case of an  appeal referred to in sub- Section.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-1993.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>or a memorandum of cross-</p>
                    <p>objections referred to in sub- section (4)."]</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-35C">
                <num>35C.</num>
                <heading>Orders of Appellate Tribunal.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-35C.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Appellate Tribunal  may, after giving the parties to the appeal an opportunity of being,</p>
                    <p>heard, pass such orders thereon as it thinks fit, confirming,</p>
                    <p>modifying or annulling the decision or order appealed against or may  refer the case back to the- authority which passed such decision or  order with such directions as the Appellate Tribunal may think fit,</p>
                    <p>for a fresh adjudication or decision, as the case may be, after taking  additional evidence, if necessary.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35C.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Appellate Tribunal may, At any time within four years  from the date of the order, with a view to rectifying any mistake  apparent from the record, amend any order passed by it under sub-</p>
                    <p>section (1) and shall make such amendments if the mistake is brought  to its notice by the Collector of Central Excise or the other party to  the appeal:</p>
                    <p>Provided that an amendment which has the effect of enhancing an  assessment or reducing a refund or otherwise increasing the liability  of the other party, shall not be made under this sub- section, unless  the Appellate Tribunal has given notice to him of its intention to do  so and has allowed him a reasonable opportunity of being heard.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35C.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Appellate Tribunal shall send a copy of every order  passed under this section to the Collector of Central Excise and the  other party to the appeal.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35C.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Save as provided in section 35G or section 35L, orders  passed by the Appellate Tribunal on appeal shall be final.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-35D">
                <num>35D.</num>
                <heading>Procedure of Appellate Tribunal.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-35D.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The provisions of  sub- sections (1), (2), (5) and (6) of section 129C of the Customs Act,</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-1962">
                <num>1962.</num>
                <heading/>
                <paragraph id="section-1962.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>, shall apply to the Appellate Tribunal in the discharge of its  functions under this Act as they apply to it in the discharge of its  functions under the Customs Act, 1962. (52 of 1962)</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-1962.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every appeal against a decision or order relating, among  other things, to the determination of any question having a relation  to the rate of duty of excise or to the value of goods for purposes of  assessment, shall be heard by a Special Bench constituted by the</p>
                    <p>President for hearings such appeals and such Bench- shall consist of  not less than" two members and shall include at least one judicial  member and one technical member.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-1962.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The President or any other member of the Appellate Tribunal  authorised in this behalf by the President may, sitting singly,</p>
                    <blockList id="section-1962.3.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>dispose of any case which has been allotted to the Bench of which he  is a member where-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-1962.3.list2.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>in any disputed case, other than a case where the  determination of any question having a relation to the rate  of duty of excise or to the value of goods for purposes of  assessment is in issue or is one of the points in issue, the  difference in duty involved or the duty involved; or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-1962.3.list2.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>the amount of fine or penalty involved,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>does not exceed  one lakh rupees]</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-35E">
                <num>35E.</num>
                <heading>Powers of Board or Collector of Central Excise to pass  certain orders.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-35E.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Board may, of its own motion, call for and  examine the record of any proceeding in which a Collector of Central</p>
                    <p>Excise as an adjudicating authority has passed any decision or order  under this Act for the purpose of satisfying itself as to the legality  or propriety of any such decision or order and may, by order, direct  such Collector to' apply to the, Appellate Tribunal  or, as the case  may be, the Customs and Excise Revenues Appellate Tribunal established  under section 3 of the Customs and Excise Revenues Appellate Tribunal</p>
                    <p>Act, 1986] (62 of 1986) for the determination of such points arising  out of the decision or order as may be specified by the Board in its  order.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35E.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Collector of Central Excise may, of his own motion, call  for and examine the record of any proceeding in which an adjudicating  authority subordinate to him has passed any decision or order under  this Act for the purpose of satisfying himself as to the legality or  propriety of any such decision or order and may, by order, direct such  authority to apply to the Collector (Appeals) for the determination of  such points arising' out of the decision or order as may be specified  by the Collector of Central Excise in his order.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35E.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>No order shall be made under sub- section (1) or sub- section</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35E.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>after the expiry of  one year] from the date of the decision or  order of the adjudicating authority.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35E.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Where in pursuance of an order under subsection (1) or sub-</p>
                    <p>section the adjudicating authority or the authorised officer makes an  application to the Appellate Tribunal  or, as the case may be, the</p>
                    <p>Customs and Excise Revenues Appellate Tribunal established under  section 3 of the Customs and Excise Revenues Appellate Tribunal Act,</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-1986">
                <num>1986.</num>
                <heading/>
                <paragraph id="section-1986.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>] (62 of 1986) or the Collector (Appeals) within a period of three  months from the date of communication of the order under sub- section</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-1986.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>or sub- section (2) to the adjudicating authority, such application  shall be heard by the Appellate Tribunal  or, as the case may be, the</p>
                    <p>Customs and Excise Revenues Appellate Tribunal established under  section 3 of the Customs and Excise Revenues Appellate Tribunal Act,</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-1986">
                <num>1986.</num>
                <heading/>
                <paragraph id="section-1986.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>] or the Collector (Appeals), as the case may be, as if such  application were an appeal made against the decision or order of the  adjudicating authority and the provisions of this Act regarding  appeals, including the provisions of sub- section (4) of section 35B</p>
                    <p>or, as the case may be the provisions of the Customs and Excise</p>
                    <p>Revenues Appellate Tribunal Act, 1986] shall, so far as may be, apply  to such application.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-1986.5">
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The provisions of this section shall not apply to any  decision or order in which the determination of any question having a  relation to the rate of duty of excise or to the value of goods for  the purposes of assessment of any duty is in issue or is one of the  points in issue.</p>
                    <p>Explanation.- For the purposes of this sub- section, the determi-</p>
                    <blockList id="section-1986.5.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>nation of a rate of duty in relation to any goods or valuation of any  goods for the purposes of assessment of duty includes the  determination of a question-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-1986.5.list3.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>relating to the rate of duty of excise for the time  being in force, whether under the Central Excise Tariff Act,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-1985">
                <num>1985.</num>
                <heading>or under any other Central Act providing for the levy  and collection of any duty of excise, in relation to any  goods on or after the 28th day of February, 1986; or</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-1985.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-1985.paragraph-0.list0">
                      <item id="section-1985.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>relating to the value of goods for the purposes of  assessment of any duty of excise in cases where the  assessment is made on or after the 28th day of February,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-1986">
                <num>1986.</num>
                <heading/>
                <paragraph id="section-1986.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-1986.paragraph-0.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>; or</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-1986.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>whether any goods are excisable goods or whether the  rate of duty of excise on any goods is nil; or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-1986.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <p>whether any goods fall under a particular heading or  sub- heading of the Schedule to the Central Excise Tariff Act,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-1985">
                <num>1985.</num>
                <heading/>
                <paragraph id="section-1985.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>, (5 of 1986) or the Additional Duties of Excise (Goods   of Special Importance) Act, 1957 (58 of 1957) or the</p>
                    <p>Additional Duties of Excise (Textiles and Textile Articles)</p>
                    <p>Act, 1978, (40 of 1978) or that any goods are or not covered  by a particular notification or order issued by the Central</p>
                    <blockList id="section-1985.paragraph-0.list4">
                      <listIntroduction>Government or the Board, as the case may be, granting total  or partial exemption from duty; or</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-1985.paragraph-0.list4.e">
                        <num>(e)</num>
                        <p>whether the value of any goods for the purposes of  assessment of duty of excise shall be enhanced or reduced by  the addition or reduction of the amounts in respect of such  matters as are specifically provided in this Act.]</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-35EA">
                <num>35EA.</num>
                <heading>Powers of revision of Board or Collector of Central</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-35EA.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Excise in certain cases.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-35EA.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Board may, of its own motion or on  the application of any aggrieved person or otherwise, call for and  examine the record of any proceeding in which a Collector of Central</p>
                    <p>Excise has passed any decision or order not being a decision or order  passed under sub- section (2) of this section of the nature referred  to in sub- section (5) of section 35E for the purpose of satisfying  itself as to correctness, legality or propriety of such decision or  order and may pass such order thereon as it thinks fit.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35EA.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Collector of Central Excise may, of his own motion or on  the application of any aggrieved person or otherwise, call for and  examine the record of any proceeding in which an adjudicating  authority subordinate to him has passed any decision or order of the  nature referred to in sub- section (5) of section 35E for the purpose  of satisfying himself as to the correctness, legality or propriety of  such decision or order and may pass such order thereon as he thinks  fit.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35EA.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-35EA.3.list0">
                      <item id="section-35EA.3.list0.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>No decision or order under this section shall be made so  as to prejudicially affect any person unless such person is given a  reasonable opportunity of making representation and if, he so desires,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-35EA.3.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>of being heard in his defence.</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-35EA.3.list2.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>Where the Board or, as the case may be, the Collector of</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Central Excise is of the opinion that any duty of excise has not  been levied or has been short- levied or short- paid or erroneously  refunded, no order requiring the affected person to pay any duty not  levied or paid, short- levied or short- paid or erroneously refunded  shall be passed under this section unless such person is given notice  within the time limit specified in section 11A to show cause against  the proposed order.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35EA.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>No proceedings shall be initiated under sub- section (1) or  sub- section (2) in respect of any decision or order after the expiry  of a period of six months from the date of communication of such  decision or order:</p>
                    <p>Provided that in respect of any decision or order passed before  the commencement of the Customs and Central Excises Laws (Amendment)</p>
                    <p>Act, 1987, the provisions of this sub- section shall have effect as if  for the words" six months", the words" one year" were substituted.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35EA.5">
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Any person aggrieved by any decision or order passed under  sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) may appeal to the Customs and</p>
                    <p>Excise Revenues Appellate Tribunal established under section 3 the</p>
                    <p>Customs and Excise Revenues Appellate Tribunal Act, 1986, against such  decision or order."]</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-35EE">
                <num>35EE.</num>
                <heading>Revision by Central Government.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-35EE.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Central</p>
                    <p>Government may, on the application of any person aggrieved by any  order passed under section 35A, where the order is of the nature  referred to in the first proviso to, sub- section (1) of section 35B,</p>
                    <p>annul or modify such order.</p>
                    <p>Explanation.- For the purposes of this sub- section," order passed  under section 35A" includes an order passed under that section before  the commencement of section 47 of the Finance Act, 1984 (21 of 1984)</p>
                    <p>against which an appeal has not been preferred before such  commencement and could have been. if the said section had not come  into force, preferred after such commencement, to the Appellate</p>
                    <p>Tribunal.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35EE.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>An application under sub- section (1) shall be made within  three months from the date of the communication to the applicant of  the order against which the application is being made:</p>
                    <p>Provided that the Central Government may, if it is satisfied that  the applicant was prevented by sufficient cause from presenting the  application within the. aforesaid period of three months, allow it to  be presented within a further period of three months.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35EE.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>An application under sub- section (1) shall be in such form  and shall be verified in such manner as may be specified by rules made  in this behalf and shall be accompanied by a fee of two hundred  rupees.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35EE.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Central Government may, of its own motion, annul or  modify any order referred to in sub- section (1).</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35EE.5">
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-35EE.5.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>No order enhancing any penalty or fine in lieu of  confiscation or confiscating goods of greater value shall be passed  under this section,-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-35EE.5.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>in any case in. which an order passed under section 35A</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-35EE.5.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>has enhanced any penalty or fine in lieu of confiscation or  has confiscated goods of greater value, and</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-35EE.5.list3.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>in any other case, unless the person affected by the  proposed order has been given notice to show cause against it  within one year from the date of the order sought to be  annulled or modified.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35EE.6">
                  <num>(6)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Where the Central Government is of opinion that any duty of  excise has not been levied or has been short- levied, no order levying  or enhancing the duty shall be made under this section unless the  person affected by the proposed order is given notice to show cause  against it within the time limit specified in section 11A.]</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-35F">
                <num>35F.</num>
                <heading>Deposit, pending appeal of duty demanded or penalty levied.</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-35F.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Where in any appeal under this Chapter, the decision or order appealed  against relates to any duty demanded in respect of goods which are not  under the control of central excise authorities or any penalty levied  under this Act, the person desirous of appealing against such decision  or order shall, pending the appeal, deposit with the adjudicating  authority the duty demanded or the penalty levied:</p>
                    <blockList id="section-35F.paragraph-0.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>Provided that where in any particular case, the Collector</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-35F.paragraph-0.list2.Appeals">
                        <num>(Appeals)</num>
                        <p>or the Appellate Tribunal is of opinion that the deposit of  duty demanded or penalty levied would cause undue hardship to such  person, the Collector (Appeals) or, as the case may be, the Appellate</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Tribunal, may dispense with such deposit subject to such conditions as  he or it may deem fit to impose so as to safeguard the interests of  revenue.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-35G">
                <num>35G.</num>
                <heading>Statement of case to High Court.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-35G.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Collector of</p>
                    <p>Central Excise or the other party may, within sixty days of the date  upon which he is served with notice of an order under section 35C (not  being an order relating, among other things, to the determination of  any question having a relation to the rate of duty of excise or to the   value of goods for purposes of assessment), by application in the  prescribed form, accompanied, where the application is made by the  other party, by a fee of two hundred rupees, require the Appellate</p>
                    <p>Tribunal to refer to the High Court any question of law arising out of  such order and, subject to the other provisions contained in this  section, the Appellate Tribunal shall, within one hundred and twenty  days of the receipt of such application, draw up a statement of the  case and refer it to the High Court:</p>
                    <p>Provided that the Appellate Tribunal may, if it is satisfied that  the applicant was prevented by sufficient cause from presenting the  application within the period hereinbefore specified, allow it to be  presented within a further period not exceeding thirty days.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35G.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>On receipt of notice that an application has been made under  sub- section (1), the person against whom such application has been  made, may, notwithstanding that he may not have filed such an  application, file, within forty- five days of the receipt of the  notice, a memorandum of cross- objections verified in the prescribed  manner against any part of the order in relation to which an  application for reference has been made and such memorandum shall be  disposed of by the Appellate Tribunal as if it were an application  presented within the time specified in sub- section (1).</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35G.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>If, on an application made under sub- section (1), the</p>
                    <p>Appellate Tribunal refuses to state the case on the ground that no  question of law arises, the Collector of Central Excise, or, as the  case may be, the other party may, within six months from the date on  which he is served with notice of such refusal, apply to the High</p>
                    <p>Court and the High Court may, if it is not satisfied with the  correctness of the decision of the Appellate Tribunal, require the</p>
                    <p>Appellate Tribunal to state the case and to refer it, and on receipt  of any such requisition, the Appellate Tribunal shall state the case  and refer it accordingly.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35G.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Where in the exercise of its powers under sub- section (3),</p>
                    <p>the Appellate Tribunal refuses to state a case which it has been  required by an applicant to state, the applicant may, within thirty  days from the date on which he receives notice of such refusal,</p>
                    <p>withdraw his application and, if he does so, the fee, if any, paid by  him shall be refunded.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-35H">
                <num>35H.</num>
                <heading>Statement of case to Supreme court in certain cases. If, on  an application made under section 35G, the Appellate Tribunal is of  opinion that, on account of conflict in the decisions of High Courts  in respect of any particular question of law, it is expedient that a  reference should be made direct to the Supreme Court, the Appellate</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-35H.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Tribunal may draw up a statement of the case and refer it through the</p>
                    <p>President direct to the Supreme Court.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-35I">
                <num>35I.</num>
                <heading>Power of High Court or Supreme Court to require statement to  be amended. If the High Court or the Supreme Court is not satisfied  that the statements in a case referred to it are sufficient to enable  it to determine the questions raised thereby, the Court may refer the  case back to the Appellate Tribunal, for the purpose of making such  additions thereto or alterations therein as it may direct in that  behalf.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-35J">
                <num>35J.</num>
                <heading>Case before High Court to be heard by not less than two</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-35J.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Judges.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-35J.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>When any case has been referred to the High Court under  section 35G, it shall be heard by a Bench of not less than two Judges  of the High Court and shall be decided in accordance with the opinion  of such Judges or of the majority, if any, of such Judges.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35J.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Where there is no such majority, the Judges shall state the  point of law upon which they differ and the case shall then be heard  upon that point only by one or more of the other Judges of the High</p>
                    <p>Court, and such point shall be decided according to the opinion of the  majority of the Judges who have heard the case including those who  first heard it.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-35K">
                <num>35K.</num>
                <heading>Decision of High Court or Supreme Court on the case stated.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-35K.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The High Court or the Supreme Court hearing any such case shall  decide the questions of law raised therein and shall deliver its  judgment thereon containing the grounds on which such decision is  founded and a copy of the judgment shall be sent under the seal of the</p>
                    <p>Court and the signature of the Registrar to the Appellate Tribunal  which shall pass such orders as are necessary to dispose of the case  in conformity with such judgment.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35K.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The costs of any reference to the High Court or the Supreme</p>
                    <p>Court which shall not include the fee for making the reference shall  be in the discretion of the Court.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-35L">
                <num>35L.</num>
                <heading>Appeal to Supreme Court. An appeal shall lie to the Supreme</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-35L.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-35L.paragraph-0.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>Court from-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-35L.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>any judgment of the High Court delivered on a reference  made under section 35G in any case which, on its own motion  or on an oral application made by or on behalf of the party  aggrieved, immediately after the passing of the judgment, the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>High Court certifies to be a fit one for appeal to the</p>
                    <blockList id="section-35L.paragraph-0.list4">
                      <listIntroduction>Supreme Court; or</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-35L.paragraph-0.list4.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>any order passed by the Appellate Tribunal relating,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>among other things, to the determination of any question  having a relation to the rate of duty of excise or to the  value of goods for purposes of assessment.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-35M">
                <num>35M.</num>
                <heading>Hearing before Supreme Court.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-35M.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The provisions of the Code  of Civil Procedure, 1908 1, (5 of 1908) relating to appeals to the</p>
                    <p>Supreme Court shall, so far as may be, apply in the case of appeals  under section 35L a, they apply in the case of appeals from decrees of  a High Court:</p>
                    <p>Provided that nothing in this sub- section shall be deemed to  affect the provisions of sub- section (1) of section 35K or section</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-35N">
                <num>35N.</num>
                <heading/>
                <subsection id="section-35N.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The costs of the appeal shall be in the discretion of the</p>
                    <p>Supreme Court.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35N.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Where the judgment of the High Court is varied or reversed in  the appeal, effect shall be given to the order of the Supreme Court in  the manner provided in section 35K in the case of a judgment of the</p>
                    <p>High Court.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-35N">
                <num>35N.</num>
                <heading>Sums due to be paid notwithstanding reference, etc.</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-35N.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Notwithstanding that a reference has been made to the High Court or  the Supreme Court or an appeal has been preferred to the Supreme</p>
                    <p>Court, sums due to the Government as a result of ail order passed  under sub- section</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-35N.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>of section 35C shall be payable in accordance  with the order so passed.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-35O">
                <num>35O.</num>
                <heading>Exclusion of time taken for copy. In computing the period  of limitation prescribed for an appeal or application under this</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-35O.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Chapter, the day on which the order complained of was served, and if  the party preferring the appeal or making the application was not  furnished with a copy of the order when the notice of the order was  served upon him, the time requisite for obtaining a copy of such order  shall be excluded.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-35P">
                <num>35P.</num>
                <heading>Transfer of certain pending proceedings and transitional  provisions.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-35P.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every appeal which is pending immediately before the  appointed day before the Board under section 35, as it stood  immediately before that day, and any matter arising out of or  connected with such appeal and which is so pending shall stand  transferred on that day to the Appellate Tribunal and the Appellate</p>
                    <p>Tribunal may proceed with such appeal or matter from the stage at  which it was on that day:</p>
                    <p>Provided that the appellant may demand that before proceeding  further wit] that appeal or matter, he may be re- heard.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35P.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every proceeding which is pending immediately before the  appointed day before the Central Government under section 36, as it  stood immediately before that day, and any matter arising out of or  connected with such proceeding and which is so pending shall stand  transferred on that day to the Appellate Tribunal and the Appellate</p>
                    <p>Tribunal may proceed with such proceeding or matter from the stage at  which it was on that day as if such proceeding or matter were an  appeal filed before it:</p>
                    <blockList id="section-35P.2.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>Provided that if any such proceeding or matter relates to an  order where-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-35P.2.list3.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>in any disputed case, other than a case where the  determination of any question having a relation to the rate  of duty of excise or to the value of goods for purposes of  assessment is in issue or is one of the points in issue, the  difference in duty involved or the duty involved; or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-35P.2.list3.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>the amount of fine or penalty determined by such order,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>does not exceed ten thousand rupees, such proceeding or matter shall  continue to be dealt with by the Central Government as if the said  section 36 had not been substituted:</p>
                    <p>Provided further that the applicant or the other party may make a  demand to the Appellate Tribunal that before proceeding further with  that proceeding or matter, he may be re- heard.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35P.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every proceeding which is pending immediately before the  appointed day before the Board or the Collector of Central Excise  under section 35A, as it stood immediately before that day, and any  matter arising out of or connected with such proceeding and which is  so pending shall continue to be dealt with by the Board or the</p>
                    <p>Collector of Central Excise, as the case may be, as if the said  section had not been substituted.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35P.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Any person who immediately before the appointed day was  authorised to appear in any appeal or proceeding transferred under  sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) shall, notwithstanding anything  contained in section 35Q, have the right to appear before the</p>
                    <p>Appellate Tribunal in relation to such appeal or proceeding.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-35Q">
                <num>35Q.</num>
                <heading>Appearance by authorised representative.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-35Q.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Any person who  is entitled or required to appear before a Central Excise Officer or  the Appellate Tribunal in connection with any proceedings under this</p>
                    <p>Act, otherwise than when required under this Act to appear personally  for examination on oath or affirmation, may, subject to the other  provisions of this section, appear by an authorised representative.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35Q.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-35Q.2.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>For the purposes of this section," authorised  representative" means a person authorised by the person referred to in  sub- section (1) to appear on his behalf, being-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-35Q.2.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>his relative or regular employee; or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-35Q.2.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>any legal practitioner who is entitled to practise in  any civil court in India; or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-35Q.2.list1.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>any person who has acquired such qualifications as the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Central Government may prescribe for this purpose.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35Q.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, no  person who was a member of the Indian Customs and Central Excise</p>
                    <p>Service- Group A and has retired or resigned from such Service after  having served for not less than three years in any capacity in that</p>
                    <p>Service, shall be entitled to appear as an authorised representative  in any proceedings before a Central Excise Officer for a period of two  years from the date of his retirement or resignation, as the case may  be.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35Q.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-35Q.4.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>No person,-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-35Q.4.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>who has been dismissed or removed from Government  service; or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-35Q.4.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>who is convicted of an offence connected with any  proceeding under this Act, the Customs Act, 1962 (52 of 1962)</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>or the Gold (Control) Act, 1968; or</p>
                    <blockList id="section-35Q.4.list4">
                      <listIntroduction>(45 of 1968)</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-35Q.4.list4.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>who has become an insolvent,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-35Q.4.list6">
                      <listIntroduction>shall be qualified to represent any person under sub- section (1), for  all times in the case of a person referred to in clause (a), and for  such time as the Collector of Central Excise or the competent  authority under the Customs Act, 1962 (52 of 1962) or the Gold</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-35Q.4.list6.Control">
                        <num>(Control)</num>
                        <p>Act, 1968, (45 of 1968) as the case may be, may, by order,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>determine in the case of a person referred to in clause (b), and for  the period during which the insolvency continues in the case of a  person referred to in clause (c).</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35Q.5">
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-35Q.5.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>If any person,-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-35Q.5.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>who is a legal practitioner, is found guilty of  misconduct in his professional capacity by any authority  entitled to institute proceedings against him, an order  passed by that authority shall have effect in relation to his  right to appear before a Central Excise Officer or the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Appellate Tribunal as it has in relation to his right to,</p>
                    <blockList id="section-35Q.5.list4">
                      <listIntroduction>practise as a legal practitioner;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-35Q.5.list4.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>who is not a legal practitioner, is found guilty of  misconduct in connection with any proceedings under this Act  by the prescribed authority, the prescribed authority may  direct that he shall thenceforth be disqualified to represent  any person under sub- section (1).</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35Q.6">
                  <num>(6)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Any order or direction under clause (b) of sub- section (4)</p>
                    <blockList id="section-35Q.6.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>or clause (b) of sub- section (5) shall be subject to the following  conditions, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-35Q.6.list2.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>no such order or direction shall be made in respect of  any person unless he has been given a reasonable opportunity  of being heard;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-35Q.6.list2.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>any person against whom any such order or direction is  made may, within one month of the making of the order or  direction, appeal to the Board to have the order or direction  cancelled; and</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-35Q.6.list2.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>no such order or direction shall take effect until the  expiration of one month from the making thereof, or, where an  appeal has been preferred, until the disposal of the appeal.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-36">
                <num>36.</num>
                <heading>Definitions. In this Chapter-</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-36.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-36.paragraph-0.list0">
                      <item id="section-36.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>" appointed day" means the date 1 of coming into force of  the amendments to this Act specified in Part II of the Fifth</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
            </chapter>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-scheduleto">
      <doc name="scheduleto">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1944/1/scheduleto"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1944/1"/>
              <FRBRalias value="the Finance (No. 2) Act, 1980; (44 of 1980)."/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1944/1/eng@1944-02-24/scheduleto"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1944/1/eng@1944-02-24"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1944/1/eng@1944-02-24/scheduleto"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1944/1/eng@1944-02-24"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduleto">
            <paragraph id="scheduleto.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <blockList id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list0">
                  <item id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <blockList id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list0.b.list0">
                      <listIntroduction>" High Court" means,--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list0.b.list0.i">
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <p>in relation to any State, the High Court for that</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <blockList id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list2">
                  <listIntroduction>State;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list2.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>in relation to a Union territory to which the  jurisdiction of the High Court of a State has been  extended by law, that High Court;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list2.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>in relation to the Union territories of Dadra and</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <p>Nagar Haveli and Goa, Daman and Diu, the High Court at</p>
                <blockList id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list5">
                  <listIntroduction>Bombay,;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list5.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>in relation to another Union territory, the  highest court of civil appeal for that territory other  than the Supreme Court of India;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="scheduleto.paragraph-0.list5.c">
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <p>" President" means the President of the Appellate</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <p>Tribunal.]</p>
                <p>CHAP</p>
                <p>PRESUMPTION AS TO DOCUMENTS]</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <chapter id="chapter-VIB">
              <num>VIB</num>
              <paragraph id="chapter-VIB.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>PRESUMPTION AS TO DOCUMENTS]</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-36A">
                <num>36A.</num>
                <heading>Presumption as to documents in certain cases. Where any  document is produced by any person or has been seized from the custody  or control of any person, in either case, under this Act or under any  other law and such document is tendered by the prosecution in evidence  against him or against him and any other person who is tried jointly  with him, the Court shall,-</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-36A.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-36A.paragraph-0.list0">
                      <item id="section-36A.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <blockList id="section-36A.paragraph-0.list0.a.list0">
                          <listIntroduction>unless the contrary is proved by such person, presume--</listIntroduction>
                          <item id="section-36A.paragraph-0.list0.a.list0.i">
                            <num>(i)</num>
                            <p>the truth of the contents of such document;</p>
                          </item>
                          <item id="section-36A.paragraph-0.list0.a.list0.ii">
                            <num>(ii)</num>
                            <p>that the signature and every other part of such  document which purports to be in the handwriting of any  particular person or which the Court may reasonably  assume to have been signed by, or to be in' the hand-</p>
                          </item>
                        </blockList>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>writing of, any particular person, is in that person' s  handwriting, and in the case of a document executed or  attested, that it was executed or attested by the person  by whom it purports to have been so executed or attest-</p>
                    <blockList id="section-36A.paragraph-0.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>ed;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-36A.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>admit, the document in evidence, notwithstanding  that it is not duly. stamped, if such document is  otherwise admissible in evidence.]</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-36B">
                <num>36B.</num>
                <heading>Admissibility of micro films, facsimile copies of  documents and computer print outs as documents and as evidence.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-36B.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-36B.1.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being  in force,-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-36B.1.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>a micro film of a document or the reproduction of the  image or images embodied in such micro film (whether enlarged   or not); or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-36B.1.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>a facsimile copy of a document; or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-36B.1.list1.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>a statement contained in a document and included in a  printed material produced by a computer (hereinafter referred   to as a' computer print out"), if the conditions mentioned in  subsection (2) and the other provisions contained in this  section are satisfied in relation to the statement and the  computer in question,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>shall be deemed to be also a document for the purposes of this Act and  the rules made thereunder and shall be admissible in any proceedings  thereunder, without further proof or production of the original, as  evidence of any contents of the original or of any fact stated therein  of which direct evidence would be admissible.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-36B.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-36B.2.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>The conditions referred to in sub- section (1) in respect of  a computer print out shall be the following, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-36B.2.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>the computer print out containing the statement was  produced by the computer during the period over which the  computer was used regularly to store or process information  for the purposes of any activities regularly carried on over  that period by the person having lawful control over the use  of the computer;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-36B.2.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>during the said period, there was regularly supplied to  the computer in the ordinary course of the said activities,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-36B.2.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>information of the kind contained In the statement or of the  kind from which the information so contained is derived;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-36B.2.list3.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>throughout the material part of the said period, the  computer was operating properly or, if not, then any respect  in which it was not operating properly or was out of  operation during that part of that period was not such as to  affect the production of the document or the accuracy of the  contents; and</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-36B.2.list3.d">
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <p>the information contained in the statement reproduces  or is derived from information supplied to the computer in  the ordinary course of the said activities.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-36B.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-36B.3.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>Where over any period, the function of storing or processing  information for the purposes of any activities regularly carried on  over that period as mentioned in clause (a) of sub- section (2) was  regularly performed by computers, whether-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-36B.3.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>by a combination of computers operating over that  period; or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-36B.3.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>by different computers operating in succession over  that period; or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-36B.3.list1.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>by different combinations of computers operating in  succession over that period; or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-36B.3.list1.d">
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <p>in any other manner involving the successive operation  over that period, in whatever order, of one or more computers  and one or more combinations of computers,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>all the computers used for that purpose during that period shall be  treated for the purposes of this section as constituting a single com-</p>
                    <p>puter; and references in this section to a computer shall be construed  accordingly.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-36B.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>In any proceedings under this: Act and the rules made there-</p>
                    <blockList id="section-36B.4.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>under where it is desired to give a statement in evidence, by virtue  of this section, a certificate doing any of the following things, that  is to say,--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-36B.4.list2.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>identifying the document containing the statement and  describing the manner in which It was produced;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-36B.4.list2.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>giving such particulars of any device involved in the  production of that document as may be appropriate for the  purpose of showing that the document was produced by a  computer;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-36B.4.list2.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>dealing with any of the matters to which the conditions  mentioned in sub- section (2) relate,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>and purporting to be signed by a person occupying a responsible  official position in relation to the operation of the relevant device  or the management of the relevant activities (whichever is appro-</p>
                    <p>priate) shall be evidence of any matter stated in the certificate; and  for the purposes of this sub- section it shall be sufficient for a  matter to; be stated to the best of the knowledge and belief of the  person stating it.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-36B.5">
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-36B.5.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>For the purposes of this section,-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-36B.5.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>information shall be taken to be supplied, to a  computer if it is supplied thereto in any appropriate form  and whether It is so supplied directly or (with or without   human intervention) by means of any appropriate equipment;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-36B.5.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>whether in the course of activities carried on by any  official, information is supplied with a view to Its, being  stored or processed for the purposes of those activities by a  computer operated otherwise than in. the course of those  activities, that information, if duly supplied to that  computer, shall be taken to be supplied to it in the course  of those activities;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-36B.5.list1.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>a document shall be taken to have been produced by a  computer whether it was produced by it directly or (with or   without human intervention) by means of any appropriate  equipment.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-36B.5.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-36B.5.list3.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>" computer" means any device that receives, stores and  processes data, applying stipulated processes to the  information and supplying results of these processes; and</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-36B.5.list3.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>any reference to information being derived from other  information shall be a reference to its being derived  therefrom by calculation comparison or an other process.]</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>CHAP</p>
                    <p>SUPPLEMENTAL PROVISIONS</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
            </chapter>
            <chapter id="chapter-VII">
              <num>VII</num>
              <paragraph id="chapter-VII.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>SUPPLEMENTAL PROVISIONS</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-37">
                <num>37.</num>
                <heading>Power of Central Government to make rules.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-37.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Central</p>
                    <p>Government may make rules to carry into effect the purposes of this</p>
                    <p>Act.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-37.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-37.2.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of  the foregoing power, such rules may--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-37.2.list1.i">
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <p>provide for determining under section 4 the nearest  ascertainable equivalent of the normal price;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-37.2.list1.ia">
                        <num>(ia)</num>
                        <p>having regard to the normal practice of the wholesale  trade, define or specify the kinds of trade discount to be  excluded from the value under section 4 including the  circumstances in which and the conditions subject to which  such discount is to be so excluded;]</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-37.2.list1.ib">
                        <num>(ib)</num>
                        <p>] provide for the assessment and collection of duties  of excise, the authorities by whom functions under this Act  are to be discharged, the issue of notices requiring payment,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-37.2.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>the manner in which the duties shall be payable, and the  recovery of duty not paid;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-37.2.list3.ic">
                        <num>(ic)</num>
                        <p>provide for the remission of duty of excise leviable  on any excisable goods, which due to any natural cause are  found to be deficient in quantity, the limit or limits of  percentage beyond which no such remission shall be allowed  and the different limit or limits of percentage for different  varieties of the same excisable goods or for different areas  or for different seasons;]</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-37.2.list3.ii">
                        <num>(ii)</num>
                        <p>prohibit absolutely, or with such exceptions, or  subject to such conditions as the Central Government thinks  fit, the production or manufacture, or any process of the  production or manufacture, of excisable goods, or of any  component parts or ingredients or containers thereof, except  on land or premises approved for the purpose;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-37.2.list3.iii">
                        <num>(iii)</num>
                        <p>prohibit absolutely, or with such exceptions, or  subject to such conditions as the Central Government thinks  fit,  the transit of excisable goods from any part of a</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-37.2.list5">
                      <listIntroduction>India] to any other part thereof;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-37.2.list5.iv">
                        <num>(iv)</num>
                        <p>regulate the removal of excisable goods from the place  where produced, stored or manufactured or subjected to any  process of production or manufacture and their transport to  or from the premises of a registered 7 or a bonded  warehouse, or to a market;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-37.2.list5.v">
                        <num>(v)</num>
                        <p>regulate the production or manufacture, or any process  of the production or manufacture, the possession, storage and  sale of salt, and so far as such regulation is essential for  the proper levy and collection of the duties imposed by this</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-37.2.list7">
                      <listIntroduction>Act, of any other excisable goods, or of any component parts  or ingredients or containers thereof;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-37.2.list7.vi">
                        <num>(vi)</num>
                        <p>provide for the employment of officers of the Government to  supervise the carrying out of any rules made under this Act;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-37.2.list7.vii">
                        <num>(vii)</num>
                        <p>require a manufacturer or the licensee of a warehouse to  provide accommodation within the precincts of his factory or warehouse  for officers employed to supervise the carrying out of regulations  made under this Act and prescribe the scale of such accommodation;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-37.2.list7.viii">
                        <num>(viii)</num>
                        <p>provide for the appointment, licensing, management, and  supervision of bonded warehouses and the procedure to be followed in  entering goods into and clearing goods from such warehouses;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-37.2.list7.ix">
                        <num>(ix)</num>
                        <p>provide for the distinguishing of goods which have been    manufactured after registration] of materials which have been  imported under licence, and of goods on which duty has been paid, or  which are exempt from duty under this Act;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-37.2.list7.x">
                        <num>(x)</num>
                        <p>impose on persons engaged in the production or manufacture,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>storage or sale (whether on their own account or as brokers or   commission agents) of salt, and, so far as such imposition is  essential for the proper levy and collection of the duties imposed by  this Act, of any other excisable goods, the duty of furnishing  information, keeping records and making returns, and prescribe the  nature of such information and the form of such records and returns,</p>
                    <blockList id="section-37.2.list10">
                      <listIntroduction>the particulars to be contained therein, and the manner in which they  shall be verified;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-37.2.list10.xi">
                        <num>(xi)</num>
                        <p>require that excisable goods shall not be sold or, offered  or kept for sale in  India] except in prescribed containers, bearing  a banderol, stamp or label of such nature and affixed in such manner  as may be prescribed;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-37.2.list10.xii">
                        <num>(xii)</num>
                        <p>provide for the issue of registration certificates 2 and  transport permits and the fees, if any, to be charged therefor:</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Provided that the fees for the licensing of the manufacture and  refining of salt and saltpetre shall not exceed. in the case of each  such licence, the following amounts, namely:-</p>
                    <p>RS.</p>
                    <p>Licence to manufacture and refine saltpetre  and to separate and purify salt in the process  of such manufacture and refining 50</p>
                    <p>Licence to manufacture saltpetre</p>
                    <blockList id="section-37.2.list16">
                      <listIntroduction>Licence to manufacture sulphate of soda</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-37.2.list16.kharinun">
                        <num>(kharinun)</num>
                        <p>by solar heat in evaporating pans 10</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-37.2.list18">
                      <listIntroduction>Licence to manufacture sulphate of soda</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-37.2.list18.knarinun">
                        <num>(knarinun)</num>
                        <p>by artificial heat 2</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Licence to manufacture other saline sub-</p>
                    <blockList id="section-37.2.list21">
                      <listIntroduction>stances 2;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-37.2.list21.xiii">
                        <num>(xiii)</num>
                        <p>provide for the detention of goods, plant, machinery or  material, for the purpose of exacting the duty, the procedure in  connection with the confiscation, otherwise than under section 10 or  section 28, of goods in respect of which breaches of the Act or rules  have been committed, and the disposal of goods so detained or  confiscated;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-37.2.list21.xiv">
                        <num>(xiv)</num>
                        <p>authorise and regulate the inspection of factories and  provide for the taking of samples, and for the making of tests, of any  substance produced therein, and for the, inspection or search of any  place or conveyance used for the production, storage, sale or  transport of salt, and so far as such inspection or search is  essential for the proper levy and collection of the duties imposed by  this Act, of any other excisable goods;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-37.2.list21.xv">
                        <num>(xv)</num>
                        <p>authorise and regulate the composition of offences against,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-37.2.list23">
                      <listIntroduction>or liabilities incurred under, this Act or the rules made thereunder;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-37.2.list23.xvi">
                        <num>(xvi)</num>
                        <p>provide for the grant of a rebate of the duty paid on goods  which are exported out of India or shipped for consumption on a voyage  to any port outside India;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-37.2.list23.xvia">
                        <num>(xvia)</num>
                        <p>provide for the credit of duty paid or deemed to have  been paid on the goods used in, or in relation to, the manufacture of  excisable goods;]</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-37.2.list23.xvib">
                        <num>(xvib)</num>
                        <p>provide for the giving of credit of sums of money with  respect to raw materials used in the manufacture of excisable goods;]</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-37.2.list23.xvii">
                        <num>(xvii)</num>
                        <p>exempt any goods from the whole or any part of the duty  imposed by this Act;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-37.2.list23.xviia">
                        <num>(xviia)</num>
                        <p>provide incentives for increased production or  manufacture of any goods by way of remission of, or any concession  with respect to, duty payable under this Act;]</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-37.2.list23.xviii">
                        <num>(xviii)</num>
                        <p>define an area no point in which shall be more than one  hundred yards from the nearest point of any place in which salt is  stored or sold by or on behalf of the Central Government, or of any  factory in which saltpetre is manufactured or refined, and regulate  the possession, storage and sale of salt within such area;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-37.2.list23.xix">
                        <num>(xix)</num>
                        <p>define an area round any other place in which salt is  manufactured, and regulate the possession, storage and sale of salt  within such area;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-37.2.list23.xx">
                        <num>(xx)</num>
                        <p>authorise the  Central Board of Excise and Customs  constituted under the Central Boards of Revenue Act, 1963] (54 of</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-1963">
                <num>1963.</num>
                <heading/>
                <paragraph id="section-1963.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>) or Collectors of Central Excise appointed for the purposes of  this Act to provide, by written instructions, for supplemental matters  arising out of any rule made by the Central Government under this  section;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list1.xxi">
                        <num>(xxi)</num>
                        <p>provide for the publication, subject to such conditions  as may be specified therein, of names and other particulars of persons  who have been found guilty of contravention of any of the provisions  of this Act or of any rule made thereunder;]</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list1.xxii">
                        <num>(xxii)</num>
                        <p>provide for the charging of fees for the examination of  excisable goods intended for export out of India and for rendering any  other service by a Central Excise Officer under this Act or the rules  made thereunder.]</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list1.xxiii">
                        <num>(xxiii)</num>
                        <p>specify the form in which application for refund shall  be made under section 11B;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list1.xxiv">
                        <num>(xxiv)</num>
                        <p>provide for the manner in which money is to be credited to  the Fund;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list1.xxv">
                        <num>(xxv)</num>
                        <p>provide for the manner in which the Fund shall be utilised  for the welfare of the consumers;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list1.xxvi">
                        <num>(xxvi)</num>
                        <p>specify the form in which the account and records relating  to the Fund shall be maintained."]</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list1.xxvii">
                        <num>(xxvii)</num>
                        <p>specify the persons who shall get themselves  registered under section 6 and the manner of their registration.]</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-1963.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>In making rules under this section, the Central Government  may provide that any person committing a breach of any rule shall,</p>
                    <p>where no other penalty is provided by this Act, be liable to a penalty  not exceeding two thousand rupees and that any article in respect of  which any such breach is committed shall be confiscated</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-1963.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-1963.4.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (3), and  without, prejudice to the provisions of section 9, in making rules  under this section, the Central Government may provide that if any  manufacturer, producer or licensee of a warehouse-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-1963.4.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>removes any excisable goods in contravention of the  provisions of any such rule, or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-1963.4.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>does not account for all such goods manufactured,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-1963.4.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>produced or stored by him, or</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-1963.4.list3.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>engages in the manufacture, production or storage of  such goods without having applied for the registration as 10  required section 6, or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-1963.4.list3.d">
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <p>contravenes the provisions of any such rule with intent to  evade payment of duty,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-1963.4.list5">
                      <listIntroduction>then-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-1963.4.list5.i">
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <p>any land, building, plant, machinery, materials,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-1963.4.list7">
                      <listIntroduction>conveyance, animal or any other thing used in connection with  the manufacture, production, storage, removal or disposal of  such goods, and</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-1963.4.list7.ii">
                        <num>(ii)</num>
                        <p>all excisable goods on such land or in such building or  produced or manufactured with such plant, machinery,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>materials or thing,</p>
                    <p>belonging to such manufacturer, producer or licensee shall be liable  to confiscation and the manufacturer, producer or licensee shall be  liable to a penalty not exceeding three times the value' of the  excisable goods in respect of which any contravention of the nature  referred to in clause (a), (b), (c) or (d) has been committed, or  five' thousand rupees, whichever is greater.]</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-1963.5">
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (3), the</p>
                    <p>Central Government any make rules to provide for the imposition upon  any person- who acquires possession of, or is in any way concerned in  transporting, removing, depositing, keeping, concealing, selling or  purchasing, or in any other manner deals with, any excisable goods  which he knows or has reason to believe are liable to confiscation  under this Act or the rules made thereunder, a penalty not exceeding  three times the value of such goods or five thousand rupees, whichever  is greater.]</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-37A">
                <num>37A.</num>
                <heading>Delegation of powers. The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, direct that subject to such  conditions, if any, as may be specified in the notification-</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-37A.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-37A.paragraph-0.list0">
                      <item id="section-37A.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>any power exercisable by the Board under this Act may  be exercisable also by  a Principal Collector of Central</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-37A.paragraph-0.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>Excise or a Collector of Central Excise] empowered in this  behalf by the Central Government;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-37A.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>any power exercisable by a Collector of Central Excise  under this Act may be exercisable also by a Deputy Collector  of Central Excise or an Assistant Collector of Central Excise  empowered in this behalf by the Central Government;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-37A.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>any power exercisable by a Deputy Collector of Central</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Excise under this Act may be exercisable also by an Assistant</p>
                    <p>Collector of Central Excise empowered in this behalf by the</p>
                    <blockList id="section-37A.paragraph-0.list6">
                      <listIntroduction>Central Government; and</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-37A.paragraph-0.list6.d">
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <p>any power exercisable by an Assistant Collector of</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Central Excise under this Act may be exercisable also by a  gazetted officer of Central Excise empowered in this behalf  by the Board.]</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-37B">
                <num>37B.</num>
                <heading>Instructions to Central Excise Officers. The Central Board  of Excise and Customs constituted under the Central Boards of Revenue</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-37B.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Act, 1963 (54 of 1963) may, if it considers it necessary or expedient  so to do for the purpose of uniformity in the classification of  excisable goods or with respect to levy of duties of excise on such  goods, issue such orders, instructions and directions to the Central</p>
                    <p>Excise Officers as it may deem fit, and such officers and all other  persons employed in the execution of this Act shall observe and follow  such orders, instructions and directions of the said Board:</p>
                    <blockList id="section-37B.paragraph-0.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>Provided that no such orders, instructions or directions shall be  issued-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-37B.paragraph-0.list3.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>so as to require any Central Excise Officer to make a  particular assessment or to dispose of a particular case in  a particular manner; or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-37B.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>so as to interfere with the discretion of the Collector  of Central Excise (Appeals) in the exercise of his appellate  functions.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-37C">
                <num>37C.</num>
                <heading>Service of decisions, orders, summons, etc.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-37C.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-37C.1.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>Any decision  or order passed or any summons or notice issued under this Act or the  rules made thereunder, shall be served,-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-37C.1.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>by tendering the decision, order, summons or notice, or  sending it by registered post with acknowledgment due, to the  person for whom it is intended or his authorised agent, if  any;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-37C.1.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>if the decision, order, summons or notice cannot be  served in the manner provided in clause (a), by affixing a  copy thereof to some conspicuous part of the factory or  warehouse or other place of business or usual place of  residence of the person for whom such decision, order,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-37C.1.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>summons or notice, as the case may be, is intended;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-37C.1.list3.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>if the decision, order, summons or notice cannot be  served in the manner provided in clauses (a) and (b), by  affixing a copy thereof on the notice board of the officer or  authority who or which passed such decision or order or  issued such summons or notice.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-37C.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every decision or order passed or any summons or notice  issued under this Act or the rules made thereunder, shall be deemed to  have been served on the date on which the decision, order, summons or  notice is tendered or, delivered by post or a copy thereof is affixed  in the manner provided in sub- section (1),]</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-37D">
                <num>37D.</num>
                <heading>Rounding off of duty, etc. The amount of duty, interest,</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-37D.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>penalty, fine or any other sum payable, and the amount of refund or  any other sum due, tinder the provisions of this Act shall be rounded  off to the nearest rupee and, for this purpose, where such amount  contains a part of a rupee consisting of paise then, if such part is  fifty paise or more, it shall be increased to one rupee and if such  part is less than fifty paise it shall be ignored.]</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-38">
                <num>38.</num>
                <heading>Publication of rules and notifications and laying of rules  before PArliament.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-38.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>All rules made and notifications issued under  this Act shall be published in the Official Gazette.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-38.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every rule made under this Act and every notification  issued under sub- section (1) of section 5A and section 11C shall be  laid, as soon as may be after it is made or issued, before each House  of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty  days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more  successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session  immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or  notification or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made or  the notification should not be issued, the rule or notification shall  thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</p>
                    <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that rule or notification."]</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-39">
                <num>39.</num>
                <heading>Repeal of enactments. Rep. by the Repealing and Amending</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-39.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Act, 1947 (2 of 1948), s. 2 and Sch.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-40">
                <num>40.</num>
                <heading>Protection of action taken under the Act.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-40.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>No suit,</p>
                    <p>prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central</p>
                    <p>Government or any officer of the Central Government or a State Gov-</p>
                    <p>ernment for anything which is done, or intended to be done, in good  faith, in pursuance of this Act or any rule made thereunder.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-40.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>No proceeding, other than a suit, shall be commenced against  the Central Government or any officer of the Central Government or a</p>
                    <p>State Government for anything done or purported to have been done in  pursuance of this Act or any rule made thereunder, without giving the</p>
                    <p>Central Government or such officer a month' s previous notice in  writing of the intended proceeding and of the cause thereof or after  the expiration of three months from the accrual of such cause.]</p>
                    <p>The First Schedule. Rep. by the Central Excise Tariff Act, 1985</p>
                    <p>(5 of 1986), s. 4 (w. e. f 28- 2- 1986).</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
            </chapter>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
