<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mdp/act/1944/2/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mdp/act/1944/2"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Madhya Pradesh Regulation of Couching Act, 1944"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mdp/act/1944/2/eng@1944-03-26/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mdp/act/1944/2/eng@1944-03-26"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1944-03-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mdp/act/1944/2/eng@1944-03-26/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mdp/act/1944/2/eng@1944-03-26"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preamble>
      <p>The Madhya Pradesh Regulation of Couching Act, 1944</p>
      <p>Act No. 02 of 1944</p>
      <p>PREAMBLE,-</p>
      <p>AN ACT to prevent couching by unqualified persons.</p>
      <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to prevent couching by unqualified persons;</p>
      <p>AND WHEREAS the Governor of the Central Provinces and Berar has assumed to himself under the Proclamation, dated the 10th November, 1939, issued by him under Section 93 of the Government of India Act, 1935, all powers vested by or under the said Act in the Provincial Legislature;</p>
      <p>Now, therefore, in exercise of the said powers, the Governor of the Central Provinces and Berar is pleased to make the following Act,-</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be cited as the Madhya Pradesh Regulation of Couching Act, 1944.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to and shall be in force in the whole of Madhya Pradesh.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Meaning of Registered Practitioner.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In this Act, the expression "registered practitioner" shall have the meaning assigned to it in the Central Provinces and Berar Medical Registration Act, 1916 (1 of 1916).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for unlawful couching.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever, not being a Registered Practitioner, or not possessing a professional qualification entitling him to be registered under the Central Provinces and Berar Medical Registration Act, 1916 (1 of 1916), couches or attempts to couch or agrees or offers by physical means or interference with the eye to give vision to a person suffering from cataract, with or without that person's consent, shall on conviction, be punishable with imprisonment of either description for a term which may extend to six months or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for abetment of offence.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever abets the commission of an offence under this Act shall, on conviction be punishable with the punishment provided for the offence in Section 3.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Offence to be cognizable, bailable and compoundable.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (V of 1898) an offence punishable under this Act shall be cognizable and bailable and may be compounded with the permission of the Court.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Jurisdiction of Magistrates.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No Magistrate having powers inferior to that of the second class shall try any offence punishable under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A Magistrate may take cognizance of an offence under this Act,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>on a report of a police officer;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>on information of any other person;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>upon his own knowledge or suspicion that such offence has been committed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that no cognizance shall be taken where the offence alleged was committed more than six months previously.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
