<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1850/12/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1850/12"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Public Accountants' Default Act, 18501"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1850/12/eng@1850-03-22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1850/12/eng@1850-03-22"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1850-03-22" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1850/12/eng@1850-03-22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1850/12/eng@1850-03-22"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Public Accountants' Default Act, 18501</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 12 OF 1850</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 22nd March, 1850]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>For avoiding loss by the default of Public Accountants.</p>
        <p>Preamble.-- For better avoidance of loss through the default of  public accountants: It is enacted as follows:--</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Public Accountants to give security.-- Every public accountant  shall give security for the due discharge of the trusts of his office,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>and for the due account of all moneys which shall come into his  possession or control, by reason of his office.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Amount and kind of security, and with what sureties.-- In  default of any Act having special reference to the office of any  public accountant, the security given shall be of such amount and  kind, real or personal, or both, and with such sureties (regard being   had to the nature of the office), as shall be required by any rules  made or to be made from time to time by the authority by which each  public accountant is appointed to his office,</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>" Public accountant" defined.-- For the purposes of  sections 1 and 2 of this Act, the expression" public accountant" means  any person who as Official Assignee or Trustee, or as sarbarahkar, is  entrusted with the receipt, custody or control of any moneys or  securities for money, or the management of any lands belonging to any  other person or persons, and for the purposes of sections 4 and 5 of  this Act the expression shall also include any person who, by reason  of any office held by him in the service of the Central Government or  the Government of a  State, is entrusted with the receipt, custody  or control of any moneys or securities for money, or the management of  any lands belonging to such Government.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Prosecution of accountants and sureties.-- The person or  persons at the head of the office to which any public accountant  belongs may proceed against any such public accountant and his  sureties for any loss or defalcation in his accounts, as if the amount  thereof were an arrear of land- revenue due to Government.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Enactments applied to proceedings by and against accountants.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>- All Regulations and Acts now or hereafter to be in force for the  recovery of arrears of land- revenue due to Government, and for  recovery of damages by any person wrongfully proceeded against for any  such arrear shall apply, with such changes in the forms of procedure  as are necessary to make them applicable to the case, to the  proceedings against and by such public accountant.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
