<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1953/49/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1953/49"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Salt Cess Act, 1953"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1953/49/eng@1953-12-26/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1953/49/eng@1953-12-26"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1953-12-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1953/49/eng@1953-12-26/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1953/49/eng@1953-12-26"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Salt Cess Act, 1953</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 49 OF 1953</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 26th December, 1953.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the levy and collection of a cess on salt for  the purpose of raising funds to meet the expenses incurred on the salt  organisation maintained by Government and on the measures taken by</p>
        <p>Government in connection with the manufacture, supply and distribution  of salt.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be  called the Salt Cess Act, 1953.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India .</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such  date as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" manufacture" in relation to salt includes collection,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>removal, preparation, steeping, evaporation, boiling or  any one or more of these processes, the separation or  purification of salt obtained in the manufacture of  saltpetre, the separation of salt from earth or other  substance so as to produce alimentary salt, and the  excavation or removal of natural saline deposits or  efflorescence; and the word manufacturer' shall be  construed accordingly and shall include not only a  person who employs hired labour in the production or  manufacture of a salt but also any person who engages  in its production or manufacture on his own account if  the salt is intended for sale.</p>
            <p>Explanation.-- In this clause, saltpetre'</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>includes rasi sajji, and all other substances  manufactured from saline earth, and kharinun and  every form of sulphate or carbonate of soda;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>' salt' includes swamp salt, spontaneous salt, and salt  or saline solutions made or produced from any saline  substances or from salt earth;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>The Act comes into force in Pondicherry on 1. 10. 1963 vide Reg. 7 of</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1963">
        <num>1963.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1963.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>, s. 3 and Sch. I.</p>
            <p>Extended to and brought into force in Dadra and Nagar Haveli (w. e. f.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>- 7- 1965) by Reg. 6 of 1963, s. 2 and Sch. I. and in Goa, Daman and</p>
            <blockList id="section-1.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Diu (w. e. f. 1- 6- 1969) by notificaation No. So. 2872, Dated 4- 6- 1969</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <blockList id="section-1.paragraph-0.list2.c.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>" salt factory" includes--</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list2.c.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>a place used or intended to be used in  the manufacture of salt and all embankments,</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>reservoirs, condensing and evaporating pans,</p>
            <p>buildings, and waste places situated within the  limits of such place, as defined from time to time  for the purposes of the Central Excises and Salt</p>
            <blockList id="section-1.paragraph-0.list6">
              <listIntroduction>Act, 1944; (1 of 1944)</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list6.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>all drying grounds and storage platforms  and storehouses appurtaining to any such place;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list6.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>land on which salt is spontaneously  produced;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list6.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Levy and collection of cess on salt. There shall be levied  and collected in such manner as may be prescribed, a cess in the  nature of an excise duty at the rate of fourteen naye paise per forty  kilograms on all salt manufactured in India in any salt factory,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>whether owned by Government or not.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Application of proceeds of cess. The proceeds of the duty  levied under this Act, reduced by the cost of collection as determined  by the Central Government, shall, if Parliament by appropriation made  by law in this behalf so provides, be utilised on all or any of the  following objects, namely:--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>meeting the expenditue incurred in connection with the  salt organisation maintained by the Central Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>meeting the cost of measures taken in connection with  the manufacture, supply and distribution of salt by</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Union agencies and the regulation and control of the  manufacture, supply and distribution of salt by other  agencies; and in particular, measures for--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list2.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the establishment and maintenance of  research stations and model salt farms;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list2.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>the establishment, maintenance and  expansion of salt factories;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list2.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>fixing the grades of salt;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list2.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>promoting and encouraging co- operative  effort among manufacturers of salt; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list2.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>promoting the welfare of labour employed  in the salt industry.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Validation of charges levied on salt before the commencement  of this Act. The charge in respect of the manufacture or production of  salt imposed by the rule made by the Central Government under section</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-37">
        <num>37.</num>
        <heading>of the Central Excises and Salt Act, 1944 (1 of 1944) and  published with the notification of the former Finance Department</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-37.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-37.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>(Revenue Division) No. 3 dated the 29th March, 1947, shall be deemed  to have been levied under this Act as if this Act was in force on  the day on which the charge was so imposed and accordingly,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-37.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any sum paid or payable by way of such charge shall be  deemed to heve been paid or payable in accordance with  the law; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-37.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>no claim shall lie in any Court for the refund of any  such so paid.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the  purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the assessment and collection of the cess levied under  this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the determination of the cost of collection of the cess;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the manner in which accounts relating to the proceeds of  the cess shall be maintained;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the manner in which the proceeds of the cess may be  applied on the object specified in section 4;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <blockList id="section-6.2.list1.e.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>the exemption from the whole or any part of the cess  levied under this Act--</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-6.2.list1.e.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>in respect of salt exported from India;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-6.2.list1.e.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>in respect of salt manufactured by any  specified categories of small manufacturers; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-6.2.list1.e.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>in respect of salt utilised in the  manufacture of any other product of industry.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made by the Central Government under this  section shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made before each</p>
            <p>House of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of  thirty days which may be comprised in one session or  in two or more  successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session  immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid] both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or  both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall  thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be no effect, as  the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment  shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done  under that rule.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
