<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1993/33/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1993/33"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Acquisition Of Certain Area At Ayodhya Act, 1993"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1993/33/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1993/33/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1993/33/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1993/33/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Acquisition Of Certain Area At Ayodhya Act, 1993</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>NO. 33 OF 1993</docNumber>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- fourth Year of the Republic  of India as follows:-</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[ 3rd April,</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the acquisition of certain area at Ayodhya  and for matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS there has been a long- standing dispute relating to the  structure (including the premises of the inner and outer courtyards of   such structure), commonly known as the Ram Janma Bhumi- Babri Masjid,</p>
        <p>situated in village Kot Ramchandra in Ayodhya, in Pargana Haveli</p>
        <p>Avadh, in tehsil Faizabad Sadar, in the district of Faizabad of the</p>
        <p>State of Uttar Pradesh;</p>
        <p>AND WHEREAS the said dispute has affected the maintenance of  public order and harmony between different communities in the  country;</p>
        <p>AND WHEREAS it is necessary to maintain public order and to  promote communal harmony and the spirit of common brotherhood amongst  the people of India;</p>
        <p>AND WHEREAS with a view to achieving the aforesaid objectives, it  is necessary to acquire certain areas in Ayodhya;</p>
        <p>CHAP</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the</p>
              <p>Acquisition of Certain Area at Ayodhya Act, 1993.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 7th day of</p>
              <p>January, 1993.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" area" means the area (including all the buildings,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>structures or other properties comprised therein) specified  in the Schedule;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" authorised person" means a person or body of persons  or trustees of any trust authorised by the Central Government  under section 7;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" Claims Commissioner" means the Claims Commissioner ap-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>pointed under subsection (2) of section 8;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Act.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>ACQUISITION OF THE AREA IN AYODHYA.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>ACQUISITION OF THE AREA IN AYODHYA</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Acquisition of rights in respect of certain area. On and from  the commencement of this Act, the right, title and interest in  relation to the area shall, by virtue of this Act, stand transferred  to, and vest in, the Central Government,</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>General effect of vesting.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The area shall be deemed to  include all assets, rights, leaseholds, powers, authority and  privileges and all property, movable and immovable, including lands,</p>
              <p>buildings, structures, shops of whatever nature or other properties  and all other rights and interests in, or arising out of, such  properties as were immediately before the commencement of this Act in  the ownership, possession, power or control of any person or the State</p>
              <p>Government of Uttar Pradesh, as the case may be, and all registers,</p>
              <p>maps, plans, drawings and other documents of whatever nature relating  thereto.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All properties aforesaid which have vested in the Central</p>
              <p>Government under section 3 shall, by force of such vesting, be freed  and discharged from any trust, obligation, mortgage, charge, lien and  all other encumbrances affecting them and any attachment, injunction,</p>
              <p>decree or order of any court or tribunal or other authority  restricting the use of such properties in any manner or appointing any  receiver in respect of the whole or any part of such properties shall  cease to have any effect.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If, on the commencement of this Act, any suit, appeal or  other proceeding in respect of the right, title and interest relating  to any property which has vested in the Central Government under  section 3, is pending before any court, tribunal or other authority,</p>
              <p>the same shall abate.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Duty of person or State Government in charge of the management  of the area to deliver all assets, etc.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may  take all necessary steps to secure possession of the area which is  vested in that Government under section 3.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On the vesting of the area in the Central Government under  section 3, the person or State Government of Uttar Pradesh, as the  case may be, in charge of the management of the area immediately  before such vesting shall be bound to deliver to the Central</p>
              <p>Government or the authorised person, all assets, registers and other  documents in their custody relating to such vesting or where it is not  practicable to deliver such registers or documents, the copies of such  registers or documents authenticated in the prescribed manner.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Power of Central Government to direct vesting of the area in  another authority or body or trust.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything  contained in sections 3, 4, 5 and 7, the Central Government may, if it  is satisfied that any authority or other body, or trustees of any  trust, set up on or after the commencement of this Act is or are  willing to comply with such terms and conditions as that Government  may think fit to impose, direct by notification in the Official</p>
              <p>Gazette, that the right, title and interest or any of them in relation  to the area or any part thereof, instead of continuing to vest in the</p>
              <p>Central Government, vest in that authority or body or trustees of that  trust either on the date of the notification or on such later date as  may be specified in the notification.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When any right, title and interest in relation to the area  or part thereof vest in the authority or body or trustees referred to  in sub- section (1), such rights of the Central Government in relation  to such area or part thereof, shall, on and from the date of such  vesting, be deemed to have become the rights of that authority or  body or trustees of that trust.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of sections 4, 5, 7 and 11 shall, so far as  may be, apply in relation to such authority or body or trustees as  they apply in relation to the Central Government and for this purpose  references therein to the Central Government shall be construed as  references to such authority or body or trustees.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>MANAGEMENT AND ADMINISTRATION OF PROPERTY.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MANAGEMENT AND ADMINISTRATION OF PROPERTY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Management of property by Government.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding  anything contained in any contract or instrument or order of any  court, tribunal or other authority to the contrary, on and from the  commencement of this Act, the property vested in the Central Govern-</p>
              <p>ment under section 3 shall be managed by the Central Government or by  a person or body of persons or trustees of any trust authorised by  that Government in this behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In managing the property vested in the Central Government  under section 3, the Central Government or the authorised person  shall ensure that the position existing before the commencement of  this Act in the area on which the structure including the premises of  the inner and outer courtyards of such structure commonly known as the</p>
              <p>Ram Janma Bhumi- Babri Masjid, stood in village Kot Ramchandra in</p>
              <p>Ayodhya, in Pargana Haveli Avadh, in tehsil Faizabad Sadar, in the dis-</p>
              <p>trict of Faizabad of the State of Uttar Pradesh is maintained.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>MISCELLANEOUS.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Payment of amount.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The owner of any land, building,</p>
              <p>structure or other property comprised in the area shall be given by  the Central Government, for the transfer to and vesting in that</p>
              <p>Government under section 3 of that land, building, structure or other  property, in cash an amount equivalent to the market value of the  land, building, structure or other property.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government shall, for the purpose of deciding  the claim of the owner or any person having a claim against the owner  under sub- section (1), by notification in the Official Gazette,</p>
              <p>appoint a Claims Commissioner.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Claims Commissioner shall regulate his own procedure for  receiving and deciding the claims.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The owner or any person having a claim against the owner may  make a claim to the Claims Commissioner within a period of ninety days  from the date of commencement of this Act:</p>
              <p>Provided that if the Claims Commissioner is satisfied that the  claimant was prevented by sufficient cause from preferring the claim  within the said period of ninety days, the Claims Commissioner may  entertain the claim, within a further period of ninety days and not  thereafter.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Act to override all other enactments. The provisions of this</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith  contained in any other law for tile time being in force or any  instrument having effect by virtue of any law other than this Act or  any decree or order of any court, tribunal or other authority.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Penalties. Any person who is in charge of the management of  the area and fails to deliver to the Central Government or the  authorised person any asset, register or other document in his custody  relating to such area or, as the case may be, authenticated copies of  such register or document, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a  term which may extend to three years or with fine which may extend to  ten thousand rupees or with both.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit, prosecution  or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central Government or  the authorised person or any of the officers or other employees of  that Government or the authorised person for anything which is in good  faith done or intended to be done under this Act.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-12.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the  provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act  shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House  of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty  days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more  successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session  immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule  or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall  thereafter have effect duly in such modified form or be of no effect,</p>
              <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that rule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Repeal and saving.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-13.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of sub-</p>
              <p>section (2), the Acquisition of Certain Area at Ayodhya Ordinance,</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1993">
          <num>1993.</num>
          <heading>(Ord. 8 of 1993), is hereby repealed.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1993.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1993.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in the said Ordinance,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1993.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the right, title and interest in relation to plot No.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-242">
          <num>242.</num>
          <heading>situated in village Kot Ramchandra specified against SI.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-242.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No. 1 of the Schedule to the said Ordinance shall be deemed  never to have been transferred to, and vested in, the Central</p>
              <blockList id="section-242.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Government;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-242.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>any suit, appeal or other proceeding in respect of the  right, title and interest relating to the said plot No. 242,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-242.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>pending before any court, tribunal or other authority, shall  be deemed never to have abated and such suit, appeal or other  proceeding (including the orders or interim orders of any   court thereon) shall be deemed to have been restored to the  position existing immediately before the commencement of the  said Ordinance;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-242.paragraph-0.list4.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>any other action taken or thing done under that Ordinance  in relation to the said plot No. 242 shall be deemed never to  have been taken or done.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-242.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action  taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or  taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
