<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1971/76/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1971/76"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Manipur (Hill Areas) District Councils Act, 1971"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1971/76/eng@1971-12-26/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1971/76/eng@1971-12-26"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1971-12-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1971/76/eng@1971-12-26/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1971/76/eng@1971-12-26"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Manipur (Hill Areas) District Councils Act, 1971</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 76 OF 1971</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 26th December, 1971.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- second Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the establishment of District Councils in the</p>
        <p>Hill Areas in the Union territory of Manipur.</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:--</p>
        <p>CHAP</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title and extent.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the Manipur</p>
              <p>(Hill Areas) District Councils Act, 1971.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It extends to the whole of the Union territory of Manipur.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" Administrator" means the administrator of the Union  territory of Manipur appointed under article 239 of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Constitution;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" autonomous district" means an autonomous district  referred to in sub- section (1) of section 3;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" building" includes a house, out- house, stable, latrine,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>urinal, shed, hut, wall (other than boundary wall) and  any other structure (whether of masonry, bricks, wood,</p>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>mud or other material) but does not include any  portable or temporary shelter;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" constituency" means a District Council constituency  provided by order made under section 5 for the purpose  of elections to the District Council;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>" Deputy Commissioner", in relation to any District</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Council, means the officer appointed as such by the</p>
              <p>Administrator, by notification in the Official Gazette,</p>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list9">
                <listIntroduction>to perform the functions of the Deputy Commissioner  under this Act in the autonomous district for which  such District Council has been constituted;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list9.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>" Hill Areas" means the Hill Areas determined by the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>President by any notification issued under sub- section</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-2.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of section 52 of the Government of Union</p>
              <blockList id="section-2.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Territories Act, 1963 (20 of 1963.) and in force  immediately before the commencement of this Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.2.list2.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>" Hill Areas Committee" means the Standing Committee  referred to in section 52 of the Government of Union</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.2.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Territories Act, 1963; (20 of 1963.)</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.2.list4.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>" market" includes any place where persons assemble for  the sale of, or for the purpose of exposing for sale  of, meat, fish, fruit, vegetables, animals intended for  human food or any other articles of human food  whatsoever with or without the consent of the owner of  such place notwithstanding that there may be no common  regulation for the concourse of buyers and sellers and  whether or not any control is exercised over the  business of, or the persons frequenting, the market by  the owner of the place or by any other persons;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.2.list4.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>" member" means a member of a District Council  constituted under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.2.list4.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>" Official Gazette" means the Gazette of the Union  territory of Manipur;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.2.list4.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>" person" does not include a body of persons;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.2.list4.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.2.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.2.list6.m">
                  <num>(m)</num>
                  <p>" Scheduled Tribes" has the same meaning assigned to it  in clause (25) of article 366 of the Constitution;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.2.list6.n">
                  <num>(n)</num>
                  <p>" vehicle" includes a carriage, cart, hand- cart, bicycle,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>tricycle and every wheeled conveyance which is used or  is capable of being used on a street but does not  include a mechanically propelled vehicle.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>CONSTITUTION OF DISTRICT COUNCILS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>CONSTITUTION OF DISTRICT COUNCILS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Division of Hill Areas into autonomous districts.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As soon  as may be after the commencement of this Act, the Administrator shall  cause all the Hill Areas to be divided into not more than six  autonomous districts.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Administrator may, by order notified in the Official</p>
              <blockList id="section-3.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Gazette,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.2.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>declare that any area in any autonomous district which  is, or is intended to be, included within the limits of  any</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.2.list4">
                <listIntroduction>municipality, cantonment or town committee shall cease  to be a part of such autonomous district;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.2.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>increase the area of any autonomous district;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.2.list4.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>diminish the area of any autonomous district;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.2.list4.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>unite two or more autonomous districts or parts thereof  so as to form one autonomous district;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.2.list4.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>define the boundaries of any autonomous district;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.2.list4.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>alter the name of any autonomous district.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No order under sub- section (2) shall be made by the</p>
              <p>Administrator except after consultation with the Hill Areas Committee.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any order made by the Administrator under sub- section (2) may  contain such incidental and consequential provisions as appear to the</p>
              <p>Administrator to be necessary for giving effect to the provisions of  the order.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Constitution of District Councils and their composition.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For each autonomous district there shall be a District Council as from  such date as the Administrator may, by notification in the Official</p>
              <p>Gazette, appoint in this behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The total number of seats in the District Council to be  filled by persons chosen by direct election on the basis of adult  suffrage from territorial constituencies shall be not more than  eighteen.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Administrator may nominate not more than two persons, not  being persons in the service of Government, to be members of any</p>
              <p>District Council.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Delimitation of constituencies. The Administrator shall, by  order, determine--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the constituencies (which shall be single member   constituencies) into which an autonomous district shall  be divided for the purpose of election of members to  the District Council of that district; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the extent of each constituency.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Power to alter or amend delimitation orders. The Administrator  may, from time to time, by order, alter or amend any order made under  section 5.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Qualifications for membership. A person shall not be qualified  to be chosen as a member of a District Council of any autonomous  district unless he is an elector for any District Council constituency  in that autonomous district.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Disqualifications for membership.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A person shall be  disqualified for being chosen as a member of a District Council if he  is for the time being disqualified for being chosen as a member of  either House of Parliament or holds any office of profit under any</p>
              <p>District Council.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purposes of this section, a person shall not be  deemed to hold an office of profit under a District Council by reason  only that he is a member thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Electors on electoral rolls.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The persons entitled to vote  at elections of members of a District Council shall be the persons  entitled, by virtue of the provisions of the Constitution and the</p>
              <p>Representation of the People Act, 1950, (43 of 1950.) to be registered  as voters at elections to the House of the People.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>So much of the electoral roll for any parliamentary  constituency for the time being in force as relates to the areas  comprised within a constituency formed under section 5 shall be deemed  to be the electoral roll for that constituency for the purposes of  this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Right to vote.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every person whose name is, for the time  being, entered in the electoral roll of a constituency shall be  entitled to vote at the election of a member of the District Council  from that constituency.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every person shall give one vote and no more to any one  candidate at an election.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Election of members. Election of members of a District</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Council shall be held in accordance with the rules made under section</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>on such date or dates as the Administrator may, by notification in  the Official Gazette, direct:</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Provided that a casual vacancy shall be filled as soon as may be  after the occurrence of the vacancy:</p>
              <p>Provided further that no election shall be held to fill up a  casual vacancy occurring within four months prior to the holding of a  general election under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Notification of results of elections. The names of all  persons elected or nominated to be members of a District Council shall  be published by the Administrator in the Official Gazette.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Term of office of members.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-13.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Save as otherwise provided in  this section, the term of office of a member shall be five years and  shall commence from the date of the notification of his election or  nomination under section 12 or from</p>
              <p>the date on which the vacancy in which he is elected or nominated has  occurred, whichever date is later:</p>
              <p>Provided that the Adminstrator may, when satisfied that it is  necessary in order to avoid administrative difficulty, extend the term  of office of all the members by such period not exceeding one year as  he thinks fit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The term of office of a member elected to fill a casual  vacancy shall commence from the date of the notification of his  election and shall continue so long only as the member in whose place  he is elected would have been entitled to hold office if the vacancy  had not occurred.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Disputes as to elections.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No election of a member shall  be called in question except by an election petition presented to the  court of the District Judge having jurisdiction in the area in which  the constituency concerned is situated, within thirty days from the  date of the notification of the result of the election under section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An election petition calling in question any such election  may be presented on one or more of the grounds specified in section 16  by any candidate at such election or by any elector of the  constituency.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A petitioner shall join as respondents to his petition all  the candidates at the election.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-12.4.list1">
                <listIntroduction>An election petition--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12.4.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>shall contain a concise statement of the material facts  on which the petitioner relies;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.4.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>shall, with sufficient particulars, set forth the ground  or grounds on which the election is called in question;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-12.4.list3">
                <listIntroduction>and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12.4.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>shall be signed by the petitioner and verified in the  manner laid down in the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>(5 of 1908.) for the verification of pleadings.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Relief that may be claimed by petitioner. A petitioner may,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>in addition to claiming a declaration that the election of all or any  of the returned candidates is void, claim a further declaration that  he himself or any other candidate has been duly elected.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Grounds on which an election may be called in question. The  election of a returned candidate may be called in question on any one  or more of the following grounds, namely:--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-16.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>that on the date of his election the returned candidate  was not qualified to be elected, or he was disqualified  for being elected, as a member under this Act; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>that the nomination paper of any candidate at the  election has been improperly rejected; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>that the result of the election has been materially  affected by the improper acceptance of a nomination  paper or by the improper acceptance or refusal of a  vote or by any other cause.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Procedure to be followed by the District Judge. The procedure  provided in the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908.) in regard  to suits shall be followed by the court of the District Judge, as far  as it can be made applicable, in the trial and disposal of an election  petition under this Act.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Decision of the District Judge.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-18.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-18.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>At the conclusion of the  trial of an election petition, the court of the District Judge shall  make an order--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-18.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>dismissing the election petition; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>declaring the election of all or any of the returned  candidates to be void; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>declaring the election of all or any of the returned  candidates to be void and the petitioner or any other  candidate to have been duly elected.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-18.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>If any person who has filed an election petition has, in  addition to calling in question the election of the returned  candidate, claimed a declaration that he himself or any other  candidate has been duly elected and the court of the District Judge is  of opinion--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-18.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>that in fact the petitioner or such other candidate  received a majority of the valid votes; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>that but for the votes obtained by the returned  candidate, the petitioner or such other candidate would  have obtained a majority of the valid votes,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>the court of the District Judge shall, after declaring the election of  the returned candidate to be void, declare the petitioner or such  other candidate, as the case may be, to have been duly elected.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Procedure in case of equality of votes.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-19.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If during the  trial of an election petition it appears that there is equality of  votes between any candidates at the election and that the addition of  a vote would entitle any of those candidates to be declared elected,</p>
              <p>then, the court of the District Judge shall decide between them by lot  and proceed as if the one on whom the lot falls had received an  additional vote.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Finality of decisions.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-20.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An order of the court of the</p>
              <p>District Judge on an election petition shall be final and conclusive.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An election of a member not called in question in accordance  with the foregoing provisions shall be deemed to be a good and valid  election.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules regulating the election of members. The</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Administrator may make rules to regulate all or any of the following  matters for the purpose of the holding of elections of members under  this Act, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the manner of the splitting up of electoral rolls for  parliamentary constituencies into parts for the purpose  of constituting one or more of such parts into  electoral roll for a constituency; and the officer or  authority by whom such splitting up is to be carried  out;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the drawing up of the programme of election;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the appointment of returning officers, presiding and  polling officers for election;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the nomination of candidates and the scrutiny of such  nomination;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the deposits to be made by candidates and the time and  manner of making such deposits;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the withdrawal of candidatures;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the appointment of agents of candidates;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>the time and manner of holding elections;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the general procedure at the elections including the  time, place and hours of poll and the method by which  votes shall be cast;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>the fee to be paid on an election petition;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>any other matter relating to elections or election  disputes in respect of which the Administrator deems it  necessary to make rules under this section or in  respect of which this Act makes no provision or makes  insufficient provision and provision is, in the opinion  of the Administrator, necessary.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Incorporation of District Councils. Each District Council  shall be a body corporate by the name respectively of" the District</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Council of (name of autonomous district)" and shall have perpetual  succession and a common seal with power to acquire, hold and dispose  of property and to contract and may by the said name sue and be sued.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Chairman and Vice- Chairman.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-23.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A District Council shall, as  soon as may be, choose two members to be respectively Chairman and</p>
              <p>Vice- Chairman thereof and so often as the office of Chairman or Vice-</p>
              <p>Chairman becomes vacant, the Council shall choose another member to be</p>
              <p>Chairman or Vice- Chairman, as the case may be:</p>
              <p>Provided that the Administrator may nominate the first Chairman  who shall hold office for a period not exceeding one year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a resolution for the removal of an elected Chairman is  passed by not less than two- thirds of the total membership of the</p>
              <p>Council at a meeting convened in accordance with the provisions of  sub- section (3), such resolution shall have the effect of removing the</p>
              <p>Chairman from his office as from the date on which the resolution is  so passed and if such resolution is passed by less than two- thirds but  not less than one- half of the total membership of the Council, the</p>
              <p>Administrator may, by order in writing, remove, for reasons to be  recorded, the Chairman from his office as from such date as may be  specified in the order:</p>
              <p>Provided that no such resolution shall be brought within one year  from the date of election of the Chairman:</p>
              <p>Provided further that if the resolution is not passed by not less  than two- thirds of the total membership of the Council, no other  resolution for the removal of the Chairman shall be allowed to be  considered within one year from the date on which such resolution was  considered.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A notice in writing of the intention to move a resolution  referred to in sub- section (2) signed by not less than one- third of  the total membership of the Council together with a copy of the  proposed resolution shall be delivered to the Deputy Commissioner in  accordance with the rules made by the Deputy Commissioner in this  behalf and the Deputy Commissioner shall, after giving not less than  fifteen days' notice thereon, convene for consideration of the  resolution a meeting of the Council to be held in the office of the</p>
              <p>Council on a date not later than thirty days from the date on which  the notice was delivered to him and he shall preside over the meeting.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chairman of the Council shall be a whole- time functionary  and shall be entitled to such salary or allowances as may be fixed by  the Administrator.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Oath or affirmation by members. Every member shall, before  taking his seat, make and subscribe at a meeting of the District</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Council, an oath or affirmation in the prescribed form.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Vacation of seats.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-25.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No person shall be a member both of  the Legislative Assembly of the Union territory of Manipur and of a</p>
              <p>District Council and if a person is chosen a member both of the</p>
              <p>Legislative Assembly and of a District Council, then, at the  expiration of fourteen days from the date of publication in the</p>
              <p>Official Gazette that he has been so chosen, that person' s seat in the</p>
              <p>District Council shall become vacant unless he has previously resigned  his seat in the Legislative Assembly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-25.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>If a member--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-25.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>becomes subject to any of the disqualifications  mentioned in section 8; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-25.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>resigns his seat by writing under his hand addressed to  the Chairman of the District Council,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>his seat shall thereupon become vacant.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If during the six successive months a member is, without the  permission of the District Council, absent from all meetings thereof,</p>
              <p>the Council may declare his seat vacant.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any question arises as to whether a member has become  subject to any of the disqualifications mentioned in section 8, it  shall be referred to the District Judge having jurisdiction in the  area in which the constituency concerned is situated and his decision  shall be final.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Allowances of members. Subject to the provisions of sub-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>section (4) of section 23, every member shall be entitled to receive  such allowances as may be determined by the Administrator.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Liability of members. Every person shall be liable for the  loss, waste or misappropriation of any money or other property  belonging to a District Council, if such loss, waste or  misappropriation is a direct consequence of his neglect or misconduct  while a member of the District Council and a suit for compensation may  be instituted against him by the Council with the previous sanction of  the Deputy Commissioner or by the Deputy Commissioner with the  previous sanction of the Administrator.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Members to be deemed to be public servants. Every member  shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of section</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>of the Indian Penal Code. (45 of 1860.)</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>FUNCTIONS OF DISTRICT COUNCILS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>FUNCTIONS OF DISTRICT COUNCILS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Functions of District Councils.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-29.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to such  exceptions and conditions as the Administrator may make and impose,</p>
              <blockList id="section-29.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>the following matters shall be under the control and administration of  a District Council, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-29.1.list2.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the maintenance and management of such property, movable  and immovable, and institutions as may be transferred  to that Council by the Administrator;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-29.1.list2.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>the construction, repair and maintenance of such of the  roads, bridges, channels and buildings as may be  transferred to that Council by the Administrator;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-29.1.list2.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>the establishment, maintenance and management of  primary schools and the construction and repair of all  buildings connected with these institutions and  institution of scholarships;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-29.1.list2.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>the establishment, maintenance and management of  dispensaries;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-29.1.list2.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>the establishment and maintenance of cattle pounds  including such functions under the Cattle- trespass Act,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1871">
          <num>1871.</num>
          <heading>(1 of 1871.) as may be transferred to that Council  by the Administrator;</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-1871.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1871.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-1871.paragraph-0.list0.vi">
                  <num>(vi)</num>
                  <p>the establishment, maintenance and management of  markets and fairs and the construction, repair and  maintenance of all buildings connected therewith;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1871.paragraph-0.list0.vii">
                  <num>(vii)</num>
                  <p>the supply, storage and prevention from pollution of  water for drinking, cooking and bathing purposes;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1871.paragraph-0.list0.viii">
                  <num>(viii)</num>
                  <p>the construction, repair and maintenance of  embankments and the supply, storage and control of  water for agricultural purposes;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1871.paragraph-0.list0.ix">
                  <num>(ix)</num>
                  <p>the preservation and reclamation of soil;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1871.paragraph-0.list0.x">
                  <num>(x)</num>
                  <p>the preservation, protection and improvement of live-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1871.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>stock and prevention of animal diseases;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1871.paragraph-0.list2.xi">
                  <num>(xi)</num>
                  <p>public health and sanitation;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1871.paragraph-0.list2.xii">
                  <num>(xii)</num>
                  <p>the management of such ferries as may be entrusted to  the charge of that Council by the Administrator;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1871.paragraph-0.list2.xiii">
                  <num>(xiii)</num>
                  <p>the initiation, inspection and control of relief  works;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1871.paragraph-0.list2.xiv">
                  <num>(xiv)</num>
                  <p>the allotment, occupation or use, or the setting apart  of land, other than land acquired for any public  purpose or land which is a reserved forest, for the  purpose of agriculture or grazing or for residential or  other non- agricultural purposes or for any other  purposes likely to promote the interests of the  inhabitants of any village or town situated within the  autonomous district for which that council is  constituted;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1871.paragraph-0.list2.xv">
                  <num>(xv)</num>
                  <p>the management of any forest not being a reserved  forest;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1871.paragraph-0.list2.xvi">
                  <num>(xvi)</num>
                  <p>the regulation of the practice of Jhum or other form  of shifting cultivation; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1871.paragraph-0.list2.xvii">
                  <num>(xvii)</num>
                  <p>any other matter which the Administrator may, in  consultation with the Hill Areas Committee, entrust to  the District Council in the field of agriculture,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>animal husbandry, community development, social and  tribal welfare, village planning or any other matter  referred to in section 52 of the Government of Union</p>
              <p>Territories Act, 1963 (20 of 1963.).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-1871.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall be competent for a District Council to recommend to  the Government of the Union territory of Manipur legislation relating  to the following matters in so far as they concern members of the</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-scheduled">
      <doc name="scheduled">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1971/76/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1971/76"/>
              <FRBRalias value="Tribes, namely:--"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1971/76/eng@1971-12-26/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1971/76/eng@1971-12-26"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1971/76/eng@1971-12-26/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1971/76/eng@1971-12-26"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduled">
            <paragraph id="scheduled.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <blockList id="scheduled.paragraph-0.list0">
                  <item id="scheduled.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>appointment or succession of Chiefs;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="scheduled.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>inheritance of property;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="scheduled.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <p>marriage and divorce; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="scheduled.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                    <num>(d)</num>
                    <p>social customs.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <p>CHAP</p>
                <p>PROCEDURE AND STAFF OF DISTRICT COUNCILS</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <chapter id="chapter-IV">
              <num>IV</num>
              <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>PROCEDURE AND STAFF OF DISTRICT COUNCILS</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-30">
                <num>30.</num>
                <heading>Conduct of business. A District Council shall conduct its  business in such manner and in accordance with such procedure as may  be prescribed.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-31">
                <num>31.</num>
                <heading>Committees. A District Council may, from time to time,</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-31.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>appoint out of its own body such and so many committees for the  efficient discharge of its duties as may be necessary.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-32">
                <num>32.</num>
                <heading>Officers and staff.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-32.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>For every District Council there  shall be a Chief Executive Officer, who shall be appointed by the</p>
                    <p>Administrator.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-32.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>If a resolution for removal of the Chief Executive Officer is  passed at a meeting of the District Council by a majority of not less  than two- thirds of the total membership of the Council, the</p>
                    <p>Administrator shall remove him forthwith.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-32.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The District Council shall appoint such officers and staff as  may be necessary for the proper and efficient execution of its duties  and make regulations for their conditions of service.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-32.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The power of appointing officers and staff (whether temporary   or permanent) shall be exercised in accordance with the rules framed  for the purpose by the Administrator.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-32.5">
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The conditions of service applicable to a person immediately  before his appointment to a post under a District Council shall not be  varied to his disadvantage except with the previous approval of the</p>
                    <p>Administrator.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-32.6">
                  <num>(6)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every officer or member of staff of a District Council shall  be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of section 21 of  the Indian Penal Code. (45 of 1860.)</p>
                    <p>CHAP</p>
                    <p>FINANCE OF DISTRICT COUNCILS AND VESTING OF PROPERTY</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
            </chapter>
            <chapter id="chapter-V">
              <num>V</num>
              <paragraph id="chapter-V.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>FINANCE OF DISTRICT COUNCILS AND VESTING OF PROPERTY</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-33">
                <num>33.</num>
                <heading>Powers of taxation. Notwithstanding anything to the contrary  contained in any other law for the time being in force, a District</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-33.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Council shall have the power to levy all or any of the following taxes  within the autonomous district for which the Council is constituted,</p>
                    <blockList id="section-33.paragraph-0.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>that is to say--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-33.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>taxes on professions, trades, callings and employments;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-33.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>taxes on animals, vehicles (other than mechanically   propelled vehicles) and boats;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-33.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>taxes on entry of goods into a market for sale there in  and tolls on passengers and goods carried in ferries;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-33.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <p>taxes for the maintenance of schools, dispensaries or  roads; and</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-33.paragraph-0.list2.e">
                        <num>(e)</num>
                        <p>any other tax falling under List II of the Seventh</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
            </chapter>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-scheduleto">
      <doc name="scheduleto">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1971/76/scheduleto"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1971/76"/>
              <FRBRalias value="the Constitution which the Legislature of  the Union territory of Manipur may, by law, empower the"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1971/76/eng@1971-12-26/scheduleto"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1971/76/eng@1971-12-26"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1971/76/eng@1971-12-26/scheduleto"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1971/76/eng@1971-12-26"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduleto">
            <heading>District Council to levy.</heading>
            <section id="section-34">
              <num>34.</num>
              <heading>Levy of fees. A District Council may fix and levy--</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-34.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-34.paragraph-0.list0">
                    <item id="section-34.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>school fees; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-34.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>fees for the use of, or benefits derived from, any of  the works done or services rendered under section 29.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-35">
              <num>35.</num>
              <heading>Procedure for imposing taxes.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-35.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A District Council may  resolve at a meeting specially convened for the purpose to propose the  imposition of any of the taxes mentioned in section 33.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-35.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>When a resolution has been passed, the Council shall publish  a notice in the Official Gazette and also in the prescribed manner,</p>
                  <p>defining</p>
                  <p>the class of persons or description of property proposed to be taxed,</p>
                  <p>the amount or rate of tax to be imposed and the system of assessment  to be adopted.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-35.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Any person, directly or indirectly affected by the proposed  tax and objecting to it, may, within thirty days from the publication  of the notice, send his objections in writing to the Council and the</p>
                  <p>Council shall, at a specially convened meeting, take all such  objections into consideration.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-35.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>If no objection is sent within the said period of thirty days  or if the objections received are deemed insufficient, the Council may  submit its proposals to the Administrator with the objections, if any,</p>
                  <p>and its decision thereon.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-35.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Administrator may then sanction the proposals or refuse  to sanction them or return them to the Council for further  consideration.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-35.6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>When the proposal in respect of a tax has been sanctioned,</p>
                  <p>the Administrator shall notify its imposition in the Official Gazette  and specify a date not later than three months from the date of  notification on which the tax shall come into force.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-36">
              <num>36.</num>
              <heading>Abolition or reduction of taxes. The Administrator may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, and a District Council may with  the previous approval of the Administrator by a resolution passed at a  meeting specially convened for the purpose, abolish or reduce any tax  imposed under section 33.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-37">
              <num>37.</num>
              <heading>Recovery of taxes and fees. All arrears of taxes and fees  levied under this Act may be recovered under the law for the time  being in force for the recovery public dues as if such arrears were  public dues.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-38">
              <num>38.</num>
              <heading>Assessment and collection of taxes and fees. A District  council may, by notification in the Official Gazette, determine the  person by whom any tax or fee shall be assessed and collected and make  rules for the assessment and collection of such tax or fee and direct  in what manner persons employed in the assessment or collection shall  be remunerated.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-39">
              <num>39.</num>
              <heading>Appeals.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-39.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>In matters connected with the assessment and  collection of any tax or fee levied under this Act, an appeal shall  lie from the order of any person authorised to make assessment or  collections to such person as the Administrator may appoint or  designate for the purpose.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-39.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>An appeal under sub- section (1) shall be presented within  thirty days from the date of the order.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-39.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The order passed on the appeal shall be final.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-40">
              <num>40.</num>
              <heading>Instalments of taxes and fees. A District Council may, by  notification in the Official Gazette and with the previous approval of  the Deputy Commissioner, prescribe by what instalments and at what  times any tax or fee shall be payable.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-41">
              <num>41.</num>
              <heading>Power to exempt from taxation. A District Council may, with  the previous approval of the Administrator, by notification in the</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-41.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Official Gazette, remit or reduce any tax or fee or exempt any persons  or class of persons or any description of property, wholly or in part,</p>
                  <p>from liability to any tax or fee and cancel any such remission,</p>
                  <p>reduction or exemption.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-42">
              <num>42.</num>
              <heading>Recoveries of moneys claimable by the Council.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-42.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Save as  provided by section 37, all moneys claimable by a District Council may  be recovered on an application to a Magistrate having jurisdiction in  the area where the person from whom the money is claimable may, for  the time being, be resident, by the distress and sale of any movable  property or by the attachment and sale of any immovable property,</p>
                  <p>within the limits of his jurisdiction belonging to such person and the  cost of such proceedings shall be recoverable in the same manner as  the said moneys.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-42.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>An application for recovery of money shall be in writing and  shall be signed by an officer authorised in this behalf by order of  the Chairman of the Council.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-43">
              <num>43.</num>
              <heading>Council Fund.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-43.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>All moneys received by or on behalf of a</p>
                  <p>District Council under the provisions of this Act or any other law for  the time being in force shall be credited to a fund which shall be  called the" Council Fund" and it shall be held by the District Council  in trust for the purposes of this Act.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-43.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>All expenditure of the Council shall be defrayed out of the</p>
                  <p>Council Fund.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-43.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Administrator may make rules for the management of the</p>
                  <p>Council Fund and for the procedure to be followed in respect of  payment of money into the said Fund, the withdrawal of moneys  therefrom, the custody of moneys therein and any other matter  connected with or ancillary to the matters aforesaid.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-43.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The accounts of a District Council shall be kept in such form  as may be prescribed.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-43.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The accounts of a District Council shall be audited in such  manner as may be prescribed.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-44">
              <num>44.</num>
              <heading>Property vested in District Council. Subject to any order of  the Administrator, all property of the nature specified below and  situated in the autonomous district shall vest in and belong to the</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-44.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>District Council for which it is constituted and shall,</p>
                  <blockList id="section-44.paragraph-0.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>with all other property which may become vested in the Council, be  under its direction, management and control and shall be held and  applied for the purposes of this Act--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-44.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>all public buildings, constructed or maintained out of  the Council Fund;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-44.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>all public roads which have been constructed or are  maintained out of the Council Fund and the stones and  other materials thereof and also all trees, erections,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-44.paragraph-0.list4">
                    <listIntroduction>materials, implements and things provided for such  roads;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-44.paragraph-0.list4.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>all land or other property transferred to the District</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Council by the Administrator or by gift, sale or  otherwise for public purposes.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-45">
              <num>45.</num>
              <heading>Budget.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-45.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A District Council shall, on or before a  prescribed day in each year submit to the Administrator an estimate of  the income and expenditure of the Council for the next financial year  in such form as may be prescribed.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-45.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Administrator may, on or before a prescribed day, return  the estimate of the Council with or without modifications.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-45.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>When a budget is returned with modifications under sub-</p>
                  <p>section (2), the Council shall consider the proposed modifications,</p>
                  <p>take a decision thereon and report the same to the Administrator.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-45.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The budget estimate finally adopted by the Council shall be  the budget of the District Council.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-45.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Any subsequent alteration in the budget or reappropriation or  transfer of provision within the estimate shall be made with the  approval of the Administrator.</p>
                  <p>CHAP</p>
                  <p>CONTROL</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <chapter id="chapter-VI">
              <num>VI</num>
              <paragraph id="chapter-VI.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>CONTROL</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-46">
                <num>46.</num>
                <heading>Control.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-46.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>It shall be the duty of the Chairman of a</p>
                    <p>District Council to furnish to the Deputy Commissioner a copy of the  proceedings of the meetings of the Council and such other information  as the Deputy Commissioner may require.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-46.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Deputy Commissioner shall have the power to give to any</p>
                    <p>District Council all such directions as he may consider necessary in  res-</p>
                    <p>pect of subjects, curricula, text books and standards of teaching in  schools vested wholly or partly in the Council and in schools wholly  or partly maintained by grants payable from the Council Fund and the</p>
                    <p>Council shall comply with such directions.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-46.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Deputy Commissioner may, by order, and for reasons to be  recorded, suspend the execution of any resolution or order of any</p>
                    <p>District Council or prohibit the doing of any act which is about to be  done, or is being done, in pursuance of or under cover of any  provision of the law relating to the constitution or functions of the</p>
                    <p>District Council, if, in his opinion, the resolution, order or act is  in excess of the powers conferred by law or the execution of the  resolution or order or the doing of the act is likely to lead to a  breach of the peace, or to cause annoyance or injury to the public or  to any class or body of persons:</p>
                    <p>Provided that the Council may, within fifteen days of the date of  the order of the Deputy Commissioner offer such explanation as it  deems fit in relation to the execution of the resolution or order  which has been suspended or the doing of the act has been prohibited.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-46.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>When the Deputy Commissioner makes any order as aforesaid, he  shall forthwith send a copy of it to the Administrator with a  statement of the reasons for making it and forward in due course to  the Administrator the explanation, if any, offered by the Council and  the Administrator may, thereupon, confirm, modify or rescind the order  of the Deputy Commissioner.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-47">
                <num>47.</num>
                <heading>Supersession of District Council.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-47.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-47.1.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>If, on receipt of a  report from the Deputy Commissioner or otherwise, the Administrator is  of opinion that--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-47.1.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>any District Council is not competent to perform, or  persistently makes default in the performance of, the  duties imposed on it by or under this Act or any other  law; or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-47.1.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>any District Council exceeds or abuses its powers; or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-47.1.list1.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>the financial position and credit position of any</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-47.1.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>District Council is seriously threatened; or</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-47.1.list3.d">
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <p>a situation has arisen in which the administration of  any District Council cannot be carried on in accordance  with the provisions of this Act,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>the Administrator may, by an order published, together with a  statement of reasons therefor, in the Official Gazette, supersede such</p>
                    <p>Council for such period, not exceeding one year, as may be specified  in the order:</p>
                    <p>Provided that before making an order of supersession as aforesaid  under clause (a) or clause (b) or clause (c), reasonable opportunity  shall</p>
                    <p>be given to such Council to show cause why such order of supersession  should not be made:</p>
                    <p>Provided further that the period of supersession may be extended  for any further period or periods not exceeding six months at a time  in consultation with the Hill Areas Committee.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-47.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-47.2.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>When any District Council is superseded by an order under  subsection (1),--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-47.2.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>all the members of the Council (including the Chairman   and Vice- Chairman thereof) shall, on such date as may  be specified in the order, vacate their offices as such  members without prejudice to their eligibility for  election or nomination under clause (d);</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-47.2.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>during the period of supersession of the Council, all  powers and duties conferred and imposed upon the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-47.2.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>Council by or under this Act or any other law shall be  exercised and performed by such officer or authority as  the Administrator may appoint in this behalf;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-47.2.list3.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>all property vested in the Council shall, until it is  reconstituted, vest in the Central Government;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-47.2.list3.d">
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <p>before the expiry of the period of supersession,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>election or nomination, as the case may be, of members  to the Council shall be held or made for the purpose of  reconstituting the Council.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-48">
                <num>48.</num>
                <heading>Effect of certain provisions during the period when the Hill</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-48.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Areas Committee is not functioning. Where at any time, consequent on  the dissolution of the Legislative Assembly of the Union territory of</p>
                    <blockList id="section-48.paragraph-0.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>Manipur, the Hill Areas Committee is not functioning, then, during the  period when such Committee is not functioning,--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-48.paragraph-0.list2.i">
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <p>section 3 shall have effect as if sub- section (3)</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-48.paragraph-0.list4">
                      <listIntroduction>thereof had been omitted;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-48.paragraph-0.list4.ii">
                        <num>(ii)</num>
                        <p>clause (xvii) of section 29 and the second proviso to  subsection (1) of section 47 have effect as if the  words" in consultation with the Hill Areas Committee"</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>had been omitted therefrom.</p>
                    <p>CHAP</p>
                    <p>OFFENCES AND PENALTIES</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
            </chapter>
            <chapter id="chapter-VII">
              <num>VII</num>
              <paragraph id="chapter-VII.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>OFFENCES AND PENALTIES</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-49">
                <num>49.</num>
                <heading>Penalty for obstruction. If any person wilfully obstructs a</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-49.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>District Council or any officer or servant of a District Council or  any person authorised by the District Council in the exercise of its  powers, he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to fifty  rupees.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-50">
                <num>50.</num>
                <heading>Penalty for entering into any contract with the Council. If  any member, officer or other employee of a District Council enters  into any contract with the Council, he shall be deemed to have  committed an offence under section 168 of the Indian Penal Code.</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-50.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>CHAP</p>
                    <p>RULES AND BYE- LAWS</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
            </chapter>
            <chapter id="chapter-VIII">
              <num>VIII</num>
              <paragraph id="chapter-VIII.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>RULES AND BYE- LAWS</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-51">
                <num>51.</num>
                <heading>Power of Administrator to make rules.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-51.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Without prejudice  to the power to make rules under any other provision of this Act, the</p>
                    <p>Administrator may, after previous publication, make, by notification  in the Official Gazette, rules for the purpose of carrying out the  provisions of this Act.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-51.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-51.2.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-51.2.list1.i">
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <p>regulate the conduct of business of a District Council;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-51.2.list1.ii">
                        <num>(ii)</num>
                        <p>prescribe the forms in which the budget estimate is to  be prepared and the dates for the various stages of its  completion;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-51.2.list1.iii">
                        <num>(iii)</num>
                        <p>determine the language in which the business of a</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-51.2.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>District Council will be transacted;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-51.2.list3.iv">
                        <num>(iv)</num>
                        <p>regulate the powers of a District Council to transfer  property;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-51.2.list3.v">
                        <num>(v)</num>
                        <p>regulate the powers of a District Council to contract  and do other things necessary for the purposes of its  constitution and the mode of executing contracts;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-51.2.list3.vi">
                        <num>(vi)</num>
                        <p>regulate the employment, payment, suspension and  removal of officers and staff of a District Council;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-51.2.list3.vii">
                        <num>(vii)</num>
                        <p>protect the terms and conditions of service of</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-51.2.list5">
                      <listIntroduction>Government servants transferred to a District Council;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-51.2.list5.viii">
                        <num>(viii)</num>
                        <p>prescribe the forms for statements, registers,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-51.2.list7">
                      <listIntroduction>estimates and accounts of a District Council and  regulate the keeping, checking and publication of such  accounts;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-51.2.list7.ix">
                        <num>(ix)</num>
                        <p>prescribe the authority by whom and the manner in which  the accounts of a District Council shall be audited;</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-51.2.list9">
                      <listIntroduction>and</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-51.2.list9.x">
                        <num>(x)</num>
                        <p>provide for any other matter for which rules have to be  made under this Act.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-52">
                <num>52.</num>
                <heading>Power to make bye- laws.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-52.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Subject to the provisions of this</p>
                    <p>Act and of the rules made thereunder, a District Council may make bye-</p>
                    <blockList id="section-52.1.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>laws to provide for all or any of the following matters in the  autonomous district for which it is constituted or in any part  thereof, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-52.1.list3.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>the maintenance and management of schools and grants of  stipends and scholarships;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-52.1.list3.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>control and administration of dispensaries, their  construction and repairs, the supply of medicines and  the measures to be taken during the prevalence of  diseases;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-52.1.list3.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>the protection from pollution of such tanks, springs,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-52.1.list5">
                      <listIntroduction>wells or parts of rivers, streams, channels or water  courses as are set apart for drinking or culinary  purposes;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-52.1.list5.d">
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <p>any other matter which is necessary for carrying out all  of any of the provisions of this Act and the rules made  there- under.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-52.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>A bye- law made under sub- section (1) shall not have effect  until it has been confirmed by the Administrator and published in such  manner as he may direct.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-52.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Administrator, in confirming a bye- law, may make any  change therein which appears to him to be necessary.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-53">
                <num>53.</num>
                <heading>Penalty for infringement of rules or bye- laws.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-53.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>In making  any rule, the Administrator, and in making any bye- law, a District</p>
                    <p>Council, may direct that the breach of the same shall be punishable  with fine which may extend to one hundred rupees and in the case of a  continuing breach with a further fine which may extend to ten rupees  of every day during which the breach is continued after the offender  has been convicted of such breach.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-53.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>In default of payment of any fine, the defaulter shall be  punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to fifteen  days.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
            </chapter>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
