<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1838/5/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1838/5"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Bengal Bonded Warehouse Association Act, 1838"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1838/5/eng@1838-03-14/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1838/5/eng@1838-03-14"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1838-03-14" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1838/5/eng@1838-03-14/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1838/5/eng@1838-03-14"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Bengal Bonded Warehouse Association Act, 1838</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 5 OF 1838</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 14th March, 1838.]</docDate>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Incorporation.-- It is hereby enacted, that the persons whose  names appear in the Schedule No. 1, hereunto annexed, shall, from the</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14th">
        <num>14th.</num>
        <heading>day of March, 1838, form a corporate body for the Warehousing of</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14th.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Goods, either in bond or otherwise, by the name of the Bengal Bonded</p>
            <p>Warehouse Association.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Power to sue and be sued, and to acquire, hold and transfer  property.--  The said Association shall sue and be sued by its  corporate name, and shall use such common seal as the Directors of the  said Association shall from time to time appoint, and may acquire may  hold absolutely, may hold by way of pledge, and may transfer, any  description of property whatever.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Capital Stock and shares.--  The sum of Rs. 10, 00, 000  subscribed for the purpose of the said Association by the Persons  hereby incorporated, shall be the Capital Stock of the said</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Association, and shall be divided into 2, 000 shares of 500 Rupees  each, and every one of the persons hereby incorporated shall have one  share of such Capital Stock for every 500 Rupees which such person  shall have subscribed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Registering of names of proprietors. Register to be open to  inspection.--  The Directors of the said Association shall cause  the names, additions, and places of residence of the proprietors of  shares in the said Capital Stock, and the number of shares held by  each proprietor, to be registered in a book, and the said shares shall  in such book be numbered, beginning from No. 1, and such book shall  be kept at the office of the said Association, and shall there be open  to the inspection of all persons during the usual hours of business.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Share- certificates.--  A certificate signed by three</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Directors of the said Association shall be delivered to every  proprietor of the said Capital Stock, and  it shall be at the  option of every proprietor of several shares to receive one  certificate for all the shares of such proprietor, or one certificate  for each of those shares or several certificates, each of which may be  for any number of those shares.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Transfer of shares.--  Any share or shares of the said</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Capital Stock may be transferred by endorsement made on the  certificate for such share or shares by the proprietor of such share  or shares, or by the Attorney of such proprietor duly authorized  thereunto; provided always, that such endorsement shall specify the  name of the party to whom the transfer is made; and provided also that  no such endorsement shall be effectual to transfer any such share or  shares until such endorsement shall have been registered in a Register  to be kept for that purpose at the office of the said Association, and  until a note of such registration, and of the date thereof, shall have  been made on the back of the indorsed certificate under the hand of an  officer appointed for that purpose by the Directors of the said</p>
            <p>Association.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Proprietors of shares to be members of Association.--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every proprietor of a share of the said Capital Stock, who shall cease  to be a proprietor of such Stock, shall cease to be a member of the  corporation created by this Act; and  every person who shall  become a proprietor of the said Capital Stock, shall become a member  of the corporation created by this Act; and shall, in respect of his  share or shares of the said Capital Stock, be under the same  liabilities under which an original proprietor of the said Capital</p>
            <p>Stock would be.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>First Directors of Association.--  The business of the  said Association shall be managed by six Directors, and Francis</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Macnaghten, Joseph Walker, Jasper Ouseley, Richard Howe Cockerell,</p>
            <p>Alexander Colvin, Joseph Willis, and James Church, Esquires, shall be  the first Directors of the said Association.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Removal and election of Directors.--  Every Director of  the said Association may be removed by a general meeting of the  proprietors, and every future Director of the said Association shall  be elected by such a general meeting.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Directors to go out by rotation.--  A rotation among the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Directors of the said Association shall be settled by lot, so that two  of the said Directors may go out of office on the Monday following the</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15th">
        <num>15th.</num>
        <heading>day of May in every year, and  on the Monday following the</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15th">
        <num>15th.</num>
        <heading>day of May, in every year, a general meeting of proprietors shall  be held, at which two Directors shall be chosen, and that no Director  going out by such rotation shall be capable of being re- elected, till  the Monday after the 15th of May in the year next following.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Election of successor, when Director ceases to be so,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>otherwise than by rotation.--  If any Director of the said</p>
            <p>Association shall cease to be a Director, otherwise than by the  operation of the rule of rotation aforesaid, the Directors of the said</p>
            <p>Association shall, with all convenient speed after such public notice  as is hereinafter directed, call an extraordinary general meeting of  the proprietors for the purpose of choosing a successor and such  successor shall come into the same place in the rotation aforesaid in  which the Director whom he has succeeded was.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Directors to be residents of Bengal Presidency.--  No  person shall be capable of being a Director of the said Association,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>unless he be resident within the Territories subject to the Presidency  of Fort William in Bengal.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Adjournment of ordinary meeting.--  Any ordinary general  meetings of the said Association may adjourn itself to a future day,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>and may, on the day to which it shall have so adjourned itself, resume  its proceedings, and transact any business which it would have been  competent to transact on the day when it originally assembled.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Extraordinary general meetings.--  Extraordinary general  meetings of the said Association shall be held according to such rules  as may be made for that purpose, in the Bye- laws of the said</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Association; provided always, that no such extraordinary general  meeting shall be held without a previous notice of not less than  fourteen days, which notice shall be published in not less than two  newspapers printed at Calcutta.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Voting at general meetings. Qualification for voting.--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>At General Meetings of the Proprietors, every election and question  shall be decided by a majority of votes; and  no proprietor shall  be allowed to vote unless he be possessed of two or more shares of the</p>
            <p>Capital Stock of the said Association, which shares shall have been  registered in his name not less than three calendar months before.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Number of votes to which proprietors are entitled.-  At  such general meetings, no proprietor shall have more than eight votes,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>and  the proprietors shall vote according to the following scale</p>
            <p>:-</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Shares shall entitle to 1 vote.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>"""" 2 votes.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>"""" 3"</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>"""" 4"</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Shares shall entitle to 6 votes.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-35">
        <num>35.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-35.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>,,,,,,,, 7"</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-50">
        <num>50.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-50.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>,,,,,,,, 8"</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Votes of joint proprietors of shares.--  If more persons  than one, being partners in trade, shall be joint proprietors of two  or more shares of the said Capital Stock, and shall agree to give a  joint vote or joint votes, such joint vote or joint votes, shall be  received in all respects as the vote or votes of a single proprietor  would be received.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Voting by proxy.--  Every proprietor entitled to vote at  any general meeting may give a proxy in writing, general or special,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>limited or unlimited, and singed by himself or by his attorney duly  authorized thereunto, to any other proprietor; and 2 the proprietor to  whom the proxy is given, may vote on behalf of the proprietor who had  given the proxy, according to the terms of such proxy.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Authority of Directors.--  The Directors of the said</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Association shall have authority to expend the money of the said</p>
            <p>Association for the purpose of purchasing and erecting warehouses, and  of warehousing and bonding goods therein, and to make and fulfil  contracts for the said purpose, and to appoint and remove such  servants as may be necessary for the said purpose and generally to  manage all the concerns of the said Association, subject to such rules  as may be laid down in the Bye- laws of the said Association, and to  keep the seal of the said Association, and to use the said seal in the  affairs of the said Association, provided always, that the said seal  shall never be affixed to any instrument except in the presence and by  the consent of three Directors, who shall sign their names on every  such instrument in token of their presence and consent.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Calls for share money.--  The Directors of the said</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Association shall have authority to call on the proprietors to pay  such instalment or instalments as shall, together with the instalments  already paid, amount to a sum not exceeding 50 per cent. on each  share; and 2 no further call shall be made, except in consequence of a  vote of a general meeting of the proprietors, authorising such further  call; provided always that no proprietor shall be called upon to pay  more in proportion to his share in the Capital Stock than any other  proprietor.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Interest to run on each call. Application of dividend in  satisfaction of unpaid calls.--  If any proprietor shall not pay  any instalment which he is lawfully called upon to pay, in the manner  described in the last section, on the day appointed for such payment,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>the said Association shall have a claim against such proprietor for  interest on the deficient sum, after the rate of 10 per cent. per  annum; and  it shall be lawful for the Directors of the said</p>
            <p>Association to apply, in satisfaction of such instalment and of such  interest, any dividend due to such proprietor, placing every dividend  so applied to the credit of such proprietor with the said Association.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Power to refuse to register transfer by defaulting  proprietor. Power to sell shares to satisfy calls, and issue fresh  certificates.--  It shall be lawful for the Directors of the said</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Association to refuse to register the transfer of any share belonging  to any proprietor who shall not have paid such instalment and interest  as aforesaid; and  in case such instalment and interest shall not  be paid within two months after notice to pay the same has been given  by lawful for the said Directors to such proprietor, or to his  attorney or attorneys duly authorised, it shall be lawful for the said</p>
            <p>Directors to sell by public sale the share or shares of such  proprietor, to such an extent as may be sufficient to satisfy such  instalment and interest, and to grant, upon such sale, a new  certificate or new certificates to the purchaser of such share or  shares whereupon the former certificate or certificates for such share  or shares shall become void, and if there by any surplus after such  instalment and interest have been satisfied, such surplus shall be  paid on demand to the proprietor of such share or shares, and shall,</p>
            <p>till demand, be credited in the books of the said Association to such  proprietor, but no interest shall run thereon.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Extension of Act No. 25 of 1836 to warehouse of Association.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>-  All the provisions of 2 Act No. XXV of 1836, of the Governor</p>
            <p>General of India in Council, relating to private licensed Warehouses,</p>
            <p>shall be applicable to all Warehouses wherein the said Association  shall receive bonded Goods.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Power to give general security for payment of import and  export duties.--  It shall be lawful for the said Association to  give general security, by bond, under the seal of the said</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Association, for payment of the full duties of importation on Goods,</p>
            <p>lodged in any Warehouse of the said Association, or for the due  exportation of such Goods; and if the said Association shall give such  bond, no security shall be required from any other party to the same  effect.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Rates for warehousing.--  The Directors of the said</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Association shall, from time to time, fix the rates at which the said</p>
            <p>Association will warehouse Goods and receive Goods at its Wharfs, and    a table of such rates shall be placed at every Warehouse and</p>
            <p>Wharf of the said Association.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28">
        <num>28.</num>
        <heading>Certificates of deposit, transferable by endorsement.--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>As often as any Goods are lodged in any Warehouse of the said</p>
            <p>Association, the Secretary of the said Association shall deliver a  warrant signed by him as such Secretary, to the person lodging such</p>
            <p>Goods, which warrant shall be, as nearly as possible, in the form set  forth in Schedule II annexed to this Act, and such warrant shall be  transferable by endorsement, and shall entitle any person to whom it  may have been so transferred by endorsement, to receive the Goods  specified in such warrant on the same terms on which the person who  originally lodged those Goods would have been entitled to receive the  same.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29">
        <num>29.</num>
        <heading>Suits against Association.--  All suits brought against  the said Association shall be brought in the Supreme Court of</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-29.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Judicature at Fort William in Bengal and not elsewhere.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-30">
        <num>30.</num>
        <heading>Joint Stock of Association.--  All the Joint Stock of the  said Association of what kind or description soever, and all the Land,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-30.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Warehouses, Messuages, Tenements, Hereditaments, Premises and Property  acquired therewith, of which the said Association shall become in any  manner possessed, entitled to, or interested in, shall be held and  enjoyed by the Proprietors thereof, and their successors respectively,</p>
            <p>as Personal Estate, or as in the nature of Chattel Interests, and not  as, or in the nature of, Real Estate.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-31">
        <num>31.</num>
        <heading>Individual members not to be liable.--  In order to  define the liability of Proprietors or shares, and to save harmless  themselves and their respective Heirs, Executors, Administrators,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-31.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Representatives and Assigns, no Proprietor, his Heirs, Executors,</p>
            <p>Administrators, Representatives or Assigns, shall be personally liable  to any person or persons whatsoever by reason of being a Proprietor in  any event, or for or on account of any acts, deeds, contracts or  liabilities of the said Association, or of the Directors or Secretary  thereof respectively, or under or by virtue of any judgment or decree  in any action or suit, but  the party or parties having any legal  or equitable demand or claim for or on the account last aforesaid, or  having obtained such judgment or decree as last aforesaid, shall and  may only recover the amount of such demand, claim, judgment or decree  from and out of or to the whole extent of the paid up Capital,</p>
            <p>accumulated Funds, Lands, Messuages, Tenements, Hereditaments and</p>
            <p>Premises whatsoever and wheresoever, which may at the time belong to  the said Association, or to which they may at the time be entitled.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-33">
        <num>33.</num>
        <heading>Increase of Capital Stock.--  It shall be lawful for the  said Association to increase its Capital Stock; provided always that  no such increase shall take place unless it be authorized by a vote of  two extraordinary general meetings of Proprietors specially convened  for that purpose, of which meetings the second shall be held not less  than three calendar months after the first.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-34">
        <num>34.</num>
        <heading>Option to original proprietors to subscribe in first  instance.--  In the event of such increase, the Proprietors of  the original Stock shall not be bound to subscribe, but shall in the  first instance have the option of subscribing for the increased</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-34.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Capital Stock in proportion to the share which each has of the  original Capital Stock; and so much of the additional Capital Stock as  shall not be subscribed for by the said Proprietors of the original  stock, within one year after the passing of the final resolution for  the increase, shall be open to the public, and be sold, for the  benefit of the said Association, by public sale.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-35">
        <num>35.</num>
        <heading>Provisions of Act to apply to additional Stock.--  All  the rules laid down in this Act respecting the original Capital Stock  of the said Association, shall be applicable to any additional Stock  which may be subscribed in the manner hereinbefore described.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-36">
        <num>36.</num>
        <heading>East India Company to have right of pre- emption.--  If  the said Association shall be desirous to dispose of any premises  purchased by the said Association from the East India Company, the  said East India Company shall have the right of pre- emption, and the  price shall be fixed by two appraisers, the one named on the part of  the said East India Company, and the other by the Directors of the  said Association; and if the said appraisers shall not agree on a  price, the price shall be fixed by an umpire named by the said  appraisers.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-38">
        <num>38.</num>
        <heading>Dissolution of Association by resolution of proprietors.-- 1</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-38.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The said Association may at any time be dissolved by a resolution  to that effect of two- thirds in number and value of the proprietors  qualified to vote at two successive extraordinary meetings specially  called for the purpose of taking into consideration the expediency of  such dissolution; provided that not less than three months shall have  elapsed between the first and second of such two extraordinary  meetings.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-39">
        <num>39.</num>
        <heading>Division of property on dissolution.--  Whenever the  dissolution of the said Association shall be ordered either by the 2</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-39.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Central Government, or by a vote of the said Association, the</p>
            <p>Directors of the said Association shall cause all the property of the  said Association to be converted into money, and shall divide whatever  surplus may remain after satisfying the debts of the said Association  among the proprietors in proportion to the shares which the  proprietors have in the Capital Stock of the said Association; and  after such distribution the said Association shall forthwith be  dissolved.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
