<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1885/18/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1885/18"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Land Acquisition (Mines) Act, 1885"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1885/18/eng@1885-10-16/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1885/18/eng@1885-10-16"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1885-10-16" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1885/18/eng@1885-10-16/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1885/18/eng@1885-10-16"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Land Acquisition (Mines) Act, 1885</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 16th October, 1885.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>ACT NO. 18 OF</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for cases in which Mines or Minerals are situate  under land which it is desired to acquire under the Land Acquisition</p>
        <p>Act, 1870.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and local extent.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Land Acquisition (Mines) Act, 1885; and</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India except the territories  which, immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised in</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <part id="part-B">
        <num>B</num>
        <heading>States.</heading>
        <subsection id="part-B.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It applies in the first instance to the territories which,</p>
            <p>immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised in the</p>
            <p>States of Madras, Andhra, West Bengal, Bihar, Assam and Orissa; but  any State Government may, from time to time, by notification in the</p>
            <p>Official Gazette, bring this Act into force in the whole or any  specified part of the territories to which this Act extends, under its  administration.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Saving for mineral rights of the Government. Except as  expressly provided by this Act, nothing in this Act shall affect the  right of  the  Government]] to any mines or minerals.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Declaration that mines are not needed.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When the    appropriate Government] makes a declaration under section 6 of the</p>
              <p>Land Acquisition Act, 1870  (10 of 1870.), that land is needed for a  public purpose or for a Company, it may, if it thinks fit, insert in  the declaration a statement that the mines of coal, iron- stone, slate  or other minerals lying under the land or any particular portion of  the land, except only such parts of the mines or minerals as it may be  necessary to dig or carry away or use in the construction of the</p>
              <p>work for the purpose of which the land is being acquired, are not  needed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When a statement as aforesaid has not been inserted in the  declaration made in respect of any land under section 6 of the Land</p>
              <blockList id="section-3.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Acquisition Act, 1870  (10 of 1870), and the Collector is of  opinion that the provisions of this Act ought to be applied to the  land, he may abstain from tendering compensation under section 11 of  the said Land Acquisition Act in respect of the mines, and may--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.2.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>when he makes an award under section 14  of that Act,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.2.list4">
                <listIntroduction>insert such a statement in his award;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.2.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>when he makes a reference to the Court under section 15    of that Act, insert such a statement in his reference; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.2.list4.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>when he takes possession of the land under section 17   of that Act, publish such a statement in such manner as  the  appropriate Government] may, from time to time,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>proscribe.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any such statement is inserted in the declaration, award  or reference, or published as aforesaid, the mines of coal, iron-</p>
              <p>stone, slate or other minerals under the land or portion of the land  specified in the statement, except as aforesaid, shall not vest in    the  Government]] when the land so vests under the said Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Notice to be given before working mines lying under land. If  the person for the time being immediately entitled to work or get any  mines or minerals lying under any land so acquired is desirous of  working or getting the same, he shall give the  appropriate</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government] notice in writing of his intention so to do sixty days  before the commencement of working.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Power to prevent or restrict working.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>At any time or times  after the receipt of a notice under the last foregoing section and  whether before or after the expiration of the said period of sixty  days, the  appropriate Government] may cause the mines or minerals  to be inspected by a person appointed by it for the purpose; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If it appears to the  appropriate Government] that the  working or getting of the mines or minerals, or any part thereof, is  likely to cause damage to the surface of the land or any works  thereon, the</p>
              <blockList id="section-5.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>appropriate Government] may publish  a declaration of its  willingness, either--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.2.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to pay compensation for the mines or minerals still  unworked or ungotten, or that part thereof, to all  persons having an interest in the same; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-5.2.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>to pay compensation to all such persons in consideration  of those mines or minerals, or that part thereof, being  worked or gotten in such manner and subject to such  restrictions as the  appropriate Government] may in  its declaration specify.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the declaration mentioned in case (a) is made, then those  mines or minerals, or that part thereof, shall not thereafter be  worked or gotten by any person.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the declaration mentioned in case (b) is made, then those  mines or minerals, or that part thereof, shall not thereafter be  worked or gotten by any person save in the manner and subject to the  restrictions specified by the  appropriate Government.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every declaration made under this section shall be  published in such manner as the  appropriate Government] may  direct.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Mode of determining persons interested and amount of  compensation. When the working or getting of any mines or minerals has  been prevented or restricted under section 5, the persons interested  in those mines or minerals and the amounts of compensation payable to  them respectively shall, subject to all necessary modifications, be  ascertained in the manner provided by the Land Acquisition Act, 1870</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>(10 of 1870.) , for ascertaining the persons interested in the land  to be acquired under that Act, and the amounts of compensation payable  to them, respectively.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>If appropriate Government does not offer to pay compensation,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>mines may be worked in a proper manner.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If before the expiration  of the said sixty days the  appropriate Government] does not publish  a declaration as provided in section 5, the owner, lessee or occupier  of the mines may, unless and until such a declaration is subsequently  made, work the mines or any part thereof in a manner proper and  necessary for the beneficial working thereof, and according to the  usual manner of working such mines in the local area where the same  are situate.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any damage or obstruction is caused to the surface of the  land or any works thereon by improper working of the mines, the owner,</p>
              <p>lessee or occupier of the mines shall at once, at his own expense,</p>
              <p>repair the damage or remove the obstruction, as the case may require.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the repair or removal is not at once effected, or, if the    appropriate Government] so thinks fit, without writing for the same  to be effected by the owner, lessee or occupier, the  appropriate</p>
              <p>Government] may execute the same and recover from the owner, lessee or  occupier the expense occasioned thereby.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Mining communications. If the working of any mines is  prevented or restricted under section 5, the respective owners,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>lessees and occupiers of the mines, if their mines extend so as to lie  on both sides of the mines the working of which is prevented or  restricted, may cut and make such and so many airways, headways,</p>
              <p>gateways or water- levels through the mines, measures or strata, the  working whereof is prevented or restricted, as may be requisite to  enable them to ventilate, drain and work their said mines; but no such  airway, headway, gateway or water- level shall be of greater dimensions  or section than may be prescribed by the  appropriate Government] in  this behalf, and, where no dimensions are so prescribed, not greater  than eight feet wide and eight feet high, nor shall the same be cut or  made upon any part of the surface or works, or so as to injure the  same, or to interfere with the use thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Appropriate Government to pay compensation for injury done to  mines; The  appropriate Government] shall, from time to time, pay to  the owner, lessee or occupier of any such mines extending so as to lie  on both sides of the mines, the working of which is prevented or  restricted, all such additional expenses and losses as may be incurred  by him by reason of the severance of the lands lying over those mines  or of the continuous working of those mines being interrupted as  aforesaid, or by reason of the same being worked in such manner and  under such restrictions as not to prejudice or injure the surface or  works, and for any minerals not acquired by the  appropriate</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government] which cannot be obtained by reason of the action taken  under the foregoing sections; and if any dispute or question arises  between the  appropriate Government] and the owner, lessee or  occupier as aforesaid, touching the amount of those losses or  expenses, the same shall be settled as nearly as may be in the manner  provided for the settlement of questions touching the amount of  compensation payable under the Land Acquisition Act, 1870  (10 of</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1870">
          <num>1870.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1870.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>and also for injury arising from any airway or other work. If  any loss or damage is sustained by the owner or occupier of the lands  lying over any such mines, the working whereof has been so prevented  or restricted as aforesaid (and not being the owner, lessee or   occupier of those mines), by reason of the making of any such airway  or other works as aforesaid, which or any like work it</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>would not have been necessary to make but for the working of the mines  having been so prevented or restricted as aforesaid, the    appropriate Government] shall pay full compensation to that owner  or occupier of the surface lands for the loss or damage so sustained  by him.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Power to officer of appropriate Government to enter and  inspect the working of mines. For better ascertaining whether any  mines lying under land acquired in accordance with the provisions of  this Act are being worked, or have been worked, or are likely to be  worked so as to damage the land or the works thereon, an officer  appointed for this purpose by the  appropriate Government] may,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>after giving twenty- four hours' notice II writing, enter into and  return from any such mines or the works connected therewith; and for  that purpose the officer so appointed may make use of any apparatus or  machinery belonging to the owner, lessee or occupier of the mines, and  use all necessary means for discovering the distance from any part of  the land acquired to the parts of the mines which have been, are  being, or are about to be worked.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Penalty for refusal to allow inspection. If any owner, lessee  or occupier of any such mines or works refuses to allow any officer  appointed by the  appropriate Government] for that purpose to enter  into and inspect any such mines or works in manner aforesaid, he shall  be punished with fines which may extend to two hundred rupees.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>If mines worked contrary to provisions of this Act,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>appropriate Government may require means to be adopted for safety of  land acquired. If it appears that any such mines have been worked  contrary to the provisions of this Act, the  appropriate Government]</p>
              <p>may, if it thinks fit, give notice to the owner, lessee or occupier  thereof to construct such works and to adopt such means as may be  necessary or proper for making safe the land acquired, and the works  thereon, and preventing injury thereto; and if, after such notice, any  such owner, lessee or occupier does not forthwith proceed to construct  the works necessary for making safe the land acquired and the works  thereon, the  appropriate Government] may itself construct the works  and recover the expense thereof from the owner, lessee or occupier.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Construction of Act when land acquired has been transferred  to a local authority or Company. When a statement under section 3 has  been made regarding any land, and the land has been acquired by the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government, and has been transferred to, or has vested by operation of  law, in a local authority or Company, then sections 4 to 13, both  inclusive, shall be read as if for the words" the  appropriate</p>
              <p>Government]", wherever they occur in those sections,  except in  section 5, sub- section (5) and</p>
              <p>section 8], the words" the local authority or Company, as the case may  be, which has acquired the land," were substituted.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Pending cases. Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1937</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>(20 of 1937), s. 3 and Sch., II.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Definition of local authority and Company. In this Act--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-16.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" local authority" means any municipal committee,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>district board, body of port commissioners or other  authority legally entitled to, or entrusted by the</p>
              <blockList id="section-16.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Government with, the control or management of any  municipal or local fund; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" Company" means a company registered under any of the  enactments relating to Companies from time to time in  force in  India], or formed in pursuance of an Act of  parliament  of the United Kingdom] or by Royal</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-16.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Charter or Letters Patent;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list5.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" appropriate Government" means in relation to  acquisition of land for the purposes of the Union, the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Central Government, and, in relation to acquisition of  land for any other purposes, the State Government.]</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>This Act to be read with Land Acquisition Act, 1870. This Act  shall, for the purposes of all enactments for the time being in force,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>be read with and taken as part of the Land Acquisition Act 1870,  (10   of 1870).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
