<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1915/16/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1915/16"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Banaras Hindu University Act, 1915"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1915/16/eng@1915-10-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1915/16/eng@1915-10-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1915-10-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1915/16/eng@1915-10-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1915/16/eng@1915-10-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-11-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Banaras] Hindu University Act, 1915</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 16 OF 1915</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 1st October, 1915.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to establish and incorporate a teaching and residential Hindu</p>
        <p>University at  Banaras].</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to establish and incorporate a teaching  and residential Hindu University at  Banaras], and to dissolve the</p>
        <p>Hindu University Society, a Society registered under the Societies</p>
        <p>Registration Act, 1860 (21 of 1860), and to transfer to, and vest in,</p>
        <p>the said University all property and rights now vested in the said</p>
        <p>Society; It is hereby enacted as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Banaras] Hindu University Act, 1915.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such  date as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" Academic Council" means the Academic Council of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" College" means a college or teaching institution</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>(other than a secondary, primary or infant school or   pathasala) maintained, by, or admitted to the  privileges of, the University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" Court" means the University Court;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>" Executive Council" means the University Executive</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6">
              <listIntroduction>Council;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>" Faculty" means a Faculty of the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>" Ordinances" means the Ordinances of the University for  the time being in force;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>" Regulations" means the Regulations of the University  for the time being in force;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>" Statutes" means the Statutes of the University for the  time being in force;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>" Teacher" means a salaried professor, reader, lecturer  or tutor who imparts instruction in a Faculty of, or in  a college maintained by, the University and includes  any other person who is declared to be a teacher by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list8">
              <listIntroduction>Academic Council;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list8.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>" University" means the Banaras Hindu University.]</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Incorporation.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chancellor and the Vice- Chancellor  and the members of the Court, the Executive Council and the Academic</p>
            <p>Council, for the time being, shall be a body corporate by the name of  the Banaras Hindu University.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The University shall have perpetual succession and a common  seal, and shall sue, and be sued, by the name first aforesaid.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>University open to all classes, castes and creeds. The</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>University shall be open to persons of either sex and of whatever  race, creed, caste or class, and it shall not be lawful for the</p>
            <p>University to adopt or impose on any person any test whatsoever of  religious belief or profession in order to entitle him to be admitted  therein, as a teacher or student, or to hold any office therein, or to  graduate thereat, or to enjoy or exercise any privilege thereof,</p>
            <p>except in respect of any particular benefaction accepted by the</p>
            <p>University, where such test is made a condition thereof by any  testamentary or other instrument creating such benefaction:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing in this section shall be deemed to prevent  religious instruction being given in the manner prescribed by the</p>
            <p>Ordinances  to those who, or, in the case of minors, whose parents  or guardians, have given their consent thereto in writing.].</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4A">
        <num>4A.</num>
        <heading>Powers of the University. The University shall have the  following powers, namely:-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to provide for instruction in such branches of learning  as the University may think fit, and to make provision  for research and for the advancement and dissemination  of knowledge;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to promote the study of religion, literature,</p>
            <p>history, science and art of Vedic, Hindu, Buddhist,</p>
            <p>Jain, Islamic. Sikh, Christian, Zoroastrian and other  civilisations and cultures;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4A.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>to hold examinations and to grant diplomas and  certificates, and confer degrees and other academic  distinctions to and on persons--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4A.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>who shall have pursued a course of study in  the University or in a college and passed the  examination or who shall have carried on research work  in the manner prescribed by the Ordinances, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4A.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>who are teachers of the University or any  college under conditions laid down in the Statutes or  the Ordinances and shall have passed the examinations  of the University under like conditions, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4A.3.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>who, being women, shall have pursued a course  of private study in subjects provided for by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Ordinances and shall have passed the examinations of  the University in their subjects under conditions laid  down in the Ordinances;]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to confer honorary degrees or other distinctions in the  manner laid down in the Statutes;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to grant such diplomas  or certificates] to, and to  provide such lectures and instruction for, persons not  being members of the University as the University may  determine;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.5A">
          <num>(5A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to withdraw degrees, diplomas, certificates and  other academic distinctions;]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to co- operate with other Universities and authorities  in such manner and for such purposes as the University  may determine;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to institute professorships, readerships, lecturerships  and other teaching posts required by the University and  to appoint persons to such professorships, readerships,</p>
            <p>lecturerships and other posts;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to institute and award fellowships (including   travelling fellowships) scholarships, studentships,</p>
            <p>exhibitions and prizes in accordance with the Statutes  and the Ordinances;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to institute and maintain halls and hostels and to  recognise places of residence for students of the</p>
            <p>University;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.9A">
          <num>(9A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to institute, establish, maintain, reconstitute,</p>
            <p>amalgamate, divide or abolish departments, faculties or  colleges</p>
            <p>and carry out inspection thereof and inquiry in  relation thereto;]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.10">
          <num>(10)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to demand and receive such fees and other charges as  may be prescribed by the Ordinances;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to supervise and control the residence and to regulate  the discipline of students of the University, and to  make arrangements for promoting their health  and  welfare];</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.12">
          <num>(12)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to make special arrangements in respect of the  residence, discipline, and teaching of women students;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.12A">
          <num>(12A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to regulate and enforce discipline among salaried  officers, teachers and other employees of the</p>
            <p>University in accordance with the Statutes and</p>
            <p>Ordinances;]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.13">
          <num>(13)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to create administrative, ministerial and other  necessary posts and to make appointments thereto;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.13A">
          <num>(13A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to acquire, hold, manage and dispose of property,</p>
            <p>movable or immovable, including trust or endowed  property, for the purposes of the University;]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.13B">
          <num>(13B)</num>
          <content>
            <p>with the approval of the Central Government, to borrow  on the security of the property of the University,</p>
            <p>money for the purpose of the University;]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.14">
          <num>(14)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to do all such other acts and things, whether  incidental to the powers aforesaid or not, as may be  requisite in order to further the objects of the</p>
            <p>University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Visitor.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The President of India shall be the Visitor of  the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Visitor shall have the right to cause an inspection to be  made, by such person or persons as he may direct, of the University,</p>
            <p>its buildings, laboratories and equipment  of any college] and of  any institution maintained by the University, and also of the  examinations, teaching and other work conducted or done by the</p>
            <p>University and to cause an inquiry to be made in like manner in  respect of any matter connected with the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Visitor shall in every case give notice to the University  of his intention to cause an inspection or inquiry to be made, and the</p>
            <p>University shall be entitled to appoint a representative who shall  have the right to be present and be heard at such inspection or  inquiry.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Visitor may address the Vice- Chancellor with reference to  the result of such inspection and inquiry, and the Vice- Chancellor</p>
            <p>shall communicate to the Executive Council the views of the Visitor  with such advice as the Visitor may offer upon the action to be taken  thereon.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Executive Council shall communicate through the Vice</p>
            <p>Chancellor to the Visitor such action, if any, as it is proposed to  take or has been taken upon the result of such inspection or inquiry.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the Executive Council does not, within a reasonable  time, take action to the satisfaction of the Visitor, the Visitor may,</p>
            <p>after considering any explanation furnished or representation made by  the Executive Council, issue such directions as he may think fit and  the Executive Council shall be bound to comply with such directions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Without prejudice to the foregoing provisions of this section  the Visitor may, by order in writing, annul any proceeding of the</p>
            <p>University which is not in conformity with this Act, the Statutes or  the Ordinances:</p>
            <p>Provided that before making any such order, he shall call upon  the University to show cause why such an order should not be made and  if any cause is shown within a reasonable time, shall consider the  same.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Officers of the University. The following shall be the  officers of the University, namely:-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the Chancellor,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the Vice- Chancellor,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the Rector,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the Registrar,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list0.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the Finance Officer,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list0.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the Deans of Faculties,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list0.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the Dean of Students,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list0.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the Librarian,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list0.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the Chief Proctor,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list0.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>such other persons in the service of the University as  may be declared by the Statutes to be the officers of  the University.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Chancellor.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chancellor shall be elected by the Court  and shall hold office for a term of three years:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Chancellor shall, notwithstanding the  expiration of his term, continue to hold his office until the election  of his successor.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the office of the Chancellor becomes vacant, the functions  of his office shall, until some person is elected under sub- section</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to the vacant office, be performed by the Vice- Chancellor.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7A">
        <num>7A.</num>
        <heading>Powers of Chancellor.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chancellor shall, by virtue of  his office, be the Head of the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chancellor shall, if present, preside at convocation of  the University for conferring degrees and at all meetings of the</p>
            <p>Court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7B">
        <num>7B.</num>
        <heading>Vice- Chancellor.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7B.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Vice- Chancellor shall be  appointed by the Visitor on the recommendation of a Selection</p>
            <p>Committee constituted by the Visitor for the purpose:</p>
            <p>Provided that, if the Visitor does not approve of such  recommendation, he may call for one or more fresh recommendations.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7B.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Vice- Chancellor shall be a whole- time salaried officer of  the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7B.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Vice- Chancellor shall hold office for a term of  three  years] from the date on which he enters upon his office and shall, on  the expiration of his term of office, be  eligible for re-</p>
            <p>appointment to that office for a second term]:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Vice- Chancellor shall, notwithstanding the  expiration of his term, continue to hold his office until his  successor is appointed and enters upon his office.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7B.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The emoluments and other terms and conditions of service of  the Vice- Chancellor shall be prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7B.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the office of the Vice- Chancellor becomes vacant, the  functions of his office shall, until some person is appointed under  sub- section (1) to the vacant office, be performed by the Rector:</p>
            <p>Provided that if there is no Rector, the Registrar shall carry on  the current duties of the Vice- Chancellor and call a meeting of the</p>
            <p>Executive Council forthwith and take its directions for the carrying  on of the work of the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7C">
        <num>7C.</num>
        <heading>Powers and duties of Vice- Chancellor.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7C.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Vice- Chancellor  who shall be the principal executive and academic officer of the</p>
            <p>University, shall take rank next to the Chancellor and shall exercise  general supervision and control over the affairs of the University and  give effect to the decisions of its authorities.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7C.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Vice- Chancellor shall be the ex officio Chairman of the</p>
            <p>Executive Council, the Academic Council  and the Finance</p>
            <p>Committee and shall, in the absence of the Chancellor, preside at any  convocation of the University for conferring degrees and also at any  meeting of the Court; he shall be entitled to be present at and to  address any meeting of any authority or board or committee of the</p>
            <p>University but shall not be entitled to vote thereat unless he is a  member of such authority or board or committee.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7C.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be the duty of the Vice- Chancellor to see that the  provisions of this Act, the Statutes, the Ordinances and the</p>
            <p>Regulations are duly observed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7C.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Vice- Chancellor shall have power to convene meetings of  the Court, the Executive Council  and the Academic Council] and  shall perform all such acts as may be necessary to carry out the  provisions of this Act, the Statutes and the Ordinances.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7C.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If, in the opinion of the Vice- Chancellor, any emergency has  arisen which requires immediate action to be taken, the Vice-</p>
            <p>Chancellor shall take such action as he deems necessary and shall  report the same for approval at the next meeting to the authority  which, in the ordinary course, would have dealt with the matter:</p>
            <p>Provided that, if the action taken by the Vice- Chancellor is not  approved by the authority concerned, he may refer the matter to the</p>
            <p>Visitor, whose decision thereon shall be final:</p>
            <p>Provided further that, where any such action taken by the Vice-</p>
            <p>Chancellor affects any person in the service of the University, such  person shall be entitled to prefer, within thirty days from the date  on which he receives notice of such action, an appeal to the Executive</p>
            <p>Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7C.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Vice- Chancellor shall exercise such other powers as may  be prescribed by the Statutes, the Ordinances or the Regulations.]]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Powers and duties of officers, terms of office and filling of  casual vacancies. Subject to the provisions of this Act, the powers  and duties of  the other officers of the University], the term for  which they shall</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>hold office, and the filling up of casual vacancies in such offices,</p>
            <p>shall be provided for by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8A">
        <num>8A.</num>
        <heading>Authorities of the University. The following shall be the  authorities of the University, namely:-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8A.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-8A.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the Court,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8A.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the Executive Council,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8A.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the Academic Council,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8A.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8A.paragraph-0.list0.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the Finance Committee,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8A.paragraph-0.list0.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the Faculties,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8A.paragraph-0.list0.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>such other authorities as may be declared by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Statutes to be the authorities of the University.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Executive Council.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Executive Council shall, subject  to the control of the  visitor], be the executive body of the</p>
            <p>University and shall have charge of the management and administration  of the revenue and property of the University and the conduct of all  administrative affairs of the University not otherwise provided for.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Executive Council  shall exercise such other powers and perform such other duties as may  be conferred or imposed on it by the Statutes or the Ordinances.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Academic Council.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The  Academic Council] shall be the  academic body of the University and, subject to the Act, the Statutes  and  Ordinances.]</p>
            <p>shall have  charge of the organization of  study and research]</p>
            <p>in the University and the Colleges, the courses of study and the  examination  of students and the conferment of ordinary and  honorary degrees  and shall exercise such other powers and perform  such other duties as may be conferred or imposed on it by the Statutes  and Ordinances, and shall have the right to advise the Executive</p>
            <p>Council on all academic matters.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>The Standing Committee of the Academic Council. Rep. by the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Banaras Hindu University (Amendment) Act, 1969 (34 of 1969), s. 7</p>
            <p>(w. e. f. 5- 9- 1969).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12A">
        <num>12A.</num>
        <heading>Other authorities. Subject to the provisions of this Act,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>the functions, powers and duties of the other authorities of the</p>
            <p>University shall be provided for by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12B">
        <num>12B.</num>
        <heading>Disqualifications.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12B.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-12B.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A person shall be disqualified for  being chosen as, and for being, a member of any of the authorities of  the University--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12B.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>if he is of unsound mind or is a deaf- mute or suffers  from contagious leprosy;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12B.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>if he is an undischarged insolvent;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12B.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>if he has been convicted by a court of law of an  offence involving moral turpitude and sentenced in  respect thereof to imprisonment for not less than six  months.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12B.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any question arises as to whether a person is or had been  subjected to any of the disqualifications mentioned in sub- section (1)</p>
            <p>the question shall be referred for the decision of the Visitor and his  decision shall be final, and no suit or other proceeding shall lie in  any court of law against such decision.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Audit of accounts.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The accounts of the University  shall, once at least in every year and at intervals of not more than  fifteen months, be audited by the Comptroller and Auditor- General of</p>
            <p>India.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The accounts, when audited, shall be published in the</p>
            <p>Official Gazette and a copy of the accounts, together with the  auditor' s reports, shall be  submitted]  to the Visitor].</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Permanent reserve to cover recurring charges. The University  shall invest, and keep invested, in securities in which trust funds  may be invested, in accordance with the provisions of the law relating  to trusts in  India], a sum of  forty- five lakhs of rupees] as a  permanent endowment to meet the recurring charges of the University  other than charges in respect of scholarships, prizes and rewards:</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Provided that--</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>any Government securities, as defined by the Indian</p>
            <p>Securities Act,  1920 (10 of 1920),] which may be  held by the University shall, for the purpose of this  section, be reckoned at their face- value; and</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the aforesaid sum of forty- five lakhs of rupees  shall be reduced by such sum as, at the commencement of  the Banaras Hindu University (Amendment) Act, 1966</p>
            <p>(52 of 1966),] the Central Government shall, by order  in writing, declare to be the total capitalised value,</p>
            <blockList id="section-14.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>for the purposes of this section--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.2.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>of all permanent recurring grants of money  which have been made to the University  by any ruler  of any Indian State]; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.2.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>of the total income accruing from immovable  property which has been transferred to the University.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Maintenance and admission to privileges of Colleges.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The</p>
            <p>Central Hindu College,  Banaras], shall, from such  date as the</p>
            <p>Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette,</p>
            <p>appoint in this behalf, be deemed to be a College maintained by the</p>
            <p>University, and the University may found and maintain</p>
            <p>other colleges and  institutions including High Schools, within a  radius of fifteen miles from the main temple of the University] for  the purposes of carrying out instruction and research.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.1A">
          <num>(1A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The University may also found and maintain (within or   beyond the aforementioned limits) special centres and laboratories for  research in Humanities, Science and Technology, Education, Medicine  and other professional subjects and in other spheres of learning and  knowledge.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>With the approval of the  Academic Council] and the  sanction of the Visitor, and subject to the Statutes and</p>
            <p>Ordinances] the University may admit colleges and  institutions  including High Schools, within the aforementioned limits] to such  privileges of the University, subject to such conditions, as it thinks  fit:</p>
            <p>Provided that no new college or institution started after the  commencement of the Banaras Hindu University (Amendment) Act, 1966</p>
            <p>(52 of 1966), shall be admitted to any such privilege of the</p>
            <p>University.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Recognition of degrees. The degrees, diplomas, certificates  and other academic distinctions granted by the University shall be  recognised by  the Central and State Governments] to the same extent  and in the same manner as the corresponding degrees, diplomas,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>certificates and other academic distinctions granted by any other</p>
            <p>University incorporated by  a Central Act.].</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16A">
        <num>16A.</num>
        <heading>Pension Provident Fund or insurance scheme. The</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>University shall constitute for the benefit of its officers, teachers  and other  employees] such pension or provident fund  or provide  such insurance scheme] as it may deem fit in such manner and subject  to such conditions as may be prescribed by the Statutes.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16B">
        <num>16B.</num>
        <heading>Conditions of service of officers and teachers.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-16B.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every salaried officer and teacher of the University shall be  appointed under a written contract, which shall be lodged with the</p>
            <p>University and a copy of which shall be furnished to the officer or  teacher concerned.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16B.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any dispute arising out of a contract between the University  and any of its officers or teachers shall, at the request of the  officer or teacher concerned or at the instance of the University, be  referred to a Tribunal of Arbitration consisting of one member  appointed by the Executive Council, one member nominated by the  officer or the teacher concerned and an umpire appointed by the</p>
            <p>Visitor.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16B.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The decision of the Tribunal of Arbitration shall be final  and shall not be questioned in any court of law.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16B.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No suit or proceeding shall lie in any court of law in  respect of any matter which is required by sub- section (2) to be  referred to the Tribunal of Arbitration.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16B.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Tribunal of Arbitration shall have power to regulate its  own procedure.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16B.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing contained in any law for the time being in force  relating to arbitration shall apply to arbitrations under this  section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16C">
        <num>16C.</num>
        <heading>Proceedings not to be invalidated by vacancies etc. No act  or proceedings of any authority or board or committee of the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16C.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-16C.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>University shall be invalid merely by reason of--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-16C.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any vacancy in, or defect in the constitution thereof,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-16C.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-16C.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any defect in the election, nomination or appointment  of a person acting as a member thereof, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16C.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any irregularity in its procedure not affecting the  merits of the case.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16D">
        <num>16D.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16D.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any officer,</p>
            <p>teacher or other employee of the University for anything which is in  good faith done or intended to be done by him under this Act or the</p>
            <p>Statutes or the Ordinances or the Regulations.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Statutes.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the</p>
            <p>Statutes may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:-</p>
            <blockList id="section-17.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.1.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the constitution of the Court and the constitution,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>powers and duties of the other authorities of the</p>
            <blockList id="section-17.1.list6">
              <listIntroduction>University other than the powers and duties provided  for in this Act;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.1.list6.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the appointment by election, nomination or  otherwise] of members of the authorities of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-17.1.list8">
              <listIntroduction>University, their continuance in office, the filling of  vacancies of members thereof and all other matters  relating to the authorities;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.1.list8.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the appointment, powers and duties of the officers of  the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.1.list8.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the institution of degrees, diplomas, certificates and  other academic distinctions;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.1.list8.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the conferment of honorary degrees;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.1.list8.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the holding of convocations to confer degrees;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.1.list8.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the establishment, reconstitution, amalgamation,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>division or abolition of faculties, departments,</p>
            <blockList id="section-17.1.list11">
              <listIntroduction>hostels, colleges and institutions;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.1.list11.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the withdrawal of degrees, diplomas, certificates and  other academic distinctions;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.1.list11.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>conditions under which colleges and institutions  including High Schools may be admitted to the  privileges of the University and the withdrawal of such  privileges;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.1.list11.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>the institution of fellowships, scholarships,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-17.1.list13">
              <listIntroduction>studentships, medals and prizes;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.1.list13.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>the registration of graduates and the maintenance of a  register of registered graduates;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.1.list13.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>the classification and the manner of appointment of  teachers in the University and the colleges;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.1.list13.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>the constitution of a pension or provident fund and the  establishment of an insurance scheme for the benefit of  the officers, teachers and other employees of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-17.1.list15">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.1.list15.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>the meetings of the Court, the Executive Council, the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Academic Council,  the Finance Committee or the</p>
            <blockList id="section-17.1.list18">
              <listIntroduction>Faculties, the quorum at such meetings and the  procedure to be followed in the conduct of their  business;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.1.list18.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>the discipline of students;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.1.list18.p">
                <num>(p)</num>
                <p>all other matters which are to be or may be provided  for by the Statutes.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Statutes in force at the commencement of the Banaras</p>
            <p>Hindu University (Amendment) Act, 1966 (52 of 1966), shall be those set  out in the Schedule to this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the Executive Council may, from time to time, make new or  additional Statutes or may amend or repeal the Statutes.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every new Statute or addition to a Statute or any  amendment or repeal of a Statute shall require the previous approval  of the Visitor who may sanction or disallow it or remit it for further  consideration.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Ordinances</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-18.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Subject to the provisions of this Act and  the Statutes, the Ordinances may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the admission of students to the University and their  enrolment as such;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the courses of study to be laid down for all degrees,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-18.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>diplomas and certificates of the University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18.1.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the qualifications for admission to courses of study  for degrees, diplomas, certificates and other academic  distinctions and to examinations of the University and  the award of degrees, diplomas, certificates and other  academic distinctions;]</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.1.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the fees to be charged for courses of study in the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>University and for admission to the examinations,</p>
            <blockList id="section-18.1.list6">
              <listIntroduction>degrees and diplomas of the University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18.1.list6.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the conditions of the award of fellowships,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-18.1.list8">
              <listIntroduction>scholarships, studentships, exhibitions, medals and  prizes;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18.1.list8.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <blockList id="section-18.1.list8.f.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>the conduct of examinations, including the terms of  office and manner of appointment and the duties of  examining bodies, examiners and moderators;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-18.1.list8.f.list0.ff">
                    <num>(ff)</num>
                    <p>the remuneration and allowances to examiners,</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-18.1.list10">
              <listIntroduction>moderators and other persons engaged in the business of  the University;]</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18.1.list10.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the maintenance of discipline among the students of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-18.1.list12">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18.1.list12.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the conditions of residence of students at the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-18.1.list14">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18.1.list14.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the special arrangements, if any, which may be made for  the residence, discipline and teaching of women  students, and the prescribing for them of special  courses to study:</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.1.list14.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>the giving of religious instruction;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.1.list14.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>the emoluments and the terms and conditions of service  of  employees] of the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.1.list14.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>the management of colleges and other institutions  founded or maintained under sub- section (1) of section</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-15.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list1.ll">
                <num>(ll)</num>
                <p>the meetings of any board or committee that may be  set up under this Act or the Statutes, the quorum at  such meetings and the procedure to be followed in the  conduct of their business;]</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list1.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>the supervision and inspection of colleges and other  institutions admitted to privileges of the University  under sub- section (2) of section 15;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list1.mm">
                <num>(mm)</num>
                <p>the powers and duties of teachers and salaried  officers and the powers which may be delegated to them;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list1.mmm">
                <num>(mmm)</num>
                <p>the conditions and qualifications for the registration  of graduates;]</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list1.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>all other matters which by this Act or the Statutes are  to be or may be provided for by the Ordinances.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Regulations of the University as in force immediately  before the commencement of the Banaras Hindu University (Amendment)</p>
            <p>Act, 1951 (55 of 1951), shall be deemed to be the first Ordinances made  under this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The said Ordinances may be amended, repealed or added to at  any time by the Executive Council:</p>
            <blockList id="section-15.3.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that no Ordinance shall be made--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.3.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>regarding the recognition of examinations of other</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Universities and institutions as equivalent to the</p>
            <blockList id="section-15.3.list5">
              <listIntroduction>University examinations, or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.3.list5.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>affecting the conditions, mode of appointment or duties  of examiners or the conduct or standard of examinations  or of any course of study,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>unless a draft of such ordinance has been proposed by the Academic</p>
            <p>Council.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Executive Council shall not have power to amend any draft  proposed by the Academic Council under the provisions of sub- section</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>but may reject the proposal or return the draft to the Academic</p>
            <p>Council for reconsideration, either in whole or in part, together with  any amendments which the Executive Council may suggest.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the Executive Council has rejected the draft of an</p>
            <p>Ordinance proposed by the Academic Council, the Academic Council may  appeal to the Visitor who may pass such order thereon as he thinks  fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All Ordinances made by the Executive Council shall be  submitted, as soon may be, to the Visitor who may disallow any such</p>
            <p>Ordinance or remit it to the Executive Council for further  consideration.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Visitor may, by order, direct that the operation of any</p>
            <p>Ordinance shall be suspended until he has had an opportunity of  exercising his power of disallowance, and any order of suspension  under this sub- section shall cease to have effect on the expiration of  one month from the date of such order.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Power to make regulations.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-19.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The authorities of the</p>
            <blockList id="section-19.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>University may make Regulations consistent with this Act, the Statutes  and the Ordinances--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-19.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>laying down the procedure to be observed at their  meetings and the number of members required to form a  quorum;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.1.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>providing for all matters which by this Act, the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Statutes or the Ordinances are to be prescribed by</p>
            <blockList id="section-19.1.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Regulations; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-19.1.list5.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>providing for all matters solely concerning such  authorities or committees appointed by them and not  provided for by this Act, the Statutes or the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Ordinances.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every authority of the University shall make Regulations  providing for the giving of notice to the members of such authority of  the dates of meetings and of the business to be considered at meetings  and for the keeping of a record of the proceedings of meetings.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Executive Council may direct the amendment, in such  manner as it may specify, of any Regulation made under this section or  the annulment of any such Regulation:</p>
            <p>Provided that any authority of the University which is  dissatisfied with any such direction may, within two months of the  date of such direction, appeal to the  Visitor], whose decision  thereon shall be final.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19A">
        <num>19A.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of boards and committees. Where any  authority of the University is given power by this Act or by the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-19A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Statutes to appoint boards or committees, such board or committee  shall, unless there is some special provision to the contrary, consist  of members of the authority concerned and of such other persons (if   any) as the authority in each case may think fit.]]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Dissolution and transfer of property of the Hindu University</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Society.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-20.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>From the commencement of this Act, the Hindu University</p>
            <p>Society shall be dissolved, and all property, movable and immovable,</p>
            <p>and all rights, powers and privileges of the Hindu University society  which, immediately before the commencement of this Act, belong to, or  were vested in, the said Society, shall vest in the University, and  shall be applied to the objects and purposes for which the University  is incorporated.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>From the commencement of this Act, all debts and liabilities  of the said Society shall be transferred and attached to the</p>
            <p>University, and shall thereafter be discharged and satisfied by the</p>
            <p>University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any will, deed or other document, whether made or executed  before or after the commencement of this Act, which contains any  bequest, gift or trust in favour of the Central Hindu College or the  said Society shall, on the commencement of this Act, be construed as  if the University were therein named, instead of the said College or</p>
            <p>Society.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
