<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1961/35/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1961/35"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Dadra And Nagar Haveli Act, 1961"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1961/35/eng@1961-09-02/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1961/35/eng@1961-09-02"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1961-09-02" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1961/35/eng@1961-09-02/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1961/35/eng@1961-09-02"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Dadra And Nagar Haveli Act, 1961</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 35 OF 1961</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 2nd September, 1961.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to make provision for the representation of the Union territory  of Dadra and Nagar Haveli in Parliament and for the adminis-</p>
        <p>tration of that Union territory and for matters connected  therewith.</p>
      </longTitle>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twelfth Year of the Republic  of India as follows:--</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be  called the Dadra and Nagar Haveli Act, 1961.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the Union territory of Dadra and</p>
            <p>Nagar Haveli.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 11th day of</p>
            <p>August, 1961.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" Administrator" means the Administrator of the Union  territory of Dadra and Nagar Haveli appointed by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>President under article 239 of the Constitution;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" appointed day" means the eleventh day of August, 1961;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" Dadra and Nagar Haveli" means the Union territory of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Dadra and Nagar Haveli;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>" Varishta Panchayat" means the Varishta Panchayat as in  existence immediately before the appointed day .</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Representation in the House of the People.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be  allotted one seat to the Union territory of Dadra and Nagar Haveli in  the House of the People.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In the Representation of the People Act, 1950 (43 of 1950),--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in section 4, in sub- section (1), after the words" to  the Laccadive, Minicoy and Amindivi Islands". the words</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>", to Dadra and Nagar Haveli" shall be inserted:</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-3.2.list3.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>in the First Schedule,--</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-3.2.list3.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>after entry 21, the following entry shall  be inserted, namely:--</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list5">
              <listIntroduction>" 22. Dadra and Nagar Haveli.......... 1";</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list5.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>entries 22 and 23 shall be re- numbered  as entries 23 and 24 respectively.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the Representation of the People Act, 1951 (43 of 1951),</p>
            <p>in section 4, after the words" to the Laccadive, Minicoy and Amindivi</p>
            <p>Islands", the words", to Dadra and Nagar Haveli" shall be inserted.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Varishta Panchayat.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Until other provision is made by law,</p>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>as from the commencement of this Act the Varishta Panchayat shall have  the right to discuss and make recommendations to the Administrator  on,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>matters of administration involving general policy and  schemes of development;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any other matter referred to it by the Administrator.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The functions of the Varishta Panchayat referred to in this  section will be advisory only but due regard shall be given to such  advice by the Administrator in reaching decisions on the matter in  relation to which the advice is given.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No act or proceeding of the Varishta Panchayat shall be  invalid by reason only of the existence of any vacancy amongst its  members or any defect in the constitution thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every member of the Varishta Panchayat shall before entering  upon his duties under this Act make and subscribe before the</p>
            <p>Administrator an oath or affirmation in the following form, namely:--</p>
            <p>" I, A. B., a member of the Varishta Panchayat of the Union  territory of Dadra and Nagar Haveli, do swear in the name of God  solemnly affirm that I will bear true faith and allegiance to the</p>
            <p>Constitution of India as by law established and that I will faithfully  discharge the duty upon which I am about to enter.".</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Other functionaries. Without prejudice to the powers of the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Central Government to appoint from time to time such officers and  authorities as may be necessary for the administration of Dadra and</p>
            <p>Nagar Haveli, all judges, magistrates and other officers and  authorities who immediately before the appointed day were exercising  lawful functions in Free Dadra and Nagar Haveli or any part thereof  shall, until other provision is made by law, continue to exercise in  connection with the administration of Dadra and Nagar Haveli their  respective functions in the same manner and to the same extent as  before the appointed day.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Property and assets. It is hereby declared that all property  and assets which immediately before the appointed day vested in the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Varishta Panchayat or the Administrator of Free Dadra and Nagar Haveli  shall, as from that day, west in the Union.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Rights an obligations. All rights, liabilities and obligations  of the Varishta Panchayat or the Administrator of Free Dadra and Nagar</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Haveli in relation to Free Dadra and Nagar Haveli shall, as from the  appointed day, be the rights, liabilities and obligations of the</p>
            <p>Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Continuance of existing laws. Save as otherwise provided in  this Act all laws in force in Free Dadra and Nagar Haveli immediately  before the appointed day shall continue to be in force until repealed  or amended by Parliament or other competent authority.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Continuance of existing taxes. All taxes, duties, cesses or  fees which, immediately before the appointed day, were being lawfully  levied in Free Dadra and Nagar Haveli or any part thereof shall  continue to be levied and to be applied to the same purposes, until  other provision is made by Parliament or other competent authority.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Power to extend enactments to Dadra and Nagar Haveli. The</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette,</p>
            <p>extend with such restrictions or modifications as it thinks fit, to</p>
            <p>Dadra and Nagar Haveli any enactment which is in force in a State at  the date of the notification.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Extension of the jurisdiction of Bombay High Court to Dadra  and Nagar Haveli. As from such date  as the Central Government may,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>by notification in the Official Gazette, specify the jurisdiction of  the High Court at Bombay shall extend to Dadra and Nagar Haveli.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Powers of courts and other authorities for purposes of  facilitating the application of laws. For the purpose of facilitating  the application of any law in Dadra and Nagar Haveli, any court or  other authority may construe any such law with such alterations not  affecting the substance, as may be necessary or proper to adapt it to  the matter before the court or other authority.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Power to remove difficulties.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any difficulty arises in  giving effect to the provisions of this Act or in connection with the  administration of Dadra and Nagar Haveli, the Central Government may,</p>
            <p>by order, make such further provision as appears to it to be necessary  or expedient for removing the difficulty.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any order under sub- section (1) may be made so as to be  retrospective to any date not earlier than the appointed day.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the  purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing powers, such rules may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the manner in which casual vacancies in the Varishta</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-14.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Panchayat may be filled;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.2.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the meetings of the Varishta Panchayat, the conduct of  business and the procedure to be followed at such  meetings;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.2.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any other matter which has to be, or may be, prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this Act shall be laid as soon as may  be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is in  session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in  one session or  in two or more successive sessions, and if, before  the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the  successive sessions aforesaid"] both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not  be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified  form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so however that any such  modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity  of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
