<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1952/58/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1952/58"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Salaries And Allowances Of Minister Act, 1952"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1952/58/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1952/58/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1952/58/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1952/58/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Salaries And Allowances Of Minister Act, 1952</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>ACT NO, 58 OF 1952</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-12th">
        <num>12th.</num>
        <heading>August, 1952.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12th.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>An Act to provide for the salaries and allowances of Ministers.</p>
            <p>Be it enacted by Parliament as follows:-</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title. This Act may be called the Salaries and</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Allowances of Short title. Ministers Act, 1952.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definition. In this Act," Minister" means a member of the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Council of Ministers, by whatever name called, and includes a Deputy</p>
            <p>Minister.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Salaries, and daily and constituency allowances. Each</p>
            <p>Minister shall be entitled to receive a salary per mensem, and  allowance for each day during the whole of his term as such Minister  at the same rates as are specified in section 3 of the Salaries,</p>
            <p>Allowances and Pension of Members of Parliament Act, 1954 with respect  to members of Parliament,</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Each Minister shall be entitled to receive a constituency  allowance at the same rate as is specified under section 8 of the said</p>
            <p>Act with respect to members of Parliament.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Residence of Ministers. Each Minister shall be  entitled without payment of rent to the use of a furnished residence  throughout his term of office and for period of  one month]</p>
            <p>immediately thereafter, and no charge shall fall on the Minister  personally in respect of the maintenance of such residence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the event of the death of the Minister, his family shall  be entitled to the use of the furnished residence occupied by the</p>
            <blockList id="section-4.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Minister-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.2.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for a period of one month immediately after his death,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-4.2.list4">
              <listIntroduction>without payment of rent and no charge shall fall on the  family of the Minister in respect of the maintenance of such  residence, and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.2.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>for a further period of one month, on payment of rent  at such rates as may be prescribed by rules made in this  behalf by the Central Government and also charges in respect  of electricity and water consumed in that residence during  such further period.]</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Explanation.- For the purposes of this section," residence" in-</p>
            <p>cludes the staff quarters and other buildings appurtenant thereto, and  the garden thereof, and" maintenance" in relation to a residence  includes the payment of local rates and taxes and the provision of  electricity and water.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Sumptuary allowance to Ministers. There shall be paid a  sumptuary</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the Prime Minister Rupees one thousand  five hundred per  mensem;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>every other Minister Rupees one thousand  who is a member of per mensem;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>the Cabinet</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>a Minister of State Rupees five hundred  per mensem;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>a Deputy Minister Rupees three hundred  per mensem.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Travelling and daily allownaces to Ministers. Subject to  any rules made in this behalf by the Central Government, a Minister  shall be entitled to-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-6.1.list1.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>travelling allowances for himself and the members of  his family and for the transport of his and his family' s  effects-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-6.1.list1.a.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>in respect of the journey to Delhi from his usual  place of residence outside Delhi for assuming office,</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-6.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>and (ii) in respect of the journey from Delhi to his  usual place of residence outside Delhi on relinquishing  office; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.1.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>travelling and daily allowances in respect of tours  undertaken by him in the discharge of his official duties,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>whether by sea, land or air.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any travelling allowance under this section may be paid in cash  or free official transport provided in lieu thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Medical treatment, etc., to Ministers. Subject to any rules  made in this behalf by the Central Government, a Minister and the  members of his family shall be entitled free of charge to  accommodation in hospitals maintained by the Government and also to  medical treatment.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Advances to Ministers for purchase of motorcars. There may be  paid to any Minister by way of a repayable advance such sum of money  as may be determined by rules made in this behalf for the purchase of  a motor- car in order that he may be able to discharge conveniently and  efficiently the duties of his office.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Ministers not to draw salary or allowances as Members of</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Parliament. No person in receipt of a salary or allowance under this</p>
            <p>Act shall be entitled to receive any sum out of funds provided by</p>
            <p>Parlia-</p>
            <p>ment by way of salary or allowance in respect of his membership of Or  either House of Parliament.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Notification respecting appointment, etc., of Ministers to be  conclusive evidence there of. The date on which any person became or  ceased to be a Minister shall be published in the Official Gazette,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>and any such notification shall be conclusive evidence of the fact  that he became, or ceased to be, a Minister on that date for all the  purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Regularisation of certain payments. All salaries paid or  payable for the period commencing on the 14th day of May, 1952, and  ending with the commencement of this Act to Ministers described as</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Ministers of Cabinet rank (but not Members of the Cabinet), all  charges incurred before the commencement of this Act in respect of the  accommodation provided in any hospital maintained by the Central</p>
            <p>Government for or on the medical treatment of any Minister or any  member of his family and all payments made before such commencement by  way of travelling or daily allowances to any Deputy Minister, shall be  deemed to have been properly paid, payable or incurred or made.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Repeal of Act 53 of 1947. Rep. by the Repealing and Amend-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>ing Act, 1957 (36 of 1957), s. 2 and Sch, 1,</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
