<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1966/53/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1966/53"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Jawaharlal Nehru University Act, 1966"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1966/53/eng@1966-12-22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1966/53/eng@1966-12-22"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1966-12-22" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1966/53/eng@1966-12-22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1966/53/eng@1966-12-22"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Jawaharlal Nehru University Act, 1966</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 53 OF 1966</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 22nd December, 1966].</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Seventeenth Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to establish and incorporate a university in Delhi.</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Jawaharlal Nehru University Act, 1966.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date  as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" College" means a college maintained by the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" Hall" means a unit of residence, by whatever name  called, for students of the University provided,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>maintained or recognised by it;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" recognised institution" means an institution of higher  learning maintained or recognised by, or associated  with, the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by Statutes, Ordinances  or Regulations;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>" Statutes"," Ordnances" and" Regulations" mean,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>respectively, the Statutes, Ordinances and Regulations  of the University made under this Act;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>" University" means the Jawaharlal Nehru University.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>The University.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be constituted in the Union  territory of Delhi a University by the name of" Jawaharlal Nehru</p>
            <p>University".</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The first Chancellor and the first Vice- Chancellor of the</p>
            <p>University and the first members of the Court, the Executive Council  and the Academic Council and all persons who may hereafter become such  officers of members so long as they continue to hold such office or  membership are hereby constituted a body corporate by the name of</p>
            <p>" Jawaharlal Nehru University".</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The University shall have perpetual succession and a common  seal, and shall sue and be sued by the said name.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Objects. The objects of the University shall be to disseminate  and advance knowledge, wisdom and understanding by teaching and  research and by the example and influence of its corporate life and in  particular the objects set out in the First Schedule.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Powers of the University. The University shall have the  following powers, namely:-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to provide for instruction including the method of  correspondence courses in such branches of learning as  the University may from time to time determine, and to  make provision for research and for the advancement and  dissemination of knowledge;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to establish within the Union territory of Delhi or  outside that territory such Special Centres and</p>
            <p>Specialised Laboratories and such other units for  research and instruction as are necessary for the  furtherance of its objects;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to organise and to undertake extra- mural teaching and  extension services;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to hold examinations and grant diplomas or certificates  to, and confer degrees and other academic distinctions  on, persons and to withdraw any such diplomas,</p>
            <p>certificates, degrees or other academic distinctions  for good and sufficient cause;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to confer honorary degrees or other academic  distinctions in the manner laid down in the Statutes;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to create such teaching, administrative and other posts  as the University may deem necessary, from time to  time, and to make appointments thereto;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to appoint or recognise persons as Professors, Readers  or Lecturers or otherwise as teachers of the</p>
            <p>University;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to institute and award Fellowships, Scholarships,</p>
            <p>Exhibitions and prizes;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to establish and maintain Colleges and Halls, to  recognise, guide, supervise and control Halls not  maintained by the University and other accommodation  for students, and to withdraw any such recognition;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.10">
          <num>(10)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to regulate and enforce discipline among students and  employees of the University and to take such  disciplinary measures in this regard as may be deemed  necessary;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to make arrangements for promoting health and general  welfare of students and employees of the University;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.12">
          <num>(12)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to determine and provide for examinations for admission  into the University;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.13">
          <num>(13)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to recognise for any purpose, either in whole or in  part, any institution or members or students thereof on  such terms and conditions as may, from time to time, be  prescribed and to withdraw such recognition;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.14">
          <num>(14)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to co- operate with any other University, authority or  association or any other public or private body having  in view the promotion of purposes and objects similar  to those of the University for such purposes as may be  agreed upon, on such terms and conditions as may, from  time to time, be prescribed;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.15">
          <num>(15)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to enter into any agreement for the incorporation in  the University of any other institution and for taking  over its rights, properties and liabilities and for any  other purpose not repugnant to this Act;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.16">
          <num>(16)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to demand and receive payment of such fees and other  charges as may be prescribed, from time to time;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.17">
          <num>(17)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to receive donations and to acquire, hold, manage and  dispose of any property movable or immovable, including  trust or endowed property within or outside the Union  territory of Delhi, for the purposes or objects of the</p>
            <p>University, and to invest funds in such manner as the</p>
            <p>University thinks fit;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.18">
          <num>(18)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to make provision for research and advisory services;</p>
            <p>and for that purpose to enter into such arrangements  with other institutions or bodies as the University may  deem necessary;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.19">
          <num>(19)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to provide for the printing, reproduction and  publication of research and other work which may be  issued by the University:</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.20">
          <num>(20)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to borrow, with the approval of the Central Government,</p>
            <p>on the security of the University property, money for  the purposes of the University;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.21">
          <num>(21)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to do all such things as may be necessary, incidental  or conducive to the attainment of all or any of the  objects of the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Jurisdiction of the University.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The jurisdiction of the</p>
            <p>University shall extend to all Colleges and recognised institutions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in clause (13) of section</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>, the Jawaharlal Nehru University shall not grant recognition, either  in whole or in part, to any institution which has already been  recognised by the University of Delhi unless the Central Government,</p>
            <p>after consultation with the University of Delhi, authorises the</p>
            <p>Jawaharlal Nehru University to do so.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On and from the date of the recognition either in whole or in  part of an institution by the Jawaharlal Nehru University under sub-</p>
            <p>section (2), the University of Delhi shall to the extent of such  recognition cease to have jurisdiction over that institution.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Powers and Jurisdiction in respect of institution or body  outside the Union territory of Delhi. Notwithstanding anything  contained in section 5,-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>where any institution or body established outside the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Union territory of Delhi seeks recognition from the</p>
            <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>University, or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>where the University establishes and maintains any  institution or body outside the Union territory of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Delhi,</p>
            <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list6">
              <listIntroduction>then the powers and jurisdiction of the University shall extend to  such institution or body subject to-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list6.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the laws in force in the State within which, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list6.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>the rules and regulations of the University within  whose jurisdiction,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>the said institution or body is situated.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Visitor.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The President of India shall be the Visitor of  the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Visitor may, from time to time, appoint one or more  persons to review the work and progress of the University and to  submit a report thereon; and upon receipt of that report, the Visitor  may, after obtaining the views of the Executive Council thereon, take  such action and issue such directions as he considers necessary in  respect of any of the matters dealt with in the report and the</p>
            <p>University shall be bound to comply with such directions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Visitor shall also have the right to cause an inspection  to be made by such person or persons as he may direct of the</p>
            <p>University, its buildings, laboratories and equipment and of any  institution maintained by the University, and also of the  examinations, teaching and other work conducted or done by the</p>
            <p>University and to cause an inquiry to be made in respect of any matter  connected with the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Visitor shall in every case give notice to the University  of his intention to cause an inspection or inquiry to be made, and the</p>
            <p>University shall be entitled to appoint a representative who shall  have the right to be present and be heard at such inspection or  inquiry.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Visitor may address the Vice- Chancellor with reference to  the result of such inspection and inquiry, and the Vice- Chancellor  shall communicate to the Executive Council the views of the Visitor  with such advice as the Visitor may offer upon the action to be taken  thereon.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Executive Council shall communicate through the Vice-</p>
            <p>Chancellor to the Visitor such action, if any, as it is proposed to  take or has been taken upon the result of such inspection or inquiry.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the Executive Council does not, within a reasonable  time, take action to the satisfaction of the Visitor, the Visitor may,</p>
            <p>after considering any explanation furnished or representation made by  the Executive Council, issue such directions as he may think fit and  the Executive Council shall be bound to comply with such directions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Visitor may be order in writing annul any proceeding of  the University which is not in conformity with this Act, the Statutes  or the Ordinances.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Visitor shall also have such other powers as may be  prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Officers of the University.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be a Chancellor  appointed in the manner prescribed by the Statutes who shall be the</p>
            <p>Head of the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chancellor shall, if present, preside at convocation of  the University for conferring degrees and all meetings of the Court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be a Vice- Chancellor appointed in the manner  prescribed by the Statutes who shall be the principal executive and</p>
            <p>Academic Officer of the University and ex officio Chairman of the</p>
            <p>Executive Council, Academic Council and Finance Committee and he  shall, in the absence of the Chancellor preside at any convocation for  conferring degrees and also at any meeting of the Court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be one or more Rectors who shall be appointed in  such manner and with such powers and duties as may be prescribed by  the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be a Dean for each School of Study who shall be  appointed in such manner and with such powers and duties as may be  prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be a Registrar who shall act as Secretary of the</p>
            <p>Court, the Executive Council and the Academic Council and he shall be  appointed in such manner and with such powers and duties as may be  prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be a Finance Officer who shall be the Secretary  of the Finance Committee and exercise such powers and perform such  duties as may be prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be such other officers as provided for in the</p>
            <p>Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Authorities of the University. The authorities of the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>University shall be the Court, the Executive Council, the Academic</p>
            <p>Council, the Schools of Studies, the Finance Committee and such other  authorities as may be declared by the Statutes to be authorities of  the University.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>The Court.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Court shall be the supreme authority of  the University, and its constitution and the terms of office of its  members shall be prescribe by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Court shall have the power to review the acts of the</p>
            <p>Executive Council and the Academic Council (save when these  authorities have acted in accordance with the powers conferred upon   them under this Act, the Statutes or the Ordinances) and shall  exercise all the powers of the University not otherwise provided for  by this Act or the Statutes:</p>
            <p>Provided that the power of review under this sub- section shall  not be exercised except by a majority of the total membership of the</p>
            <p>Court and by a majority of not less than two- thirds of the members of  the Court present and voting.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>The Executive Council.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Executive Council shall be the  executive body of the University, and its constitution and the terms  of office of its members, other than ex officio members, shall be  prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be in charge of the general management and  administration (including the revenue and property) of the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>The Academic Council.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Academic Council shall be the  academic body of the University, and its constitution and the terms of  office of its members, other than ex officio members, shall be  prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Academic Council shall, subject to the provisions of this</p>
            <p>Act, the Statutes and the Ordinances, have the control and general  regulation, and be responsible for the maintenance, of standards of  instruction, education and examination within the University, and  shall exercise such other powers and perform such other duties as may  be conferred or imposed upon it by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>The Academic Advisory Committee.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be  constituted an Academic Advisory Committee of the University which  shall advise generally on the planning and development to the</p>
            <p>University and keep under review the standard of education and  research in the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Committee shall consist of-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>not more than seven persons of high academic standing  who shall be appointed in such manner as may be  prescribed by the statutes, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the Vice- Chancellor.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Visitor may determine a date with effect from which the</p>
            <p>Academic Advisory Committee shall stand dissolved.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Statutes. Subject to the provisions of this Act, the statutes  may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-15.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the constitution, powers and duties of the authorities  and other bodies of the University, the qualifications  and disqualifications for membership of such  authorities and other bodies, appointment and removal  of members thereof and other matters connected  therewith;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the appointment, powers and duties of the officers of  the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the appointment, terms and conditions of service and  the powers and duties of the employees of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-15.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the terms and conditions under which institution may be  associated with the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list2.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the administration of the University, the establishment  and abolition of Colleges, institutions and Halls, the  grant and withdrawal of recognition to institutions,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>the institution of Fellowships, Awards and the like,</p>
            <blockList id="section-15.paragraph-0.list5">
              <listIntroduction>the conferment of degrees and other academic  distinctions and the grant of diplomas and  certificates;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list5.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>any other matter which is necessary for the proper and  effective management and conduct of the affairs of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>University and which by this Act is to be or may be  provided by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Statutes, how made.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-16.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The first Statutes are those set out  in the Second Schedule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Executive Council may, from time to time, make new or  additional Statutes or may amend or repeal the Statutes in the manner  hereafter in this section provided:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Executive Council shall not make any Statute or  any amendment of a Statute affecting the status, powers or  constitution of any existing authority of the University until such  authority has been given an opportunity of expressing an opinion on  the proposal, and any opinion so expressed shall be in writing and  shall be considered by the Executive Council:</p>
            <p>Provided further that no Statute shall be made by the Executive</p>
            <p>Council affecting the discipline of students, and standards of  instruction, education and examination except after consultation with  the Academic Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every new Statute or addition to the Statutes or any  amendment or repeal of a Statute shall require the approval of the</p>
            <p>Visitor who may assent thereto or withhold assent on remit to the</p>
            <p>Executive Council for consideration.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A new Statute or a Statute amending or repealing an existing</p>
            <p>Statute shall have no validity unless it has been assented to by the</p>
            <p>Visitor.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Ordinances.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act and the</p>
            <blockList id="section-17.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Statutes, the Ordinances may provide for all or any of the following  matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the admission of students, the courses of study and the  fees therefor, the qualifications pertaining to  degrees, diplomas, certificates and other academic  distinctions, the conditions for the grant of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-17.1.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Fellowships, Awards and the like;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.1.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the conduct of examinations, including the terms of  office and appointment of examiners, and the conditions  of residence of students and their general discipline;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.1.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the management of colleges and institutions maintained  by the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.1.list4.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>any other matter which by this Act or the Statutes is  to be or may be provided by the Ordinances.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The first Ordinances shall be made by the Vice- Chancellor  with the previous approval of the Central Government and the</p>
            <p>Ordinances so made may be amended, repealed or added to at any time by  the Executive Council in the manner prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Regulations. The authorities of the University may make</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Regulations consistent with this Act, the Statutes and the Ordinances  for the conduct of their own business and that of the committees  appointed by them and not provided for by this Act, the Statutes or  the Ordinances in the manner prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Annual report.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-19.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The annual report of the University shall  be prepared under the direction of the Executive Council and shall be  submitted to the Court on or before such date as may be prescribed by  the Statutes and shall be considered by the Court at its annual  meeting.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Court may communicate its comments thereon to the</p>
            <p>Executive Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Audit of accounts.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-20.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The accounts of the University shall,</p>
            <p>once at least in every year and at intervals of not more than fifteen  months, be audited by the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India, or  any person authorised by him in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The accounts, when audited shall be published in the Gazette  of India, and a copy of the accounts together with the audit report  shall be submitted by the Registrar to the Visitor and to the Court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Disputes as to constitution of University authorities and  bodies. If any question arises whether any person has been duly  elected or appointed as, or is entitled to be, a member of any  authority or other body of the University, the matter shall be  referred to the Visitor whose decision thereon shall be final.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of committees. Where any authority of the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>University is given power by this Act or the Statutes to appoint  committees, such committees shall, save as otherwise provided, consist  of members of the authority concerned and of such other persons (if   any) as the authority in each case may think fit.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Filling of casual vacancies. All casual vacancies among the  members (other than ex officio members) of any authority or other body  of the University shall be filled, as soon as conveniently may be, by  the person or body who appointed, elected or co- opted the member whose  place has become vacant, and the person appointed, elected or co- opted  to a casual vacancy shall be a member of such authority or body for  the residue of the term for which the person whose place he fills  would have been a member.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Proceedings of the University authorities and bodies not  invalidated by vacancies. No act or proceedings of any authority or  other body of the University shall be invalidated merely by reason of  the existence of a vacancy or vacancies among its members.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Removal of difficulties. If any difficulty arises in giving  effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government may, by  order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions not  inconsistent with the purposes of this Act, as appear to it to be  necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Transitional provisions. Notwithstanding anything contained  in this Act and the Statutes-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-26.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the first Chancellor, members of the Court, the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-26.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Executive Council and the Academic Council shall be  nominated by the Visitor and shall hold office for a  term of three years;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the first Vice- Chancellor shall be appointed by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Visitor and he shall hold office for a term of five  years.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of Act 8 of 1922. In the Delhi University Act,</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1922">
        <num>1922.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1922.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>, in sub- section (2) of section 5, after the words" for the time  being in force", the words and figures" but subject to the provisions  contained in the Jawaharlal Nehru University Act, 1966" shall be  inserted.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
