<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/70/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/70"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Displaced Persons (Debts Adjustment) Act, 1951"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/70/eng@1951-11-07/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/70/eng@1951-11-07"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1951-11-07" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/70/eng@1951-11-07/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/70/eng@1951-11-07"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Displaced Persons (Debts Adjustment) Act, 1951</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 70 OF 1951</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 7th November, 1951.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament as follows:--</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to make certain provisions for the adjustment and settlement of  debts due by displaced persons, for the recovery of certain debts due  to them and for matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.</p>
        <p>CHAP</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be  called the Displaced Persons (Debts Adjustment) Act, 1951.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu  and Kashmir.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on such date  as the Central</p>
              <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint, and  different dates may be appointed for different States or for different  parts thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
          <subsection id="section-2.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" company" means a company as defined in the Indian</p>
              <p>Companies Act, 1913  (7 of 1913), and includes a  company deemed to be registered under that Act by  reason of any of the provisions contained in this Act;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" Companies Act" means the Indian Companies Act, 1913</p>
              <p>(7 of 1913);</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" compensation" means any compensation paid, whether in  cash or in kind, in respect of any immovable property  in West Pakistan belonging to a displaced person under  any general scheme arrived at in this behalf between  the Government of India and the Government of Pakistan  or framed by the Government of India;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" co- operative society" means a co- operative society  registered under the Co- operative Societies Act, 1912</p>
              <p>(2 of 1912), or under any other law for the time being  in force in any State for the registration of co-</p>
              <p>operative societies;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" Co- operative Societies Act" means the Co- operative</p>
              <p>Societies Act, 1912 (2 of 1912), and includes any other  law for the time being in force in any State relating  to co- operative societies;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" debt" means any pecuniary liability, whether payable  presently or in future, or under a decree or order of a</p>
              <blockList id="section-2.6.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Civil or Revenue Court or otherwise, or whether  ascertained or to be ascertained, which--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.6.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>in the case of a displaced person who has left  or been displaced from his place of residence in any  area now forming part of West Pakistan, was incurred  before he came to reside in any area now forming part  of India;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.6.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>in the case of a displaced person who, before  and after the 15th day of August, 1947, has been  residing in any area now forming part of India, was  incurred before the said date on the security of any  immovable property situate in the territories now  forming part of West Pakistan:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.6.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that where any such liability was  incurred on the security of immovable properties  situate both in India and in West Pakistan, the  liability shall be so apportioned between the said  properties that the liability in relation to each of  the said properties bears the same proportion to the  total amount of the debts as the value of each of the  properties as at the date of the transaction bears to  the total value of the properties furnished as  security, and the liability, for the purposes of this  clause, shall be the liability which is relatable to  the property in West Pakistan;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.6.list4.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>is due to a displaced person from any other  person (whether a displaced person or not) ordinarily  residing in the territories to which this Act extends;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>and includes</p>
              <p>any pecuniary liability incurred before the  commencement of this Act by any such person as is  referred to in this clause which is based on, and is  solely by way of</p>
              <p>renewal of, any such liability as is referred to in  sub- clause (a) or sub- clause (b) or sub- clause (c):</p>
              <p>Provided that in the case of a loan, whether in  cash or in kind, the amount originally advanced and not  the amount for which the liability has been renewed  shall be deemed to be the extent of the liability;</p>
              <p>but does not include</p>
              <p>any pecuniary liability due under a decree passed  after the 15th day of August, 1947, by any Court  situate in West Pakistan or any pecuniary liability the  proof of which depends merely on an oral agreement;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" displaced bank" means a banking company which, before  the 15th day of August, 1947, carried on the business  of banking, whether wholly or partially, in any area  now forming part of West Pakistan and is declared to be  a displaced bank within the meaning of this Act by the</p>
              <p>Central Government by notification  in the Official  gazette;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" displaced creditor" means a displaced person to whom a  debt is due from any other person, whether a displaced  person or not;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" displaced debtor" means a displaced person from whom a  debt is due or is being claimed;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.10">
            <num>(10)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" displaced person" means any person who, on account of  the setting up of the Dominions of India and Pakistan,</p>
              <p>or on account of civil disturbances or the fear of such  disturbances in any area now forming part of West</p>
              <p>Pakistan, has, after the 1st day of March, 1947, left,</p>
              <p>or been displaced from, his place of residence in such  area and who has been subsequently residing in India,</p>
              <p>and includes any person who is resident in any place  now forming part of India and who for that reason is  unable or has been rendered unable to manage, supervise  or control any immovable property belonging to him in</p>
              <p>West Pakistan, but does not include a banking company;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.11">
            <num>(11)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
              <p>Act;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.12">
            <num>(12)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" Tribunal" means any Civil Court specified under  section 4 as having authority to exercise jurisdiction  under this Act;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.13">
            <num>(13)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" verified claim" means any claim registered under the</p>
              <p>Displaced Persons (Claims) Act, 1950 (44 of 1950) in  respect of which a final order has been passed under  that Act relating to its verification and valuation;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.14">
            <num>(14)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" West Pakistan" means the territories of Pakistan  excluding the Province of East Bengal.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Overriding effect of Act, rules and orders. Save as otherwise  expressly provided in this Act, the provisions of this Act and of the  rules and orders made thereunder shall have effect notwithstanding  anything inconsistent therewith contained in any other law for the  time being in force, or in any decree or order of a Court, or in any  contract between the parties.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Tribunals competent to exercise jurisdiction under this Act.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette,</p>
              <p>specify any Civil Court or class of Civil Courts as the Tribunal or</p>
              <p>Tribunals having authority to exercise jurisdiction under this Act and  may define the areas in which and the extent to which such  jurisdiction may be exercised.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>DEBT ADJUSTMENT PROCEEDINGS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>DEBT ADJUSTMENT PROCEEDINGS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Application by displaced debtors for adjustment of debts.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>At any time within one year after the date on which this Act comes  into force in any local area, a displaced debtor may make an  application for the adjustment of his debts to the Tribunal within the  local limits of whose jurisdiction he actually and voluntarily  resides, or carries on business or personally works for gain.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-5.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Every application by a displaced debtor shall contain the  following particulars, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the place where he resides;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-5.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the trade, calling, profession or other employment in  which he is now engaged and in which he was engaged in</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-5.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>West Pakistan before he became a displaced person;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.2.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>his average annual income in India during the three  years immediately preceding the application;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-5.2.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the income- tax and super- tax, if any, to which he has  been assessed for the three years immediately preceding  the application;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-5.2.list3.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>such other particulars as may be prescribed;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-5.2.list5">
                <listIntroduction>and shall be accompanied by the following schedules, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.2.list5.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>a schedule containing full particulars of all his  debts, whether owed jointly or individually, with the  names and addresses of his creditors and joint- debtors,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-5.2.list7">
                <listIntroduction>if any, so far as they are known to, or can by the  exercise of reasonable care and diligence be  ascertained by him;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.2.list7.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>a schedule of all his properties, both movable and  immovable (including claims due to him) which are not  liable to attachment either under the Code of Civil</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-5.2.list9">
                <listIntroduction>Procedure, 1908, (5 of 1908) as amended by section 31  of this Act or under any other law for the time being  in force, a specification of the values thereof and of  the places where the same may be found;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.2.list9.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>a schedule of all his properties, both movable and  immovable (including claims due to him) which are not  included in the schedule under item (ii) of this  clause; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-5.2.list9.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>a schedule of all his properties in respect of which a  claim has been submitted to the registering officer  under the Displaced Persons (Claims) Act, 1950, (44 of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1950">
          <num>1950.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1950.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>) and, where any order has been passed in relation  to the verification and valuation of the claim under  that Act, with a certified copy of the order.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-1950.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All persons whose names are shown in any schedule as having  claims against the displaced debtor and all persons whose names are  shown as joint- debtors shall be deemed to be the respondents to the  application and there shall be filed along with the application, or  with the permission of the Tribunal at any later stage of the  proceedings, as many copies of the application and as many envelopes  and notices in the prescribed form duly addressed to the respondents  as there are respondents.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Rejection of application in certain cases. Where an  application made under section 5 does not comply with any of the  requirements of that section, the Tribunal may either reject it, or  grant to the applicant such further time as it thinks fit to comply  with such requirements.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Issue of notice. If the application is not rejected under  section 6, the Tribunal shall, after causing the date for the hearing  of the application to be entered in the notices referred to in section</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>, cause them to be served on the respondents.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Objection by respondents. In response to a notice under  section 7, the respondent may show cause against the application by  filing a written statement containing his objections to the  application:</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Provided that where he does not appear in person or through any  authorized agent, the written statement may be sent by registered  post, acknowledgment due, to the Tribunal after having been signed in  the presence of a civil judicial officer or a Magistrate or any other  prescribed officer and duly attested by such officer or Magistrate.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Proceeding after service of notice on respondents.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If  there is a dispute as to whether the applicant is a displaced person  or not or as to the existence or the amount of the debt due to any  creditor or the assets of any displaced debtor, the Tribunal shall  decide the matter after taking such evidence as may be adduced by all  the parties concerned and shall pass such decree in relation thereto  as it thinks fit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If there is no such dispute or if the respondents do not  appear or have no objection to the application being granted, the</p>
              <p>Tribunal may, after considering the evidence placed before it, pass  such decree in relation thereto as it thinks fit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Claims by creditors against displaced debtors. Any displaced  person having a claim against a displaced debtor may make an  application, in such form as may be prescribed, for the determination  thereof to the Tribunal within the local limits of whose jurisdiction  the displaced debtor actually and voluntarily resides, or carries on  business, or personally works for gain, together with a statement of  the debts owed to the creditor with full particulars thereof.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Procedure on creditor' s petition.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where an application  under section 10 has been made, the Tribunal shall cause notice  thereof to be served on the displaced debtor calling upon him either  to show cause, if any, against the application or to make an  application on his own behalf under section 5.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If, in response to a notice under sub- section (1), the  displaced debtor makes an application in accordance with the  provisions of section 5, the Tribunal shall proceed further in the  matter as if it had commenced with an application by the displaced  debtor under section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>, and all the other provisions of this Act shall apply accordingly;</p>
              <p>but, if the displaced debtor does not choose to make any such  application, the Tribunal shall, after considering such evidence, if  any, as may be produced before it, determine the claim and pass such  decree in relation thereto as it thinks fit.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-5.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The period of limitation specified in sub- section (1) of  section 5 in respect of an application by a displaced debtor shall not  apply to an application made under sub- section (2).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Objection by creditor to schedule of assets.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-12.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any creditor  of a displaced debtor may make an application to the Tribunal stating  that the displaced debtor, who has made an application under section 5  or sub- section (2) of section 11, has concealed any part of his  assets, and the Tribunal shall, after giving due notice thereof to the  displaced debtor, determine the matter.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the Tribunal finds that the displaced debtor has wilfully  and fraudulently omitted to include such assets in his application,</p>
              <p>the Tribunal may dismiss the application or refuse to allow to the  displaced debtor any of the reliefs under this Act to which he would  otherwise have been entitled or pass such other order in relation  thereto as it thinks fit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Claims by displaced creditors against persons who are not  displaced debtors. At any time within one year after the date on which  this Act comes into force in any local area, any displaced creditor  claiming a debt from any other person who is not a displaced person  may make an application, in such form as may be prescribed, to the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Tribunal within the local limits of whose jurisdiction he or the  respondent or, if there are more respondents than one, any of such  respondents, actually and voluntarily resides, or carries on business  or personally works for gain, together with a statement of the debt  owing to him with full particulars thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Procedure on displaced creditor' s petition.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where an  application under section 13 has been made to the Tribunal, the</p>
              <p>Tribunal shall cause notice thereof to be given to the debtor, calling  upon him to show cause, if any, against the application.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If there is a dispute as to whether the applicant is a  displaced creditor or not or as to the existence of the debt or as to  the amount thereof, the Tribunal shall decide the matter, after taking  such evidence as may be produced before it, and pass such decree in  relation thereto as it thinks fit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If there is no such dispute or if the debtor does not appear  or has no cause to show, the Tribunal may, after considering the  evidence placed before it, pass such decree in relation thereto as it  thinks fit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Consequences of application by displaced debtor. Where a  displaced debtor has made an application to the Tribunal under section</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>or under sub- section (2) of section 11, the following consequences  shall ensue, namely:--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>all proceedings pending at the date of the said  application in any Civil Court in respect of any debt  to which the displaced debtor is subject (except  proceedings by way of appeal or review or revision  against decrees or orders passed against the displaced   debtor) shall be stayed, and the records of all such  proceedings other than those relating to the appeals,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>reviews or revisions as aforesaid shall be transferred  to the Tribunal and consolidated;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>all attachments, injunctions, orders appointing  receivers or other processes issued by any such Court  and in force at the date of the said application in  respect of any such debt shall cease to have effect and  no fresh process shall, except as hereinafter expressly  provided, be issued:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that where an order appointing a receiver  ceases to have effect under this section, the receiver  shall; within fourteen days from the date on which his  appointment ceases to have effect or within such  further time as the Tribunal may in any case allow,</p>
              <p>submit to the Tribunal instead of to the Court which  appointed him his outstanding accounts, and the</p>
              <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Tribunal shall, in relation to such accounts, have the  same powers with respect to the receiver as the Court  which appointed him had or could have had;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list6.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>no fresh suit or other proceeding other than any such  appeal, review or revision as is referred to in clause</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list6.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>shall be instituted against a displaced debtor in  respect of any debt mentioned by him in the relevant  schedule to his application:</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list6.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>any immovable property belonging to the displaced  debtor and liable to attachment shall not be  transferred except under the authority of the Tribunal  and no such terms as it thinks fit, until the  application of the displaced debtor has been finally  disposed of or any decree passed against</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>him is satisfied in accordance with the provisions of  this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Debts secured on immovable property.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-16.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where a debt  incurred by a displaced person is secured by a mortgage, charge or  lien on the immovable property belonging to him in West Pakistan, the</p>
              <p>Tribunal may, for the purpose of any proceeding under this Act,</p>
              <p>require the creditor to elect to retain the security or to be treated  as an unsecured creditor.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the creditor elects to retain the security, he may apply  to the Tribunal, having jurisdiction in this behalf as provided in  section 10, for a declaration of the amount due under his debt.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-16.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Where in any case, the creditor elects to retain his  security, if the displaced debtor received any compensation in respect  of any such property as is referred to in sub- section (1), the  creditor shall be entitled--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-16.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>Where the compensation is paid in cash, to a first  charge thereon:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-16.3.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that the amount of the debt in respect of  which he shall be entitled to the first charge shall be  that amount as bears to the total debt the same  proportion as the compensation paid in respect of the  property bears to the value of the verified claim in  respect thereof and to that extent the debt shall be  deemed to have been reduced:</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-16.3.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>Where the compensation is by way of exchange of  property, to a first charge on the property situate in</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>India so received by way of exchange:</p>
              <p>Provided that the amount of the debt in respect of  which be shall be entitled to the first charge shall be  that amount as bears to the total debt the same  proportion as the value of the property received by way  of exchange bears to the value of the verified claim in  respect thereof and to that extent the debt shall be  deemed to have been reduced.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, where a  debt is secured by a mortgage of agricultural lands belonging to a  displaced person in West Pakistan and the mortgage was with  possession, the mortgagee shall, if he has been allotted lands in</p>
              <p>India in lieu of the lands of which he was in possession in West</p>
              <p>Pakistan, be entitled</p>
              <p>to continue in possession of the lands so allotted until the debt is  satisfied from the usufruct of the lands or is redeemed by the debtor:</p>
              <p>Provided that in either case the amount of the debt shall be only  that amount as bears to the total debt the same proportion as the  value of the lands allotted to the creditor in India bears to the  value of the lands left behind by him in West Pakistan and to that  extent the debt shall be deemed to have been reduced.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where a creditor elects to be treated as an unsecured  creditor in relation to the debt, the provisions of this Act shall  apply accordingly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Debts secured on movable property.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-17.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Where in respect of a  debt incurred by a displaced debtor and secured by the pledge of  movable property belonging to him, the creditor had been placed in  possession of such property at any time before the debtor became a  displaced person, the following rules shall regulate the rights and  liabilities of the creditor and the debtor, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the creditor may, if he is still in possession of the  pledged property, realise the sum due to him by the  sale of such property after giving to the debtor  reasonable notice of the sale:</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the creditor shall not be entitled, in any case where  the pledged property is no longer in his possession or  is not available for redemption by the debtor to  recover from the debtor the debt or any part thereof  for which the pledged property was security:</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the debtor shall not be liable, in the case of a sale  by the creditor of any pledged property, whether under  clause (a) or otherwise, to pay the balance where the  proceeds of such sale are less than the amount of the  debt due:</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the creditor shall, in any case where the proceeds of  the sale of the pledged property are greater than the  amount of the debt due, pay over the surplus to the  debtor.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Explanation I.- For the purposes of this section, the creditor  shall be deemed to be in possession of the pledged property in any  case in which the pledged property, although not delivered to him was  delivered to a person authorized by him or was being held by the  debtor on behalf of the creditor, and the ownership of possession  thereof could not have been transferred to a third party without the  express consent or permission of the creditor.</p>
              <p>Explanation II.- Where any motor vehicle or other movable property  has been purchased with money the whole or any part of which has been  advanced by a creditor who retains the ownership thereof by way of  security but allows the debtor to use it with his permission, the  property shall for the purposes of this section be deemed to be  pledged property of the debtor in the possession of the creditor.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, the  creditor shall be entitled to receive, and to give a valid discharge  in respect of, any sum due under this Act or under any other law for  the time being in force from an insurance company in respect of any  claim arising out of the loss or destruction of the pledged property,</p>
              <p>but the creditor shall, in any case where the sum received from the  insurance company is greater than the amount of the debt due to him,</p>
              <p>pay over the surplus to the debtor.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Claims against insurance companies.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-18.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where any property in</p>
              <blockList id="section-18.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>West Pakistan belonging to a displaced person was insured with any  insurance company before the 15th day of August, 1947, against any  risk arising out of fire or theft or riot and civil commotion and  there has been a loss in respect of such property arising out of any  such risk at a time when the contract of insurance was in force, such  company shall not be entitled to refuse payment of the sum due under  any claim in relation thereto on the ground that--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-18.1.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>no report was lodged with the police within the agreed  time, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.1.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the claim was not made to the company with the agreed  time, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.1.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>in the case of a policy covering any risk arising out  of riot and civil commotion, the disturbances in West</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-18.1.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Pakistan were not in the nature of a riot or civil  commotion, or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-18.1.list4.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the displaced person has not fulfilled any other  condition of the contract which in the opinion of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Central government is of a technical nature and which  the Central Government has, by notification  in the</p>
              <p>Official Gazette, specified as a condition of the  contract for the purposes of this section,</p>
              <p>and any contract to the contrary, to the extent to which it is in  contravention of the provisions of this sub- section, shall be deemed  to have had no effect.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where a loss has been incurred in respect of any property in  the circumstances specified in sub- section (1), the Tribunal shall, in  every proceeding where it is necessary to do so, determine  respectively the amount of the loss, the amount for which the property  was insured on the date of such loss, and the amount, if any, paid by  the insurance company, and shall make a report thereof to such board  or other authority as may be prescribed, and the prescribed board or  other authority shall, after taking into account such matters as may  be prescribed as being relevant thereto, and subject to any rules made  in this behalf, in turn propose to the Tribunal the amount for which  the claim against the insurance company shall be decreed, and the</p>
              <p>Tribunal shall pass a decree accordingly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The amount realised from the insurance company under any  decree passed under sub- section (2) shall first be applied towards the  satisfaction of the debt due from the displaced person, and the  balance, if any, shall be refunded to the displaced person.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An application under this section may be made either by a  displaced person having a claim against the insurance company in the  circumstances specified in sub- section (1) or by an assignee or any  other person having an interest in the claim of any such displaced  person, to the Tribunal within the local limits of whose jurisdiction  the displaced person actually and voluntarily resides or carries on  business or personally works for gain or, in the case of a displaced  bank making an application under this section, within whose limits the  bank carries on business, for the determination of the amount due in  respect of the claim in accordance with the provisions of sub- section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>To every proceeding under sub- section (4) the insurance  company and all persons interested in the claim shall be made parties:</p>
              <p>Provided that the Tribunal may at any stage of the proceeding  direct that the name of any person whose presence before the Tribunal  may be necessary in order to enable the Tribunal effectually and  completely to adjudicate upon and settle all the questions involved,</p>
              <p>be added to the proceeding.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No application under this section shall be entertained in any  case where no claim has been made to the insurance company within one  year after the date of the loss.</p>
              <p>Explanation.- A claim shall be deemed to have been made within the  meaning of this sub- section if intimation thereof has been given to  the insurance company within one year after the date of the loss  notwithstanding that the intimation does not specify the amount of the  claim or is not in the form, if any, required by the contract of  insurance or in any other specified form.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Calls on shares in companies.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-19.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where a company or a co-</p>
              <p>operative society has made any call upon a displaced person or a  displaced bank in respect of any moneys remaining unpaid on any share  held by him or it on the 15th day of August, 1947, in the company or  co- operative society, as the case may be, and there has been a failure  on the part of the shareholder to pay any moneys due in respect of  such call, then, notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in  the Companies Act, or in the memorandum or articles of association or  the Co- operative Societies Act, no interest shall be payable in  respect of any such moneys due and the company or the co- operative  society, as the case may be, shall not be entitled to forfeit the  share or any part thereof, and any forfeiture made before the  commencement of this Act in respect of any share in the circumstances  specified in the sub- section shall be deemed to have had no effect,</p>
              <p>and no person shall be deemed to have ceased to be a member of the  company or co- operative society merely by reason of such forfeiture.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Companies Act, or  in the memorandum or articles of association, or the Co- operative</p>
              <p>Societies Act, it shall be lawful for a displaced person or a  displaced bank to apply to the company or the co- operative society, as  the case may be, for the conversion of any partly paid- up share held  by him or it in the company or society into such smaller number of  fully paid- up shares as the society or company may have issued and in  respect of which calls have already been made.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where any share forfeited before the commencement of this Act  has been disposed of by the company in accordance with its articles of  association and it is not possible for the company to give to the  displaced person the relief to which he is entitled under this section  without increasing its capital, the capital of the company shall be  deemed to have been increased to the extent to which it is necessary  to provide that relief.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the company or the co- operative society refuses to comply  with any such request as is contained in an application under sub-</p>
              <p>section (2), the Tribunal may, on application made to it in this  behalf</p>
              <p>and if satisfied that there is no cause for such refusal, issue a  direction to the company or the co- operative society accordingly, and  the company or society shall be bound to comply therewith and every  such direction shall take effect from the date thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Save as otherwise provided in this section, nothing contained  herein shall affect the validity of any action taken by the company or  its board of directors in pursuance of the provisions of the Companies</p>
              <p>Act or of the memorandum or articles of association relating to the  company.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of this section shall have effect for a period  of ten years from the 15th day of August, 1947, and thereafter shall  cease to have effect except as respects things done or omitted to be  done.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>No calls to be made on displaced person or bank when company  or co- operative society is in liquidation.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-20.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where a company or a  co- operative society is being wound up, no displaced person or  displaced bank shall be called upon, notwithstanding anything to the  contrary contained in the Companies Act or in the memorandum or  articles of association or the Co- operative Societies Act, to make any  contribution to the assets of the company or co- operative society, as  the case may be, in respect of any share held by him or it in the  company or society on the 15th day of August, 1947.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of this section shall have effect for a period  of ten years from the 15th day of August, 1947, and shall also apply  in respect of any calls made and not satisfied before that date, and  shall cease to have effect after the expiry of the said period except  as respects things done or omitted to be done.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Power to revise certain decree and settlement.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-21.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where,</p>
              <p>before the commencement of this Act, a decree has been passed by a</p>
              <p>Civil court against, or a settlement has been entered into by, a  displaced debtor in respect of any debt, the Tribunal shall, on the  application of such debtor revise it so as to bring it into accord  with the provisions of the Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-21.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In determining the amount due under any such decree or  settlement, the Tribunal shall accept as binding the findings of the</p>
              <p>Court which passed the decree or the facts contained in the  settlement, as the case may be, to the extent to which the findings  or the facts are not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act:</p>
              <p>Provided that the Tribunal shall not determine any claim under  any such decree until any appeal or revision filed against it has been  finally decided or the period allowed for any appeal therefrom has</p>
              <p>expired, and in all such cases the finding of the Tribunal shall be  based on the final decree.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-21.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, no</p>
              <p>Tribunal shall in respect of any debt revise any settlement arrived at  before the commencement of this Act between an insurance company and a  displaced person or between an insurance company and a displaced bank  having an interest in the claim of a displaced person against the  insurance company and arriving at such settlement by virtue of that  interest:</p>
              <p>Provided that payment in full has been made in pursuance of such  settlement.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Apportionment of joint debts. Where a debt is due from a  displaced person jointly with another person, the Tribunal shall, for  the purposes of this Act, apportion the liability between them  according to the following rules, namely:--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-22.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-22.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>if the liability of each debtor is defined, then  according to the defined share of each;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-22.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>if the debt was taken for any trade or business of the  joint debtors, then according to the shares held by  each of the joint debtors in the trade or business;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-22.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>if the debt was not taken in any defined shares or for  any trade or business in which the partners have any  defined share, the debt shall be apportioned into as  many parts as there are joint debtors, and each joint  debtor shall be liable only for the part apportioned to  him;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-22.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>if one joint debtor is a displaced person and another  is not, the sum apportioned to the non- displaced person  shall not be deemed to be a debt within the meaning of  this Act and the creditor may in respect of such debt  seek any remedy open to him in a Civil court or  otherwise;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-22.paragraph-0.list0.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>if the debt was taken by a joint Hindu family, the  members of the joint Hindu family shall be deemed to be  joint debtors within the meaning of this section and  the debt shall be apportioned amongst the members  thereof in the same proportion in which shares would be  allotted to them on partition:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that the share of any member of such a  joint family any of whose male lineal ascendants in the  male line of ascent is alive and joint with such</p>
              <blockList id="section-22.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>member shall be deemed to be included in the share of  his oldest surviving ascendant in the male line of  ascent, and such member shall not be separately  regarded as a joint debtor for the purpose of this  clause;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-22.paragraph-0.list3.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>if the liability is secured by a mortgage of movable  and immovable properties, the debt shall be apportioned  between the two properties in the same proportion as  the value of each property bears to the total value of  the properties;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-22.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Explanation.- For the purposes of this clause, the  value of the movable property shall be deemed to be the  value thereof immediately before the date on which the  debtor became a displaced person, and the value of the  immovable property shall be deemed to be the value of  the verified claim in respect thereof;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-22.paragraph-0.list5.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>Where the relationship between the joint debtors is  that of principal and surety, nothing contained in this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Act shall prevent the institution of a suit for the  recovery of the debt against the surety but no decree  shall be passed in such suit for an amount in excess of  the amount decreed or which can be decreed against the  principal debtor in accordance with the provisions of  this Act:</p>
              <p>Provided that the total amount which may be  recovered from the principal debtor and the surety  shall not exceed the amount decreed or which can be  decreed by the Tribunal against the principal debtor in  accordance with the provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Simplified procedure in certain cases. In the determination  of any individual debt which does not exceed five thousand rupees,--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-23.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-23.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>it shall not be necessary for the Tribunal to take down  the evidence of the witnesses in writing at length but  the Tribunal, as the examination of each witness  proceeds, shall make a memorandum of the substance of  what he deposes and such memorandum shall be written  and signed by the Tribunal and shall form part of the  record;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the decision of the Tribunal need not contain more than  the points for determination and the decision thereon.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Presumption respecting registered documents. It shall be  presumed until the contrary is proved that any document registered  under the Indian Registration Act, 1908 (16 of 1908) or any certified  copy thereof and produced before the Tribunal has been proved.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Application of Act 5 of 1908. Save as otherwise expressly  provided in this Act or in any rules made thereunder, all proceedings  under this Act shall be regulated by the provisions contained in the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Signing and verification of applications and written  statements. Every application and the schedules, if any, attached  thereto and every written statement filed before the Tribunal for any  relief under this Act shall be signed and verified in the manner  prescribed by the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), for the  signing and verification of pleadings.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Contents of decrees. In all cases in which the Tribunal  passes a decree on the application of a displaced person, it shall  prepare a complete schedule of the creditors and of the assets and  liabilities of the displaced person.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Execution of decrees. It shall be competent for the Civil</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Court which has been specified as the Tribunal for the purposes of  this Act to execute any decree or order passed by it as the Tribunal  in the same manner as it could have done if it were a decree or order  passed by it as a Civil Court.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>RELIEFS CHAPTER III</p>
              <p>RELIEFS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Cesser of accrual of interest.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-29.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On and from the 15th day  of August, 1947, no interest shall accrue or be deemed to have accrued  in respect of any debt owed by a displaced person, and no Tribunal  shall allow any future interest in respect of any decree or order  passed by it:</p>
              <blockList id="section-29.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-29.1.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>where the debt is secured by the pledge of shares,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>stocks, Government securities of a local authority, the</p>
              <blockList id="section-29.1.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Tribunal shall allow, for the period commencing from  the 15th day of August, 1947, and ending with the date  of commencement of this Act, interest to the creditor  at the rate mutually agreed upon or at a rate at which  any dividend or interest has been paid or is payable in  respect thereof, whichever is less;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-29.1.list5.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>in any other case the Tribunal may, if it thinks it  just and proper to do so after taking into account the  paying capacity of the debtor as defined in section 32,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>allow, for the period mentioned in clause (a), interest  at a rate not exceeding four per cent. per annum  simple.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in this section shall apply to the interest payable  in respect of any moneys advanced by a creditor, including an  insurance company, on the security of a policy of life insurance of a  displaced debtor in order to keep it alive.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading>Exemption from arrest. No displaced person shall be liable to  arrest or imprisonment in execution of any decree for the recovery of  any debt whether passed before or after the commencement of this Act.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading>Further reliefs in the matter of attachment of property.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-31.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Section 60 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) shall, in  relation to the execution of any decree for a debt against a displaced  person (whether passed before or after the commencement of this Act),</p>
              <p>have effect, as if--</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-31.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>for clause (c) of the proviso to sub- section (1), the  following clauses had been substituted, namely:--</p>
              <p>" (c) houses and other buildings (with the  materials and the sites thereof and the land  immediately appertaining thereto and necessary for   their enjoyment) belonging to an agriculturist and not  proved by the decree- holder to have been let out on  rent or otherwise to any person other than the father,</p>
              <p>mother, wife, son, daughter, daughter- in- law, brother,</p>
              <blockList id="section-31.1.list4">
                <listIntroduction>sister or other dependant of the judgment- debtor or to  have been left vacant for a period of one year or more;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-31.1.list4.cc">
                  <num>(cc)</num>
                  <p>milch animals, whether in milk or in calf,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-31.1.list6">
                <listIntroduction>kids, animals used for the purpose of transport or  draught cart and open spaces or enclosures belonging to  an agriculturist and required for use in case of need  for tying cattle, parking carts or stacking fodder or  manure;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-31.1.list6.ccc">
                  <num>(ccc)</num>
                  <p>one main residential house and other  buildings attached to it (with the materials and the  sites thereof and the land immediately appertaining   thereto and necessary for their enjoyment) belonging to  a judgment- debtor other than an agriculturist and  occupied by him";</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>in clause (i), for the words" hundred rupees" the words</p>
              <p>" two hundred and fifty rupees" had been substituted;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>after clause (p), the following had been inserted,</p>
              <p>namely:--</p>
              <blockList id="section-31.3.list3">
                <listIntroduction>" (q) two- thirds of the agricultural produce of the  judgment- debtor;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-31.3.list3.r">
                  <num>(r)</num>
                  <p>so much of any other property of the judgment-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-31.3.list5">
                <listIntroduction>debtor as constitutes the means of his livelihood and  as is likely, in the opinion of the Court, to yield to  him an income of not less than two hundred and fifty  rupees a month;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-31.3.list5.s">
                  <num>(s)</num>
                  <p>any loan advanced or agreed to be advanced by  or on behalf of or out of the funds of the Central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Government or a State Government, or any asset created  from any such loan;"</p>
              <p>Explanation.- Where any such asset as is referred to in clause (s)</p>
              <p>has been created partly from such loan and partly from the private  funds of the judgment- debtor, that portion of the asset which has been  created from the private funds shall, if severable from the remaining  portion, be liable to attachment or sale.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>Scaling down of debts.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-32.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where, on the application of a  displaced debtor under section 5 or sub- section (2) of section 11, the</p>
              <p>Tribunal has determined the amount due in respect of each debt in  accordance with the provisions of this Act, it shall proceed to  determine the paying capacity of the debtor.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the paying capacity of the debtor is equal to or exceeds  the aggregate sum of all the debts so determined (exclusive of any  debt in respect of which the creditor has elected to retain the   security in accordance with the provisions of section 16), the</p>
              <p>Tribunal shall pass a decree for the aggregate sum so determined,</p>
              <p>specifying the amount due to each creditor and shall allow repayment  thereof in instalments, in accordance with the provisions contained in  section 33, unless for reasons to be recorded it directs otherwise.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the paying capacity of the debtor is less than the  aggregate sum referred to in sub- section (2), the Tribunal shall  divide the decree into two parts and provide in the first part thereof</p>
              <p>(hereinafter referred to as the first part of the decree) that the sum  equivalent to the paying capacity shall, subject to the provisions  contained in section 33, be realised from the assets of the debtor in</p>
              <p>India, and provide in the</p>
              <p>second part thereof (hereinafter referred to as the second part of the   decree) that the balance shall be realised, subject to the provisions  contained in sub- section (6), from any compensation which the debtor  may receive:</p>
              <p>Provided that if no such compensation is received, the balance  shall be irrecoverable.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A creditor who has elected to retain his security under  section 16 shall have no right to realise any money due to him from  the assets of the debtor in India, but nothing in this sub- section  shall affect any of the rights given to him by section 16.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A creditor shall have the right at any time at least six  months before the receipt by the debtor of compensation to apply that  the whole or the balance of the first part of the decree, in so far as  any debt due to him is concerned, may be added to the second part of  the decree, and thereupon he shall have no right to realise any money  from the assets of the debtor in India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purposes of this Act, the amount payable from the  compensation for the satisfaction of the second part of the decree  shall be that amount as bears to the aggregate amount of all the debts  in the second part of the decree including therein any sum added to  it under sub- section (5) and the sum determined in favour of the  secured creditor in the manner specified in the proviso to clause (a)</p>
              <blockList id="section-32.6.list2">
                <listIntroduction>of sub- section (3) of section 16 as the compensation in respect of  the property of the debtor payable to him under the Displaced Persons</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.6.list2.Claims">
                  <num>(Claims)</num>
                  <p>Act, 1950 (44 of 1950) bears to the verified claim; and the  balance of the compensation, if any, shall be refunded to the  displaced debtor.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every instalment paid by the displaced debtor in respect of  the first part of the decree and any sum payable from the compensation  in accordance with sub- section (6) shall be distributed rateably  amongst the decree- holders, if more persons than one are entitled  thereto:</p>
              <p>Provided that the secured creditor who has not elected to be  treated as an unsecured creditor under section 16 shall be entitled to  a prior charge on the amount payable from the compensation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where a displaced person receives compensation by way of  exchange of property, then, subject to the prior charge, if any, of a  creditor under section 16, the aggregate sum payable in respect of the  second part of the decree shall be a second charge upon the property  received by way of exchange, but the amount of the second charge shall  be that amount as bears to the total sum the same proportion as the  value of the property received by way of exchange bears to the</p>
              <p>value of the original property verified and valued under the Displaced</p>
              <p>Persons (Claims) Act, 1950 (44 of 1950).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where a displaced person makes a default in the payment of  any instalment fixed in respect of the first part of the decree or  does not pay the amount determined in accordance with sub- section (4)</p>
              <p>of section 16 or sub- section (8) of this section for which the first  or the second charge may have been created upon the property received  by way of exchange, the creditor may apply for the execution of the  decree by the attachment and sale of the attachable assets of the  judgment- debtor or by the sale of the property obtained by way of  exchange upon which the charge has been created, as the case may be,</p>
              <p>and the amount realised by such execution shall be distributed  rateably among the decree- holders:</p>
              <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall affect  the rights of any charge- holders.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.10">
            <num>(10)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purposes of this Act, where the compensation is paid  in cash, the amount which shall be available for purposes of  satisfaction of the debts in the second part of the decree shall in no  case exceed seventy- five per cent. of the amount of such compensation;</p>
              <p>and where it is by way of exchange or property, the extent of the  property which shall be available for the said purposes shall in no  case exceed seventy- five per cent. in value of such property.</p>
              <p>Explanation.- In this section the expression" paying capacity"</p>
              <p>means the aggregate of the market value of all the attachable assets  in India of the displaced debtor plus the income which is likely to  accrue to him for the next three years succeeding, excluding from the  computation of such income a sum calculated at the rate of two hundred  and fifty rupees a month.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading>Matters to be taken into account in directing payment by  instalments.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-33.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-33.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In directing payment of any sums by instalments  under the first part of the decree, the Tribunal shall take into  account among other matters-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-33.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the present income of the displaced debtor from all  sources and the income that is likely to accrue to him  in future;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-33.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the size of the family dependant upon him for the  ordinary necessaries of life and the expenditure likely  to be incurred for the education and marriage of the  children of the displaced person dependant upon him.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-33.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where a displaced creditor is a minor, or a widow or a person  who, by reason of any physical disability, is permanently disabled  from</p>
              <p>earning his livelihood, the Tribunal may direct that any instalment  payable to him or her shall be twenty- five per cent. higher than what  would otherwise have been directed to be paid, and where it does so,</p>
              <p>it shall also direct that the instalments of other decree- holders  shall be proportionately reduced.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-34">
          <num>34.</num>
          <heading>Variation of maintenance allowances. Where a displaced debtor  has been ordered to pay an allowance periodically to any person for  his maintenance under any decree or order of a Court, or is liable to  pay such allowance under any agreement voluntarily entered into, the  rate at which such allowance is payable may be varied by the Tribunal  on application made to it in his behalf, if in view of the change in  the circumstances of the displaced debtor, the Tribunal thinks that  such variation is necessary, and such variation shall have effect for  such period as the Tribunal may direct, notwithstanding anything in  any decree, order or agreement to the contrary.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading>Taxation of lawyer' s fees. In directing payment of costs by  any person as costs in respect of fees to any legal practitioner  employed in any proceeding before it, the Tribunal shall be guided by  any rules for the time being in force regulating the payment of such  costs in proceedings of a similar nature before the ordinary Civil</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-35.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Courts, and shall not award more than one- half of what in its opinion  the costs before the Civil court would have been.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-36">
          <num>36.</num>
          <heading>Extension of period of limitation. Notwithstanding anything  contained in the Indian Limitation Act, 1908 (9 of 1908) or in any  special or local law or in any agreement,--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-36.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-36.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-36.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>any suit or other legal proceeding in respect whereof  the period of limitation was extended by section 8 of  the Displaced Persons (Institution of Suits) Act, 1948</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-36.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>(47 of 1948), and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-36.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>any suit or other legal proceeding for the enforcement  of a claim against an insurance company not falling  within the provisions of clause (a) in respect whereof  the cause of action had arisen, whether wholly or in  part, in the territories now situate in West Pakistan  and the institution of the suit or other legal  proceeding has become barred by reason of a condition  in the contract, which, but for the condition, would  have been governed by the provisions obtained in clause</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-36.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>may be instituted at any time within one year from the commencement of  this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-37">
          <num>37.</num>
          <heading>Curtailment of period of limitation for execution of certain  decrees. Notwithstanding anything contained in section 48 of the Code  of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), or in any other law for the time  being in force, no order for the execution of a decree in respect of a  debt against a displaced person shall be made upon an application  presented after the expiration of--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-37.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-37.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-37.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>in the case of decrees passed before the commencement  of this Act, six years from such commencement;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-37.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>in the case of decrees passed after the commencement of  this Act, six years from the date of the decrees;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-37.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>in the case of decrees directing payment of money to be  made at prescribed intervals or on certain dates, six  years from the date of default in making the payment in  respect of which the decree- holder seeks to have the  decree executed:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that nothing in this section shall be construed as  extending the limit of time for execution as provided in section 48 of  the said Code for an application for the execution of a decree passed  before the commencement of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-38">
          <num>38.</num>
          <heading>Sale of immovable property in execution.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-38.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where in the  execution of any decree for the recovery of a debt against a displaced  person his immovable property is sought to be sold, the Court  executing the decree shall, in the first instance, determine the  market value of the property and, if the value so determined is less  than or equal to the amount of the decree together with the  proportionate amount of any prior encumbrance, the Court shall  transfer the property to the decree- holder.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-38.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the value determined under sub- section (1) is greater than  the amount of the decree together with the proportionate amount of any  prior encumbrance, the Court shall determine the portion of such  property the value of which is equal to the amount of the decree with  proportionate amount of such prior encumbrance, and may, if it is  reasonable or convenient to do so, transfer that portion to the  decree- holder.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-38.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where any property is transferred under the provisions  of this section to the decree- holder, the decree shall be deemed to be  satisfied to the extent of the value of the property so transferred:</p>
              <p>Provided that if the decree- holder does not desire to take the  property or, in the opinion of the Court, it is not reasonable or  convenient</p>
              <p>to transfer the property to him, the property may be sold by public  auction, but irrespective of the price fetched at the public auction  the market value of the property as determined under this section (and  not the amount payable to the decree- holder out of the sale proceeds   of the public auction) shall be deemed to be the amount which has been  paid to the decree- holder in respect of the decree, and satisfaction  thereof shall be entered accordingly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-39">
          <num>39.</num>
          <heading>Encouragement of settlements. If the displaced debtor and the  creditor or, where there are more creditors than one, such number  thereof as hold more than two- thirds in value of the debts due from  the displaced debtor enter into an agreement for the adjustment of the  liabilities, the Tribunal shall, if an application is made to it in  this behalf, after giving due notice to the other creditors affected,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-39.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>adjust the remaining debts accordingly if the terms of the agreement  are just and fair, and pass a decree accordingly.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>APPEALS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>APPEALS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-40">
          <num>40.</num>
          <heading>General provisions relating to appeals. Save as otherwise  provided in section 41, an appeal shall lie from--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-40.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-40.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-40.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>any final decree or order of the Tribunal, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-40.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>any order made in the course of execution of any decree  or order of the Tribunal, which if passed in the course  of execution of a decree or order of a Civil Court  would be appealable under the Code of Civil Procedure,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1908">
          <num>1908.</num>
          <heading>(5 of 1908).</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-1908.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>to the High Court within the limits of whose jurisdiction the Tribunal  is situate.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-41">
          <num>41.</num>
          <heading>Restrictions on right of appeal in certain cases.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-41.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in section 40, where the subject-</p>
              <p>matter of the appeal relates to the amount of a debt and such amount  on appeal is less than rupees five thousand, no appeal shall lie.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-42">
          <num>42.</num>
          <heading>Parties to appeals. For the purpose of any appeal under this</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-42.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Act, it shall be sufficient if only such persons as, in the opinion of  the appellant, are necessary parties to the appeal for the purpose of  determining the real questions in controversy between them, are  impleaded as respondents to the appeal:</p>
              <p>Provided that where it appears to the High Court at the hearing  that any person who was a party to the proceeding before the Tribunal</p>
              <p>from whose decree the appeal is preferred but who has not been made a  party to the appeal is interested in the result of the appeal, the</p>
              <p>Court may adjourn the hearing to a future date to be fixed by the</p>
              <p>Court and direct that such person be made a respondent.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-V.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-43">
          <num>43.</num>
          <heading>Registration of certain societies and companies under Indian  law.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-43.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where the registered office of any society or company  registered before the 15th day of August, 1947, under the Societies</p>
              <p>Registration Act, 1860 (21 of 1860), or the Co- operative Societies</p>
              <p>Act, 1912 (2 of 1912), or under any other law then in force in any</p>
              <p>Province for the registration of co- operative societies or the Indian</p>
              <p>Companies Act, 1913 (7 of 1913), is situated in the territory now  forming part of West Pakistan but a majority of its members for the  time being are resident in India, or, in the case of a company, more  than thirty- three and one- third per cent. of its shares in value are  being held by persons resident in India, the society, or company, as  the case may be, may apply within one year from the commencement of  this Act to the Registrar of Societies, Co- operative Societies or</p>
              <p>Companies, as the case may be, within the local limits of whose  jurisdiction the majority of the members of the governing body reside  or carry on business, for the recognition of the society or company as  such in India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-43.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Registrar, after making such inquiry into the matter as  he deems fit, may either accord such recognition or refuse to do so.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-43.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An appeal shall lie from the order of the Registrar under  sub- section (2) to the State Government and no order passed by the</p>
              <p>Registrar or by the State Government on appeal shall be called in  question in any Court.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-43.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where the Registrar accords recognition to a society, co-</p>
              <p>operative society or company, he shall cause necessary entries thereof  to be made in his register and thereupon, notwithstanding anything to  the contrary contained in any law for the time being in force or in  any instrument, the society or the company, as the case may be, shall  be deemed to have been formed and registered under the relevant law as  in force in India, and every such society or company shall, among  other matters, have the right to demand and receive any moneys due to  it from any person residing or carrying on business in India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-44">
          <num>44.</num>
          <heading>Bar of further applications in certain cases. Subject to the  other provisions contained in this Act, where an application made by a  displaced debtor under section 5 or under</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-44.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>sub- section (2) of section 11, or by a displaced creditor under  section 13 has been dismissed, no further application for the same  purpose shall lie.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-45">
          <num>45.</num>
          <heading>Amendment of applications. Clerical or arithmetical mistakes  in any application or in any schedule annexed thereto arising from any  accidental slip or omission may at any time be corrected by the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-45.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Tribunal, either of its own motion or on the application of any of the  parties.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-46">
          <num>46.</num>
          <heading>Service of notices. Every notice issued under this Act shall  be served by registered post, acknowledgment due, unless the Tribunal  for reasons to be recorded, directs service in any of the other modes  specified in Order V of the First Schedule to the Code of Civil</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-46.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-47">
          <num>47.</num>
          <heading>Effect of failure on the part of displaced debtor to disclose  certain matters. Where a displaced debtor has not mentioned in the  relevant schedule to his application any debt owing by him or any  property, movable or immovable, belonging to him, whether such  property is liable to attachment or not liable to attachment at all,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-47.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-47.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>nothing contained in this Act shall prevent--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-47.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>in the case of the debt, the creditor from instituting  any proceeding for the recovery thereof under any law  for the time being in force other than this Act; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-47.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>in the case of the property, from being attached or  otherwise dealt with under any such law.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-48">
          <num>48.</num>
          <heading>Proceedings not to abate on death of debtor. Notwithstanding  anything contained in this Act, no proceeding before a Tribunal shall  be deemed to abate by reason merely of the death of the debtor who is  a party to the proceeding, and a decree may be passed notwithstanding  the death and such decree shall have the same force and effect as if  it had been passed before the death took place:</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-48.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Provided that the Tribunal on an application made in that behalf,</p>
              <p>shall cause the legal representative of the deceased debtor to be made  a party to the proceeding, and any person so made a party may make any  defence appropriate to his character as legal representative of the  deceased debtor:</p>
              <p>Provided further that nothing contained herein shall be deemed to  render the legal representative of the deceased debtor liable to  satisfy the decree except to the extent to which any of the assets of  the deceased debtor have devolved on him.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-49">
          <num>49.</num>
          <heading>Past transactions not to be affected.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-49.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If before the  commencement of this Act a displaced debtor has satisfied or  discharged any of his liabilities in any manner whatsoever, such  transactions shall not be affected by anything contained in this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-49.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where the Tribunal has determined the amount due in respect  of any debt in accordance with the provisions of this Act, any  payments (including payments by way of interest) made by the displaced  debtor towards the debt prior to such determination shall be adjusted  towards the amount so determined:</p>
              <p>Provided that no creditor shall be called upon to refund any  amount paid to him if it is found that it is in excess of the amount  determined as being due to him under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-50">
          <num>50.</num>
          <heading>Displaced debtor not to be deemed insolvent. Notwithstanding  anything contained in any law for the time being in force relating to  insolvency, no displace debtor shall be deemed to be insolvent or to  have been adjudicated as such within the meaning of any law for the  time being in force relating to insolvency by reason only of his  applying to get his debts adjusted under this Act, and no petition in  insolvency shall lie against a displaced debtor in respect of any debt  incurred by him before the 15th day of August, 1947.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-51">
          <num>51.</num>
          <heading>Compromises or arrangements between banks and their debtors  not to be reopened in certain cases. Notwithstanding anything  contained in this Act, no compromise or arrangement arrived at,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-51.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>whether before or after the commencement of this Act, between a  displaced debtor and a bank relating to the repayment, discharge or  satisfaction of any debt owing by the displaced debtor to the bank  shall be reopened by the Tribunal, and nothing contained in this Act  shall affect any such compromise or arrangement:</p>
              <p>Provided that there is in force in respect of the bank a  compromise or arrangement between it and its own creditors or any  class of such creditors which has been duly sanctioned by the Court  under section 153 of the Indian Companies Act, 1913 (7 of 1913): and</p>
              <blockList id="section-51.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Provided further that the particulars specified in clauses (c),</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-51.paragraph-0.list3.cc">
                  <num>(cc)</num>
                  <p>, (ccc), (i), (q), (r), and (s) of the proviso to sub- section (1)</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>of section 60 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), as  amended by section 31 of this Act, shall not be liable to attachment  or sale in any proceeding against the displaced debtor.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-52">
          <num>52.</num>
          <heading>Communication of contents of decrees to prescribed authority.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-52.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every Tribunal shall communicate to the prescribed authority, in  such manner as may be prescribed, the amount of the prior</p>
              <p>charge declared under sub- section (3) of section 16, and shall also  forward to it a copy of the decree passed on the application of a  displaced debtor under section 5 or sub- section (2) of section 11 and  also of any order passed under sub- section (5) of section 32,</p>
              <p>specifying the amount due to the creditor mentioned therein on the  date of the order.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-52.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The prescribed authority shall scale down the debts reported  to him in accordance with sub- section (6) of section 32 and shall,</p>
              <p>subject to any rules made in this behalf, meet the prior charge of the  secured creditor in accordance with sub- section (2) of section 16 in  the first instance and thereafter distribute the balance of the  compensation available for distribution within the meaning of sub-</p>
              <p>section (10) of section 32 rateably amongst the other decree- holders  whose decrees have been reported to him:</p>
              <p>Provided that in making any such rateable distribution the  prescribed authority shall have due regard to the provisions contained  in sub- section (2) of section 33.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-52.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The balance from the amount of the compensation payable shall  be refunded to the displaced debtor.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-52.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any amount paid by the prescribed authority to any decree-</p>
              <p>holder under the provisions of this section shall, to that extent, be  a valid discharge of the debt due by the displaced debtor.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-53">
          <num>53.</num>
          <heading>Application of the Limitation Act. Subject to the other  provisions contained in this Act, the Indian Limitation Act, 1908 (9   of 1908) shall apply to the institution of any proceeding under this</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-53.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Act, and, for the purpose of determining and computing the period of  limitation prescribed by that Act in relation thereto, every  application made under this Act shall be deemed to be a suit for the  purpose of that Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-54">
          <num>54.</num>
          <heading>Order XXX VIII of the First Schedule to the Code of Civil</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-54.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Procedure not to apply. Nothing contained in Order XXXVIII of the</p>
              <p>First Schedule to the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908),</p>
              <p>relating to arrest and attachment before judgment, shall apply to any  proceeding under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-55">
          <num>55.</num>
          <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-55.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Government  or any person, in respect of anything done or intended to be done by  it or him in good faith in pursuance of this Act or of any rule or  order made thereunder.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-56">
          <num>56.</num>
          <heading>Delegation of Powers. The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, direct that any power  exercisable by it under this Act may also be exercised by such officer  or authority subordinate to the Central Government or by the State</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-56.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government or by any officer or authority subordinate to the State</p>
              <p>Government as may be specified in the direction.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-57">
          <num>57.</num>
          <heading>Power of Central Government to make rules.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-57.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central</p>
              <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules   for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-57.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-57.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the  provisions contained in sub- section (1), the rules so made may provide  for all or any of the following matters, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-57.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the additional particulars, if any, which an  application under section 5, should contain;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-57.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the form in which notices under this Act may be issued;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-57.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the form in which applications under section 10 or  section 13 may be made;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-57.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the registers which should be maintained under this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-57.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-57.2.list3.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the authorities required to be prescribed under this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-57.2.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-57.2.list5.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the board or other authority to which any report under  sub- section (2) of section 18 may be made and the  matters which such board or other authority should take  into account in making its report.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-58">
          <num>58.</num>
          <heading>Power of State Government to make rules. The State Government  may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules providing  for--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-58.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-58.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-58.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the distribution of business amongst the various</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-58.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Tribunals within the State;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-58.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which copies of documents produced before  the Tribunals should be certified;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-58.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the returns to be made by the Tribunals and the  authorities to which they may be so made.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-58A">
          <num>58A.</num>
          <heading>Laying of rules.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-58A.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made by the State</p>
              <p>Government under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is  made, before the State Legislature.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-58A.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act  shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House  of Parliament while it is in session, for a total period of thirty  days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more  successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session  immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or  both Houses agree that thereafter have effect only in such modified  form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any  such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the  validity of anything previously done under that rule.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-59">
          <num>59.</num>
          <heading>Repeals. Save as otherwise provided in section 36, the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-59.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Displaced Persons (Institution of Suits) Act, 1948 (47 of 1948) and  the Displaced Persons (Legal Proceedings) Act, 1949 (25 of 1949) shall  cease to apply to displaced persons as defined in this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
