<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1956/40/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1956/40"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Bihar And West Bengal (Transfer Of Territories) Act, 1956"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1956/40/eng@1956-09-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1956/40/eng@1956-09-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1956-09-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1956/40/eng@1956-09-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1956/40/eng@1956-09-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Bihar And West Bengal (Transfer Of Territories) Act, 1956</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 40 OF 1956</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 1st September, 1956.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Seventh Year of the Republic  of India as follows:--</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the transfer of certain territories from</p>
        <p>Bihar to West Bengal and for matters connected therewith.</p>
        <p>PART</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <part id="part-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="part-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title. This Act may be called the Bihar and West Bengal</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>(Transfer of Territories) Act, 1956.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" appointed day" means the 1st day of November, 1956;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" article" means an article of the Constitution;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" assembly constituency"," council constituency" and</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>" parliamentary constituency" have the same meanings as  in the Representation of the People Act, 1950 (43 of</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1950">
          <num>1950.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1950.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>);</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" Election Commission" means the Election Commission  appointed by the President under article 324;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>" law" includes any enactment, ordinance, regulation,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>order, bye- law, rule, scheme, notification or other  instrument having the force of law in the whole or in  any part of Bihar or West Bengal;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list3.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>" notified order" means an order published in the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Official Gazette;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list5.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>" population ratio" means such ratio as the Central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list7">
                <listIntroduction>Government may, by notified order, specify to be the  ratio between the population as ascertained at the last  census of the State of Bihar excluding the transferred  territories and the population as so ascertained of the  transferred territories;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list7.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list9">
                <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list9.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>" sitting member" in relation to either House of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Parliament or of the Legislature of a State means a  person who,</p>
              <blockList id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list12">
                <listIntroduction>immediately before the appointed day, is a member of  that House;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list12.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>" transferred territories" means the territories  transferred from the State of Bihar to the State of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list14">
                <listIntroduction>West Bengal by section 3;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list14.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>" treasury" includes a sub- treasury.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>TRANSFER OF TERRITORIES</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="part-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>TRANSFER OF TERRITORIES</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Transfer of territories from Bihar to West Bengal.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>As from  the appointed day, there shall be added to the State of West Bengal  the territories which on the 1st day of March, 1956, were comprised  in--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>that portion of Kishanganj sub- division of Purnea  district which lies to the east of the boundary line  demarcated in accordance with the provisions of sub-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>section (2) by an authority appointed in this behalf by  the Central Government and that portion of Gopalpur  thana of the said district which lies to the east or  north, as the case may be, of the said boundary line;</p>
              <blockList id="section-3.1.list4">
                <listIntroduction>and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.1.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>Purulia sub- division of Manbhum district, excluding Chas  thana, Chandil thana and Patamda police station of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Barabhum thana;</p>
              <p>and the said territories shall thereupon cease to form part of the</p>
              <p>State of Bihar.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The boundary line referred to in sub- section (1) shall be so  demarcated as to be generally two hundred yards to the west of the  highway in Purnea district connecting Dalkola, Kishanganj and Chopra  with Siliguri in Darjeeling district and two hundred yards to the  south or south- west of the highway in Purnea district connecting</p>
              <p>Dalkola and Karandighi with Raiganj in West Dinajpur district:</p>
              <p>Provided that the boundary line shall be so demarcated as not to  cut across any village or town:</p>
              <p>Provided further that from the point where the first- mentioned  highway meets the southern boundary of Kishanganj municipality to the  point where it leaves the northern boundary of that municipality, the  boundary line shall be the same as the boundary of that municipality  on the east.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The territory specified in clause (a) of sub- section (1)</p>
              <p>shall be included in, and form part of, Darjeeling district, and the  territory specified in clause (b) of that sub- section shall form a  separate</p>
              <p>district to be known as Purulia district within Burdwan division of  the State of West Bengal.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in sub- section (3) shall be deemed to affect the  power of the State Government to alter after the appointed day the  name, extent and boundaries of any district or division in the State  of West Bengal.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Amendment of First Schedule to the Constitution. As from the  appointed day, in the First Schedule to the Constitution, in Part A,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>in the description of the territories of States,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>after the paragraph relating to the territory of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>State of Assam, the following paragraphs shall be  inserted, namely:--</p>
              <p>" The territory of the State of Bihar shall  comprise the territories which immediately before  the commencement of this Constitution were either  comprised in the Province of Bihar or were being  administered as if they formed part of that</p>
              <p>Province, but shall not include the territories  specified in sub- section (1) of section 3 of the</p>
              <p>Bihar and West Bengal (Transfer of Territories)</p>
              <p>Act, 1956.</p>
              <p>The territory of the State of West Bengal  shall comprise the territories which immediately  before the commencement of this Constitution were  either comprised in the Province of West Bengal or  were being administered as if they formed part of  that Province and the territory of Chandernagore  as defined in clause (c) of section 2 of the</p>
              <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list9">
                <listIntroduction>Chandernagore (Merger) Act, 1954, and also the  territories specified in sub- section (1) of  section 3 of the Bihar and West Bengal (Transfer   of Territories) Act, 1956.";</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list9.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>in the last paragraph, the words, brackets, letter and  figures" and in the case of the State of West Bengal,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list11">
                <listIntroduction>shall also comprise the territory of Chandernagore as  defined in clause (c) of section 2 of the Chandernagore</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list11.Merger">
                  <num>(Merger)</num>
                  <p>Act, 1954," shall be omitted.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>REPRESENTATION IN THE LEGISLATURES</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="part-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>REPRESENTATION IN THE LEGISLATURES</p>
            <p>Council of States</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Amendment of Fourth Schedule to the Constitution. As from the  appointed day, in the Fourth Schedule to the Constitution, in the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Table of Seats, for the entries in the second</p>
              <p>column relating to Bihar and West Bengal, the entries" 22" and" 16"</p>
              <p>shall, respectively, be substituted.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>By- elections to fill vacancies in the Council of States. As  soon as may be after the appointed day, by- elections shall be held to  fill the vacancies existing on that day in the seats allotted to Bihar  and West Bengal.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Term of office of members of the Council of States. In order  that, as nearly as may be, one- third of the members of the Council of</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>States may retire on the 2nd day of April, 1958, and on the expiration  of every second year thereafter, the President shall, after  consultation with the Election Commission, make by order such  provisions as he thinks fit in regard to the terms of office of the  members elected under section 6.</p>
              <p>House of the people</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Provision as to existing House of the People. Nothing in  section 3 shall be deemed to affect the extent of the constituency of  any sitting member of the existing House of the People from Bihar.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Legislative Assemblies</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Allocation of certain sitting members of the Bihar Legislative</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Assembly. The sitting members of the Legislative Assembly of Bihar  representing the Thakurganj, Karandighi, Para- cum- Chas and Bara- bazar-</p>
              <p>cum- Chandil constituencies shall, notwithstanding the redution in the  extent of those constituencies by the transfer of portions thereof to</p>
              <p>West Bengal, continue to be members of the legislative Assembly of</p>
              <p>Bihar; and the sitting members of that Assembly representing any other  constituency lying wholly or partly in the transferred territories  shall, as from the appointed day, be deemed to have been elected to  the Legislative Assembly of West Bengal and cease to be members of the</p>
              <p>Legislative Assembly of Bihar.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Duration of Legislative Assemblies of Bihar and West Bengal.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The changes in the composition of the Legislative Assemblies of Bihar  and West Bengal under section 9 shall not affect their duration as  provided in clause</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of article 172.</p>
              <p>Legislative Councils.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Bihar Legislative Council.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any reference in the</p>
              <p>Delimitation of Council Constituencies (Bihar) Order, 1951, to the</p>
              <p>State of Bihar, Bhagalpur division or Chota Nagpur division shall be  construed as excluding the transferred territories from that State or  division, as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every sitting member of the Legislative Council of Bihar  representing a council constituency the extent of which is altered</p>
              <p>by virtue of sub- section (1) shall, as from the appointed day, be  deemed to have been elected to the said Council by that constituency  as so altered.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>West Bengal Legislative Council.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-12.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any reference in the</p>
              <p>Delimitation of Council Constituencies (West Bengal) Order, 1951, to  the State of West Bengal, Burdwan division or Darjeeling district  shall be construed as including the transferred territories to that</p>
              <p>State, division or district, as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the Table appended to the said Order, in the entry in the  second column, against West Bengal West (Graduates) Constituency,</p>
              <p>after the word" Bankura", the word" Purulia" shall be inserted.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every sitting member of the Legislative Council of West</p>
              <p>Bengal representing a council constituency the extent of which is  altered by virtue of sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) shall, as from  the appointed day, be deemed to have been elected to the said Council  by that constituency as so altered.</p>
              <p>Delimitation of constituencies</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Allocation of seats in the House of the People and assignment  of seats to State Legislative Assemblies. The number of seats in the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>House of the People allotted to Bihar and to West Bengal and the  number of seats assigned to the Legislative Assembly of each of those</p>
              <p>States by order of the Delimitation Commission under the Delimitation</p>
              <p>Commission Act, 1952 (81 of 1952), shall be modified as follows:--</p>
              <p>Number of seats in Number of seats in  the House of the the Legislative</p>
              <p>People Assembly</p>
              <p>Bihar....... 53 318</p>
              <p>West Bengal...... 36 252</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Modification of the Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Orders. As soon as may be after the commencement of this Act, the</p>
              <p>President may, by notified order, make such modifications in the</p>
              <p>Constitution (Scheduled Castes) Order, 1950, and the Constitution</p>
              <p>(Scheduled Tribes) Order, 1950, as he thinks fit, having regard to the  transfer of territories effected by section 3.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Determination of population of Scheduled Castes and Scheduled</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Tribes.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-15.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>After the said Orders have been so modified, the  population as at the last census of the Scheduled Castes and of the</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </part>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-scheduled">
      <doc name="scheduled">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1956/40/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1956/40"/>
              <FRBRalias value="Tribes in Bihar and West Bengal shall be ascertained or  estimated by the census authority in such manner as may be prescribed  and shall be notified by that authority in the Gazette of India."/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1956/40/eng@1956-09-01/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1956/40/eng@1956-09-01"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1956/40/eng@1956-09-01/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1956/40/eng@1956-09-01"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduled">
            <subsection id="scheduled.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The population figures so notified shall be taken to be the  relevant population figures as ascertained at the last census and  shall supersede any figures previously published.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <section id="section-16">
              <num>16.</num>
              <heading>Delimitation of constituencies.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-16.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-16.1.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>As soon as may be after  the commencement of this Act, the Central Government shall, by  notified order, appoint an authority--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-16.1.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>to determine on the basis of the population figures  notified under section 15 the number of seats to be  reserved for the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Tribes of Bihar and of West Bengal in the House of the</p>
                  <p>People and in the Legislative Assembly of each of those</p>
                  <p>States, having regard to the relevant provisions of the</p>
                  <blockList id="section-16.1.list6">
                    <listIntroduction>Constitution and of this Act; and</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-16.1.list6.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>to revise to such extent as may be necessary or  expedient, having regard to the said provisions, the  orders of the Delimitation Commission made under  section 8 of the Delimitation Commission Act, 1952 (81   of 1952), with respect to Bihar and West Bengal.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-16.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The said authority shall perform its functions in such manner  and shall follow such procedure, as may be prescribed.</p>
                  <p>PART</p>
                  <p>HIGH COURTS</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <part id="part-IV">
              <num>IV</num>
              <paragraph id="part-IV.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>HIGH COURTS</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-17">
                <num>17.</num>
                <heading>Extension of jurisdiction of, and transfer of proceedings to</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Calcutta High Court.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-17.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-17.1.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>Except as hereinafter provided,--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-17.1.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>the jurisdiction of the High Court at Calcutta shall, as  from the appointed day, extend to the transferred  territories; and</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-17.1.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>the High Court at Patna shall, as from that day, have no  jurisdiction in respect of the transferred territories.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-17.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Such proceedings pending in the High Court at Patna  immediately before the appointed day as are certified by the Chief</p>
                    <p>Justice of that High Court, having regard to the place of accrual of  the cause of action and other circumstances, to be proceedings which  ought to be heard and decided by the High Court at Calcutta shall, as  soon as may be after such certification, be transferred to the High</p>
                    <p>Court at Calcutta.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-17.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- sections (1) and</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-17.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>, but save as hereinafter provided, the High Court at Patna shall  have, and the High Court at Calcutta shall not have, jurisdiction to  entertain, hear or dispose of appeals, applications for leave to  appeal to the Supreme Court, applications for review and other  proceedings, where any such proceedings seek any relief in respect of  any order passed by the High Court at Patna before the appointed day:</p>
                    <p>Provided that if, after such proceedings have been entertained by  the High Court at Patna, it appears to the Chief Justice of that High</p>
                    <p>Court that they ought to be transferred to the High Court at Calcutta,</p>
                    <p>he shall order that they shall be so transferred, and such proceedings  shall thereupon be transferred accordingly.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-17.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-17.4.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>Any order made by the High Court at Patna--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-17.4.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>before the appointed day in any proceedings transferred  to the High Court at Calcutta by virtue of sub- section</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-17.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-17.2.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>; or</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-17.2.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>in any proceedings with respect to which the High Court  at Patna retains jurisdiction by virtue of sub- section</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-17.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>,</p>
                    <p>shall, for all purposes, have effect, not only as an order of the High</p>
                    <p>Court at Patna, but also as an order made by the High Court at</p>
                    <p>Calcutta.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-18">
                <num>18.</num>
                <heading>Right to appear in any proceedings transferred to Calcutta</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>High Court. Any person who immediately before the appointed day is an  advocate entitled to practise in the High Court at Patna and was  authorized to appear in any proceedings transferred from that High</p>
                    <p>Court to the High Court at Calcutta under section 17 shall have the  right to appear in the High Court at Calcutta in relation to those  proceedings.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-19">
                <num>19.</num>
                <heading>Interpretation. For the purposes of sections 17 and 18,--</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-19.paragraph-0.list0">
                      <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>proceedings shall be deemed to be pending in the High</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Court at Patna until that Court has disposed of all  issues between the parties, including any issues with  respect to the taxation of the costs of the proceedings  and shall include appeals, applications for leave to  appeal to the Supreme Court, applications for review,</p>
                    <blockList id="section-19.paragraph-0.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>petitions for revision and petitions for writs;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>references to a High Court shall be construed as  including references to a Judge or Division Court  thereof, and references to an order made by a Court or  a Judge shall be</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>construed as including references to a sentence,</p>
                    <p>judgment or decree passed or made by that Court or</p>
                    <p>Judge.</p>
                    <p>PART</p>
                    <p>AUTHORIZATION OF EXPENDITURE</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
            </part>
            <part id="part-V">
              <num>V</num>
              <paragraph id="part-V.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>AUTHORIZATION OF EXPENDITURE</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-20">
                <num>20.</num>
                <heading>Appropriation of moneys for expenditure in transferred</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Appropriation Acts.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-20.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>As from the appointed day, any Act passed by  the Legislature of West Bengal before that day for the appropriation  of any money out of the Consolidated Fund of the State to meet any  expenditure in respect of any part of the financial year 1956- 57 shall  have effect also in relation to the transferred territories, and it  shall be lawful for the State Government to spend any amount in those  territories out of the amount authorized by such Act to be expended  for any service in that State.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-20.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Governor of West Bengal may, after the appointed day,</p>
                    <p>authorize such expenditure from the Consolidated Fund of the State as  he deems necessary for any purpose or service in the transferred  territories for any period not extending beyond the 31st day of March,</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-1957">
                <num>1957.</num>
                <heading/>
              </section>
              <section id="section-21">
                <num>21.</num>
                <heading>Distribution of revenues. Section 3 of the Union Duties of</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Excise (Distribution) Act, 1953, (3 of 1953.) and paragraphs 3, 4 and</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-5">
                <num>5.</num>
                <heading>of the Constitution (Distribution of Revenues) Order, 1953, shall,</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>in respect of the financial year 1956- 57 have effect subject to such  modifications as the President may, by notified order, specify having  regard to the transfer of territories effected by section 3 of this</p>
                    <p>Act.</p>
                    <p>PART</p>
                    <p>APPORTIONMENT OF ASSETS AND LIABILITIES</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
            </part>
            <part id="part-VI">
              <num>VI</num>
              <paragraph id="part-VI.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>APPORTIONMENT OF ASSETS AND LIABILITIES</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-22">
                <num>22.</num>
                <heading>Land and goods.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-22.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Subject to the other provisions of this</p>
                    <p>Part, all land and all stores, articles and other goods in the  transferred territories belonging to the State of Bihar shall, as from  the appointed day, pass to the State of West Bengal.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-22.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Any unissued stores of any class in Bihar shall be divided  between West Bengal and Bihar in proportion to the total indents for  stores of that class made in the period of three years ending with the</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-31st">
                <num>31st.</num>
                <heading>day of March, 1956, for the transferred territories and for the  rest of Bihar:</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-31st.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Provided that nothing in this sub- section shall apply to stores  held for specific purposes such as use or utilisation in particular</p>
                    <p>institutions, workshops or undertakings or on particular works under  construction.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-31st.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>In this section, the expression" land" includes immovable  property of every kind and any rights in or over such property and the  expression" goods" does not include coins, bank notes and currency  notes.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-23">
                <num>23.</num>
                <heading>Treasury and bank balances. The total of the cash balances in  all treasuries of Bihar and the credit balances of Bihar with the</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Reserve Bank of India immediately before the appointed day shall be  divided between that State and West Bengal according to the population  ratio:</p>
                    <p>Provided that for the purposes of such division, there shall be  no transfer of cash balances from any treasury to any other treasury  and the apportionment shall be effected by adjusting the credit  balances of Bihar and West Bengal in the books of the Reserve Bank of</p>
                    <p>India on the appointed day.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-24">
                <num>24.</num>
                <heading>Arrears of taxes. The right of Bihar to recover arrears of  any tax or duty on property situate in the transferred territories,</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>including land revenue, shall belong to West Bengal and the right of</p>
                    <p>Bihar to recover arrears of any other tax or duty in any case where  the place of assessment of that tax or duty is in the transferred  territories shall also belong to West Bengal.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-25">
                <num>25.</num>
                <heading>Right to recover loans and advances. The right to recover any  loans or advances made before the appointed day by Bihar to any local  body, society, agriculturist or other person in the transferred  territories shall belong to West Bengal.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-26">
                <num>26.</num>
                <heading>Credits in certain funds. The investments in the cash balance  investments account, the famine relief fund and the general fund of</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Bihar and the sums at the credit of Bihar in the central road fund  shall be divided between Bihar and West Bengal according to the  population ratio; and the investments in any special fund the objects  of which are confined to the transferred territories or any part  thereof shall pass to West Bengal.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-27">
                <num>27.</num>
                <heading>Assets and liabilities of State undertakings.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-27.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The assets  and liabilities relating to any commercial or industrial undertaking  of Bihar located in the transferred territories shall pass to West</p>
                    <p>Bengal.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-27.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Where a depreciation reserve fund is maintained by Bihar for  any such commercial or industrial undertaking, the securities</p>
                    <p>held in respect of investments made from that fund shall also pass to</p>
                    <p>West Bengal.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-28">
                <num>28.</num>
                <heading>Public debt.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-28.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The public debt of Bihar attributable to  loans raised by the issue of Government securities and outstanding  with the public immediately before the appointed day shall continue to  be the debt of Bihar:</p>
                    <blockList id="section-28.1.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>Provided that--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-28.1.list2.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>West Bengal shall be liable to pay to Bihar a share of  the sums due from time to time for the servicing and  repayment of the public debt; and</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-28.1.list2.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>for the purpose of determining the said share, the said  debt shall be deemed to be divided between Bihar and</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>West Bengal as if it were a debt referred to in sub-</p>
                    <p>section (2).</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-28.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The public debt of Bihar attributable to loans taken from the</p>
                    <p>Central Government, the Reserve Bank of India or any other bank before  the appointed day shall be divided between Bihar and West Bengal in  proportion to the total expenditure on all capital works and other  capital outlays incurred up to the appointed day in the territories of</p>
                    <p>Bihar excluding the transferred territories and in the transferred  territories, respectively:</p>
                    <p>Provided that for the purposes of such division, only expenditure  on assets for which capital accounts have been kept shall be taken  into account.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-28.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Where a sinking fund or depreciation fund is maintained by</p>
                    <p>Bihar for the repayment of any loan raised by it, the securities held  in respect of investments made from that fund shall be divided between</p>
                    <p>Bihar and West Bengal in the same proportion as the public debt  referred to in sub- section (2).</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-28.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>In this section, the expression" Government security" means a  security created and issued for the purpose of raising a public loan  and having any of the forms specified or prescribed under clause (2)</p>
                    <p>of section 2 of the Public Debt Act, 1944 (18 of 1944).</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-29">
                <num>29.</num>
                <heading>Refund of taxes collected in excess. The liability of Bihar  to refund any tax or duty on property situate in the transferred  territories, including land revenue, collected in excess shall be the  liability of West Bengal and the liability of Bihar to refund any  other tax or duty collected in excess in any case where the place of  assessment of that tax or duty is in the transferred territories shall  also be the liability of West Bengal.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-30">
                <num>30.</num>
                <heading>Deposits. The liability of Bihar in respect of any civil  deposit or local fund deposit made in the transferred territories  shall, as from the appointed day, be the liability of West Bengal.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-31">
                <num>31.</num>
                <heading>Provident Funds. The liability of Bihar in respect of the  provident fund account of any Government servant who, being in service  on the appointed day, is permanently allotted to West Bengal shall, as  from that day, be the liability of West Bengal.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-32">
                <num>32.</num>
                <heading>Pensions. The liability of Bihar in respect of pensions shall  be apportioned between that State and West Bengal in accordance with  the provisions contained in the Schedule.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-33">
                <num>33.</num>
                <heading>Contracts.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-33.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Where, before the appointed day, the State of</p>
                    <blockList id="section-33.1.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>Bihar has made any contract in the exercise of its executive power for  any purposes of the State, that contract shall be deemed to have been  made in the exercise of the executive power--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-33.1.list2.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>of Bihar, if the purposes of the contract are, as from  the appointed day, exclusively purposes of that State;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-33.1.list2.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>of West Bengal, if the purposes of the contract are, as  from that day, exclusively purposes of that State; and</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-33.1.list2.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>of Bihar, in any other case;</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>and all rights and liabilities which have accrued, or may accrue,</p>
                    <p>under any such contract shall, to the extent to which they would have  been rights or liabilities of Bihar, be rights or liabilities of Bihar  or of West Bengal, as the case may be:</p>
                    <p>Provided that, in any such case as is referred to in clause (c),</p>
                    <p>the initial allocation of rights and liabilities made by this sub-</p>
                    <p>section shall be subject to such financial adjustment as may be agreed  upon between the two States, or in default of such agreement, as the</p>
                    <p>Central Government may by order direct.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-33.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-33.2.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>For the purposes of this section, there shall be deemed to be  included in the liabilities which have accrued or may accrue under any  contract--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-33.2.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>any liability to satisfy an order or award made by any</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-33.2.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>Court or other tribunal in proceedings relating to the  contract; and</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-33.2.list3.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>any liability in respect of expenses incurred in or in  connection with any such proceedings.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-33.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>This section shall have effect subject to the other  provisions of this part relating to the apportionment of liabilities  in respect of loans, guarantees and other financial obligations; and  bank balances and securities shall, notwithstanding that they partake  of the nature of contractual rights, be dealt with under those  provisions.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-34">
                <num>34.</num>
                <heading>Liability in respect of actionable wrong. Where, immediately  before the appointed day, Bihar is subject to any liability in respect  of actionable wrong other than breach of contract, that liability  shall,--</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-34.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-34.paragraph-0.list0">
                      <item id="section-34.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>if the cause of action arose wholly within the  transferred territories, be a liability of West Bengal;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-34.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>if the cause of action arose wholly within the  territories of Bihar excluding the transferred  territories, be a liability of Bihar; and</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-34.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>in any other case, be initially a liability of Bihar,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>but subject to such financial adjustment as may be  agreed upon between that State and West Bengal, or in  default of such agreement, as the Central Government  may by order direct.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-35">
                <num>35.</num>
                <heading>Liability as guarantor of co- operative societies. Where,</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-35.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-35.paragraph-0.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>immediately before the appointed day, Bihar is liable as guarantor in  respect of any liability of a registered co- operative society, that  liability shall--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-35.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>if the area of the society' s operations is limited to  the transferred territories, be a liability of West</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-35.paragraph-0.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>Bengal; and</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-35.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>in any other case, continue to be a liability of Bihar.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-36">
                <num>36.</num>
                <heading>Items in suspense. If any item in suspense is ultimately  found to affect an asset or liability of the nature referred to in any  of the foregoing provisions of this Part, it shall be dealt with in  accordance with that provision.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-37">
                <num>37.</num>
                <heading>Power of the Central Government to order allocation or  adjustment in certain cases. Where either Bihar or West Bengal becomes  entitled to any property or obtains any benefits or becomes subject to  any liability, and the Central Government, on a reference made within  a period of three years from the appointed day by either of the</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-37.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>States, is of opinion that it is just and equitable that that property  or those benefits should be transferred to, or shared with, the other</p>
                    <p>State or that a contribution towards that liability should be made by  the other State, the said property or benefits shall be allocated in  such manner between the two States, or the other State shall make to  the State</p>
                    <p>subject to the liability such contribution in respect thereof, as the</p>
                    <p>Central Government may, after consultation with the two State</p>
                    <p>Government, by order determine.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-38">
                <num>38.</num>
                <heading>Certain expenditure to be charged on the Consolidated Fund.</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-38.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>All sums payable by either Bihar or West Bengal to the other State by  virtue of the provisions of this Part shall be charged on the</p>
                    <p>Consolidated Fund of the State by which such sums are payable.</p>
                    <p>PART</p>
                    <p>ADMINISTRATIVE PROVISIONS</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
            </part>
            <part id="part-VII">
              <num>VII</num>
              <paragraph id="part-VII.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>ADMINISTRATIVE PROVISIONS</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-39">
                <num>39.</num>
                <heading>State Financial Corporations.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-39.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>As from the appointed day,</p>
                    <p>the Financial Corporations constituted under the State Financial</p>
                    <p>Corporations Act, 1951 (63 of 1951), for the States of Bihar and West</p>
                    <p>Bengal shall be deemed to have been constituted for those States with  their areas as altered by the provisions of section 3.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-39.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Bihar shall be liable to pay to West Bengal on account of its  share of the paid- up capital of the Bihar State Financial Corporation  such amount as the Central Government may by order determine.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-40">
                <num>40.</num>
                <heading>Temporary provisions as to the continuance of certain  existing road transport permits.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-40.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Notwithstanding anything  contained in section 63 of the Motor Vehicles Act, 1939 (4 of 1939),</p>
                    <p>a permit granted by the State Transport Authority of Bihar or by any</p>
                    <p>Regional Transport Authority in Bihar shall, if such permit was  immediately before the appointed day valid and effective in any area  within the transferred territories, be deemed to continue to be valid  and effective in that area after that day subject to the provisions of  that Act as for the time being in force in that area; and it shall not  be necessary for any such permit to be countersigned by the State</p>
                    <p>Transport Authority of West Bengal or by any Regional Transport</p>
                    <p>Authority in West Bengal for the purpose of validating it for use in  such area:</p>
                    <p>Provided that the Central Government may, after consultation with  the State Governments, add to, amend or vary the conditions attached  to the permit by the authority by which the permit was granted.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-40.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>No toll, entrance fee or other charge of a like nature shall  be levied after the appointed day in respect of any transport vehicle  for its operations in the transferred territories under any such  permit, if such vehicle was immediately before that day exempt from</p>
                    <p>the payment of any such toll, entrance fee or other charge for its  operations beyond the boundaries of Bihar:</p>
                    <p>Provided that the Central Government may, after consultation with  both the State Governments, authorize the levy of any such toll,</p>
                    <p>entrance fee or other charge as the case may be.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-41">
                <num>41.</num>
                <heading>Provisions relating to services.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-41.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every person who  immediately before the appointed day is serving in connection with the  affairs of Bihar shall, as from that day, continue so to serve, unless  he is required by general or special order of the Central Government  to serve provisionally in connection with the affairs of West Bengal.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-41.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>As soon as may be after the appointed day, the Central</p>
                    <p>Government shall, by general or special order, determine the State to  which every person provisionally allotted to West Bengal shall be  finally allotted for service and the date from which such allotment  shall take effect or be deemed to have taken effect.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-41.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every person who is finally allotted under the provisions of  sub- section (2) to Bihar or West Bengal shall, if he is not already  serving therein, be made available for serving in that State from such  date as may be agreed upon between the two State Governments and in  default of such agreement, as may be determined by the Central</p>
                    <p>Government.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-41.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Nothing in this section shall be deemed to affect after the  appointed day the operation of the provisions of Chapter I of Part XIV</p>
                    <p>of the Constitution in relation to the determination of the conditions  of service of persons serving in connection with the affairs of Bihar  or of West Bengal:</p>
                    <p>Provided that the conditions of service applicable immediately  before the appointed day to the case of any person provisionally or  finally allotted to West Bengal under this section shall not be varied  to his disadvantage except with the previous approval of the Central</p>
                    <p>Government.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-41.5">
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Central Government may at any time before or after the  appointed day give such directions to either State Government as may  appear to it to be necessary for the purpose of giving effect to the  foregoing provisions of this section and the State Government shall  comply with such directions.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-42">
                <num>42.</num>
                <heading>Provisions as to the continuance of officers in the same  posts. Every person who, immediately before the appointed day, is  holding or discharging the duties of any post or office in connection  with the affairs of Bihar in any area within the transferred  territories shall continue to hold the same post or office in West</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-42.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Bengal, and shall be deemed as from that day to have been duly  appointed to that post or office by the Government of, or other  appropriate authority in, West Bengal:</p>
                    <p>Provided that nothing in this section shall be deemed to prevent  a competent authority, after the appointed day, from passing in  relation to any such person any order affecting his continuance in  such post or office.</p>
                    <p>PART</p>
                    <p>LEGAL AND MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
            </part>
            <part id="part-VIII">
              <num>VIII</num>
              <paragraph id="part-VIII.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>LEGAL AND MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-43">
                <num>43.</num>
                <heading>Territorial extent of laws. The provisions of section 3 shall  not be deemed to have effected any change in the territories to which  any law in force immediately before the appointed day extends or  applies, and territorial references in any such law to Bihar or West</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-43.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Bengal shall, until otherwise provided by a competent legislature or  other competent authority, be construed as meaning the territories  within that State immediately before the appointed day.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-44">
                <num>44.</num>
                <heading>Power to adapt laws. For the purpose of facilitating the  application of any law in relation to Bihar or West Bengal, the  appropriate Government may, before the expiration of one year from the  appointed day, by order make such adaptations and modifications of the  law, whether by way of repeal or amendment, as may be necessary or  expedient, and thereupon every such law shall have effect subject to  the adaptations and modifications so made until altered, repealed or  amended by a competent authority or competent legislature.</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-44.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Explanation.-- In this section, the expression" appropriate</p>
                    <p>Government" means, as respects any law relating to a matter enumerated  in the Union List, the Central Government, and as respects any other  law, the State Government.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-45">
                <num>45.</num>
                <heading>Power to construe laws. Notwithstanding that no provision or  insufficient provision has been made for the adaptation of a law made  before the appointed day, any Court, tribunal or authority, required  or empowered to enforce such law may, for the purpose of facilitating  its application in relation to Bihar or West Bengal, construe the law  in such manner, without affecting the substance, as may be necessary  or proper in regard to the matter before the Court, tribunal or  authority.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-46">
                <num>46.</num>
                <heading>Power to name authorities, etc., for exercising statutory  functions. The Government of West Bengal may, by notification in the</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-46.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Official Gazette, specify the authority, officer or person who, as  from</p>
                    <p>the appointed day, shall be competent to exercise such functions  exercisable under any law in force on that day in any part of the  transferred territories as may be mentioned in that notification, and  such law shall have effect accordingly.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-47">
                <num>47.</num>
                <heading>Legal proceedings. Where, immediately before the appointed  day, the State of Bihar is a party to any legal proceedings with  respect to any property, rights or liabilities transferred to the</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-47.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>State of West Bengal under this Act, that State shall be deemed to be  substituted for the State of Bihar as a party to those proceedings, or  added as a party thereto, as the case may be, and the proceedings may  continue accordingly.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-48">
                <num>48.</num>
                <heading>Transfer of pending proceedings.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-48.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every proceeding pending  immediately before the appointed day before a Court (other than a High</p>
                    <blockList id="section-48.1.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>Court), tribunal, authority or officer--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-48.1.list2.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>in any area which on that day remains within Bihar  shall, if it is a proceeding relating exclusively to  any part of the transferred territories, stand  transferred to the corresponding Court, tribunal,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-48.1.list4">
                      <listIntroduction>authority or officer in West Bengal; and</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-48.1.list4.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>in any area which on that day falls within the  transferred territories shall, if it is a proceeding  relating exclusively to any part of the territories  remaining within Bihar, stand transferred to the  corresponding Court, tribunal authority or officer in  that State.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-48.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>If any question arises as to whether any proceeding should  stand transferred under sub- section (1), it shall be referred to the</p>
                    <p>High Court having jurisdiction in respect of the area in which the</p>
                    <p>Court, tribunal, authority or officer before which, or before whom,</p>
                    <p>such proceeding is pending on the appointed day, is functioning and  the decision of that High Court shall be final.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-48.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-48.3.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>In this section,--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-48.3.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>" proceeding" includes any suit, case or appeal; and</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-48.3.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <blockList id="section-48.3.list1.b.list0">
                          <listIntroduction>" corresponding Court, tribunal, authority or officer" in  a State means--</listIntroduction>
                          <item id="section-48.3.list1.b.list0.i">
                            <num>(i)</num>
                            <p>the Court, tribunal, authority or officer  in which, or before whom, the proceeding would  have lain if the proceeding had been instituted  after the appointed day, or</p>
                          </item>
                          <item id="section-48.3.list1.b.list0.ii">
                            <num>(ii)</num>
                            <p>in case of doubt, such Court, tribunal,</p>
                          </item>
                        </blockList>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>authority or officer in that State as may be  determined after the appointed day by the</p>
                    <p>Government of that State, or before the appointed  day by the Government of Bihar, to be the  corresponding Court, tribunal, authority or  officer.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-49">
                <num>49.</num>
                <heading>Right of pleaders to practise in certain Courts. Any person  who, immediately before the appointed day, is enrolled as a pleader  entitled to practise in any subordinate Courts in the transferred  territories shall, for a period of six months from that day, continue  to be entitled to practise in those Courts, notwithstanding that the  whole or any part of the territories within the jurisdiction of those</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-49.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Courts has been transferred to West Bengal.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-50">
                <num>50.</num>
                <heading>Effect of provisions inconsistent with other laws. The  provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything  inconsistent therewith contained in any other law.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-51">
                <num>51.</num>
                <heading>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in  giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the President may by  order do anything not inconsistent with such provisions which appears  to him to be necessary or expedient for the purpose of removing the  difficulty.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-52">
                <num>52.</num>
                <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-52.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to give effect to the  provisions of this Act.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-52.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon  as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it  is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be  comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and  if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session  or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule, or both Houses agree that the rule should  not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such  modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however,</p>
                    <p>that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to  the validity of anything previously done under that rule.]</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
            </part>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
