<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1985/21/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1985/21"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Bhopal Gas Leak Disaster (Processing Of Claims) Act, 1985"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1985/21/eng@1985-03-29/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1985/21/eng@1985-03-29"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1985-03-29" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1985/21/eng@1985-03-29/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1985/21/eng@1985-03-29"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Bhopal Gas Leak Disaster (Processing Of Claims) Act, 1985</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 21 OF 1985</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 29th March, 1985.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty- sixth Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to confer certain powers on the Central Government to secure  that claims arising out of, or connected with, the Bhopal gas leak  disaster are dealt with speedily, effectively, equitably and to the  best advantage of the claimants and for matters incidental thereto.</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:--</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Bhopal Gas Leak Disaster (Processing of Claims) Act, 1985.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 20th day of</p>
            <p>February, 1985.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" Bhopal gas leak disaster" or" disaster" means the  occurrence on the 2nd and 3rd days of December, 1984, which  involved the release of highly noxious and abnormally dangerous  gas from a plant in Bhopal (being a plant of the Union Carbide</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>India Limited, a subsidiary of the Union Carbide Corporation,</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>U. S. A.) and which resulted in loss of life and damage to property  on an extensive scale;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>" claim" means--</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>a claim, arising out of, or connected with, the  disaster, for compensation or damages for any loss of life  or personal injury which has been, or is likely to be,</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5">
              <listIntroduction>suffered;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>a claim, arising out of, or connected with, the  disaster, for any damage to property which has been, or is  likely to be, sustained;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>a claim for expenses incurred or required to be  incurred for containing the disaster or mitigating or  otherwise coping with the effects of the disaster;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>any other claim (including any claim by way of   loss of business or employment) arising out of, or connected  with, the disaster;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" claimant" means a person entitled to make a claim;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>" Commissioner" means the Commissioner appointed under  section 6;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>" person" includes the Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>" Scheme" means a Scheme framed under section 9.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Explanation.-- For the purposes of clauses (b) and (c), where the  death of a person has taken place as a result of the disaster, the  claim for compensation or damages for the death of such person shall  be for the benefit of the spouse, children (including a child in the   womb) and other heirs of the deceased and they shall be deemed to be  the claimants in respect thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to represent claimants.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the other provisions of this Act, the Central Government  shall, and shall have the exclusive right to, represent, and act in  place of (whether within or outside India) every person who has made,</p>
            <p>or is entitled to make, a claim for all purposes connected with such  claim in the same manner and to the same effect as such person.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  provisions of sub- section (1), the purposes referred to therein  include--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>institution of any suit or other proceeding in or before  any court or other authority (whether within or outside India) or  withdrawal of any such suit or other proceeding, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>entering into a compromise.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of sub- section (1) shall apply also in  relation to claims in respect of which suits or other proceedings have  been instituted in or before any court or other authority (whether   within or outside India) before the commencement of this Act:</p>
            <p>Provided that in the case of any such suit or other proceeding  with respect to any claim pending immediately before the commencement  of this Act in or before any court or other authority outside India,</p>
            <p>the Central Government shall represent, and act in place of, or along  with, such claimant, if such court or other authority so permits.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Claimant' s right to be represented by a legal practition,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Power of Central Government. Notwithstanding anything contained in  section 3, in representing, and acting in place of, any person in  relation to any claim, the Central Government shall have due regard to  any matters which such person may require to be urged with respect to  his claim and shall, if such person so desires, permit at the expense  of such person, a legal practitioner of his choice to be associated in  the conduct of any suit or other proceeding relating to his claim.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of  discharging its functions under this Act, the Central Government shall  have the powers of a civil court while trying a suit under the Code of</p>
            <blockList id="section-5.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908.) in respect of the following  matters, namely:--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person  from any part of India and examining him on oath;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>requiring the discovery and production of any document;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>receiving evidence on affidavits;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>requisitioning any public record or copy thereof from  any court or office;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses or  documents;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list2.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>any other matter which the Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, specify.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every notification made under clause (f) of sub- section (1)</p>
            <p>shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House  of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty  days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more  successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session  immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the  notification or both Houses agree that the notification should not be  made, the notification shall thereafter have effect only in such  modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however,</p>
            <p>that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to  the validity of anything previously done under that notification.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Commissioner and other officers and employees.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the  purpose of assisting it in discharging its functions under this Act,</p>
            <p>the Central Government may appoint an officer, to be known as the</p>
            <p>Commissioner for the welfare of the victims of the Bhopal gas leak  disaster, and such other officers and employees to assist him as that</p>
            <p>Government may deem fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commissioner shall discharge such functions as may be  assigned to him by the Scheme.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commissioner and such of the officers subordinate to him  as may be authorised by the Central Government by notification in the</p>
            <p>Official Gazette in this behalf may, for the discharge of their  functions under the Scheme, exercise all or any of the powers which  the Central Government may exercise under section 5.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All officers and authorities of the Government shall act in  aid of the Commissioner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commissioner and the officers subordinate to him author-</p>
            <p>ised to discharge functions under the scheme shall be deemed to be a  civil court for the purposes of section 195 and Chapter XXVI of the  code of criminal procedure, 1973.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Power to delegate. The Central Government may, by notification  in the Official Gazette, delegate, subject to such conditions and  limitations as may be specified in the notification, all or any of its  powers under this Act (excepting the power under section 9 to frame a</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Scheme) to the Government of Madhya Pradesh or an officer of the</p>
            <p>Central Government not below the rank of a Joint Secretary to that</p>
            <p>Government or an officer of the Government of Madhya Pradesh not below  the rank of a Secretary to that Government.  or the Commmissinor]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In computing; under the Limitation Act, 1963 (36 of 1963.)</p>
            <p>or any other law for the time being in force, the period of limitation  for the purpose of instituting a suit or other proceeding for the  enforcement of a claim, any period after the date on which such claim  is registered under, and in accordance with, the provisions of the</p>
            <p>Scheme shall be excluded.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in sub- section (1) shall apply to any proceedings by  way of appeal.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Power to frame a Scheme.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government shall, for  carrying into effect the purposes of this Act, frame by notification  in the Official Gazette a Scheme as soon as may be after the  commencement of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  provisions of sub- section (1), a Scheme may provide for all or any of  the following matters, namely:--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the registration of the claims under the Scheme and all  matters connected with such registration;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the processing of the claims for securing their  enforcement and matters connected therewith;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the maintenance of records and registers in respect of  the claims;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the creation of a fund for meeting expenses in  connection with the administration of the Scheme and of the  provisions of this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the amounts which the Central Government may, after due  appropriation made by Parliament by law in that behalf, credit to  the fund referred to in clause (d) and any other amounts which  may be credited to such fund;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the utilisation, by way of disbursal (including   apportionment) or otherwise, of any amounts received in  satisfaction of the claims;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the officer (being a judicial officer of a rank not   lower than that of a District Judge) who may make such disbursal  or apportionment in the event of a dispute;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the maintenance and audit of accounts with respect to  the amounts referred to in clauses (e) and (f);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the functions of the Commissioner and other officers and  employees appointed under section 6.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Scheme framed under sub- section (1) shall be laid, as  soon as may be after it is framed, before each House of Parliament,</p>
            <p>while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be  comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and  if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session  or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the Scheme or both Houses agree that the Scheme should  not be framed, the Scheme shall thereafter have effect only in such  modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however,</p>
            <p>that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to  the validity of anything previously done under that Scheme.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Removal of doubts. For the removal of doubts, it is hereby  declared that--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any sums paid by the Government to a claimant otherwise  than by way of disbursal of the compensation or damages received  as a result of the adjudication or settlement of his claim by a  court or other authority, shall be deemed to be without prejudice  to the adjudication or settlement by such court or other  authority of his claim to receive compensation or damages in  satisfaction of his claim and shall not be taken into account by  such court or other authority in determining the amount of  compensation or damages to which he may be entitled in  satisfaction of his claim;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in disbursing under the Scheme the amount received by  way of compensation or damages in satisfaction of a claim as a  result of the adjudication or settlement of the claim by a court  or other authority, deduction shall be made from such amount of  the sums, if any, paid to the claimant by the Government before  the disbursal of such amount.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Overriding effect. The provisions of this Act and of any</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Scheme framed thereunder shall have effect notwithstanding anything  inconsistent therewith contained in any enactment other than this Act  or any instrument having effect by virtue of any enactment other than  this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Repeal and saving.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Bhopal Gas Leak Disaster</p>
            <p>(Processing of Claims) Ordinance, 1985 (1 of 1985), is hereby  repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action  taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or  taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
