<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1956/90/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1956/90"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Faridabad Development Corporation Act, 1956"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1956/90/eng@1956-12-28/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1956/90/eng@1956-12-28"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1956-12-28" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1956/90/eng@1956-12-28/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1956/90/eng@1956-12-28"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Faridabad Development Corporation Act, 1956</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 90 OF 1956</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 28th December, 1956.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Seventh Year of the Republic  of India as follows:-</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the establishment and regulation of a trading</p>
        <p>Corporation for the purpose of carrying on and promoting trade and  industry in the town of Faridabad, assisting in the rehabilitation of  displaced persons settled therein and for matters connected therewith.</p>
        <p>CHAP</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title. This Act may be called the Faridabad Development</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Corporation Act, 1956.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context  otherwiserequires,- (a)" Corporation" means the Faridabad Development</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Corpo- ration established under sec</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>ESTABLISHMENT OF THE CORPORATION</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>ESTABLISHMENT OF THE CORPORATION</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Incorporation.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>With effect from such date as the Central</p>
              <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint in  this behalf, there shall be established a Corporation by the name of  the Faridabad Development Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The said Corporation shall be a body corporate having  perpetual succession and a common seal, and shall by the said name sue  and to be sued.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Constitution of the Corporation. The Corporation shall consist  of a Chairman and such other members, being not less than four and not  more than eight, as the Central Government may, by notification in the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Term and conditions of service of members.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The term of  office and conditions of service of the Chairman and other members  shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chairman or any other member may resign his office by  writing under his hand addressed to the Central Government, but he  shall continue in office until the appointment of his successor is  notified in the Official Gazette.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A casual vacancy created by the resignation of the Chairman  or any other member under sub- section (2) or for any other reason  shall be filled by fresh appointment.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Disqualification for being appointed, or for continuing as,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>member of the Corporation. A person shall be disqualified for being  appointed or for continuing as a member of the Corporation if he has,</p>
              <p>directly or indirectly, any interest in a subsisting contract made  with, or in any work being done, for, the Corporation except as a  shareholder (other than a director) in an incorporated company:</p>
              <p>Provided that where he is a shareholder, he shall disclose to the</p>
              <p>Central Government the nature and extent of shares held by him in such  company.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Temporary absence of any member. If any member of the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Corporation is by infirmity or otherwise rendered temporarily  incapable of carrying out his duties or is absent on leave or  otherwise in circumstances not involving the</p>
              <p>vacation of his appointment, the Central Government may appoint  another person to act in his place during his absence.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Vacancies amongst members or defect in the constitution not to  invalidate acts or proceedings of the Corporation. No act or  proceeding of the Corporation shall be invalid by reason only of the  existence of any vacancy amongst its members or any defect in the  constitution thereof.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Committees of the Corporation. The Corporation may constitute  such committees for general or special purposes as the Corporation  deems necessary to carry out the purposes of this Act.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Meetings of the Corporation.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Corporation shall meet  for the transaction of business at such times and places as may be  prescribed:</p>
              <p>Provided that the Chairman may, whenever he thinks fit, and  shall, upon the written requisition of not less than two members, call  a special meeting.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chairman or, in his absence, any member chosen by the  members present from among themselves, shall preside at a meeting of  the Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All questions which come before any meeting of the</p>
              <p>Corporation shall be decided by majority of votes of the members  present, and in the case of an equality of votes, the Chairman, or in  his absence, any other person presiding, shall have a second or  casting vote.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Authentication of orders and other instruments of theCorporation. All  orders and decisions of the Corporation sha</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Appointment of Administrator and other officer of the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-12.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>There shall be an Administrator of the Corporation  who shall be appointed by the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Administrator shall be the chief executive officer of the</p>
              <p>Corporation and all other officers of the Corporation shall be  subordinate to him.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Administrator shall have the right to take part in the  discussions of the Corporation or of any of its committees but shall  not have the right to vote at the meetings of the Corporation or of  any of its committees:</p>
              <p>Provided that when one of the members of the Corporation is  appointed under sub- section (1) as the Administrator, such</p>
              <p>Administrator shall have all the rights and privileges of a member.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Corporation may appoint such other officers as it may  consider necessary for the efficient performance of its functions  under this Act.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>POWERS AND FUNCTIONS OF THE CORPORATION</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>POWERS AND FUNCTIONS OF THE CORPORATION</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>General duty of Corporation. It shall be the general duty of  the Corporation to carry on and promote trade, business and industry  in Faridabad, to assist in the rehabilitation of displaced persons  settled therein and to manage and develop the property of the Union  vested in the Corporation.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Powers of the Corporation.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Corporation may exercise  all such powers as may be necessary or expedient for the purpose of  carrying out its functions under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-14.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing  provision, such power shall include the power-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-14.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to acquire and hold such property, both movable and  immovable, as the Corporation may deem necessary for  efficiently performing its functions under this Act and  to make improvements in such property and to transfer  by way of sale, lease or otherwise any such property;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>to carry on or promote any trade, business or industry;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>to give financial or other assistance to persons to  enable them to carry on trade, business or industry in</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-14.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Faridabad primarily with a view to providing employment  to, and rehabilitating, displaced persons settled  therein;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-14.2.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>to construct or cause to be constructed residential or  other buildings and to sell or let such buildings or  cause them to be sold or let, on such terms as may be  prescribed;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.2.list3.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>to advance loans on such terms and for such purposes as  may be prescribed;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.2.list3.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>to supply or cause to be supplied, in accordance with  the law for the time being in force, electrical energy  for domestic and industrial purposes at reasonable  rates;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.2.list3.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>to take such other measures as the Corporation may deem  necessary for the rehabilitation of displaced persons  settled in Faridabad;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.2.list3.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>to take such steps as may be necessary for improving  the economic and social conditions of the inhabitants  of Faridabad.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in this section shall affect the exercise of any  power or the performance of any function by any local authority having  jurisdiction in Faridabad.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Capital of the Corporation. All non- recurring expenditure  incurred by the Central Government or the body known as the Faridabad</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Development Board for and in connection with the development of</p>
              <p>Faridabad or for any of the purposes referred to in this Act upto the  date of the establishment of the Corporation and declared to be  capital expenditure by the Central Government shall be treated as the  capital provided by the Central Government to the Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Grants and loans to the Corporation. The Central Government  may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in this behalf,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>make such grants and advance such loans to the Corporation as the</p>
              <p>Central Government may deem necessary for the performance of the  functions of the Corporation under this Act; and all grants made and  all loans advanced shall be on such terms and conditions as the</p>
              <p>Central Government may determine.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Vesting of property in the Corporation. All property, assets  and funds owned or acquired by the Central Government or purporting to  have been owned or acquired by the body known as the Faridabad</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Development Board for the purposes of the development of Faridabad or  for any of the purposes referred to in this Act before the  establishment of the Corporation shall, on such establishment, vest in  the Corporation unless the Central Government otherwise directs in  respects of any part of such property, assets or funds.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Repayment of capital and loan with interest. The Corporation  shall repay, at such intervals and on such terms as the Central</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government may determine, the amount of capital provided under section</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>and all loans advanced under section 16 with interest at such rate  as may, from time to time, be fixed by that Government and such  repayment of capital or loan or payment of interest shall be deemed to  be part of the expenditure of the Corporation.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Corporation to have rights and liabilities of the Central</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government in certain case.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-19.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All rights, liabilities and  obligations of the Central Government which, whether arising out of  any contract or otherwise, were acquired or incurred by it in  connection with any transaction for the development of Faridabad or  for any of the purposes referred to in this Act before the  establishment of the Corporation, shall be deemed to have been  acquired or incurred by the Corporation and shall be the rights,</p>
              <p>liabilities and obligations, respectively, of the Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All suits or other legal proceedings instituted or which  might but for the issue of the notification under sub- section (1) of  section 3</p>
              <p>have been instituted by or against the Central Government may be  continued or instituted by or against the Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Fund of the Corporation.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-20.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Corporation shall have its  own Fund and all receipts of the Corporation shall be carried thereto  and all payments by the Corporation shall be made therefrom.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All moneys belonging to the Fund shall be deposited in such  bank or invested in such manner as may be decided by the Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Provision for depreciation and reserve and other funds.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-21.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Corporation shall make such provision for depreciation and for  reserve and other funds as the Central Government may from time to  time direct.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-21.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The management of these funds, the sums to be carried from  time to time to the credit thereof and the application of the moneys  comprised therein shall be determined in accordance with such  directions as the Central Government may from time to time issue.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Power of the Corporation to spend. The Corporation shall have  power to spend such sums as it thinks fit for performing its functions  under this Act, and such sums shall be treated as expenditure payable  out of the Fund of the Corporation.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Budget. The Corporation shall prepare, in such form and at  such time each year as may be prescribed, a budget in respect of every  financial year next ensuing showing the estimated receipts and  expenditure, and copies thereof shall be forwarded to the Central</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Annual report. The Corporation shall prepare in such form and  at such time each year as may be prescribed an annual report giving a  true and full account of its activities during the previous financial  year and copies thereof shall be sent to the Central Government and  the Government of the State of Punjab.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Accounts and audit.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-25.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Corporation shall cause to be  maintained such books of account and other books in relation to its  accounts in such form and in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The accounts of the Corporation shall be audited at such  times and in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Amount due to the Corporation to be first charge.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-26.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law, where a loan has  been advanced to any person for the construction of a building or  where a building has been transferred to any person,</p>
              <p>the amount due to the Corporation on account of the loan or transfer  together with interest thereon shall be a first charge on the building  so constructed or transferred.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-26.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Corporation may also take such further security as it may  consider necessary for advancing any loan or for transferring any  building.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Direction. For the purposes of this Act, the Central</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government may, from time to time, give to the Corporation such  general or special directions as the Central Government thinks fit and  in the performance of the functions, the Corporation shall comply with  such directions.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Returns and reports. The Corporation shall furnish to the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Central Government such returns, statistics, accounts and other  information with respect to its property or activities as the Central</p>
              <p>Government may from time to time require.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Mode of recovery of moneys due to the Corporation. When any  money is due to the Corporation from any person, then, without  prejudice to any other mode of recovery, the Corporation may, after  giving that person an opportunity of being heard, issue a certificate  to the Collector of the amount due and the Collector shall proceed to  recover that amount in the same manner as an arrear of land revenue.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading>Delegation of powers. The Corporation may, by general or  special order in writing, delegate to the Chairman or any other member  or any officer of the Corporation, subject to such conditions and  limitations (if any) as may be specified in the order, such of its  powers and duties under this Act as it may deem necessary for the  efficient running of the day- to- day administration of the Corporation.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading>Members and officers of the Corporation to be public  servants. All members and officers of the Corporation shall, when  acting or purporting to act in pursuance of any of the provisions of  this Act, be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of  section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>Removal of disqualification for membership of Parliament. It  is hereby declared that the office of the member of the Corporation  shall not disqualify its holder for being chosen as, or for being, a  member of either House of Parliament.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading>Bar of legal proceedings. No suit or other legal proceedings  shall lie against any member or officer of the Corporation in respect  of anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in  pursuance of this Act.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-34">
          <num>34.</num>
          <heading>Validation of certain transactions. On the establishment of  the Corporation under section 3,-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-34.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-34.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-34.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>all action purporting to have been taken, and all  transactions purporting to have been made, by or with  the body known as the Faridabad Development Board</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-34.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>(including any action or transaction by which any  property, asset or right was purported to have been  acquired or any liability or obligation, whether by  contract or otherwise, was purported to have been   incurred) shall be deemed to have been validly and  lawfully taken or made by or with the Corporation as if  this Act were in force and the Corporation were in  existence on the day on which such action was taken or  transaction was made; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-34.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-34.paragraph-0.list2.b.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>in particular, and without prejudice to the generality  of the foregoing provision,--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-34.paragraph-0.list2.b.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>all property and assets vesting in the body  known as the Faridabad Development Board shall vest in  the Corporation;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-34.paragraph-0.list2.b.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>all rights, liabilities and obligations of  the body known as the Faridabad Development Board,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>whether arising out of any contract or otherwise, shall  be the rights, liabilities and obligations,</p>
              <blockList id="section-34.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>respectively, of the Corporation; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-34.paragraph-0.list5.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>all leases granted by, all contracts made  with, and all instruments executed on behalf of, the  body known as the Faridabad Development Board shall be  deemed to have been granted by, made with, or executed  on behalf of, the Corporation and shall have effect  accordingly.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading>Power to remove difficulties. If any doubt or difficulty  arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-35.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government may, by order, make such provision or give such direction,</p>
              <p>not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as may appear to it  to be necessary or expedient for the removal of the doubt or  difficulty, and the order of the Central Government, in such cases,</p>
              <p>shall be final.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-36">
          <num>36.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-36.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the  purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-36.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-36.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the term of office and other conditions of service of  members;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-36.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the terms and conditions of service of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-36.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Administrator and other officers of the Corporation;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-36.2.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>meetings of the Corporation and the procedure for  conducting business thereat;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-36.2.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the intervals at which, and the terms on which, the  capital provided or loan advanced by the Central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-36.2.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Government to the Corporation may be repaid, and the  rate at which interest may be paid on the capital  provided or loan advanced by the Central Government;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-36.2.list5.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the form and manner in which the budget and the annual  report may be prepared;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-36.2.list5.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which the accounts of the Corporation may  be maintained and audited;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-36.2.list5.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the form and manner in which returns, statistics,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>accounts and other information may be furnished to the</p>
              <blockList id="section-36.2.list8">
                <listIntroduction>Central Government;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-36.2.list8.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>any other matter which has to be, or may be, prescribed  under this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All rules made under this section shall, as soon as may be  after they are made, be laid before both Houses of Parliament.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
