<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1960/17/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1960/17"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Maharashtra State-Aid To Industries Act, 1960"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1960/17/eng@2017-02-08/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1960/17/eng@2017-02-08"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-02-08" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1960/17/eng@2017-02-08/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1960/17/eng@2017-02-08"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-02-03" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Maharashtra State-Aid To Industries Act, 1960</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[7th October, 1960.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No. 17 of 1960</p>
        <p>An Act to regulate grant of loans to Small Scale and Cottage Industries in the State of Maharashtra and for purposes connected therewith.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to regulate the grant of loans to Small Scale and Cottage Industries in the State of Maharashtra;</p>
        <p>It is hereby enacted in the Eleventh Year of the Republic of India as follows-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Maharashtra State-aid to Industries Act, 1960.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Maharashtra.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context requires otherwise,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“borrower” means a person who has received a loan under this Act and which has not been repaid in full;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“cottage industry” means an industry prescribed by rules made by the State Government, regard being had in particular to the fact that such industry is carried on by an artisan in or near this home, and the capital of which does not exceed Rs. 25,000 (or such other sum as the State Government may from time to time in such rules denote);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“industry” means the manufacture, preservation or processing of goods, or any handicraft, or industrial business or enterprise, carried on by any person;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>“loan” means a loan granted under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>“small scale industry” means any industry which has a capital investment in plant and machinery of not more than rupees seven hundred and fifty thousand, irrespective of the number of persons employed therein.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Explanation- The value of the plant and machinery for ascertaining the capital investment shall be the price paid by the borrower of such plant and machinery.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Power of State Government to grant loans to village and small scale industries.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of encouraging the economical development of the State in general, subject to such rules as may be made under section 7, loans may be granted under this Act, by such officers of the State Government as the State Government may empower in this behalf, to small scale and cottage industries.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Application for loans.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person desiring to obtain a loan under section 3 for any cottage industry, or small scale industry, shall make an application addressed to the officer empowered under that section in such form, and containing such particulars, as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The officer, on receiving an application under sub-section (1), may after making such inquiries as he thinks fit, but subject to any rules made under section 7, grant the loan applied for.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Repayment of loan.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every loan shall be repayable by instalments (in the form of annuity or otherwise) together with interest (including penal interest), if any, at such rate or rates and within such period from the date of actual advance of the loan, as may, from time to time, be prescribed by rules made under section 7:</p>
            <p>Provided that, nothing in this section shall prevent the borrower from repaying all or any of the instalments of the loan at any time earlier than the due date.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Recovery of loans.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Subject to any rules made under section 7, all loans, all interest (including any penal interest), chargeable thereon, and costs incurred in making or recovering the same, shall be recoverable when they become due, by the collector, or such officer as the State Government may authorise in this behalf, on receipt of the intimation from the authority sanctioning the loan, in one or more of the following modes, namely-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>from the borrower, -as if they were an arrear of land revenue due by him;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>from his surety if any, -as if they were arrears of land revenue due by him;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>out of the assets created out of the amount of loan advanced, -according to the procedure for realisation of land revenue by the sale of such assets;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>out of the property comprised in the collateral security (if any) according to the procedure for the realisation of land revenue by the sale of such property.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any sum due on account of any such loan, interest or costs is paid to the Collector by a surety or an owner of property comprised in any collateral security, or is recovered under sub-section (1) by the Collector from a surety or out of any such property, the Collector shall, on the application of the surety or the owner of that property, as the case may be, recover that sum on his behalf from the borrower, or out of the assets of the industry for the benefit of which the loan was granted in the manner provided by sub-section (1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the manner of making applications for loan, the form of the application and particulars of the form under sub-section (1), and the manner of conducting inquiries relating to such applications under sub-section (2), of section 4;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the nature and extent of security to be taken for the due application and repayment of money, the rate of interest at which and the conditions under which, loans may be granted, and the manner and time of granting loans;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>inspection of works for which loans are granted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the instalment by which and the mode in which, the loans, the rates of interest (including any penal interest), if any, to be charged on loans, and the costs incurred in the making thereof, shall be paid, under section 5;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the manner of keeping and auditing the accounts of the expenditure of loans, and of the payment made in respect of the same;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the valuation of securities;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the insurance of property mortgaged for securing the loan;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the form of agreement deed and mortagage deed in respect of the property offered as security for the loan;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>all other matters pertaining to the working of the Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The rules made under this section shall be subject to the condition of previous publication.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All rules made under this section shall be laid for not less than thirty days before each House of the State Legislature as soon as possible after they are made and shall be subject to such modification as the State Legislature may make during the session in which they are so laid or the session immediately following, and publish in the Official Gazette.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
