<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1968/24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1968/24"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Bihar And Uttar Pradesh (Alteration Of Boundaries) Act, 1968"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1968/24/eng@1968-05-22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1968/24/eng@1968-05-22"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1968-05-22" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1968/24/eng@1968-05-22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1968/24/eng@1968-05-22"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Bihar And Uttar Pradesh (Alteration Of Boundaries) Act, 1968</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 24 OF 1968</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 22nd May, 1968]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Nineteenth Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the alteration of boundaries of the States of</p>
        <p>Bihar and Uttar Pradesh and for matters connected therewith.</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:--</p>
        <p>PART</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <part id="part-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="part-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title. This Act may be called the Bihar and Uttar</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Pradesh (Alteration of Boundaries) Act, 1968.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" appointed day" means the day which the Central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Government may, by notification in the Official</p>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Gazette, appoint;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" assembly constituency"," council constituency" and</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>" parliamentary constituency" have the same meanings as  in the Representation of the People Act, 1950 (43 of</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1950">
          <num>1950.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1950.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>);</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" deep stream", in relation to the river Ganga or the  river Ghaghra, means the deep stream thereof as  verified and agreed upon by the State Governments of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Bihar and Uttar Pradesh after the 30th day of September  of the year preceding the year in which the appointed  day falls and before the 1st day of January of the year  in which the appointed day falls and in default of  agreement between the State Governments, as determined  by such authority as may be specified by the Central</p>
              <blockList id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Government;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list4.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" fixed boundary" means the boundary line demarcated  under the provisions of sub- section (2) of section 3 in  relation to the river Ganga or the river Ghaghra, as  the case may be;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list4.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>" law" includes any enactment, ordinance, regulation,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>order, bye- law, rule, scheme, notification or other  instrument</p>
              <blockList id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list7">
                <listIntroduction>having the force of law in the whole or in any part of  the State of Bihar or Uttar Pradesh;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list7.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>" notified order" means an order published in the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list9">
                <listIntroduction>Official Gazette;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list9.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list11">
                <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list11.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>" sitting member", in relation to either House of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list13">
                <listIntroduction>Parliament or of the Legislature of a State, means a  person who immediately before the appointed day is a  member of that House;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list13.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>" transferred territories" means,--</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list13.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>in relation to the State of Bihar, the  territories transferred by this Act from that State to  the State of Uttar Pradesh, and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list13.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>in relation to the State of Uttar Pradesh,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list15">
                <listIntroduction>the territories transferred by this Act from that State  to the State of Bihar;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list15.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>any reference to a district of a State shall be  construed as a reference to the area physically  comprised within that district immediately before the  appointed day.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>TRANSFER OF TERRITORIES</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="part-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>TRANSFER OF TERRITORIES</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Transfer of territories.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>As from the appointed day,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-3.1.list1.a.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>there shall be added to the State of Bihar--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-3.1.list1.a.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>all the territories of Ballia district of the State  of Uttar Pradesh lying between the fixed boundary and the  deep stream of the river Ghaghra, and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3.1.list1.a.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>all the territories of that district lying between  the fixed boundary and the deep stream of the river Ganga,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>and the said territories shall thereupon cease to form part of the</p>
              <blockList id="section-3.1.list4">
                <listIntroduction>State of Uttar Pradesh; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.1.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-3.1.list4.b.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>there shall be added to the State of Uttar Pradesh--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-3.1.list4.b.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>all the territories of Saran district of the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.1.list6">
                <listIntroduction>State of Bihar lying between the fixed boundary and the  deep stream of the river Ghaghra, and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.1.list6.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>all the territories of Shahabad district of  the State of Bihar lying between the fixed boundary and  the deep stream of the river Ganga,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>and the said territories shall thereupon cease to form part  of the State of Bihar.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The fixed boundary in relation to each of the rivers</p>
              <p>Ganga and Ghaghra shall be demarcated by an authority  appointed in this behalf by the Central Government so  as to be generally in conformity with the boundary line  described in the Schedule in relation to that river:</p>
              <blockList id="section-3.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that in the process of such demarcation, the said  authority shall have power to rationalise to the extent considered  necessary by him, the boundary alignment between the high banks of the  river Ganga or the river Ghaghra, as the case may be, and in  particular shall try--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.2.list3.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to ensure, as far as possible, the stability of the  boundary pillars and the recognition of the boundary  alignment both during the dry and flood seasons; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.2.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>to avoid, as far as possible, the splitting up of the  existing abadis.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>For the purposes of such demarcation,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the decision of the said authority on any matter  relating to the interpretation of any part of the  description of the boundary given in the Schedule</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>(including the determination of the relevant record   referred to in the Explanatory Note to the Schedule)</p>
              <blockList id="section-3.3.list4">
                <listIntroduction>shall be final;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.3.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the said authority shall have power to determine the  location of the points at which the boundary pillars  shall be constructed and to specify the State</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.3.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Government which shall be responsible for the  construction and maintenance of the boundary pillars at  such points according to such specifications as that  authority may indicate (the pillars of the same  specifications being apportioned, as far as practicable   equally between the two State Governments), the  decision of the said authority in regard to these  matters being final;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.3.list6.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>it shall be lawful for the said authority and for any  person specified by such authority to enter upon and  survey any</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>area in the vicinity of the boundary line and to do all  other acts as may be necessary.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.4.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The authority referred to in sub- section (2) shall also  prepare a map of the transferred territories showing--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.4.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the deep stream of the river Ghaghra or the river Ganga,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.4.list3">
                <listIntroduction>as the case may be, and the fixed boundary in relation  to that river;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.4.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the names and boundaries of the villages in the  transferred territories, as indicated by the State</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Government having jurisdiction over the territories  before their transfer, with reference to the revenue  record of that Government in force immediately before  the preparation of such map,</p>
              <p>and forward such map to the Central Government who shall cause it to  be published in the transferred territories in such manner as it  thinks fit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As from the appointed day, the State Government of Bihar or</p>
              <p>Uttar Pradesh shall, by order in the Official Gazette, provide for the  administration of the territories transferred to that State under sub-</p>
              <p>section (1) by including them or any part of them in such district,</p>
              <p>sub- division, police- station or other administrative unit as may be  specified in the order.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Amendment of First Schedule to the Constitution. As from the  appointed day, in the First Schedule to the Constitution, under the  heading" I. THE STATES"--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>for the entry against" 3. Bihar", the following shall be  substituted, namely:--</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>" The territories which immediately before the  commencement of this Constitution were either comprised  in the Province of Bihar or were being administered as  if they formed part of that Province and the  territories specified in clause (a) of sub- section (1)</p>
              <p>of section 3 of the Bihar and Uttar Pradesh (Alteration   of Boundaries) Act, 1968, but excluding the territories  specified in sub- section (1) of section 3 of the Bihar  and West Bengal (Transfer of Territories) Act, 1956,</p>
              <p>and the territories specified in clause (b) of sub-</p>
              <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>section (1) of section 3 of the first mentioned Act";</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list5.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>for the entry against" 13. Uttar Pradesh", the following  shall be substituted, namely:--</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>" The territories which immediately before the  commencement of this Constitution were either comprised  in the Province known as the United Provinces or were  being administered as if they formed part of that</p>
              <p>Province and the territories specified in clause (b) of  sub- section 91 of section 3 of the Bihar and Uttar</p>
              <p>Pradesh (Alteration of Boundaries) Act, 1968, but  excluding the territories specified in clause (a) of  sub- section (1) of section 3 of that Act.".</p>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>REPRESENTATION IN THE LEGISLATURES</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="part-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>REPRESENTATION IN THE LEGISLATURES</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Construction of Delimitation Orders. As from the appointed  day, any reference in any order relating to delimitation of  parliamentary constituencies, assembly constituencies or council  constituencies--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0.a.list0">
                    <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0.a.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>to the State of Bihar, shall be construed as  including the territories transferred to that State  from the State of Uttar Pradesh under clause (a) of  sub- section (1) of section 3, but excluding the  territories transferred from the State of Bihar to the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>State of Uttar Pradesh under clause (b) of that sub-</p>
              <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>section;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list3.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>to any district, sub- division, police- station or other  administrative unit in the State of Bihar, shall be  construed as including that part of the territories, if  any, transferred to that State, which is included in  that district, sub- division, police- station or other  administrative unit by order made under sub- section (5)</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>of section 3;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list5.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list5.b.list0">
                    <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list5.b.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>to the State of Uttar Pradesh, shall be construed as  including the territories transferred to that State  from the State of Bihar under clause (b) of sub- section</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of section 3, but excluding the territories  transferred from the State of Uttar Pradesh to the</p>
              <blockList id="section-5.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>State of Bihar under clause (a) of that sub- section;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.1.list2.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>to any district, sub- division, police- station or other  administrative unit in the State of Uttar Pradesh,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>shall be construed as including that part of the  territories, if any,</p>
              <p>transferred to that State, which is included in that  district, sub- division, police- station or other  administrative unit by order made under sub- section (5)</p>
              <p>of section 3.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Provision as to sitting members.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every sitting member of  the House of the People representing any parliamentary constituency  the extent of which has been altered by virtue of the provisions of  this Act shall, notwithstanding such alteration, be deemed, as from  the appointed day, to have been elected to that House by that  constituency as so altered.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every sitting member of the Legislative Assembly of the State  of Bihar or Uttar Pradesh representing any assembly constituency the  extent of which has been altered by virtue of the provisions of this</p>
              <p>Act shall, notwithstanding such alteration, be deemed, as from the  appointed day, to have been elected to the said Legislative Assembly  by that constituency as so altered.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every sitting member of the Legislative Council of Bihar or</p>
              <p>Uttar Pradesh representing any council constituency the extent of  which has been altered by virtue of the provisions of this Act, shall,</p>
              <p>notwithstanding such alteration, be deemed, as from the appointed day,</p>
              <p>to have been elected to the said Legislative Council by that  constituency as so altered.</p>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>HIGH COURTS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="part-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>HIGH COURTS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Extension of jurisdiction of, and transfer of proceedings to,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>High Court at Patna.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-7.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Except as hereinafter provided--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the jurisdiction of the High Court at Patna shall, as  from the appointed day, extend to the territories  transferred by this Act from the State of Uttar Pradesh  to the State of Bihar; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the High Court of Judicature at Allahabad shall, as from  that day, have no jurisdiction in respect of the said  territories.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Such proceedings pending in the High Court of Judicature at</p>
              <p>Allahabad immediately before the appointed day as are certified by the</p>
              <p>Chief Justice of that High Court, having regard to the place of  accrual of the cause of action and other circumstances, to be  proceedings which ought to be heard and decided by the High Court at</p>
              <p>Patna shall, as soon as may be after such certification, be  transferred to the High Court at Patna.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- sections (1) and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, but save as hereinafter provided, the High Court of Judicature at</p>
              <p>Allahabad shall have, and the High Court at Patna shall not have,</p>
              <p>jurisdiction to entertain, hear or dispose of appeals, applications  for leave to appeal to the Supreme Court, applications for review and  other proceedings, where any such proceedings seek any relief in  respect of any order passed by the High Court of Judicature at</p>
              <p>Allahabad before the appointed day:</p>
              <p>Provided that if, after such proceedings have been entertained by  the High Court of Judicature at Allahabad, it appears to the Chief</p>
              <p>Justice of that High Court that they ought to be transferred to the</p>
              <p>High Court at Patna, he shall order that they shall be so transferred  and such proceedings shall thereupon be transferred accordingly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-7.4.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Any order made by the High Court of Judicature at Allahabad--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.4.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>before the appointed day in any proceedings transferred  to the High Court at Patna by virtue of sub- section</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-7.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>, or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>in any proceedings with respect to which the High Court  of Judicature at Allahabad retains jurisdiction by  virtue of sub- section (3),</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>shall, for all purposes, have effect not only as an order of the High</p>
              <p>Court of Judicature at Allahabad, but also as an order made by the</p>
              <p>High Court at Patna.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to any rule made or direction given by the High Court  at Patna, any such person who immediately before the appointed day is  an advocate entitled to practise in the High Court of Judicature at</p>
              <p>Allahabad as may be specified in this behalf by the Chief Justice of  the High Court at Patna having regard to the transfer of territories  from the State of Uttar Pradesh to the State of Bihar, shall be  recognised as an advocate entitled to practise in the High Court at</p>
              <p>Patna.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Extension of jurisdiction of, and transfer of proceedings to,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>High Court at Allahabad.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-8.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Except as hereinafter provided--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the jurisdiction of the High Court of Judicature at</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-8.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Allahabad shall, as from the appointed day, extend to  the territories transferred by this Act from the State  of Bihar to the State of Uttar Pradesh; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.1.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the High Court at Patna shall, as from that day, have no  jurisdiction in respect of the said territories.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Such proceedings pending in the High Court at Patna  immediately before the appointed day as are certified by the Chief</p>
              <p>Justice of that High Court, having regard to the place of accrual of  the cause of action and other circumstances, to be proceedings which  ought to be heard and decided by the High Court of Judicature at</p>
              <p>Allahabad shall, as soon as may be after such certification, be  transferred to the High Court of Judicature at Allahabad.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- sections (1) and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, but save as hereinafter provided, the High Court at Patna shall  have, and the High Court of Judicature at Allahabad shall not have,</p>
              <p>jurisdiction to entertain, hear or dispose of appeals, applications  for leave to appeal to the Supreme Court, applications for review and  other proceedings, where any such proceedings seek any relief in  respect of any order passed by the High Court at Patna before the  appointed day:</p>
              <p>Provided that if, after such proceedings have been entertained by  the High Court at Patna, it appears to the Chief Justice of that High</p>
              <p>Court that they ought to be transferred to the High Court of</p>
              <p>Judicature at Allahabad, he shall order that they shall be so  transferred and such proceedings shall thereupon be transferred  accordingly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-8.4.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Any order made by the High Court at Patna--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.4.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>before the appointed day in any proceedings transferred  to the High Court of Judicature at Allahabad by virtue  of sub- section (2), or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.4.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>in any proceedings with respect to which the High Court  at Patna retains jurisdiction by virtue of sub- section</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>,</p>
              <p>shall, for all purposes, have effect not only as an order of the High</p>
              <p>Court at Patna, but also as an order made by the High Court of</p>
              <p>Judicature at Allahabad.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to any rule made or direction given by the High Court  of Judicature at Allahabad, any such person who immediately before the  appointed day is an advocate entitled to practise in the High Court at</p>
              <p>Patna as may be specified in this behalf by the Chief Justice of the</p>
              <p>High Court of Judicature at Allahabad having regard to the transfer of  territories from the State of Bihar to the State of Uttar Pradesh,</p>
              <p>shall be recognised as an advocate entitled to practise in the High</p>
              <p>Court of Judicature at Allahabad.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Right to appear in any proceedings transferred under section 7  or section 8. Any person who immediately before the appointed day is  an advocate entitled to practise in the High Court at Patna or the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>High Court of Judicature at Allahabad and was authorised to appear in  any proceedings transferred under section 7 or section 8 shall have  the right to appear in the High Court to which the proceedings have  been transferred, in relation to those proceedings.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Interpretation. For the purposes of sections 7 and 8,--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>proceedings shall be deemed to be pending in the High</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Court at Patna or the High Court of Judicature at</p>
              <p>Allahabad until that Court has disposed of all issues  between the parties, including any issue with respect  to the taxation of the costs of the proceedings and  shall include appeals, applications for leave to appeal  to the Supreme Court, applications for review,</p>
              <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>petitions for revision and petitions for writs;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>references to the High Court at Patna or the High Court  of Judicature at Allahabad shall be construed as  including references to a Judge or division court  thereof, and references to an order made by a court or  a Judge shall be construed as including references to a  sentence, judgment or decree passed or made by that  court or Judge.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>AUTHORISATION OF EXPENDITURE</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <paragraph id="part-V.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>AUTHORISATION OF EXPENDITURE</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Appropriation of moneys for expenditure in transferred  territories under existing appropriation Acts.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As from the  appointed day, any Act passed by the Legislature of the State of Bihar  or Uttar Pradesh before that day for the appropriation of any moneys  out of the Counsolidated Fund of the State of meet any expenditure in  respect of any part of the financial year in which the appointed day  falls shall have effect also in relation to the territories  transferred to that State by the provisions of Part II and it shall be  lawful for the State Government to spend any amount in those  territories out of the amount authorised by such Act to be expended  for any service in that State.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Governor of Bihar or of Uttar Pradesh may, after the  appointed day, authorise such expenditure from the Consolidated Fund  of the State as he deems necessary for any purpose or service in the  territories transferred to that State for a period of not more than  six months beginning with the appointed day pending the sanction of  such expenditure by the Legislature of the State.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Reports relating to accounts of Bihar and Uttar Pradesh. The  reports of the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India referred to in  clause (2) of article 151 of the Constitution relation to the accounts  of the State of Bihar or Uttar Pradesh in respect of any period prior  to the appointed day shall be submitted to the Governor of each of the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>States of Bihar and Uttar Pradesh who shall cause them to be laid  before the Legislature of the State.</p>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>APPORTIONMENT OF ASSETS AND LIABILITIES</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-VI">
        <num>VI</num>
        <paragraph id="part-VI.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>APPORTIONMENT OF ASSETS AND LIABILITIES</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Land and goods.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-13.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the other provisions of this</p>
              <p>Part, all land and all stores, articles and other goods belonging to  the State of Bihar or Uttar Pradesh in the transferred territories  shall, as from the appointed day, pass to the State to which the  territories are transferred.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In this section, the expression" land" includes immovable  property of every kind and any rights in or over such property.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Arrears of taxes. The right of Bihar or Uttar Pradesh to  recover arrears of any tax or duty on property situate in the  transferred territories, including land revenue. or to recover arrears  of any other tax or duty in any case where the place of assessment of  that tax or duty is in the transferred territories shall belong to the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>State to which the territories are transferred.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Right to recover loans and advances. The right to recover any  loans or advances made before the appointed day by Bihar or Uttar</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Pradesh to any local body, society agriculturist, or other person in  the transferred territories shall belong to the State to which the  territories are transferred.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Refund of taxes collected in excess. The liability of Bihar  or Uttar Pradesh to refund any tax or duty on property situate in the  transferred territories, including land revenue, collected in excess  shall be the liability of the State to which the territories are  transferred, and the liability of Bihar or Uttar Pradesh to refund any  other tax or duty collected in excess in any case where the place of  assessment of the tax or duty is in the transferred territories shall  also be the liability of the State to which the territories are  transferred.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Deposits. The liability of Bihar or Uttar Pradesh in respect  of any civil deposit or local fund deposit made in the transferred  territories shall,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>as from the appointed day, be the liability of the State to which the  territories are transferred.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Contracts.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-18.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where, before the appointed day, the State of</p>
              <blockList id="section-18.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Bihar or Uttar Pradesh has made any contract in the exercise of its  executive power for any purposes of the State, that contract shall be  deemed to have been made in the exercise of the executive power--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-18.1.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>if such purposes are, as from that day, purposes  relatable exclusively to the transferred territories,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>of the State to which the territories are transferred;</p>
              <blockList id="section-18.1.list5">
                <listIntroduction>and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-18.1.list5.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>in any other case, of the State which made the contract,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>and all rights and liabilities which have accrued, or may accrue,</p>
              <p>under any such contract shall, to the extent to which they are rights  or liabilities of the State which made the contract, be rights or  liabilities of the State specified in clause (a) or clause (b) above.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-18.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>For the purposes of this section, there shall be deemed to be  included in the liabilities which have accrued or may accrue under any  contract--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-18.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>any liability to satisfy an order or award made by any  court or other tribunal in proceedings relating to the  contract; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>any liability in respect of expenses incurred in or in  connection with any such proceedings.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This section shall have effect subject to the other  provisions of this Part relating to the apportionment of liabilities  in respect of loans, guarantees and other financial obligations.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Liability in respect of actionable wrong. Where, immediately  before the appointed day, the State of Bihar or Uttar Pradesh is  subject to any liability in respect of an actionable wrong, other than  breach of contract, that liability shall,--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-19.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>if the cause of action arose wholly within the  transferred territories, be a liability of the State to  which the territories are transferred; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>in any other case, continue to be a liability of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>State which, immediately before that day, was subject  to such liability.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Liability as guarantor of co- operative societies. Where,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>immediately before the appointed day, the State of Bihar or Uttar</p>
              <blockList id="section-20.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Pradesh is liable as guarantor in respect of any liability of a  registered co- operative society, that liability shall,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>if the area of the society' s operations is limited to  the transferred territories, be a liability of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-20.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>State to which the territories are transferred; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>in any other case, continue to be a liability of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>State which, immediately before that day, was subject  to such liability.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Items in suspense. If any item in suspense is ultimately  found to affect an asset or liability of the nature referred to in any  of the foregoing provisions of this Part, it shall be dealt with in  accordance with that provision.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Apportionment of assets or liabilities by agreement. Where  the States of Bihar and Uttar Pradesh agree that the benefit or burden  of any particular asset or liability should be apportioned between  them in a manner other than that provided for in the foregoing  provisions of this Part, then, notwithstanding anything contained  therein, the benefit or burden of that asset or liability shall be  apportioned in the manner agreed upon.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Power of Central Government to order allocation or adjustment  in certain cases. Where, by virtue of any of the provisions of this</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Part, either of the States of Bihar or Uttar Pradesh becomes subject  to any liability, and the Central Government, on a reference made  within a period of three years from the appointed day by either of the</p>
              <p>States, is of opinion that it is just and equitable that property or  those benefits should be transferred to, or shared with, the other</p>
              <p>State or that a contribution towards that liability should be made by  the other State, the said property or benefits shall be allocated in  such manner between the two States, or the other State shall make to  the State subject to the liability such contribution in respect  thereof, as the Central Government may, after consultation with the  two State Governments, by order determine.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Expenditure to be charged on the Consolidated Fund. All sums  payable by either Bihar or Uttar Pradesh to the other State by virtue  of the provisions of this Part shall be charged on the Consolidated</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Fund of the State by which such sums are payable.</p>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>LEGAL AND MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-VII">
        <num>VII</num>
        <paragraph id="part-VII.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>LEGAL AND MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>State Financial Corporations and State Electricity Boards. As  from the appointed day--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-25.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the Financial Corporation constituted under the State</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Financial Corporations Act, 1951 (63 of 1951.), for the</p>
              <blockList id="section-25.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>States of Bihar and Uttar Pradesh, and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the State Electricity Boards constituted under the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Electricity (Supply) Act, 1948 (54 of 1948.), for the  said States,</p>
              <p>shall be deemed to have been constituted for those States with their  areas as altered by the provisions of section 3.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Territorial extent of laws. The provisions of section 3 shall  not be deemed to have effected any change in the territories to which  any law in force immediately before the appointed day extends or  applies, and territorial references in any such law to the State of</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Bihar or Uttar Pradesh shall, until otherwise provided by a competent</p>
              <p>Legislature or other competent authority, be construed as meaning the  territories within that State immediately before the appointed day.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Power to adapt laws. For the purpose of facilitating the  application of any law in relation to the State of Bihar or Uttar</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Pradesh, the appropriate Government may, before the expiration of one  year from the appointed day, by order make such adaptations and  modifications of the law, whether by way of repeal or amendment as may  be necessary or expedient, and thereupon every such law shall have  effect subject to the adaptations or modifications so made until  altered, repealed or amended by a competent Legislature or other  competent authority.</p>
              <p>Explanation.-- In this section, the expression" appropriate</p>
              <p>Government" means as respects any law relating to a matter enumerated  in the Union List, the Central Government, and as respects any other  law, the State Government.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Power to construe laws. Notwithstanding that no provision or  insufficient provision has been made for the adaptation of a law made  before the appointed day, any court, tribunal or authority, required  or empowered to enforce such law may, for the purpose of facilitating  its application in relation to the State of Bihar or Uttar Pradesh,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>construe the law in such manner, without affecting the substance, as  may be necessary or proper in regard to the matter before the court,</p>
              <p>tribunal or authority.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Legal proceedings. Where, immediately before the appointed  day, the State of Bihar or Uttar Pradesh is a party to any legal  proceedings with respect to any property, rights or liabilities  transferred to the other State under this Act, the other State shall  be deemed to be substituted for the State from which such property  rights or liabilities are transferred as a party to those proceedings,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-29.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>or added as a party thereto, as the case may be, and the proceedings  may continue accordingly.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading>Transfer of pending proceedings.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-30.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every proceeding pending  immediately before the appointed day before a court (other than a High</p>
              <p>Court), tribunal, authority or officer in any area which on that day  falls within the State of Bihar or Uttar Pradesh shall, if it is a  proceeding relatable exclusively to any part of the territories which  as from that day are the territories of the other State, stand  transferred to the corresponding court, tribunal, authority or officer  in the other State.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-30.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any question arises as to whether any proceeding should  stand transferred under sub- section (1), it shall be referred to the</p>
              <p>High Court having jurisdiction in respect of the area in which the  court, tribunal, authority or officer before which, or before whom,</p>
              <p>such proceeding is pending on the appointed day, is functioning, and  the decision of that High Court shall be final.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-30.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-30.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In this section,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-30.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" proceeding" includes any suit, case or appeal; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.3.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-30.3.list1.b.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>" corresponding court, tribunal, authority or officer" in  a State means--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-30.3.list1.b.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>the court, tribunal, authority or officer in  which, or before whom, the proceeding would have lain  if the proceeding had been instituted after the  appointed day, or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-30.3.list1.b.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>in case of doubt, such court, tribunal,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>authority or officer in that State as may be determined  after the appointed day by the Government of that</p>
              <p>State, or before the appointed day by the Government of  the other State, to be the corresponding court,</p>
              <p>tribunal, authority or officer.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading>Right of pleaders to practise in certain courts. Any person  who, immediately before the appointed day, is enrolled as a pleader  entitled to practise in any subordinate courts in the transferred  territories shall, for a period of six months from</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-31.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>that day, continue to be entitled to practise in those courts,</p>
              <p>notwithstanding that the whole or any part of the territories within  the jurisdiction of those courts has been transferred to another</p>
              <p>State.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>Construction of boundary pillars, etc.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-32.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall be lawful  for the State Government which is responsible for the construction of  any boundary pillar under sub- section (3) of section 3 to cause such  pillar to be constructed and maintained and no suit, prosecution or  other legal proceeding shall lie against the State Government or any  of its officers for anything in good faith done or intended to be done  under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The boundary pillars shall be inspected jointly by the  officers of the State Governments of Bihar and Uttar Pradesh in  accordance with such rules as the Central Government may make in this  behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Whoever wilfully removes or injures any boundary pillar shall  be punishable with imprisonment of either description for a term which  may extend to one year, or with fine, or with both.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal</p>
              <p>Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898.), an offence under sub- section (3) may be  inquired into and tried by a court in either of the States of Bihar  and Uttar Pradesh.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading>Validity of demarcation done before commencement of Act. All  things done, and all steps taken, before the commencement of this Act  in connection with the demarcation of the fixed boundary in relation  to the river Ganga or the river Ghaghra, as the case may be, shall, in  so far as they are in conformity with the provisions of sub- sections</heading>
          <subsection id="section-33.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and (3) of section 3, be deemed to have been done in accordance  with law.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-34">
          <num>34.</num>
          <heading>Effect of provisions inconsistent with other laws. The  provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding any law,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-34.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>custom or usage which is inconsistent therewith.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in  giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the President may, by  notified order, do anything, not inconsistent with such provisions  which appears to him to be necessary or expedient for the purpose of  removing the difficulty.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-36">
          <num>36.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-36.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to give effect to the  provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as  may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament while it is  in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in  one session or  in two or more successive sessions, and if, before  the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the  successive sessions aforesaid] both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not  be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified  form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so, however, that any  such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the  validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </part>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
