<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-wbg/act/1870/06/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-wbg/act/1870/06"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Village Chaukidari Act, 1870 [Bengal]"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-wbg/act/1870/06/eng@2017-01-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-wbg/act/1870/06/eng@2017-01-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-wbg/act/1870/06/eng@2017-01-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-wbg/act/1870/06/eng@2017-01-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-12-08" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Village Chaukidari Act, 1870</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No. 06 of 1870</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the appointment, dismissal and maintenance of village-chaukidar.</p>
        <p>Whereas it is expedient to make provision for the appointment, dismissal and maintenance of village-chaukidars in the provinces subject to the Lieutenant-Governor of Bengal;</p>
        <p>It is enacted as follows:--</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The following words and expressions shall, in the construction of this Act, have the several meanings hereby assigned to them respectively, except where a different intention shall appear from the context (that is say):--</p>
            <p>"District Magistrate."</p>
            <p>the words "District Magistrate" shall mean the chief officer charged with the executive administration of a district in criminal matters by whatsoever designation such officer is called:</p>
            <p>"Chaukidari chakaran lands."</p>
            <p>the words "chaukidari chakaran lands" shall mean lands which may have been assigned, otherwise than under a temporary settlement, for the maintenance of the officer who may have been bound to keep watch in any village and report crime to the police, and in respect to which such officer may be at the time of the passing of this Act liable to render service to a zamindar.</p>
            <p>"Zamindar."</p>
            <p>the word "zamindar" shall mean the person whose name is registered in the general register of estates paying revenue directly to Government as the proprietor of an estate so paying revenue, or the person whose name is registered in the general register of rent-free tenures as proprietor of a rent-free tenure.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>- 47. Omitted</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-48">
        <num>48.</num>
        <heading>Chaukidari chakaran lands to be transferred to zamindars</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-48.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>All chaukidari chakaran lands before the passing of this Act assigned for the benefit of any village in which a panchayat shall be appointed shall be transferred in manner and subject as hereinafter mentioned to the zamindar of the estate or tenure within which may be situate such lands.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-49">
        <num>49.</num>
        <heading>Assessment to be fixed at one-half of value</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-49.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>All lands so transferred shall be subject to an assessment which shall be fixed at one-half of the annual value of such land according to the average rates of letting land similar in quality in the neighbourhood of such land, and such assessment shall be made by the panchayat of the village.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-50">
        <num>50.</num>
        <heading>Collector to make transfer</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-50.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Such assessment when made by the panchayat shall be submitted to the Collector of the district, and he or any other officer exercising the powers of a Collector by him thereunto appointed may approve, or revise and approve, the same (provided that it shall be lawful for the zamindar to contest the assessment before it is so approved), and after such approval the Collector of the district shall, by an order under his hand in the form in Schedule C, transfer to such zamindar such land subject to the assessment so approved.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-51">
        <num>51.</num>
        <heading>Effect of transfer</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-51.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Such order shall operate to transfer to such zamindar the land therein mentioned subject to the amount of assessment therein mentioned, and subject to all contracts there to fore made, in respect of, under, or by virtue of, which any person other than the zamindar may have any right to any land, portion of his estate, or tenure, in the place in which such land may be situate.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-52">
        <num>52.</num>
        <heading>Assessment to be permanent charge on lands</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-52.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The amount of the assessment mentioned in such order shall be a permanent yearly charge on such land, and shall be payable to the collecting member of the panchayat yearly in advance on the first day of the year current in the village by the person for the time being entitled to recover the rents of such land from the occupier thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-53">
        <num>53.</num>
        <heading>Mode of realization</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-53.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every such assessment shall be deemed to be a demand to be realized in the manner hereinafter provided.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-54">
        <num>54.</num>
        <heading>Notice of arrear</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-54.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whenever such assessment shall be in arrear for the space of fifteen days after it shall have become payable, the collecting member of the panchayat shall forward to the Collector of the district in which the land so assessed is situate notice of the amount of such arrear and the name of the person liable to pay such assessment, in the form in Schedule D annexed to this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-55">
        <num>55.</num>
        <heading>Mode and effect of sale</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-55.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Immediately after the receipt of the said notice the Collector or other officer authorized to hold sales under the law for the lime being in force for regulating sales of land for arrears of revenue shall proceed, without any preliminary notice for payment, to issue a notification for sale under section 6 of the Bengal Land-revenue Sales Act, 1859 (XI of 1859);</p>
            <p>and, unless the arrears be paid within the time mentioned in such notification, shall sell such land according to the provisions of such law as if such land were an estate within the meaning of the Bengal Land-revenue Sales Act, 1868 (Ben. Act VII of 1868);</p>
            <p>and all provisions of the law for the time being in force with respect to the sale of such estates shall apply to the sale of such land, and every such sale shall have such and the same force and effect as if the same were a sale of an estate for arrears of its own revenue, and such land shall be held by the purchaser thereof subject to such assessment, but freed from all other charges and in cumbrances save those to which he would have been liable if the said land had been an estate sold for arrears of its own revenue.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-56">
        <num>56.</num>
        <heading>Application of proceeds of sale</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-56.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Such Collector shall, out of the proceeds of such sale, after defraying the costs of and attending such sale, pay to the collecting member of the panchayat, within one week after such sale shall have become final, the amount due for arrears of such assessment, and pay the balance of such proceeds to the person named in the notice from the collecting member of me panchayat as the person liable to pay the assessment of such land.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-57">
        <num>57.</num>
        <heading>Right to service from occupier of transferred land to cease</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-57.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>When any land shall have been transferred to any zamindar under the provisions hereinbefore contained, the right to the performance of any services to any person by the occupier of such lands in respect of his occupation thereof shall wholly cease and determine.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-58">
        <num>58.</num>
        <heading>Appointment of commission</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-58.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In any district or part of a district in which may be situated lands before the passing of this Act assigned for the maintenance of an officer to keep watch in any village and to report crime to the police, it shall be lawful for the State Government of West Bengal by an order to be published in the Official Gazette, to appoint a commission, consisting of one or more persons, to ascertain and determine the chaukidari chakaran lands and other lands before the passing of this Act assigned for the maintenance of an officer to keep watch in any village and to report crime to the police in such district.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-59">
        <num>59.</num>
        <heading>Power to refer to commission question relating to chakaran land</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-59.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whenever in any district in which such commission shall have been appointed, any question shall arise whether any or what lands arc chaukidari chakaran lands or other lands before the passing of this Act assigned for the maintenance of an officer to keep watch in any village and to report crime to the police, it shall be lawful for such commission to inquire into such question.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-60">
        <num>60.</num>
        <heading>Powers of commission</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-60.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In inquiring into such question the commission shall, as far as may be necessary for the purposes of this Act, exercise all such and the same powers as are conferred by Regulation VII of 18221 and the Regulations and Acts amending the same upon a Collector making a settlement of land-revenue.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-61">
        <num>61.</num>
        <heading>Duties of commission and effect of their order</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-61.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Such commission shall demarcate the boundaries of any lands which they may determine to be chaukidari chakaran lands or other lands before the passing of this Act assigned for the maintenance of an officer to keep watch in any village and to report crime to the police, and shall make orders under their hand setting forth the land which they shall have determined to be chaukidari chakaran lands or other lands as aforesaid, and the boundaries thereof, and the name of the village for the benefit of which such lands arc assigned, and distinguishing whether such land be or be not chaukidari chakaran lands or other lands as aforesaid.</p>
            <p>Every such order shall be final and conclusive respecting all matters hereinbefore required to be set forth in such order so far as the same shall be therein set forth.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-62">
        <num>62.</num>
        <heading>-65. Omitted.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-66">
        <num>66.</num>
        <heading>Duly of zamindar to report crimes not affected</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-66.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in this Act contained shall diminish or in any way affect any liability, duty or obligation of any zamindar, under any law in force at the time of the passing of this Act to report crimes of offences occurring within his estate or tenure.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-67">
        <num>67.</num>
        <heading>Village watch where panchayat not appointed not affected</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-67.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in the Act contained, save the provisions of sections 58, 59,60 and 61, shall affect any lands before the passing of this Act assigned for the maintenance, in any village in which a panchayat may not be appointed, of an officer to keep watch in such village and to report crime to the police, and every such officer in such village shall be bound to perform the same duties, and shall have the same rights unto such lands, and may be removed and a successor to him appointed, as if this Act had not been passed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-68">
        <num>68.</num>
        <heading>Omitted</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-69">
        <num>69.</num>
        <heading>Short title</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-69.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Village Chaukidari Act, 1870.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
