<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/33/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/33"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Finance Commission (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act, 1951"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/33/eng@1951-05-16/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/33/eng@1951-05-16"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1951-05-16" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/33/eng@1951-05-16/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/33/eng@1951-05-16"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Finance Commission (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act, 1951</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 33 OF 1951</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 16th May. 1951.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to determine the qualifications requisite for appointment  as members of the Finance Commission and the manner in which they  shall be selected, and to prescribe their powers.</p>
      </longTitle>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament as follows:--</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title. This Act may be called the Finance Commission</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>(Miscellaneous Provisions) Act, 1951.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definition. In this Act," the Commission" means the Finance</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Commission constituted by the President pursuant to clause</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of  article 280 of the Constitution.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Qualifications for appointment as, and the manner of selection  of, members of the commission. The Chairman of the Commission shall be  selected from among persons who have had experience in public affairs,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>and the four other members shall be selected from among persons who--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>are, or have been, or are qualified to be appointed as</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Judges of a High Court; or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>have special knowledge of the finances and accounts of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Government; or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list5.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>have had wide experience in financial matters and in  administration; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list5.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>have special knowledge of economics.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Personal interest to disqualify members. Before appointing a  person to be a member of the Commission, the President shall satisfy  himself that that person will have no such financial or other interest  as is likely to affect prejudicially his functions as a member of the  commission; and the President shall also satisfy himself from time to  time with respect to every member of the Commission that he has no  such interest and any person who is, or whom the President proposes to  appoint to be, a member of the Commission shall, whenever required by  the President so to do, furnish to him such information as the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>President considers necessary for the performance by him of his duties  under this section.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Disqualifications for being a member of the Commission. A</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>person shall be disqualified for being appointed as, or for being, a  member of the Commission,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>if he is of unsound mind;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>if he is an undischarged insolvent;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>if he has been convicted of an offence involving moral  turpitude;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>if he has such financial or other interest as is likely  to affect prejudicially his functions as a member of  the Commission.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Term of office of members and eligibility for reappointment.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every member of the Commission shall hold office for such period as  may be specified in the order of the President appointing him, but  shall be eligible for reappointment:</p>
            <p>Provided that he may, by letter addressed to the President,</p>
            <p>resign his office.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Conditions of service and salaries and allowances of members.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>] The members of the Commission shall render whole- time or part-</p>
            <p>time service to the Commission as the President may in each case  specify, and there shall be paid to the members of the Commission such  fees or salaries and such allowances as the Central Government may, by  rules made  by notification in the Official Gazette,] in this behalf  determine.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon  as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it  is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be  comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and  if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session  or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not  be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified  form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any  such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the  validity of anything previously done under that rule.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Procedure and powers of the Commission.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commission  shall determine their procedure and in the performance of their  functions shall have all the powers of a civil court under the Code of</p>
            <blockList id="section-8.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), while trying a suit in respect of  the following matters, namely:--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>summoning and enforcing the attendance of witnesses;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.1.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>requiring the production of any document;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.1.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>requisitioning any public record from any court or  office.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commission shall have power to require any person to  furnish information on such points or matters as in the opinion of the</p>
            <p>Commission may be useful for, or relevant to, any matter under the  consideration of the Commission  and any person so required shall,</p>
            <p>notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (2) of section 54 of  the Indian Income- tax Act, 1922 (11 of 1922), or in any other law for  the time being in force, be deemed to be legally bound to furnish such  information within the meaning of section 176 of the Indian Penal Code</p>
            <p>(45 of 1860)].</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commission shall be deemed to be a civil court for the  purposes of sections 480 and 482 of the Code of Criminal Procedure,</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1898">
        <num>1898.</num>
        <heading>(5 of 1898).</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1898.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Explanation.-- For the purposes of enforcing the attendance of  witnesses, the local limits of the Commission' s jurisdiction shall be  the limits of the territory of India.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
