<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1977/33/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1977/33"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Salary And Allowances Of Leaders Ofopposition In Parliament Act, 1977"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1977/33/eng@1977-08-18/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1977/33/eng@1977-08-18"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1977-08-18" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1977/33/eng@1977-08-18/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1977/33/eng@1977-08-18"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Salary And Allowances Of Leaders Ofopposition In Parliament Act, 1977</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 33 OF 1977</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 18th August, 1977.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- eighth Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the Salary and Allowances of Leaders of</p>
        <p>Opposition in Parliament.</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:-</p>
        <p>Short title and commencement.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Salary and Allowences of Leaders of Opposition in Parliament Act,</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1977">
        <num>1977.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-1977.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date 1 as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
            <p>Definition.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definition. In this Act," Leader of the Opposition", in  relation to either House of Parliament, means that member of the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Council of States or the House of the People, as the case may be, who  is, for the time being, the Leader in that House of the party in  opposition to the Government having the greatest numerical strength  and recognised as such by the Chairman of the Council of States or the</p>
            <p>Speaker of the House of the People, as the case may be.</p>
            <p>Explanation.- Where there are two or more parties in opposition to  the Government, in the Council of States or in the House of the People  having the same numerical strength, the Chairman of the Council of</p>
            <p>States or the Speaker of the House of the People, as the case may be,</p>
            <p>shall, having regard to the status of the parties, recognise any one  of the Leaders of such parties as the Leader of the Opposition for the  purposes of this section and such recognition shall be final and  conclusive.</p>
            <p>Salary, and daily, constituency and sumptuary allowances.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Salary, and daily, constituency and sumptuary allowances.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Each Leader of the Opposition shall, so long as he continues as  such leader, be entitled to receive a salary per mensem and allowance  for each day at the same rates as are specified in section 3 of  the Salary, Allowances and Pension of Members of Parliament Act, 1954  with respect to members of Parliament.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Each Leader of the Opposition shall also be entitled to  receive a constituency allowance at the same rate as is for the time  being specified under section 8 of the said Act with respect to  members of Parliament.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be paid to each Leader of the Opposition a sum-</p>
            <p>ptuary allowance of one thousand rupees per mensem.]</p>
            <p>Residence for Leaders of Opposition.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Residence for Leaders of Opposition.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Each Leader of the</p>
            <p>Opposition shall, so long as he continues as such Leader and for a  period of one month immediately thereafter, be entitled without  payment of rent to the use of a furnished residence</p>
            <p>and no charge shall fall on the Leader of the Opposition personally in  respect of the maintenance of such residence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In the event of death of a Leader of the Opposition, his  family shall be entitled to the use of the furnished residence  occupied by him-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for a period of one month immediately after his death,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-4.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>without payment of rent and no charge shall fall on his  family in respect of the maintenance of such residence; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.2.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>for a further period of one month, on payment of rent  at such rates as may be prescribed by rules made in this  behalf by the Central Government and also charges in respect  of electricity and water consumed in that residence during  such further period.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Explanation.- For the purposes of this section," residence"</p>
            <p>includes the staff quarters and other buildings appurtenant thereto,</p>
            <p>and the garden thereof, and" maintenance" in relation to a residence  includes the payment of local rates and taxes and the provision of  electricity and water.</p>
            <p>Travelling and daily allowances to Leaders of Opposition.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>] Travelling and daily allowances to Leaders of</p>
            <p>Opposition. Subject to any rules made in this behalf by the Central</p>
            <blockList id="section-5.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Government, a Leader of the Opposition shall be entitled to-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.1.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-5.1.list3.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>travelling allowances for himself and the members of  his family and for transport of his and his family' s effects-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-5.1.list3.a.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>in respect of the journey to Delhi from his usual  place of residence outside Delhi for assuming office;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.1.list5">
              <listIntroduction>and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.1.list5.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>in respect of the journey from Delhi to his usual  place of residence outside Delhi on relinquishing  office; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list5.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>travelling and daily allowances in respect of tours  undertaken by him in the discharge of his duties as Leader of  the Opposition, whether by sea, land or air.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A Leader of the Opposition and any One member of his family  accompanying him shall be entitled to travelling allowances in respect  of not more than six return journeys performed, during each year,</p>
            <p>within India at the same rates at which travelling allowances are  payable to such Leader under clause (b) of sub- section (1) in respect  of tours referred to in that clause.</p>
            <p>Explanation.-- For the purposes of this sub- section," return  journey" means a journey from one place to another place and the  return journey from such other place to the first mentioned place.]</p>
            <p>Medical treatment, etc., to Leaders of Opposition.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Medical treatment, etc., to Leaders of Opposition. Subject to  any rules made in this behalf by the Central Government, a Leader of  the Opposition and the members of his family shall be entitled free  of charge to accommodation in hospitals maintained by the Government  and also to medical treatment.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Leaders of Opposition not to draw salary or allowances as Members  ofParliament.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Leaders of Opposition not to draw salary or allowances as</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Members of Parliament. No Leader of the Opposition in receipt of a  salary or allowance under this Act shall be entitled to receive any  sum out of funds provided</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Renumbered and Ins. by Act 98 of 1985, S. 3 (w. e. f. 26- 12- 1985)</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>by Parliament by way of salary or allowance in respect of his member-</p>
            <p>ship of either House of Parliament.</p>
            <p>Amenities to Leaders of Opposition.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Amenities to Leaders of Opposition.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to any rules  made in this behalf by the Central government, each Leader of the</p>
            <p>Opposition shall be entitled to telephone and secretarial facilities.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to any rules made in this behalf by the Central</p>
            <p>Government, each Leader of the Opposition shall be entitled to a  conveyance allowance of  three thousand rupees] per month:</p>
            <p>Provided that where a Leader of the Opposition is provided with  conveyance facility with a driver for the purposes of security or  otherwise for any period, he shall not be entitled to the conveyance  allowance for that period.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8A">
        <num>8A.</num>
        <heading>Advance to Leader of Opposition for purchase of motor car.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>There may be paid to a Leader of the Opposition, by way of a repayable  advance, such sum of money as may be prescribed by rules made in this  behalf by the Central Government for the purchase of a motor car in  order that he may be able to discharge conveniently and efficiently  the duties of his office.]</p>
            <p>Notification respecting the date on which persons became or ceased tobe</p>
            <p>Leaders of Opposition to be conclusive evidence thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Notification respecting the date on which persons became or  ceased to be Leaders of Opposition to be conclusive evidence thereof.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The date on which any person became or ceased to be a Leader the</p>
            <p>Opposition shall be published in the Official Gazette, and any such  notification shall be conclusive evidence of the fact that he became,</p>
            <p>or ceased to be, a Leader of the Opposition on that date for all the  purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9A">
        <num>9A.</num>
        <heading>Exemption from liability to pay income- tax on certain  perquisites received by a Leader of the Opposition. Notwithstanding  anything contained in the Income- tax Act, 1961, the value of rent free  furnished residence (including maintenance thereof) provided to a</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Leader of the Opposition under sub- section</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-9A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of section 4 shall not  be included in the computation of his income chargeable under the  heading" Salaries" under section 15 of the Income- tax Act. 1961.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rule</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out  the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of  the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the rates at which rent shall be payable by the family  of a deceased Leader of the Opposition to the use of the  furnished residence occupied by him under clause (b) of sub-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-10.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>section (2) of section 4;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.2.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the travelling and daily allowances admissible to a</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-10.2.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Leader of the Opposition under section 5;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.2.list5.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the medical treatment admissible to a Leader of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-10.2.list7">
              <listIntroduction>Opposition and the members of his family under section 6;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.2.list7.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the telephone and secretarial facilities admissible to  a Leader of the Opposition and the conditions subject to  which he shall be entitled to conveyance allowance under  section 8.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list7.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the advance payable to a Leader of the Opposition  under section 8A.]</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as  may after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in  session,</p>
            <p>for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one  session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the  expiry of the session immediately following the session or the  successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not  be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified  form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any  such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the  validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
            <p>Section 11 relates to amendment of the Salary, Allowances and</p>
            <p>Pension of Members of Parliament Act, 1954. Not printed.</p>
            <p>Section 12 relates to amendment of the Parliament (Prevention of</p>
            <p>Disqualification) Act, 1959. Not printed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
