<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1973/24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1973/24"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The North- Eastern Hill University Act, 1973"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1973/24/eng@1973-05-26/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1973/24/eng@1973-05-26"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1973-05-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1973/24/eng@1973-05-26/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1973/24/eng@1973-05-26"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The North- Eastern Hill University Act, 1973</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 24 OF 1973</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 26th May, 1973]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- fourth Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to establish and incorporate a teaching and affiliating</p>
        <p>University for the hill areas of the North- Eastern region.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to establish and incorporate a teaching  and affiliating University for the benefit of the people of the hill  areas of the North- Eastern region and to develop the intellectual,</p>
        <p>academic and cultural background of the said people;</p>
        <p>AND WHEREAS in pursuance of clause (1) of article 252 of the</p>
        <p>Constitution, resolutions have been passed by the Legislatures of the</p>
        <p>States of Meghalaya and Nagaland to the effect that the setting up of  a Central University for the hill areas of the North- Eastern region  shall be regulated by Parliament by law;</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be  called the North- Eastern Hill University Act, 1973.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the State of Meghalaya  and the Union  territories of Arunachal Pradesh and Mizoram.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date  as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, and in all Statutes made hereunder,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>unless the context otherwise requires,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" Academic Council" means the Academic Council of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" academic staff" means such categories of staff as are  designated as academic staff by the Ordinances;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" Board of Studies" means the Board of Studies of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>" Chancellor"," Vice- Chancellor" and" Pro- Vice-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Chancellor" mean, respectively, the Chancellor, Vice-</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list8">
              <listIntroduction>Chancellor and Pro- Vice- Chancellor of the University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list8.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>" College" means a College maintained by, or admitted to  the privileges of, the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list8.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>" Court" means the Court of the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list8.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>" Department" means a Department of Studies, and  includes a Centre of Studies;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list8.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>" employee" means any person appointed by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10">
              <listIntroduction>University, and includes teachers and other staff of  the University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>" Executive Council" means the Executive Council of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list12">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list12.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>" Hall" means a unit of residence or of corporate life  for the students of the University, College or</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Institution, provided, maintained or recognised by the</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list15">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list15.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>" Institution" means an academic institution, not being  a College, maintained by, or admitted to the privileges  of, the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list15.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>" North- Eastern region" means the North- Eastern region  of India comprising the  State of Meghalaya] and the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list17">
              <listIntroduction>Union territories of Arunachal Pradesh and Mizoram;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list17.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>" Principal" means the Head of a College or an</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Institution, and includes where there is no Principal,</p>
            <p>the person for the time being duly appointed to act as</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list21">
              <listIntroduction>Principal, and, in the absence of the Principal or the  acting Principal, a Vice- Principal duly appointed as  such;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list21.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>" recognised teachers" means such persons as are  recognised by the University for the purpose of  imparting instruction in a College or an Institution  admitted to the privileges of the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list21.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>" School" means a School of Studies of the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list21.p">
                <num>(p)</num>
                <p>" Statutes"," Ordinances" and" Regulations", mean,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list23">
              <listIntroduction>respectively, the Statutes, Ordinances and Regulations  of the University for the time being in force;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list23.q">
                <num>(q)</num>
                <p>" teachers of the University" means Professors, Readers,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Lecturers and such other persons as may be appointed  for imparting instruction or conducting research in the</p>
            <p>University or in any College or Institution maintained  by the University and are designated as teachers by the</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list27">
              <listIntroduction>Ordinances;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list27.r">
                <num>(r)</num>
                <p>" University" means the North- Eastern Hill University.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>The University.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be established a University by  the name of" North- Eastern Hill University".</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The headquarters of the University shall be at Shillong and  it shall have campuses in the  State of Meghalaya] it may also  establish campuses at such other places within its jurisdiction as it  may deem fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The first Chancellor and the first Vice- Chancellor and the  first members of the Court, the Executive Council and the Academic</p>
            <p>Council and all persons who may hereafter become such officers or  members, so long as they continue to hold such office or membership,</p>
            <p>are hereby constituted a body corporate by the name of" North- Eastern</p>
            <p>Hill University".</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The University shall have perpetual succession and a common  seal, and shall sue and be sued by the said name.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Objects. The objects of the University shall be to disseminate  and advance knowledge by providing instructional and research  facilities in such branches of learning as it may deem fit; to pay  special attention to the improvement of the social and economic  conditions and welfare of the people of the hill areas of the North-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Eastern region and, in particular, their intellectual, academic and  cultural advancement.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Powers of the University. The University shall have the  following powers, namely:-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to provide for instruction in such branches of learning  as the University may, from time to time, determine and  to make provision for research and for the advancement  and dissemination of knowledge;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to take such academic steps as would contribute to the  improvement of the economic conditions and welfare of  the people of the hill areas of the North- Eastern  region;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to grant, subject to such conditions as the University  may determine, diplomas or certificates to, and confer  degrees and other academic distinctions on the basis of  examinations, evaluation or any other method of  testing, on persons, and to withdraw any such diplomas,</p>
            <p>certificates, degrees or other academic distinctions  for good and sufficient cause;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to organise and to undertake extra- mural studies and  extension services;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to confer honorary degrees or other distinctions in the  manner prescribed by the Statutes;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to provide instruction, including correspondence and  such other courses, to such persons as are not members  of the University, as it may determine;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to institute principalships, professorships,</p>
            <p>readerships, lecturerships, and other teaching or  academic posts required by the University and to  appoint persons to such principalships, professorships,</p>
            <p>readerships, lecturerships or other posts;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to recognise persons for imparting instruction in any</p>
            <p>College or Institution admitted to the privileges of  the University;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to appoint persons working in any other University or  organisation as teachers of the University for a  specified period;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.10">
          <num>(10)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to create administrative, ministerial and other posts  and to make appointments thereto;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to co- operate or collaborate with any other University  or authority in such manner and for such purposes as  the University may determine;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.12">
          <num>(12)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to establish such campuses, centres, specialised  laboratories or other units for research and  instruction as are, in the opinion of the University,</p>
            <p>necessary for the furtherance of its objects;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.13">
          <num>(13)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to institute and award fellowships, scholarships,</p>
            <p>studentships, medals and prizes;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.14">
          <num>(14)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to establish and maintain Colleges, Institutions and</p>
            <p>Halls;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.15">
          <num>(15)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to admit to its privileges Colleges and Institutions  not maintained by the University; to withdraw all or  any of those privileges in accordance with such  conditions as may be prescribed by the Statutes; and to  recognise Halls not maintained by the University and to  withdraw any such recognition;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.16">
          <num>(16)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to declare a college, an Institution or a Department as  an autonomous College or an Institution or a</p>
            <p>Department, as the case may be;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.17">
          <num>(17)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to determine standards for admission into the</p>
            <p>University, which may include examination, evaluation  or any other method of testing;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.18">
          <num>(18)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to demand and receive payment of fees and other  charges;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.19">
          <num>(19)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to supervise the residences of the students of the</p>
            <p>University and to make arrangements for promoting their  health and general welfare;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.20">
          <num>(20)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to make special arrangements in respect of women  students as the University may consider desirable;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.21">
          <num>(21)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to regulate and enforce discipline among the employees  and students of the University and take such  disciplinary measures in this regard as may be deemed  necessary;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.22">
          <num>(22)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to make arrangements for promoting the health and  general welfare of the employees;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.23">
          <num>(23)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to acquire, hold, manage and dispose of property,</p>
            <p>movable or immovable, including trust and endowment  properties for the purposes of the University;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.24">
          <num>(24)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to borrow, with the approval of the Central Government,</p>
            <p>on the security of the property of the University,</p>
            <p>money for the purposes of the University;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.25">
          <num>(25)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to do all such other acts and things as may be  necessary, incidental or conducive to the attainment of  all or any of its objects.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Jurisdiction.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The jurisdiction of the University shall  extend to the  State of Meghalaya] and the Union territories of</p>
            <p>Arunachal Pradesh and Mizoram.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No College or Institution situated within the local limits of  the jurisdiction of the University shall be compulsorily affiliated to  the University, and affiliation shall be granted by the University  only to such Colleges or Institutions as may agree to accept the</p>
            <p>Statutes and Ordinances.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any College or Institution admitted to the privileges of the</p>
            <p>University shall cease to be associated with, or be admitted to the  privileges of, any other University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No College or Institution situated within the local limits of  the jurisdiction of the University, but not admitted to its  privileges, shall be associated with, or be admitted to the privileges  of, any other University except with the previous approval of the</p>
            <p>Government of the State in which, or the Administrator of the Union  territory in which, such College or Institution is situate.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>University open to all classes, castes and creed. The</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>University shall be open to persons of either sex and of whatever  race, creed, caste, or class, and it shall not be lawful for the</p>
            <p>University to adopt or impose on any person any test whatsoever of  religious belief or profession in order to entitle him to be admitted  therein, as a teacher or student, or to hold any office therein, or to  graduate thereat:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing in this section shall be deemed to prevent  the University from making special provisions for admission of  students of the weaker sections of the people in the North- Eastern  region and, in particular, of the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled</p>
            <p>Tribes.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Visitor.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The President of India shall be the Visitor of  the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Visitor shall have the right to cause an inspection to be  made by such person or persons as he may direct, of the University,</p>
            <p>its buildings, laboratories and equipment, and of any College or</p>
            <p>Institution maintained by the University or admitted to its  privileges; and also of the examinations, teaching and other work  conducted or done by the University and to cause an inquiry to be made  in like manner in respect of any matter connected with the  administration or finances of the University, Colleges or</p>
            <p>Institutions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Visitor shall, in every case, give notice of his  intention to cause an inspection or inquiry to be made,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to the University, if such inspection or inquiry is to  be made in respect of the University, College or</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-8.3.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Institution maintained by it, or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.3.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to the management of the College or Institution, if the  inspection or inquiry is to be made in respect of a</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>College or an Institution admitted to the privileges of  the University,</p>
            <p>and the University or the management, as the case may be, shall have  the right to make such representations to the Visitor, as it may  consider necessary.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>After considering the representations, if any, made by the</p>
            <p>University or the management, as the case may be, the Visitor may  cause to be made such inspection or inquiry as is referred to in sub-</p>
            <p>section (2).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any inspection or inquiry has been caused to be made by  the Visitor, the University or the management, as the case may be,</p>
            <p>shall be entitled to appoint a representative who shall have the right  to be present and be heard at such inspection or inquiry.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Visitor may, if the inspection or inquiry is made in  respect of the University or any College or Institution maintained by  it, address the Vice- Chancellor with reference to the result of such  inspection or inquiry, and the Vice- Chancellor shall communicate to  the Executive Council the views of the Visitor with such advice as the</p>
            <p>Visitor may be pleased to offer upon the action to be taken thereon.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Visitor may, if the inspection or inquiry is made in  respect of any College or Institution admitted to the privileges of  the University, address the management concerned through the Vice-</p>
            <p>Chancellor with reference to the result of such inspection or inquiry,</p>
            <p>his views thereon and such advice as he may be pleased to offer upon  the action to be taken thereon.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Executive Council or the management, as the case may be,</p>
            <p>shall communicate through the Vice- Chancellor to the Visitor such  action, if any, as it is proposed to take or has been taken upon the  result of such inspection or inquiry.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the Executive Council or the management does not,</p>
            <p>within a reasonable time, take action to the satisfaction of the</p>
            <p>Visitor, the Visitor may, after considering any explanation furnished  or representation made by the Executive Council or management, issue  such directions as he may think fit and the Executive Council or  management, as the case may be, shall comply with such directions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.10">
          <num>(10)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Without prejudice to the foregoing provisions of this  section, the Visitor may, by order in writing, annul any proceeding of  the University which is not in conformity with this Act, the Statutes  or Ordinances:</p>
            <p>Provided that before making any such order, he shall call upon  the University to show cause why such an order should not be made,</p>
            <p>and, if any cause is shown within a reasonable time, he shall consider  the same.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Visitor shall have such other powers as may be  prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Chief Rector. The Governor of the  State of Meghalaya] shall  be the Chief Rector of the University.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Officers of the University. The following shall be the  officers of the University:-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chancellor;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Vice- Chancellor;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Pro- Vice- Chancellors;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Deans of Schools;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Registrar;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Finance Officer; and</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Such other officers as may be declared by the Statutes  to be officers of the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>The Chancellor.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chancellor shall be appointed by the</p>
            <p>Visitor in such manner as may be prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chancellor shall, by virtue of his office, be the Head of  the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chancellor shall, if present, preside at the convocations  of the University held for conferring degrees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>The Vice- Chancellor.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Vice- Chancellor shall be  appointed by the Visitor in such manner as may be prescribed by the</p>
            <p>Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Vice- Chancellor shall be the principal executive and  academic officer of the University, and shall exercise general  supervision and control over the affairs of the University and give  effect to the decisions of all the authorities of the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Vice- Chancellor may, if he is of opinion that immediate  action is necessary on any matter, exercise any power conferred on any  authority of the University by or under this Act and shall report to  such authority the action taken by him on such matter:</p>
            <p>Provided that if the authority concerned is of opinion that such  action ought not to have been taken, it may refer the matter to the</p>
            <p>Visitor whose decision thereon shall be final:</p>
            <p>Provided further that any person in the service of the University  who is aggrieved by the action taken by the Vice- Chancellor under this  sub- section shall have the right to appeal against such action</p>
            <p>to the Executive Council within three months from the date on which  decision on such action is communicated to him and thereupon the</p>
            <p>Executive Council may confirm, modify or reverse the action taken by  the Vice- Chancellor.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Vice- Chancellor shall exercise such other powers and  perform such other functions as may be prescribed by the Statutes or</p>
            <p>Ordinances.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>The Pro- Vice- Chancellors. Every Pro- Vice- Chancellor shall be  appointed in such manner and shall exercise such powers and perform  such duties as may be prescribed by the Statutes.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Deans of Schools. Every Dean of a School shall be appointed  in such manner and shall exercise such powers and perform such duties  as may be prescribed by the Statutes.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>The Registrar.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Registrar shall be appointed in such  manner as may be prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Registrar shall have the power to enter into agreements,</p>
            <p>sign documents and authenticate records on behalf of the University  and shall exercise such other powers and perform such other duties as  may be prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>The Finance Officer. The Finance Officer shall be appointed  in such manner and shall exercise such powers and perform such duties  as may be prescribed by the Statutes.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Other officers. The manner of appointment and powers and  duties of other officers of the University shall be prescribed by the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Authorities of the University. The following shall be the  authorities of the University:-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Court;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Executive Council;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Academic Council;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Boards of Schools; and</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Such other authorities as may be declared by the</p>
            <p>Statutes to be authorities of the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>The Court.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-19.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The constitution of the Court and the term of  office of its members shall be prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-19.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Court shall have  the following powers and functions, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to review, from time to time, the broad policies and  programmes of the University and to suggest measures  for the improvement and development of the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to consider and pass resolutions on the annual report  and the annual accounts of the University and the audit  report on such accounts;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to advise the Visitor in respect of any matter which  may be referred to it for advice; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>to perform such other functions as may be prescribed by  the Statutes.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>The Executive Council.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-20.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Executive Council shall be the  principal executive body of the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The constitution of the Executive Council, the term of office  of its members and its powers and duties shall be prescribed by the</p>
            <p>Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>The Academic Council.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-21.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Academic Council shall be the  principal academic body of the University and shall, subject to the  provisions of this Act, the Statutes and Ordinances, co- ordinate and  exercise general supervision over the academic policies of the</p>
            <p>University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-21.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The constitution of the Academic Council, the term of office  of its members and its powers and duties shall be prescribed by the</p>
            <p>Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Other authorities of the University. The constitution, powers  and functions of the Boards of Schools and of such other authorities  as may be declared by the Statutes to be authorities of the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>University, shall be prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Planning Board.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-23.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be constituted a Planning</p>
            <p>Board of the University which shall advise generally on the planning  and development of the University and keep under review the standard  of education and research in the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-23.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Planning Board shall consist of-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-23.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>The Vice- Chancellor, who shall be the Chairman, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-23.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>not more than eight persons of high academic standing  who shall be appointed in such manner as may be  prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Visitor may determine a date with effect from which the</p>
            <p>Planning Board shall stand dissolved.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Power to make Statutes. Subject to the provisions of this</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Act, the Statutes may provide for all or any of the following matters,</p>
            <blockList id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the constitution, powers and functions of the  authorities and other bodies of the University, as may  be constituted from time to time;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the election and continuance in office of the members  of the said authorities and bodies, the filling of  vacancies of members, and all other matters relative to  those authorities and other bodies for which it may be  necessary or desirable to provide;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the appointment, powers and duties of the officers of  the University and their emoluments;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the appointment of teachers of the University and other  academic staff and their emoluments;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the appointment of teachers and other academic staff  working in any other University or organisation for a  specified period for undertaking a joint project;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the conditions of service of employees including  provision for pension, insurance and provident fund,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-24.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>the manner of termination of service and disciplinary  action;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list4.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the principles governing seniority of service of  employees;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list4.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the procedure for arbitration in cases of dispute  between employees or students and the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list4.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the procedure for appeal to the Executive Council by  any employee or student against the action of any  officer or authority of the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list4.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>the establishment and recognition of Students' Union or  associations of teachers, academic staff or other  employees;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list4.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>the participation of students in the affairs of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-24.paragraph-0.list6">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list6.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>the conferment of honorary degrees;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list6.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>the withdrawal of degrees, diplomas, certificates and  other academic distinctions;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list6.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>the institution of fellowships, scholarships,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-24.paragraph-0.list8">
              <listIntroduction>studentships, medals and prizes;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list8.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>the maintenance of discipline among the students;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list8.p">
                <num>(p)</num>
                <p>the establishment and abolition of Schools,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-24.paragraph-0.list10">
              <listIntroduction>Departments, Halls, Colleges and Institutions;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list10.q">
                <num>(q)</num>
                <p>the conditions under which Colleges and Institutions  may be admitted to the privileges of the University and  the withdrawal of such privileges;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list10.r">
                <num>(r)</num>
                <p>the delegation of powers vested in the authorities or  officers of the University; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list10.s">
                <num>(s)</num>
                <p>all other matters which by this Act are to be, or may  be, provided by the Statutes.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Statutes how made.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-25.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The first Statutes are those set out  in the Schedule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Executive Council may, from time to time, make new or  additional Statutes or may amend or repeal the Statutes referred to in  sub- section (1):</p>
            <p>Provided that the Executive Council shall not make, amend or  repeal any Statute affecting the status, powers or constitution of any  authority of the University until such authority has been given an  opportunity of expressing an opinion in writing on the proposed  changes, and any opinion so expressed shall be considered by the</p>
            <p>Executive Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every new Statute or addition to the Statutes or any  amendment or repeal of a Statute shall require the approval of the</p>
            <p>Visitor who may assent thereto or withhold assent or remit to the</p>
            <p>Executive Council for consideration.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A new Statute or a Statute amending or repealing an existing</p>
            <p>Statute shall have no validity unless it has been assented to by the</p>
            <p>Visitor.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing sub-</p>
            <p>sections, the Visitor may make new or additional Statutes or amend or  repeal the Statutes referred to in sub- section (1) during the period  of three years immediately after the commencement of this Act:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Visitor may, on the expiry of the said period  of three years make, within one year from the date of such expiry,</p>
            <p>such detailed Statutes as he may consider necessary and such detailed</p>
            <p>Statutes shall be laid before both Houses of Parliament.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Ordinances.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-26.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act and the</p>
            <blockList id="section-26.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Statutes, the Ordinances may provide for all or any of the following  matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-26.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the admission of students to the University and their  enrolment as such;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-26.1.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the courses of study to be laid down for all degrees,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-26.1.list4">
              <listIntroduction>diplomas and certificates of the University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-26.1.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the medium of instruction and examination;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-26.1.list4.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the award of degrees, diplomas, certificates and other  academic distinctions, the qualifications for the same  and the means to be taken relating to the granting and  obtaining of the same;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-26.1.list4.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the fees to be charged for courses of study in the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>University and for admission to the examinations,</p>
            <blockList id="section-26.1.list7">
              <listIntroduction>degrees and diplomas of the University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-26.1.list7.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the conditions of award of fellowships, scholarships,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-26.1.list9">
              <listIntroduction>studentships, medals and prizes;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-26.1.list9.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the conduct of examinations, including the term of  office and of appointment and the duties of examining  bodies, examiners and moderators;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-26.1.list9.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the conditions of residence of the students of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-26.1.list11">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-26.1.list11.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the special arrangements, if any, which may be made for  the residence, discipline and teaching of women  students and the prescribing of special courses of  studies for them;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-26.1.list11.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>the appointment and emoluments of employees other than  those for whom provision has been made in the Statutes;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-26.1.list11.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>the establishment of Centres of Studies, Boards of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-26.1.list13">
              <listIntroduction>Studies, Special Centres, specialised laboratories and  other Committees;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-26.1.list13.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>the manner of co- operation and collaboration with other</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-26.1.list15">
              <listIntroduction>Universities and authorities including learned bodies  or associations;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-26.1.list15.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>the creation, composition and functions of any other  body which is considered necessary for improving the  academic life of the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-26.1.list15.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>such other terms and conditions of service of teachers  and other academic staff as are not prescribed by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-26.1.list17">
              <listIntroduction>Statutes;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-26.1.list17.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>the management of Colleges and Institutions established  by the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-26.1.list17.p">
                <num>(p)</num>
                <p>the supervision and management of Colleges and</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Institutions admitted to the privileges of the</p>
            <blockList id="section-26.1.list20">
              <listIntroduction>University; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-26.1.list20.q">
                <num>(q)</num>
                <p>all other matters which by this Act or the Statutes may  be provided for by the Ordinances.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The first Ordinances shall be made by the Vice- Chancellor  with the previous approval of the Central Government and the</p>
            <p>Ordinances so made may be amended, repealed or added to at any time by  the Executive Council in the manner prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Regulations. The authorities of the University may make</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Regulations consistent with this Act, the Statutes and the Ordinances  for the conduct of their own business and that of the Committees  appointed by them and not provided for by this Act, the Statutes or  the Ordinances in the manner prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28">
        <num>28.</num>
        <heading>Annual report.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-28.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The annual report of the University shall  be prepared under the direction of the Executive Council and shall be  submitted to the court on or after such date as may be prescribed by  the Statutes and the Court shall consider the report in its annual  meeting.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-28.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Court shall submit the annual report to the Visitor along  with its comments, if any.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29">
        <num>29.</num>
        <heading>Annual accounts.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-29.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The annual accounts and balance- sheet of  the University shall be prepared under the directions of the Executive</p>
            <p>Council and shall once at least every year and at intervals of not  more than fifteen months be audited by the Comptroller and Auditor-</p>
            <p>General of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The annual accounts when audited shall be published in the</p>
            <p>Gazette of India and a copy of the accounts together with the report  of the Comptroller and Auditor- General shall be submitted to the Court  and the Visitor along with the observations of the Executive Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any observations made by the Visitor on the annual accounts  shall be brought to the notice of the Court and the observations of  the Court, if any, shall, after being considered by the Executive</p>
            <p>Council, be submitted to the Visitor.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-30">
        <num>30.</num>
        <heading>Conditions of service of employees.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-30.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every employee shall  be appointed under a written contract which shall be lodged with the</p>
            <p>University and a copy of which shall be furnished to the employee  concerned.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-30.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any dispute arising out of a contract between the University  and any employee shall, at the request of the employee, be referred to  a Tribunal of Arbitration consisting of one member appointed by the</p>
            <p>Executive Council, one member nominated by the employee concerned and  an umpire appointed by the Visitor. The decision of</p>
            <p>the Tribunal shall be final, and no suit shall lie in any civil court  in respect of the matters decided by the Tribunal. Every such request  shall be deemed to be a submission to arbitration upon the terms of  this section within the meaning of the Arbitration Act, 1940 (2 of</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1940">
        <num>1940.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1940.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-31">
        <num>31.</num>
        <heading>Procedure of appeal and arbitration in disciplinary cases  against students.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-31.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any student or candidate for an examination  whose name has been removed from the rolls of the University by the  orders or resolution of the Vice- Chancellor, Discipline Committee or</p>
            <p>Examination Committee, as the case may be, and who has been debarred  from appearing at the examinations of the University for more than one  year, may, within ten days of the date of receipt of such orders or  copy of such resolution by him, appeal to the Executive Council and  the Executive Council may confirm, modify or reverse the decision of  the Vice- Chancellor or the Committee, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-31.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any dispute arising out of any disciplinary action taken by  the University against a student shall, at the request of such  student, be referred to a Tribunal of Arbitration and the provisions  of sub- section (2) of section 30 shall, as far as may be, apply to a  reference made under this sub- section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-32">
        <num>32.</num>
        <heading>Right to appeal. Every employee or student of the University  or of a College or Institution shall, notwithstanding anything  contained in this Act, have a right to appeal, within such time as may  be prescribed by the Statutes, to the Executive Council against the  decision of any officer or authority of the University or of the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-32.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Principal or the management of any College or Institution, as the case  may be, and thereupon the Executive Council may confirm, modify or  reverse the decision appealed against.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-33">
        <num>33.</num>
        <heading>Provident and pension funds.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-33.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The University shall  constitute for the benefit of its employees such pension or provident  fund or provide such insurance schemes as it may deem fit in such  manner and subject to such conditions as may be prescribed by the</p>
            <p>Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-33.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where such provident or pension fund has been so constituted,</p>
            <p>the Central Government may declare that the provisions of the</p>
            <p>Provident Funds Act, 1925 (19 of 1925), shall apply to such fund, as  if it were a Government provident fund.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-34">
        <num>34.</num>
        <heading>Disputes as to constitution of University authorities and  bodies. If any question arises as to whether any person has been duly  elected or appointed as, or is entitled to be, a member of any  authority or other body of the University, the matter shall be  referred to the Visitor whose decision thereon shall be final.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-35">
        <num>35.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of Committees. Where any authority of the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-35.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>University is given power by this Act or the Statutes to appoint</p>
            <p>Committees, such Committees shall, save as otherwise provided, consist  of the members of the authority concerned and of such other persons</p>
            <p>(if any) as the authority in each case may think fit.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-36">
        <num>36.</num>
        <heading>Filling of casual vacancies. All casual vacancies among the  members (other than exofficio members) of any authority or other body  of the University shall be filled, as soon as conveniently may be, by  the person or body who appointed, elected or co- opted the member whose  place has become vacant and the person appointed, elected or co- opted  to a casual vacancy shall be a member of such authority or body for  the residue of the term for which the person whose place he fills  would have been a member.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-37">
        <num>37.</num>
        <heading>Proceedings of University authorities or bodies not  invalidated by vacancies. No act or proceedings of any authority or  other body of the University shall be invalidated merely by reason of  the existence of a vacancy or vacancies among its members.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-38">
        <num>38.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit or other  legal proceedings shall lie against any officer or employee of the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-38.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>University for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be  done in pursuance of any of the provisions of this Act, the Statutes  or Ordinances.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-39">
        <num>39.</num>
        <heading>Mode of proof of University record. A copy of any receipt,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-39.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>application, notice, order, proceeding, resolution of any authority or</p>
            <p>Committee of the University, or other documents in possession of the</p>
            <p>University, or any entry in any register duly maintained by the</p>
            <p>University, if certified by the Registrar, shall be received as prima  facie evidence of such receipt, application, notice, order, proceeding  or resolution, documents or the existence of entry in the register and  shall be admitted as evidence of the matters and transactions therein  where the original thereof would, if produced, have been admissible in  evidence, notwithstanding anything contained in the Indian Evidence</p>
            <p>Act, 1872 (1 of 1872) or in any other law for the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-40">
        <num>40.</num>
        <heading>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in  giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government  may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-40.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as appear to it to  be necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty:</p>
            <p>Provided that no such order shall be made under this section  after the expiry of three years from the commencement of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-41">
        <num>41.</num>
        <heading>Transitional provisions. Notwithstanding anything contained  in this Act and the Statutes-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-41.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-41.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-41.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the first Chancellor and the first Vice- Chancellor  shall be appointed by the Visitor and each of the said  officers shall hold office for a term of five years;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-41.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the first Registrar and the first Finance Officer shall  be appointed by the Visitor and each of the said  officers shall hold office for a term of three years;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-41.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the first Court and the first Executive Council shall  consist of not more than thirty members and eleven  members respectively, who shall be nominated by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-41.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Visitor and shall hold office for a term of three  years;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-41.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the first Academic Council shall be constituted on the  expiry of a period of six months from the commencement  of this Act and during the said period of six months,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-41.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>the powers of the Academic Council shall be performed  by the Planning Board constituted under section 23;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-41.paragraph-0.list4.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the first Academic Council shall consist of not more  than twenty- one members, who shall be nominated by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Visitor and shall hold office for a term of three  years:</p>
            <p>Provided that if any vacancy occurs in the above offices or  authorities, the same shall be filled by appointment or nomination, as  the case may be, by the Visitor, and the person so appointed or  nominated shall hold office for so long as the officer or member in  whose place he is appointed or nominated would have held office, if  such vacancy had not occurred.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-42">
        <num>42.</num>
        <heading>Completion of courses of students in Colleges or Institutions  affiliated to the University. Notwithstanding anything contained in  this Act, or in the Statutes or the Ordinances, any student of a</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-42.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>College or Institution, who, immediately before the admission of such</p>
            <p>College or Institution to the privileges of the North- Eastern Hill</p>
            <p>University, was studying for a degree, diploma or certificate of the</p>
            <p>Gauhati University, shall be permitted by the North- Eastern Hill</p>
            <p>University to complete his course for that degree, diploma or  certificate, as the case may be, and the North- Eastern Hill University  and such College or Institution shall provide for the instruction and  examination of such student in accordance with the syllabus of studies  of the Gauhati University.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be  called the North- Eastern Hill University Act, 1973.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the States of Meghalaya and Nagaland and the</p>
            <p>Union territories of Arunachal Pradesh and Mizoram.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such 1date as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, and in all Statutes made hereunder,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>unless the context otherwise requires,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" Academic Council" means the Academic Council of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" academic staff" means such categories of staff as are  designated as academic staff by the Ordinances;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" Board of Studies" means the Board of Studies of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>" Chancellor"," Vice- Chancellor" and" Pro- Vice- Chancellor"</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>mean, respectively, the Chancellor, Vice- Chancellor and Pro-</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list8">
              <listIntroduction>Vice- Chancellor of the University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list8.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>" College" means a College maintained by, or admitted to  the privileges of, the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list8.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>" Court" means the Court of the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list8.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>" Department" means a Department of Studies, and includes</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10">
              <listIntroduction>Centre of Studies;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>" employee" means any person appointed by the University,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list12">
              <listIntroduction>and includes teachers and other staff of the University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list12.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>" Executive Council" means the Executive Council of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list14">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list14.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>" Hall" means a unit of residence or of corporate life for  the students of the University, College or Institution,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list16">
              <listIntroduction>provided, maintained or recognised by the University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list16.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>" Institution" means an academic Institution, not being a</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>College. maintained by, or admitted to the privileges of, the</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list19">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list19.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>" North- Eastern region" means the North- Eastern region of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>India comprising the States of Meghalaya and Nagaland and the</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list22">
              <listIntroduction>Union territories of Arunachal Pradesh and Mizoram;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list22.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>" Principal" means the Head of a College or an</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Institution, and includes where there is no Principal, the  person for the time being duly appointed to act as Principal,</p>
            <p>and, in the absence of the Principal or the acting Principal,</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list26">
              <listIntroduction>a Vice- Principal duly appointed as such;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list26.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>" recognised teachers" means such persons as are  recognised by the University for the purpose of imparting  instruction in a College or an Institution admitted to the  privileges of the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list26.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>" School" means a School of Studies of the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list26.p">
                <num>(p)</num>
                <p>" Statutes"," Ordinances" and" Regulations", mean,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>respectively, the Statutes, Ordinances and Regulations of the</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list29">
              <listIntroduction>University for the time being in force;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list29.q">
                <num>(q)</num>
                <p>" teachers of the University" means Professors, Readers,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Lecturers and such other persons as may be appointed for  imparting instruction or conducting research in the</p>
            <p>University or in any College or Institution maintained by the</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list33">
              <listIntroduction>University and are designated as teachers by the Ordinances;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list33.r">
                <num>(r)</num>
                <p>" University" means the North- Eastern Hill University.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>The University.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be established a University by  the name of" North- Eastern Hill University".</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The headquarters of the University shall be at Shillong and  it shall have campuses in the States of Meghalaya and Nagaland; it may  also establish campuses at such other places within its jurisdiction  as it may deem fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The first Chancellor and the first Vice- Chancellor and the  first members of the Court, the Executive Council and the Academic</p>
            <p>Council and all persons who may hereafter become such officers or  members, so long as they continue to hold such office or membership,</p>
            <p>are hereby constituted a body corporate by the name of" North- Eastern</p>
            <p>Hill University".</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The University shall have perpetual succession and a common  seal, and shall sue and be sued by the said name.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Objects. The objects of the University shall be to disseminate  and advance knowledge by providing instructional and research  facilities in such branches of learning as it may deem fit; to pay  special attention to the improvement of the social and economic  conditions and welfare of the people of the hill areas of the North-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Eastern region and, in particular, their intellectual, academic and  cultural advancement.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Powers of the University. The University shall have the  following powers, namely:-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to provide for instruction in such branches of learning  as the University may, from time to time, determine and to  make provision for research and for the advancement and  dissemination of knowledge;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to take such academic steps as would contribute to the  improvement of the economic conditions and welfare of the  people of the hill areas of the North- Eastern region;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to grant, subject to such conditions as the University  may determine, diplomas or certificates to, and confer  degrees and other academic distinctions on the basis of  examinations, evaluation or any other method of testing, on  persons, and to withdraw any such diplomas, certificates,</p>
            <p>degrees or other academic distinctions for good and  sufficient cause;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to organise and to undertake extra- mural studies and  extension services;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to confer honorary degrees or other distinctions in the  manner prescribed by the Statutes;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to provide instruction, including correspondence and such  other courses, to such persons as are not members of the</p>
            <p>University, as it may determine;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to institute principalships, professorships, readerships,</p>
            <p>lecturerships, and other teaching or academic posts required  by the University and to appoint persons to such  principalships, professorships, readerships, lecturerships or  other posts;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to recognise persons for imparting instruction in any</p>
            <p>College or Institution admitted to the privileges of the</p>
            <p>University;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to appoint persons working in any other University or  organisation as teachers of the University for a specified  period;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.10">
          <num>(10)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to create administrative, ministerial and other posts  and to make appointments thereto;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to co- operate or collaborate with any other University  or authority in such manner and for such purposes as the</p>
            <p>University may determine;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.12">
          <num>(12)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to establish such campuses, centres, specialised  laboratories or other units for research and instruction as  are, in the opinion of the University, necessary for the  furtherance of its objects;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.13">
          <num>(13)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to institute and award fellowships, scholarships,</p>
            <p>studentships, medals and prizes;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.14">
          <num>(14)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to establish and maintain Colleges, Institutions and</p>
            <p>Halls;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.15">
          <num>(15)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to admit to its privileges Colleges and Institutions not  maintained by the University; to withdraw all or any of those  privilege' s in accordance with such conditions as may be  prescribed by the Statutes; and to recognise Halls not  maintained by the University and to withdraw any such  recognition;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.16">
          <num>(16)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to declare a College, an Institution or a Department as  an autonomous College or an Institution or a Department, as  the case may be;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.17">
          <num>(17)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to determine standards for admission into the</p>
            <p>University, which may include examination, evaluation or any  other method of testing;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.18">
          <num>(18)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to demand and receive payment of fees and other charges;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.19">
          <num>(19)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to supervise the residences of the students of the</p>
            <p>University and to make arrangements for promoting their  health and general welfare;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.20">
          <num>(20)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to make special arrangements in respect of women  students as the University may consider desirable;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.21">
          <num>(21)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to regulate and enforce discipline among the employees  and students of the University and take such disciplinary  measures in this regard as may be deemed necessary;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.22">
          <num>(22)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to make arrangements for promoting the health and  general welfare of the employees;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.23">
          <num>(23)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to acquire, hold, manage and dispose of property,</p>
            <p>movable or immovable, including trust and endowment  properties for the purposes of the University;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.24">
          <num>(24)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to borrow, with the approval of the Central Government,</p>
            <p>on the security of the property of the University, money for  the purposes of the University;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.25">
          <num>(25)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to do all such other acts and things as may be  necessary, incidental or conducive to the attainment of all  or any of its. objects.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Jurisdiction.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The jurisdiction of the University shall  extend to the States of Meghalaya and Nagaland and the Union  territories of Arunachal Pradesh and Mizoram.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No College or Institution situated within the local limits of  the jurisdiction of the University shall be compulsorily affiliated to  the University, and affiliation shall be granted by the University  only to such</p>
            <p>Colleges or Institutions as may agree to accept the Statutes and Ordi-</p>
            <p>nances.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any College or Institution admitted to the privileges of the</p>
            <p>University shall cease to be associated with, or be admitted to the  privileges of any other University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No College or Institution situated within the local limits of  the jurisdiction of the University, but not admitted to its  privileges, shall be associated with, or be admitted to the privileges  of, any other University except with the previous approval of the</p>
            <p>Government of the State in which, or the Administrator of the Union  territory in Which, such College or Institution is situate.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>University open to all classes, castes and creed. The</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>University shall be open to persons of either sex and of whatever  race, creed, caste, or class, and it shall not be lawful for the</p>
            <p>University to adopt or impose on any person any test whatsoever of  religious belief or profession in order to entitle him to be admitted  therein, as a teacher or student, or to hold any office therein, or to  graduate thereat:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing in this section shall be deemed to prevent  the University from making special provisions for admission of  students of the weaker sections of the people in the North- Eastern  region and, in particular, of the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled</p>
            <p>Tribes.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Visitor.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The President of India shall be the Visitor of  the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The, Visitor shall have the right to cause an inspection to  be made by such person or persons as he may direct, of the University,</p>
            <p>its buildings, laboratories and equipment, and of any College or</p>
            <p>Institution maintained by the University or admitted to its  privileges; and also of the examinations, teaching and other work  conducted or done by the University and to cause an inquiry to be made  in like manner in respect of any matter connected with the  administration or finances of the University, Colleges or</p>
            <p>Institutions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Visitor shall, in every case, give notice of his  intention to cause an inspection or inquiry to be made,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to the University, if such inspection or inquiry is to be  made in respect of the University, College or Institution  maintained by it, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to the management of the College or Institution, if the  inspection or inquiry is to be made in respect of a College  or an Institution admitted to the privileges of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>University,</p>
            <p>and the University or the management, as the case may be, shall have  the right to make such representations to the Visitor, as it may  consider necessary.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>After considering the representations, if any, made by the</p>
            <p>University or the management, as the case may be, the Visitor may  cause to be made such inspection or inquiry as is referred to in sub-</p>
            <p>section (2).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any inspection or inquiry has been caused to be made by  the Visitor, the University or the management, as the case may be,</p>
            <p>shall be entitled to appoint a representative who shall have the right  to be present and be heard at such inspection or inquiry.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Visitor may, if the inspection or inquiry is made in  respect of the University or any College or Institution maintained by  it, address the Vice- Chancellor with reference to the result of such  inspection or inquiry, and the Vice- Chancellor shall communicate to  the Executive Council the views of the Visitor with such advice as the</p>
            <p>Visitor may be pleased to offer upon the action to be taken thereon.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Visitor may, if the inspection or inquiry is made in  respect of any College or Institution admitted to the privileges of  the University, address the management concerned through the Vice-</p>
            <p>Chancellor with reference to the result of such inspection or inquiry,</p>
            <p>his views thereon and such advice as he may be pleased to offer upon  the action to be taken thereon.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Executive Council or the management, as the case may be,</p>
            <p>shall communicate through the Vice- Chancellor to the Visitor such ac-</p>
            <p>tion, if any, as it is proposed to take or has been taken upon the  result of such inspection or inquiry.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the Executive Council or the management does not within  reasonable time take action to the satisfaction of the Visitor, the</p>
            <p>Visitor may after considering any explanation furnished or  representation made by the Executive Council or management, issue such  directions as he may think, fit and the Executive Council or  management, as the case may be shall comply with such directions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.10">
          <num>(10)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Without prejudice to the foregoing provisions of this  section, the Visitor may, by order in writing, annul any proceeding of  the University which is not in conformity with this Act, the Status or</p>
            <p>Ordinances:</p>
            <p>Provided that before making any such order, he shall call upon  the University to show cause why such an order should not be made,</p>
            <p>and, if any cause is' shown within a reasonable time, he shall  consider the same.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Visitor shall have such other powers as may be  prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Chief Rector. The Governor of the States of Meghalaya and</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Nagaland shall be the Chief Rector of the University.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>The Chancellor.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chancellor shall be appointed by the</p>
            <p>Visitor in such manner as may be prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chancellor shall, by virtue of his office, be the Head of  the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chancellor shall, if present, preside at the convocations  of the University held for conferring degrees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>The Vice- Chancellor.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Vice- Chancellor shall be  appointed by the Visitor in such manner as may be prescribed by the</p>
            <p>Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Vice- Chancellor shall be the principal executive and  academic officer of the University, and shall exercise general  supervision and control over the affairs of the University and give  effect to the decisions of all the authorities of the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Vice- Chancellor may, if he is of opinion that immediate  action is necessary on any matter, exercise any power conferred on any  authority of the University by or under this Act and shall report to  such authority the action taken by him on such matter:</p>
            <p>Provided that if the authority concerned is of opinion that such  action ought not to have been taken, it may refer the matter to the</p>
            <p>Visitor whose decision thereon shall be final:</p>
            <p>Provided further that any person in the service of the University  who is aggrieved by the action taken by the Vice- Chancellor under this  subsection shall have the right to appeal against such action to the</p>
            <p>Executive Council within three months from the date on which decision  on such action is communicated to him and thereupon the Executive</p>
            <p>Council may confirm, modify or reverse the action taken by the Vice-</p>
            <p>Chancellor.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Vice- Chancellor shall exercise such other powers and  perform such other functions as may be prescribed by the Statutes or</p>
            <p>Ordinances.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>The Pro- Vice- Chancellors. Every Pro- Vice- Chancellor shall be  appointed in such manner and shall exercise such powers and perform  such duties, as may be prescribed by the Statutes.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Deans of Schools. Every Dean of a School shall be appointed  in such manner and shall exercise such powers and perform such duties  as may be prescribed by the Statutes.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>The Registrar.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Registrar shall be appointed in such  manner as may be prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Registrar shall have the power to enter into agreements,</p>
            <p>sign documents and authenticate records on behalf of the University  and shall exercise such other powers and perform such other duties as  may be prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>The Finance Officer. The Finance Officer shall be appointed  in such manner and shall exercise such powers and perform such duties  as may be prescribed by the Statutes.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Other officers. The manner of appointment and powers and  duties of other officers of the University shall be prescribed by the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Authorities of the University. The following shall be the  authorities of the University:-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Court;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Executive Council;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Academic Council;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board of Schools; and</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Such other authorities as may be declared by the</p>
            <p>Statutes to be authorities of the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>The Court.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-19.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The constitution of the Court and the term of  office of its members shall be prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-19.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Court shall have  the following powers and functions, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-19.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to review, from time to time, the broad policies and pro-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-19.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>grammes of the University and to suggest measures for the  improvement and development of the University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-19.2.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to consider and pass resolutions on the annual report and  the annual accounts of the University and the audit report on  such accounts;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to advise the Visitor in respect of any matter which may  be referred to it for advice; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.2.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>to perform such other functions as may be prescribed by  the Statutes.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>The Executive Council.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-20.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Executive Council shall be the  principal executive body of the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The constitution of the Executive Council, the term of office  of its members and its powers and duties shall be prescribed by the</p>
            <p>Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>The Academic Council.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-21.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Academic Council shall be the  principal academic body of the University and shall, subject to the  provisions of this Act, the Statutes and Ordinances, co- ordinate and  exercise general supervision over the academic policies of the</p>
            <p>University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-21.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The constitution of the Academic Council, the term of office  of its members and its powers and duties shall be prescribed by the</p>
            <p>Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Other authorities of the University. The constitution, powers  and functions of the Boards of Schools and of such other authorities  as may be declared by the Statute' s to be authorities of the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>University, shall be prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Planning Board.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-23.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be constituted a Planning</p>
            <p>Board of the University which shall advise generally on the planning  and development of the University and keep under review the standard  of education and research in the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-23.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Planning Board shall consist of-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-23.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the Vice- Chancellor, who shall be the Chairman, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-23.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>not more than eight persons of high academic standing who  shall be appointed in such manner as, may be prescribed by  the Statutes.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Visitor may determine a date with effect from which the</p>
            <p>Planning Board shall stand dissolved.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Power to make Statutes. Subject to the provisions of this</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Act, the Statutes may provide for all or any of the following Matters,</p>
            <blockList id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the constitution, powers and functions of the authorities  and other bodies of the University, as may be constituted  from time to time;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the election and continuance in office of the members of  the said authorities and bodies, the filling of vacancies of  members, and all other matters relative to those authorities  and other bodies for which it may be necessary or desirable  to provide;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the appointment, powers and duties of the officers of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-24.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>University and their emoluments;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list4.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the appointment of teachers of the University and other  academic staff and their emoluments;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list4.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the appointment of teachers and other academic staff  working in a other University or organisation for a specified  period for undertaking a joint project;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list4.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the conditions of service of employees including  provision for pension, insurance and provident fund, the  manner of termination of service and disciplinary action;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list4.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the principles governing seniority of service of  employees;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list4.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the procedure for arbitration in cases of dispute between  employees or students and the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list4.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the procedure for appeal to the Executive Council by any  employee or student against the action of any officer or  authority of the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list4.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>the establishment and recognition of Student' s Union or  associations of teachers, academic staff or other employees;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list4.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>the participation of students in the affairs of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-24.paragraph-0.list6">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list6.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>the conferment of honorary degrees;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list6.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>the withdrawal of degrees, diplomas, certificates and  other academic distinctions;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list6.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>the institution of fellowships, scholarships,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-24.paragraph-0.list8">
              <listIntroduction>studentships, medals and prizes;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list8.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>the maintenance of discipline among the students;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list8.p">
                <num>(p)</num>
                <p>the establishment and abolition of Schools. Departments.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-24.paragraph-0.list10">
              <listIntroduction>Halls, Colleges and Institutions;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list10.q">
                <num>(q)</num>
                <p>the conditions under which Colleges and Institutions may  be admitted to the privileges of the University and the  withdrawal of such privileges;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list10.r">
                <num>(r)</num>
                <p>The delegation of powers vested in the authorities or  officers of the University; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list10.s">
                <num>(s)</num>
                <p>all other matters which by this Act are to be, or may be,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>provided by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Statutes how made.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-25.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The first Statutes are those set out  in the Schedule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Executive Council may, from time to time, make new or  additional Statutes or may amend or repeal the Statutes referred to in  subsection (1):</p>
            <p>Provided that the Executive Council shall not make, amend or  repeal any Statute affecting the status, powers or constitution of any  authority</p>
            <p>of the University until such authority has been given an opportunity  of expressing an opinion in writing on the proposed changes, and any  opinion so expressed shall be considered by the Executive Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every new Statute or addition to the Statutes or any  amendment or repeal of a Statute shall require the approval of the</p>
            <p>Visitor who may assent thereto or withhold assent or remit to the</p>
            <p>Executive Council for consideration.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A new Statute or a Statute amending or repealing an existing</p>
            <p>Statute shall have no validity unless it has been assented to by the</p>
            <p>Visitor.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing sub-</p>
            <p>sections, the Visitor may make new or additional Statutes or amend or  repeal the Statutes referred to in sub- section (1) during the period  of three years immediately after the commencement of this Act:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Visitor may, on the expiry of the said period  of three years make, within one year from the date of such expiry,</p>
            <p>such detailed Statutes as he may consider necessary and such detailed</p>
            <p>Statutes shall be laid before both Houses of Parliament.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Ordinances.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-26.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act and the</p>
            <blockList id="section-26.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Statutes, the Ordinances may provide for all or any of the following  matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-26.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the admission of students to the University and their  enrolment as such;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-26.1.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the courses of study to be laid down for all degrees,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-26.1.list4">
              <listIntroduction>diplomas and certificates of the University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-26.1.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the medium of instruction and examination;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-26.1.list4.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the award of degrees, diplomas, certificates and other  academic distinctions, the qualifications for the same and  the means to be taken relating to the granting and obtaining  of the same;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-26.1.list4.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the fees to be charged for courses of study in the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-26.1.list6">
              <listIntroduction>University and for admission to the examinations, degrees and  diplomas of the University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-26.1.list6.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the conditions of award of fellowships, scholarships,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-26.1.list8">
              <listIntroduction>student ships, medals and prizes;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-26.1.list8.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the conduct of examinations, including the term of office  and of appointment and the duties of examining bodies,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-26.1.list10">
              <listIntroduction>examiners and moderators;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-26.1.list10.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the conditions of residence of the students of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-26.1.list12">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-26.1.list12.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the special arrangements, if any, which may be made for  the residence, discipline and teaching of women students and  the prescribing of special courses of studies for them;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-26.1.list12.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>the appointment and emoluments of employees other than  those for whom provision has been made in the Statutes;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-26.1.list12.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>the establishment of Centres of Studies, Boards of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Studies, Special Centres, specialised laboratories and other</p>
            <blockList id="section-26.1.list15">
              <listIntroduction>Committees;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-26.1.list15.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>the manner of co- operation and collaboration with other</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-26.1.list17">
              <listIntroduction>Universities and authorities including learned bodies or  associations;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-26.1.list17.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>the creation, composition and functions of any other body  which is considered necessary for improving the academic life  of the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-26.1.list17.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>such other terms and conditions of service of teachers  and other academic staff as are not prescribed by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-26.1.list19">
              <listIntroduction>Statutes;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-26.1.list19.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>the management of Colleges and Institutions established  by the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-26.1.list19.p">
                <num>(p)</num>
                <p>the supervision and management of Colleges and</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Institutions admitted to the privileges of the University;</p>
            <blockList id="section-26.1.list22">
              <listIntroduction>and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-26.1.list22.q">
                <num>(q)</num>
                <p>all other matters which by this Act or the Statutes may  be provided for by the Ordinances.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The first Ordinances shall be made by the Vice- Chancellor  with the previous approval of the Central Government and the</p>
            <p>Ordinances so made may be amended, repealed or added to at any time by  the Executive Council in the manner prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Regulations. The authorities of the University may make</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Regulations consistent with this Act, the Statutes and the Ordinances  for the conduct of their own business and that of the Committees  appointed by them and not provided for by this Act, the Statutes or  the Ordinances in the manner prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28">
        <num>28.</num>
        <heading>Annual report.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-28.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The annual report of the University shall  be prepared under the direction of the Executive Council and shall be  submitted to the Court on or after such date as may be prescribed by  the Statutes and the Court shall consider the report in its annual  meeting.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-28.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Court shall submit the annual report to the Visitor along  with its comments, if any.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29">
        <num>29.</num>
        <heading>Annual accounts.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-29.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The annual accounts and balance- sheet of  the University shall be prepared under the directions of the Executive</p>
            <p>Council and shall once at least every year and at intervals of not  more than fifteen months be audited by the Comptroller and Auditor-</p>
            <p>General of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The annual accounts when audited shall be published in the</p>
            <p>Gazette of India and a copy of the accounts together with the report  of the Comptroller and Auditor- General shall be submitted to the Court  and the Visitor along with the observations of the Executive Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any observations made by the Visitor on the annual accounts  shall be brought to the notice of the Court and the observations of  the Court, if any, shall, after being considered by the Executive</p>
            <p>Council, be submitted to the Visitor.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-30">
        <num>30.</num>
        <heading>Conditions of service of employees.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-30.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every employee shall  be appointed under a written contract which shall be lodged with the</p>
            <p>University and a copy of which shall be furnished to the employee  concerned.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-30.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any dispute arising out of a contract between the University  and any employee shall, at the request of the employee, be referred to  a Tribunal of Arbitration consisting of one member appointed by the</p>
            <p>Executive Council, one member nominated by the employee concerned and  an umpire appointed by the Visitor. The decision of the Tribunal  shall be final, and no suit shall lie in any civil court in respect of  the matters decided by the Tribunal. Exery such request shall be  deemed to be a submission to arbitration upon the terms of this  section within the meaning of the Arbitration Act, 1940. (2 of 1940)</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-31">
        <num>31.</num>
        <heading>Procedure of appeal and arbitration in disciplinary cases  against students.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-31.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any student or candidate for an examination  whose name has been removed from the rolls of the University by the  orders or resolution of the Vice- Chancellor, Discipline Committee or</p>
            <p>Examination Committee, as the case may be, and who has been debarred  from appearing at the examinations of the University for more than one  year, may, within ten days of the date of receipt of such orders or  copy of such resolution by him, appeal to the Executive Council and  the Executive Council may confirm, modify or reverse the decision of  the Vice- Chancellor or the Committee, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-31.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any dispute arising out of any disciplinary action taken by  the University against a student shall, at the request of such  student, be referred to a Tribunal of Arbitration and the provisions  of sub- section (2) of section 30 shall, as far as may be, apply to a  reference made under this sub- section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-32">
        <num>32.</num>
        <heading>Right to appeal. Every employee or student of the University  or of a College or Institution shall, notwithstanding anything  contained in this Act, have a right to appeal, within such time as may  be prescribed by the Statutes, to the Executive Council against the  decision of any officer or authority of the University or of the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-32.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Principal or the management of any college or Institution, as the case  may be, and thereupon the Executive Council may confirm, modify or  reverse the decision appealed against.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-33">
        <num>33.</num>
        <heading>Provident and pension funds.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-33.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The University shall  constitute for the benefit of its employees such pension or provident  fund or provide such insurance schemes as it may deem fit in such  manner and subject to such conditions as may be prescribed by the</p>
            <p>Statutes.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-33.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where such provident or pension fund has been so constituted,</p>
            <p>the Central Government may declare that the provisions of the</p>
            <p>Provident Funds Act, 1925, (19 of 1925) shall apply to such fund, as  if it were a Government provident fund.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-34">
        <num>34.</num>
        <heading>Disputes as to constitution of University authorities and  bodies. If any question arises as to whether any person has been duly  elected or appointed as, or is entitled to be, a member of any  authority or other body of the University, the matter shall be  referred to the Visitor whose decision thereon shall be final.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-35">
        <num>35.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of Committees. Where any authority of the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-35.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>University is given power by this Act or the Statutes to appoint</p>
            <p>Committees, such Committees shall, save as otherwise provided, consist  of the members of the authority concerned and of such other persons</p>
            <p>(if any) as the authority in each case may think fit.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-36">
        <num>36.</num>
        <heading>Filling of casual vacancies. All casual vacancies among the  members (other than ex- officio members) of any authority or other body  of the University shall be filled as soon as conveniently may be, by  the person or body who appointed elected or co- opted the member whose  place has become vacant and the person appointed, elected or co- opted  to a casual vacancy shall be a member of such authority or body for  the residue of the term for which the person whose place he fills  would have been a member.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-37">
        <num>37.</num>
        <heading>Proceedings of University authorities of bodies not  invalidated by vacancies. No act or proceedings of any authority or  other body of the University shall be invalidated merely by reason of  the existence' of a vacancy or vacancies among its members.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-38">
        <num>38.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit or other  legal proceedings shall lie against Any officer or employee of the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-38.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>University for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be  done in pursuance of any of the provisions of this Act, the Statutes  or Ordinances.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-39">
        <num>39.</num>
        <heading>Mode of proof of University record. A copy of any receipt,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-39.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>application, notice, order, proceeding, resolution of any authority or</p>
            <p>Committee of the University, or other documents in possession of the</p>
            <p>University, or any entry in any register duly maintained by the</p>
            <p>University, if certified by the Registrar, shall be received as prima  facie evidence of such receipt, application, notice, order, proceeding  or resolution, documents or the existence of entry in the register and  shall be admitted as evidence of the matters and transactions' therein  where the original thereof would, if produced, have been admissible in  evidence, notwithstanding anything contained in the Indian Evidence</p>
            <p>Act, 1872 (1 of 1872) or in any other law for the time being in  force.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-40">
        <num>40.</num>
        <heading>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in  giving effect to the provisions of this the Central Government may, by  order published in the official Gazette, make such Provisions, not  inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as appear to it to be  necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty:</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-40.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Provided that no such order shall be made under this section  after the expiry of three years from the commencement of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-41">
        <num>41.</num>
        <heading>Transitional provisions. Notwithstanding anything contained  in this Act and the Statutes-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-41.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-41.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-41.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the first Chancellor and the first Vice- Chancellor shall  be' appointed by the Visitor and each of the said officers  shall hold office for a term of five years;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-41.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the first Registrar and the first Finance Officer shall  be appointed by the Visitor and each of the said officers  shall hold office for a term of three years;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-41.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the first Court and the first Executive Council shall  consist of not more than thirty members and eleven members  respectively, who shall be nominated by the Visitor and shall  hold office for a term of three years;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-41.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the first Academic Council shall be constituted on the  expiry of a period of six months from the commencement of  this Act and during the said period of six months, the powers  of the Academic Council shall be performed by the Planning</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-41.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Board constituted under section 23;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-41.paragraph-0.list2.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the first Academic Council shall consist of not more than  twenty- one members, who shall be nominated by the Visitor and  shall hold office for a term of three years:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that if any vacancy occurs in the above offices or  authorities, the same shall be filled by appointment or nomination, as  the case may be, by the Visitor, and the, person so appointed or  nominated shall hold office for so long as the officer or member in  whose place he is appointed or nominated would have held office, if  such vacancy had not occurred.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-42">
        <num>42.</num>
        <heading>Completion of courses of students in Colleges or Institutions  affiliated to the University. Notwithstanding anything contained in  this Act, or in the Statutes or the Ordinances, any student of a</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-42.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>College or Institution, who, immediately before the admission of such</p>
            <p>College or Institution to the privileges of the North- Eastern Hill</p>
            <p>University, was studying for a degree, diploma or certificate of the</p>
            <p>Gauhati University, shall be permitted by the North- Eastern Hill</p>
            <p>University to complete his course for that degree, diploma or  certificate, as the case may be, and the North- Eastern Hill University  and such College or Institution shall provide for the instruction and  examination of such student in accordance with the syllabus of studies  of the Gauhati University.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>The Vice- Chancellor.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Vice- Chancellor shall be a whole-</p>
            <p>time salaried officer of the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Vice- Chancellor shall hold office for a term of five  years from the date on which he enters upon his office and shall be  eligible for reappointment for not more than another term:</p>
            <p>Provided that notwithstanding the expiry of the said period of  five years, he shall continue in office until his successor is  appointed and enters upon his office:</p>
            <p>Provided further that the Visitor may direct that a Vice-</p>
            <p>Chancellor, whose term of office has expired, shall continue in office  for such period, not exceeding a total period of one year, as may be  specified in the direction.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in clause (2), a person  appointed as Vice- Chancellor shall, if he completes the age of sixty-</p>
            <p>five years during the term of his office or any extension thereof,</p>
            <p>retire from office.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-1.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The emoluments and other terms and conditions of service of  the Vice- Chancellor shall be as follows:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1.4.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>There shall be paid to the Vice- Chancellor a salary of  two thousand and five hundred rupees per mensem and he shall  be entitled, without payment of rent, to use a furnished  residence throughout his term of office and no charge shall  fall on the Vice- Chancellor personally in respect of the  maintenance of such residence.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1.4.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>The Vice- Chancellor shall not be entitled to the  benefits of the University Provident Fund:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-1.4.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that where an employee of--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1.4.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the University or College or Institution maintained by,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-1.4.list5">
              <listIntroduction>or affiliated to, it; or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1.4.list5.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any other University or College or Institution maintained  by, or affiliated to, that University,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-1.4.list7">
              <listIntroduction>is appointed as Vice- Chancellor, he shall be allowed to  continue to contribute to the provident fund to which he is a  subscriber, and the contribution of the University shall be  limited to what he had been contributing immediately before  his appointment as Vice- Chancellor.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1.4.list7.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>The Vice- Chancellor shall be entitled to travelling  allowances at such rates as may be fixed by the Executive</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-1.4.list9">
              <listIntroduction>Council.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1.4.list9.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>The Vice- Chancellor shall be entitled to leave on full  pay for one- eleventh of the period spent by him on active  service.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1.4.list9.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>The Vice- Chancellor shall also be entitled, on medical  grounds or otherwise, to leave without pay for a period not  exceeding three months during the term of his office:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that such leave may be converted into leave on full pay  to the extent to which he is entitled to leave under sub- clause (iv).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the office of the Vice- Chancellor becomes vacant due to  death, resignation or otherwise or if he is unable to perform his  duties owing to absence, illness or any other cause, the Pro- Vice-</p>
            <p>Chancellor or if there is more than one Pro- Vice- Chancellor, the  senior- most Pro- Vice- Chancellor, shall perform the duties of the Vice-</p>
            <p>Chancellor until a new Vice- Chancellor assumes office or until the  existing Vice- Chancellor attends to the duties of his office, as the  case may be:</p>
            <p>Provided that if a Pro- Vice- Chancellor is not available, the  seniormost Professor shall perform the duties of the Vice- Chancellor.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Powers and duties of the Vice- Chancellor.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Vice-</p>
            <p>Chancellor shall be ex- officio Chairman of the Court, the Executive</p>
            <p>Council, the Academic Council and the Finance Committee, and shall, in  the absence of the Chancellor, preside at the Convocations of the</p>
            <p>University held for conferring degrees. The Vice- Chancellor shall be  entitled to be present at, and to address, any meeting of any  authority or other body of the University, but shall not be entitled  to vote thereat unless he is a member of such authority or body.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be the duty of the Vice- Chancellor to see that this</p>
            <p>Act, these Statutes, the Ordinances and the Regulations are duly  observed, and he shall have all powers necessary to ensure such  observance.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Vice- Chancellor shall have the power to convene or cause  to be convened meetings of the Court, the Executive Council, the</p>
            <p>Academic Council and the Finance Committee.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Pro- Vice- Chancellor.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Pro- Vice- Chancellor shall be  appointed by the Executive Council on the recommendations of the Vice-</p>
            <p>Chancellor:</p>
            <p>Provided that where the recommendation of the Vice- Chancellor is  not accepted by the Executive Council, the matter shall be referred to  the Visitor who may either appoint the person recommended by the Vice-</p>
            <p>Chancellor or ask the Vice- Chancellor to recommend another person to  the Executive Council:</p>
            <p>Provided further that the Executive Council may, on the recommen-</p>
            <p>dation of the Vice- Chancellor, appoint a Professor to discharge the  duties of a Pro- Vice- Chancellor in addition to his own duties as a</p>
            <p>Professor.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The term of office of a Pro- Vice- Chancellor shall be such as  may be decided by the Executive Council, but it shall not in any case  exceed five years or until the expiration of the term of office of the</p>
            <p>Vice- Chancellor, whichever is earlier, and he shall be eligible for  reappointment:</p>
            <p>Provided that a Pro- Vice- Chancellor shall retire on attaining the  age of sixty- five years.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The emoluments and other terms and conditions of service of a</p>
            <p>Pro- Vice- Chancellor shall be such as may be prescribed by the</p>
            <p>Ordinances.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A Pro- Vice- Chancellor shall assist the Vice- Chancellor in  respect of such matters as may be specified by the Vice- Chancellor in  this behalf, from time to time, and shall also exercise such powers  and perform such duties as may be assigned or delegated to him by the</p>
            <p>Vice- Chancellor.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Registrar.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Registrar shall be a whole- time salaried  officer of the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The emoluments and other terms and conditions of service of  the Registrar shall be such as may be prescribed by the Ordinances:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Registrar shall retire on attaining the age of  sixty years:</p>
            <p>Provided further that a Registrar shall, notwithstanding his  attaining the age of sixty years, continue in office until his  successor is appointed and enters upon his office or until the expiry  of a period of one year Whichever is earlier.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When the office of the Registrar is vacant or when the</p>
            <p>Registrar is, by reason of illness, absence or any other cause, unable  to perform the duties of his office, the duties of the office shall be  performed by such person as the Vice- Chancellor may appoint for the  purpose.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.4.list0">
              <item id="section-4.4.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>The Registrar shall have power to take disciplinary  action against such of the employees, excluding teachers and academic  staff as may be specified in the orders of the Executive Council and  to suspend them pending inquiry, to administer warnings to them or to  impose on them the penalty of censure or the withholding' of  increment:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-4.4.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that no such penalty shall be imposed unless the person  concerned has been given a reasonable opportunity of showing cause  against the action proposed to be taken in regard to him.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.4.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>An appeal shall lie to the vice- Chancellor against any order  of the Registrar imposing any of the penalties specified in sub- clause</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.4.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.4.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>In a case where the inquiry discloses that a punishment  beyond the powers of the Registrar is called for, the Registrar shall,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>upon conclusion of the inquiry, make a report to the Vice- Chancellor  along with his recommendations:</p>
            <p>Provided that an appeal shall lie to the Executive Council  against an order of the Vice- Chancellor imposing any penalty.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Registrar shall be ex- officio Secretary of the Executive</p>
            <p>Council, the Academic Council and the Boards of Schools, but shall not  be deemed to, be a member of any of these authorities. He' shall be  ex- officio Member- Secretary of the Court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.6.list1">
              <listIntroduction>It shall be the duty of the Registrar,---</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.6.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to be the custodian of the records, the common seal and  such</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-4.6.list3">
              <listIntroduction>other property of the University as the Executive Council  shall commit to his charge;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.6.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to issue all notices convening meetings of the Court, the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Executive Council, the Academic Council, the Boards of</p>
            <p>Schools, the Boards of Studies, the Boards of Examiners and  of any Committees appointed by the authorities of the</p>
            <blockList id="section-4.6.list7">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.6.list7.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to keep the minutes of all the meetings of the Court, the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Executive Council, the Academic Council, the Boards of</p>
            <blockList id="section-4.6.list10">
              <listIntroduction>Schools and of any Committees appointed by the authorities of  the University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.6.list10.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>to conduct the official correspondence of the Court, the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-4.6.list12">
              <listIntroduction>Executive Council and the Academic Council;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.6.list12.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>to arrange for and superintend the examinations of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>University in accordance with the manner prescribed by the</p>
            <blockList id="section-4.6.list15">
              <listIntroduction>Ordinances;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.6.list15.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>to supply to the Visitor, copies of the agenda of the  meetings of the authorities of the University as soon as they  are issued and the minutes of such meetings;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.6.list15.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>to represent the University in suits or proceedings by or  against the University, sign powers of attorney and verify  pleadings or depute his representative for the purpose; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.6.list15.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>to perform such other duties as may be specified in these</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Statutes, the Ordinance' s or the Regulations or as may be  required, from time to time, by the Executive Council or the</p>
            <p>Vice- Chancellor.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Finance Officer.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Finance Officer shall be a whole- time  salaried officer of the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The emoluments and other terms and conditions of service of  the Finance Officer shall be such as may be prescribed by the</p>
            <p>Ordinances:</p>
            <p>Provided that a Finance Officer shall retire on attaining the age  of sixty years:</p>
            <p>Provided further that the Finance Officer shall, notwithstanding  his attaining the age of sixty years, continue in office until his  successor is appointed and enters upon his office or until the expiry  of a period of one year whichever is earlier.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When the office of the Finance Officer is vacant or when the</p>
            <p>Finance Officer is, by reason of illness, absence or any other cause,</p>
            <p>unable to perform the duties of his office, the duties of the office  shall be performed by such person as the Vice- Chancellor may appoint  for the purpose.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Finance Officer shall be ex- officio Secretary of the</p>
            <p>Finance Committee, but shall not be deemed to be a member of such</p>
            <p>Committee.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.5.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Finance Officer shall-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.5.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>exercise general supervision over the funds of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.5.list3">
              <listIntroduction>University and shall advise it as regards its financial  policy; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.5.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>perform such other financial functions as may be  assigned to him by the Executive Council or as may be  prescribed by these Statutes or the Ordinances:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that the Finance Officer shall not incur any expenditure  or make any investment exceeding ten thousand rupees without the  previous approval of the Executive Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the control of the Executive Council, the Finance</p>
            <blockList id="section-5.6.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Officer shall-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.6.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>hold and manage the property and investments of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.6.list4">
              <listIntroduction>University including trust and endowed property;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.6.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>ensure that the limits fixed by the Executive council for  recurring and non- recurring expenditure for a year are not  exceeded and that all moneys are expended on the purposes for  which they are granted or allotted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.6.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>be responsible for the preparation of annual accounts and  the budget of the University and for their presentation to  the Executive Council;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.6.list4.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>keep a constant watch on the state of the cash and bank  balances and on the state of investments;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.6.list4.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>watch the progress of the collection of revenue and  advise on the methods of collection employed;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.6.list4.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>ensure that the registers of buildings, land, furniture  and equipment are maintained up- to- date and that stock-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>checking is conducted, of equipment and other consumable  materials in all offices, Special Centres, specialised  laboratories, Colleges and Institutions maintained by the</p>
            <blockList id="section-5.6.list7">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.6.list7.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>call for explanation for unauthorised expenditure and for  other financial irregularities and suggest disciplinary  action against persons at fault; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.6.list7.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>call for from any office, Centre, laboratory, College or</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Institution maintained by the University, any information or  returns that he may consider necessary for the performance of  his duties.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The receipt of the Finance Officer or of the person or  persons duly authorised in this behalf by the Executive Council for  any money payable to the University shall be sufficient discharge for  payment of such money.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Deans of Schools of Studies.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Dean of a School of</p>
            <p>Studies shall be appointed by the Vice- Chancellor from among the</p>
            <p>Professors in the School for a period of three years and he shall be  eligible for re- appointment,</p>
            <p>Provided that a Dean on attaining the age of sixty years shall  cease to hold office as such:</p>
            <p>Provided further that if at any time there is no Professor in a</p>
            <p>School, the Vice- Chancellor, or a Pro- Vice- Chancellor if authorised by  the Vice- Chancellor in this behalf, shall exercise the powers of the</p>
            <p>Dean of the school.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When the office of the Dean is vacant or when the Dean is, by  reason of illness, absence or any other cause, unable to perform the  duties of his office, the duties of the office shall be performed by  such person as the Vice- Chancellor may appoint for the purpose.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Dean shall be the Head of the School and shall be  responsible for the conduct and maintenance of the standards of  teaching and research in the School The Dean shall have such other  functions as may be prescribed by the Ordinances.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Dean shall have the right to be present and to speak at  any meeting of the Boards of Studies or Committees of the School, as  the case may be, but shall not have the right to vote thereat unless  he is a member thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Heads of Departments.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the case of Departments which  have more than one Professor, the Head of the Department shall be  appointed by the Executive Council on the recommendation of the Vice-</p>
            <p>Chancellor from among the Professors.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the case of Departments where there is only one Professor,</p>
            <p>the Executive Council shall have the option to appoint, on the recom-</p>
            <p>mendation of the Vice- Chancellor, either the Professor or a Reader as  the Head of the Department;</p>
            <p>Provided that it shall be open to a Professor or Reader to  decline the offer of appointment as the Head of the Department.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A person appointed as the Head of the Department shall hold  office as such for a period of three years and shall be eligible for  reappointment.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A Head of a Department may resign his office at any time  during his tenure of office.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A Head of a Department shall perform such functions as may be  prescribed by the Ordinances.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Deans of Students' Welfare.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Dean of Students'</p>
            <p>Welfare shall be appointed from amongst the teachers of the</p>
            <p>University, not below the rank of a Reader, by the Executive Council  on the recommendation of the Vice- Chancellor.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Dean appointed under clause (1) shall be a whole- time  officer and shall hold office for a term of three years and shall be  eligible for re- appointment:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Executive Council may, if it is considered  necessary appoint, on the recommendation of the Vice- Chancellor, a  teacher, not below the rank of a Reader, to discharge the duties of  the Dean of Students' Welfare in addition to his duties as such  teacher, and in such a case, the Executive Council may sanction a  suitable allowance to be paid to him.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A person who is appointed as a Dean of Students' Welfare  shall continue to hold his lien on his substantive post and shall be  eligible to all the benefits that would have otherwise accrued to him,</p>
            <p>but for his appointment as the Dean of Students' Welfare.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When the office of a Dean of Students' Welfare is vacant or  when the Dean of Students' Welfare is, by reason of illness or absence  or any other cause, unable to perform the duties of his office, the  duties of the office shall be performed by such person as the Vice-</p>
            <p>Chancellor may appoint for the purpose.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The duties and powers of a Dean of Students' Welfare shall be  prescribed by the Ordinances.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Proctors.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Proctor shall be appointed by the</p>
            <p>Executive Council on the recommendation of the Vice- Chancellor and  shall exercise such powers and perform such duties as may be assigned  to him by the Vice- Chancellor.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Proctor shall hold office for a term of two years and  shall be eligible for re- appointment.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Librarians.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Librarian shall be appointed by the</p>
            <p>Executive Council on the recommendation of a Selection Committee  constituted for the purpose and he shall be a whole- time officer of  the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Librarian shall exercise such powers and perform such  duties as may be assigned to him by the Executive Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Meetings of the Court.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An annual meeting of the Court  shall be held on a date to be fixed by the Executive Council unless  some other date has been fixed by the Court in respect of any year.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>At an annual meeting of the Court, a report on the working of  the University during the previous year, together with a statement of  the receipts and expenditure, the balance- sheet, as audited, and the  financial estimates for the next year shall be presented.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A copy a the statement of receipts and expenditure, the  balancesheet and the financial estimates referred to in clause (2)</p>
            <p>shall be sent to every member of the Court at least seven days before  the date of the annual meeting.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Twelve members of the Court shall form a quorum for a meeting  of the Court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Special meetings of the Court may be convened by the</p>
            <p>Executive Council or the Vice- Chancellor, or, if there is no Vice-</p>
            <p>Chancellor, by a Pro- Vice- Chancellor, or if there is no Pro- Vice-</p>
            <p>Chancellor, by the Registrar.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Quorum for meetings of the Executive Council. Five members of  the Executive Council shall form a quorum for a meeting of the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Executive Council.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Powers and functions of Executive Council.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Executive</p>
            <p>Council shall have the management and administration of the revenue  and property of the University and the conduct of all administrative  affairs of the University not otherwise provided for.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act, these Statutes and the</p>
            <blockList id="section-13.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Ordinances, the Executive Council shall, in addition to. all other  powers vested in it, have the following powers, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.2.list2.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>to create teaching and academic posts, to determine the  number and emoluments of such posts and to define the duties  and conditions of service of Professors, Readers, Lecturers  and other academic staff and Principals of Colleges and</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Institutions maintained by the University:</p>
            <p>Provided that no action shall be taken by the Executive</p>
            <p>Council in respect of the number, qualifications and the  emoluments of teachers and academic staff otherwise than  after consideration of the recommendations of the Academic</p>
            <blockList id="section-13.2.list7">
              <listIntroduction>Council;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.2.list7.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>to appoint such Professors, Readers, Lecturers and other  academic staff, as may be necessary, and Principals of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-13.2.list9">
              <listIntroduction>Colleges and Institutions maintained by the University on the  recommendation of the Selection Committee constituted for the  purpose and to fill up temporary vacancies therein;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.2.list9.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>to create administrative, ministerial and other  necessary posts and to make appointments thereto in the  manner prescribed by the Ordinances;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list9.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>to grant leave of absence to any officer of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>University, other than the Chancellor and the Vice-</p>
            <blockList id="section-13.2.list12">
              <listIntroduction>Chancellor, and to make necessary arrangements for the  discharge of the functions of such officer during his  absence;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.2.list12.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>to regulate and enforce discipline among employees in  accordance with these Statutes and the Ordinances:</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list12.vi">
                <num>(vi)</num>
                <p>to manage and regulate the finances, accounts,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-13.2.list14">
              <listIntroduction>investments, property, business and all other administrative  affairs of the University, and for that purpose, to appoint  such agents as it may think fit;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.2.list14.vii">
                <num>(vii)</num>
                <p>to fix limits on the total recurring and the total non-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-13.2.list16">
              <listIntroduction>recurring expenditure for a year on the recommendations of  the Finance Committee;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.2.list16.viii">
                <num>(viii)</num>
                <p>to invest any money belonging to the University,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-13.2.list18">
              <listIntroduction>including any unapplied income, in such stocks, funds, shares  or securities as it shall, from time to time, think fit, or  in the purchase of immovable property in India, with the like  powers of varying such investments from time to time;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.2.list18.ix">
                <num>(ix)</num>
                <p>to transfer or accept transfers of any movable or immov-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-13.2.list20">
              <listIntroduction>able property on behalf of the University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.2.list20.x">
                <num>(x)</num>
                <p>to provide buildings, premises, furniture and apparatus  and other means needed for carrying on the work of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-13.2.list22">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.2.list22.xi">
                <num>(xi)</num>
                <p>to enter into, vary, carry out and cancel contracts on  behalf of the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list22.xii">
                <num>(xii)</num>
                <p>to entertain, adjudicate upon, and, if thought fit, to  redress any grievances of the employees and students of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-13.2.list24">
              <listIntroduction>University, who may, for any reason feel aggrieved;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.2.list24.xiii">
                <num>(xiii)</num>
                <p>to appoint examiners and moderators and, if necessary  to remove them, and to fix their fees, emoluments and  travelling and other allowances, after consulting the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-13.2.list26">
              <listIntroduction>Academic Council;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.2.list26.xiv">
                <num>(xiv)</num>
                <p>to select a common seal for the University and provide  for the custody and use of such seal;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list26.xv">
                <num>(xv)</num>
                <p>to make such special arrangements as may be necessary  for the residence and discipline of women students;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list26.xvi">
                <num>(xvi)</num>
                <p>to delegate any of its powers to the Vice- Chancellor,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>the Pro- Vice- Chancellors, the Registrar or the Finance</p>
            <blockList id="section-13.2.list29">
              <listIntroduction>Officer or such other employee or authority of the University  or to a Committee appointed by It as it may deem fit;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.2.list29.xvii">
                <num>(xvii)</num>
                <p>to institute fellowships, scholarships, studentships,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-13.2.list31">
              <listIntroduction>medals and prizes; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.2.list31.xviii">
                <num>(xviii)</num>
                <p>to exercise such other powers and perform such other  duties as may be conferred or imposed on it by this Act, or  these Statutes.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Quorum for meetings of the Academic Council. Nine members of  the Academic Council shall form a quorum for a meeting of the Academic</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Council.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Powers of the Academic Council. Subject to this Act, these</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-15.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Statutes and the Ordinances, the Academic Council shall, in addition  to all other powers vested in it, have the following powers, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to exercise general supervision over the academic  policies of the University and to give directions regarding  methods of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>instruction, co- operative teaching among Colleges and</p>
            <blockList id="section-15.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Institutions, evaluation of research or improvements in  academic standards;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to bring about inter- School co- ordination, to establish  or appoint Committees or Boards, for taking up projects on an  inter- School basis;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to consider matters of general academic interest either  on its own initiative or on a reference by a School or the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-15.paragraph-0.list6">
              <listIntroduction>Executive Council and to take appropriate action thereon; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list6.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>to frame such regulations and rules consistent with  these. Statutes and the Ordinances regarding the academic  functioning of the University, discipline, residences,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>admissions, award of fellowships and studentships, fee  concessions, corporate life and, attendance.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>The Planning Board.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-16.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The members of the Planning Board  shall be appointed by the Visitor and shall hold office for such  period as he may determine.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Planning Board shall, in addition to all other powers  vested in it by this Act, have the right to advise the Executive</p>
            <p>Council and the Academic Council on any academic matter.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On the date determined by the Visitor under sub- section (3)</p>
            <p>of section 23, this Statute shall cease to have effect.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Schools of Studies and Departments.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The University shall  have such Schools of Studies as may be specified by the Ordinances.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every School shall have a School Board. The members of the  first School Board shall be nominated by the Executive Council and  shall hold office for a period of three years.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The powers and functions of a School Board shall be  prescribed by the Ordinances.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The conduct of the meetings of a School Board and the quorum  required for such meetings shall be prescribed by the Ordinances.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-17.5.list0">
              <item id="section-17.5.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>Each School shall consist of such Departments as may be  assigned to it by the Ordinances.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.5.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>No Department shall be established or abolished except by  these Statutes:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-17.5.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that the Executive Council may, on the recommendation of  the Academic Council, establish Centres of Studies to which may be  assigned such teachers of the University as the Executive Council may  consider necessary.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.5.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>Each Department shall consist of the following members,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-17.5.list4">
              <listIntroduction>namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.5.list4.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>teachers of the Department;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.5.list4.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>persons conducting research in the, Department;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.5.list4.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>Dean of the School or Deans of, the Schools concerned;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.5.list4.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>honorary Professors, if any, attached to the Department; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.5.list4.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>such other persons as may be members of the Department in  accordance with the provisions of the Ordinances.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Boards of Studies.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Each Department shall have two Boards  of Studies, one for Post- graduate Studies and the other for Under-</p>
            <p>graduate Studies.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The constitution of a Board of Post- graduate Studies and the  term of office of its emmbers shall be prescribed by the Ordinances.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The functions of a Board of Post- graduate Studies shall be to  approve subjects for research for various degrees and other  requirements of research degrees and to recommend to the concerned</p>
            <blockList id="section-18.3.list2">
              <listIntroduction>School Board in the manner prescribed by the Ordinances:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18.3.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>courses of studies and appointment of examiners for post-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-18.3.list4">
              <listIntroduction>graduate courses, but excluding research degrees;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18.3.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>appointment of supervisors of research; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.3.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>measures for the improvement of the standard of post-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>graduate teaching and research.</p>
            <p>Provided that the above functions of a Board of Post- graduate</p>
            <p>Studies shall, during the period of three years immediately after the  commencement of this Act, be performed by the Department.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The constitution and functions of a Board of Under- graduate</p>
            <p>Studies and the term of office of its members shall be prescribed by  the Ordinances.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Finance Committee.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-19.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-19.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Finance Committee shall consist of  the following members, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-19.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>The Vice- Chancellor;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.1.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>A Pro- Vice- Chancellor appointed by the Executive Council;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.1.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>Three persons nominated by the Executive Council, out of  whom at least one shall be a member of the Executive Council; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.1.list1.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>Three persons nominated by the Visitor.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Five members of the Finance Committee shall form a quorum for  meeting of the Finance Committee.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All the members of the Finance Committee, other than ex-</p>
            <p>officio, members, shall hold office for a term of three years.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A member of the Finance Committee shall have the right to  record a minute of dissent if he does not agree with any decision of  the Finance Committee.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Finance Committee shall meet at least twice every year to  examine the accounts and to scrutinise proposals for expenditure.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The annual accounts and the financial estimates of the</p>
            <p>University prepared by the Finance Officer shall be laid before the</p>
            <p>Finance Committee for consideration and comments and thereafter  submitted to the Executive Council for approval.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Finance Committee shall recommend limits for the total  recurring expenditure and the total non- recurring expenditure for the  year, based on the income and resources of the University (which, in   the case of productive works, may include the proceeds of loans).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Selection Committees.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-20.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be Selection Committees  for making recomemndations to, the Executive Council for appointment  to the posts of Professor,</p>
            <p>Reader, Lecturer, Librarian and Principals of Colleges and</p>
            <p>Institutions maintained by the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Selection Committee for appointment to the posts  specified in column 1 of the Table below shall consist of the Vice-</p>
            <p>Chancellor, a Pro- Vice- Chancellor appointed by the Executive Council,</p>
            <p>a nominee of the Visitor and the persons specified in the  corresponding entry in column 2 of the said Table:</p>
            <p>TABLE</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>2</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Professor (i) The Head of the Department concerned, if he is a</p>
            <blockList id="section-1.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Professor.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list2.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>One Professor to be nominated by the Vice Chancellor.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list2.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>Three persons not in the service of the University, nominated by  the Executive Council, out of a panel of names recommended by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Academic Council for their special knowledge of or interest in the  subject with which the Professor will be concerned.</p>
            <p>Reader (i) The Head of the Department concerned.</p>
            <p>Lecturer (ii) One Professor to be nominated by the Vice-</p>
            <blockList id="section-1.paragraph-0.list7">
              <listIntroduction>Chancellor.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list7.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>Two persons not in the service of the University, nominated by  the Executive Council, out of a panel of names recommended by the Aca-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>demic Council for their special knowledge of or interest in the  subject with which the Reader or Lecturer will be concerned.</p>
            <p>Librarian (i) Two persons not in the service of the University,</p>
            <p>who have special knowledge of the subject of Library Science Library</p>
            <blockList id="section-1.paragraph-0.list12">
              <listIntroduction>Administration to be nominated by the Executive Council.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list12.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>One person, not in the service of the University, nominated by  the Executive Council.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Principal Three persons not in the service of the Uni-</p>
            <p>of College versity of whom two shall be nominated by the  or Institu- Executive Council and one by the Academic  tion main- Council for their special knowledge of or interest  tained by in a subject in which instruction is being provided  the Uni- by the College or Institution.</p>
            <p>versity</p>
            <p>NOTE 1.- Where the appointment is being made for an inter-</p>
            <p>disciplinary project, the Head of the project shall be deemed to be  the Head of the Department concerned.</p>
            <p>NOTE 2.- The Professor to be nominated shall be a Professor  concerned with the speciality for which the selection is being made  and that the Vice- Chancellor shall consult the Head of the Department  and the Dean of School before nominating the Professor.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Vice- Chancellor, or in his absence, the senior- most Pro-</p>
            <p>Vice- Chancellor, shall preside at the meetings of a Selection</p>
            <p>Committee.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The meetings of a Selection Committee shall be convened by  the Vice- Chancellor or In his absence, by the senior- most Pro- Vice-</p>
            <p>Chancellor.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The procedure to be followed by a Selection Committee in  making recommendations shall be laid down in the Ordinances.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the Executive Council Is unable to accept the  recommendations made by a Selection Committee, it shall record its  reasons and submit the case to the Visitor for final orders.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Appointments to temporary posts shall be made in the manner</p>
            <blockList id="section-1.7.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Indicated below:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1.7.list2.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>If the temporary vacancy is for a duration longer than one  academic session, it shall be filled on the advice of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Selection Committee in accordance with the procedure  indicated in the foregoing clauses:</p>
            <p>Provided that if the Vice- Chancellor is satisfied that in the</p>
            <blockList id="section-1.7.list6">
              <listIntroduction>Interests of work it is necessary to fill the vacancy, the  appointment may be made on a purely temporary basis by a  local Selection Committee referred to in sub- clause (ii) for  a period not exceeding six months.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1.7.list6.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>If the temporary vacancy is for a period less than a  year, an appointment to such vacancy shall be made on the  recommendation of a local Selection Committee consisting of  the Dean of the School concerned, the Head of the Department  and a nominee of the Vice- Chancellor:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that if the same person holds the offices of the</p>
            <p>Dean and the Head of the Department. the Selection Committee  may contain two nominees of the Vice- Chancellor:</p>
            <blockList id="section-1.7.list10">
              <listIntroduction>Provided further that in case of sudden casual vacancies of  teaching posts caused by death or any other reason, the Dean  may, in consultation with the Heed of the Department  concerned, make a temporary appointment for a month and  report to the Vice- Chancellor and the Registrar about such  appointment.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1.7.list10.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>No teacher appointed temporarily shall, if he is not  recommended by a regular Selection Committee for appointment  under these Statutes, be continued in service on such  temporary employment, unless he is subsequently selected by a  local Selection Committee or a regular Selection Committee,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>for a temprory or permanent appointment, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Special mode of appointment.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-21.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything  contained in Statute 20, the Executive Council may invite a person of  high academic distinction and professional attainments to accept a  post of Professor or Reader or any other academic past in the</p>
            <p>University, as the case may be on such terms and conditions as it  deems fit, and on the person agreeing to do so, appoint him to the  post.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-21.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Executive Council may appoint a teacher or any other  academic staff working in any other University or Organisation for  undertaking a joint project in accordance with the manner laid down in  the Ordinances.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Appointment for a fixed tenure. The Executive Council may  appoint a person selected in acocrdance with the procedure laid down  in Statute 20 for a fixed tenure on such terms and conditions as it  deems fit.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Recognised teachers.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-23.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The qualifications of recognised  teachers shall be such as may be prescribed by the Ordinances.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All applications for the recognition of teachers shall be  made in such manner as may be laid down in the Ordinances.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No teacher shall be recognised as a teacher except on the  recommendation of a Selection Committee constituted for the purpose in  the manner laid down in the Ordinances.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The period of recognition of a teacher shall be determined by</p>
            <p>Ordinances made in that behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Academic Council may, by a special resolution passed by a  majority of not less than two- thirds of the members present and  voting, withdraw recognition from a teacher:</p>
            <p>Provided that no such resolution shall be passed until a notice  in writing has been given to the person concerned calling upon him to  show cause, within such time as may be specified in the notice, why  such resolution should not be passed and until his objections, if any,</p>
            <p>and any evidence he may produce in support of them, have been  considered by the Academic Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person aggrieved by an order of withdrawal under clause</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>may, within three months from the date of communication to him of  such order, appeal to the Executive Council which may pass such orders  thereon as it thinks fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Committees. Any authority of the University may appoint as  many standing or special committees as it may deem fit, and may  appoint to such committees persons who are not, members of such  authority. Any such committee may deal with any subject delegated to  it subject to subsequent confirmation by the authority appointing it.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Terms and conditions of service of University teachers.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-25.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All the teachers of the University shall, in the absence of any  agreement to the contrary, be governed by the terms and conditions of  service as specified in these Statutes, the Ordinances and the</p>
            <p>Regulations.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every teacher of the University shall be appointed on a  written contract, the form of which shall be prescribed by the</p>
            <p>Ordinances. A copy of the contract shall be deposited with the</p>
            <p>Registrar.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Seniority lists.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-26.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whenever, in accordance with these</p>
            <p>Statutes, any person is to hold an office or be a member of an  authority of the University by rotation according to seniority, such  seniority shall be determined according to the length of continuous  service of such person in his grade, and, in accordance with such  other principles as the Executive Council may, from time to time,</p>
            <p>prescribe.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be the duty of the Registrar to prepare and  maintain, in respect of each class of persons to whom the provisions  of these Statutes apply, a. complete and up- to- date seniority list in  accordance with the provisions of clause (1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If two or more persons have equal length of continuous  service in a particular grade or the relative seniority of any person  or persons is otherwise in doubt, the Registrar may, on his own motion  and shall at the request of any such person, submit the matter to the</p>
            <p>Executive Council whose decision thereon shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Removal of teachers.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-27.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where there is an allegation of  misconduct against a teacher, or a member of the academic staff, the</p>
            <p>Vice- Chancellor may, if he thinks fit, by order in writing, place the  teacher under suspension and shall forthwith report to the Executive</p>
            <p>Council the circumstances in which the order was made:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Executive Council may, if it is of the opinion,</p>
            <p>that the circumstances of the case do not warrant the suspension of  the teacher or a member of the academic staff, revoke such order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the terms of his  contract of service or of his appointment, the Executive Council shall  be entitled to remove a teacher or a member of the academic staff on  the ground of misconduct.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Save as aforesaid, the Executive Council shall not be  entitled to remove a teacher or a member of the academic staff except  for good cause and after giving three months' notice in writing or on  payment of three months' salary in lieu of notice.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No teacher or a member of the academic staff shall be removed  under clause (2) or under clause (3) until he has been given a  reasonable opportunity of showing cause against the action proposed to  be taken in regard to him.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The removal of a teacher or a member of the academic staff  shall require a two- thirds majority of the members of the Executive</p>
            <p>Council present and voting.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The removal of a teacher or a member of the academic staff  shall take effect from the date on which the order of removal is made:</p>
            <p>Provided that where a teacher or a member of the academic staff  is under suspension at the time of his removal, the removal shall take  effect from the date on which he was placed under suspension.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in these Statutes, a  teacher or a member of the academic staff may resign by giving three  months' notice in writing to the Executive Council or on payment of  three months' salary in lieu thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28">
        <num>28.</num>
        <heading>Removal of employees other than teachers of the University.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-28.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-28.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in the terms of his contract of  service or of his appointment, an employee, other than a teacher or a  member of the academic staff, may be removed by the authority which is  competent to appoint the employee-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-28.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>if he is of unsound mind or is a deaf- mute or suffers  from contagious leprosy;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>if he is an undischarged insolvent;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>if he has been convicted by a court of law of any offence  involving moral turpitude and sentenced in respect thereof to  imprisonment for not less than six months;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>if he is otherwise guilty of misconduct:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that no employee shall be removed from his office unless  a resolution to that effect is passed by the Executive Council by a</p>
            <p>Majority of two- thirds of its members present and voting.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-28.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No employee shall be removed under clause (1) until he has  been given a reasonable opportunity of showing cause against the  action proposed to be taken in regard to him.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-28.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the removal of such employee is for a reason other than  that specified in sub- clause (c) or sub- clause (d) of clause (1), he  shall be given three months' notice in writing or paid three months'</p>
            <p>salary in lieu of such notice.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-28.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in these Statutes, an em-</p>
            <blockList id="section-28.4.list2">
              <listIntroduction>ployee, not being a teacher or a member of the academic staff, shall  be entitled to resign,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-28.4.list2.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>if he is a permanent employee, only after giving three  month' s notice in writing to the appointing authority or  paying to the University three months' salary in lieu  thereof;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28.4.list2.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>if he is not a permanent employee, only after giving one  months' notice in writing to the appointing authority or  paying to the University one month' s salary in lieu thereof:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that such resignation shall take effect, from the date  on which the resignation is accepted by the appointing authority.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29">
        <num>29.</num>
        <heading>Honorary degrees.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-29.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Executive Council may, on the  recommendation of the Academic Council and by a resolution passed by a  majority of not less than two- thirds of the members present and  voting, make proposals to the Visitor for the conferment of honorary  degrees:</p>
            <p>Provided that in case of emergency, the Executive Council may, on  its own, make such proposals.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Executive Council may, by a resolution passed by a  majority of not less than two- thirds of the members present and  voting, withdraw, with the previous sanction of the Visitor, any  honorary degree conferred by the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-30">
        <num>30.</num>
        <heading>Withdrawal of degrees, etc. The Executive Council may, by a  special resolution passed by a majority of not less than two- thirds of  the members present and voting, withdraw any degree or academic  distinction conferred on, or any certificate or diploma granted to,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-30.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>any person by the University for good and sufficient cause:</p>
            <p>Provided that no such resolution shall be passed until a notice  in writing has been given to that person calling upon him to show  cause within such time as may be specified in the notice why such a  resolution should not be passed and until his objections, if any, and  any evidence he may produce. in support of them, have been considered  by the Executive Council.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-31">
        <num>31.</num>
        <heading>Maintenance of discipline among students of the University.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-31.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All powers relating to discipline and disciplinary action in  relation to students of the University shall vest in the Vice-</p>
            <p>Chancellor.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-31.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Vice- Chancellor may delegate all or any of his powers as  he deems proper to a Proctor and to such other officers as he may  specify in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-31.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Without prejudice to the generality of his powers relating to  the maintenance of discipline and taking such action, as may seem to  him appropriate for the maintenance of discipline, the Vice- Chancellor  may, in the exercise of his powers, by order, direct that any student  or students be expelled, or rusticated, for a specified period, or be  not admitted to a course or courses of study in a College, Institution  or Department of the University for a stated period, or be punished  with fine for an amount to be specified in the order, or be debarred  from taking an examination or examinations conducted by the</p>
            <p>University, College, Institution or a Department for one or more  years, or that the results of the student or students concerned in the  examination or examinations in which he or they have appeared be  cancelled.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-31.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Principals of Colleges, Institutions, Heads of Special</p>
            <p>Centres, Deans of Schools of Studies and Heads of teaching Departments  in the University shall have the authority, to exercise all such  disciplinary powers over the students in their respective Colleges,</p>
            <p>Institutions, Special Centres, Schools and teaching Departments in the</p>
            <p>University as may be necessary for the proper conduct of such</p>
            <p>Colleges, Institutions, Special Centres, Schools and teaching in the</p>
            <p>Departments.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-31.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Without prejudice to the powers of the Vice- Chancellor, the</p>
            <p>Principals and other persons specified in clause (4), detailed rules  of discipline and proper conduct shall be made by the University. The</p>
            <p>Principals of Colleges, Institutions, Heads of Special Centres, Deans  of Schools of Studies and Heads of teaching Departments in the</p>
            <p>University may also make the supplementary rules as they deem  necessary for the aforesaid purposes. Every student shall be supplied  with a copy of the rules made by the University and a copy of the  supplementary rules shall be supplied tot the students concerned.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-31.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>At the time of admission, every student shall be required to  sign a declaration to the effect that he submits himself to the  disciplinary jurisdiction of the Vice- Chancellor and other authorities  of the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-32">
        <num>32.</num>
        <heading>Maintenance of discipline among students of College, etc. All  powers relating to discipline and disciplinary action in relation to  students of a College or an Institution, not maintained by the Univer-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-32.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>sity, shall vest in the Principal of the College or Institution, as  the case may be, in accordance with the procedure prescribed by the</p>
            <p>Ordinances.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-33">
        <num>33.</num>
        <heading>Admission of College, etc., to the privileges of the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-33.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>University.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-33.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-33.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Colleges and other Institutions situated within the  jurisdiction of the University may be admitted to such privileges of  the University as the Executive Council may decide on the following  conditions, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-33.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>Every such College or Institution shall have a regularly  constituted Governing Body, consisting of not more than  fifteen persons approved by the Executive Council and  including, among others, two teachers of the University to be  nominated by the Executive Council</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>and three representatives of the teaching staff of whom the</p>
            <p>Principal of the College or Institution shall be one. The  procedure for appointment of members of the Governing Body  and other matters affecting the management of a College or an</p>
            <p>Institution shall be prescribed by the Ordinances:</p>
            <blockList id="section-33.1.list6">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that the said condition shall not apply in the case  of Colleges and Institutions maintained by Government which  shall, however, have an Advisory Committee consisting of not  more than fifteen persons which shall consist of, among  others, three teachers including the Principal of the College  or Institution, and two teachers of the University nominated  by the Executive Council.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-33.1.list6.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>Every such College or Institution shall satisfy the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-33.1.list8">
              <listIntroduction>Executive Council on the following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-33.1.list8.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the suitability and adequacy of its accommodation  and equipment for teaching;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-33.1.list8.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the qualifications and adequacy of its teaching  staff and the conditions of their service;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-33.1.list8.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the arrangements for the residence, welfare,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-33.1.list10">
              <listIntroduction>discipline and supervision of students;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-33.1.list10.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the adequacy of financial provision made for the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-33.1.list12">
              <listIntroduction>Continued maintenance of the College or Institution; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-33.1.list12.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <blockList id="section-33.1.list12.e.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>such other matters as are essential for the  maintenance of the standards of University education.</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-33.1.list12.e.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>No College or Institution shall be admitted to any  privileges of the University except on the  recommendation of the Academic Council made after  considering the report of a Committee of Inspection  appointed for the purpose by the Academic Council.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-33.1.list12.e.list0.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>Colleges and Institutions desirous of admission to  any privileges of the University shall be required to  intimate their intention to do so in writing so as to  reach the Registrar not later than the 15th August,</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-33.1.list14">
              <listIntroduction>preceding the year from which permission applied for is  to have effect.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-33.1.list14.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>A College or an Institution shall not, without the  previous permission of the Executive Council and the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Academic Council, suspend instruction in any subject or  course of study which it is authorised to teach and  teaches.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-33.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Appointment to the teaching staff and Principals of Colleges  or Institutions admitted to the privileges of the University shall be  made in the manner prescribed by the Ordinances:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing in this clause shall apply to Colleges and</p>
            <p>Institutions maintained by Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-33.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The service conditions of the administrative and other non-</p>
            <p>academic staff of every College or Institution referred to in clause</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-33.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>shall be such as may be laid down in the Ordinances:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing in this clause shall apply to Colleges and</p>
            <p>Institutions maintained by Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-33.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every College or Institution admitted to the privileges of  the University shall be inspected at least once in every two academic  years by a Committee appointed by the Academic Council, and the report  of that Committee shall be submitted to the Academic Council, which  shall forward the same to the Executive Council with such  recommendations as it may deem fit to make. The Executive Council,</p>
            <p>after considering the report and the recommendations, if any, of the</p>
            <p>Academic Council, shall forward a copy of the report to the Governing</p>
            <p>Body of the College or Institution with such remarks, if any, as it  may deem fit, for suitable action.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-33.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Executive Council may, after consulting the Academic</p>
            <p>Council, withdraw any privileges granted to a College or Institution,.</p>
            <p>at any lime it considers that the College or Institution does not  satisfy any of the conditions on the fulfilment of which the College  or Institution was admitted to such privileges:</p>
            <p>Provided that before any privileges are so withdrawn, the</p>
            <p>Governing Body of the College or Institution concerned shall be given  an opportunity to represent to the Executive Council why such action  should not be taken.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-33.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the conditions set forth in clause (1), the</p>
            <blockList id="section-33.6.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Ordinances may prescribe-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-33.6.list2.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>such other conditions as may be considered necessary;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-33.6.list2.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>the procedure for the admission of Colleges and</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Institutions to the privileges of the University and for the  withdrawal of those privileges.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-34">
        <num>34.</num>
        <heading>Convocations. Convocations of the University for the  conferring of degrees or for tither purposes shall be held in such  manner as may be prescribed by the Ordinances.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-35">
        <num>35.</num>
        <heading>Acting Chairman of meetings. Where no provision is made for a</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-35.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>President or Chairman to preside over a meeting of any authority of  the University or any Committee of such authority or when the</p>
            <p>President or Chairman so provided for is absent, the members present  shall elect one from among themselves to preside at such meeting.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-36">
        <num>36.</num>
        <heading>Resignation. Any member, other than an ex- officio member of  the Court, the Executive Council, the Academic Council or any other  authority of the University or any Committee of such authority may  resign by letter addressed to the Registrar and the resignation shall  take effect as soon as such letter is received by the Registrar.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-37">
        <num>37.</num>
        <heading>Disqualifications.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-37.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-37.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A person shall be disqualified for  being chosen as, and for being, a member of any of the authorities of  the University-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-37.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>if he is of unsound mind or is a deaf- mute or  suffers from contagious leprosy;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-37.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>if he is an undischarged insolvent;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-37.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>if he has been convicted by a court of law of an  offence involving moral turpitude and sentenced in  respect thereof to imprisonment for not less than six  months.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-37.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any question arises as to whether a person is or had been  subjected to any of the disqualifications mentioned in clause (1), the  question shall be referred for the decision of the Visitor and his  decision shall be final and no suit or other proceeding shall lie in  any civil court against such decision.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-38">
        <num>38.</num>
        <heading>Residence condition for membership and office.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-38.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in these Statutes, no per who is  not ordinarily resident in India shall be eligible to be ail officer  of the University or a member of any authority of the University.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-39">
        <num>39.</num>
        <heading>Membership of authorities by virtue of membership of other  bodies. Notwithstanding anything contained in these Statutes, a  person who holds any post in the University or- is a member of any  authority or body of the University in his capacity as a member of a  particular authority or body or as the holder of a particular  appointment shall hold such office or membership only for so long as  he continues to be a member of that particular authority or body or  the holder of that particular appointment, as the case may be.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-40">
        <num>40.</num>
        <heading>Alumni Association.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-40.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be an Alumni Association  for the University.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-40.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The subscription for membership of the Alumni Association  shall be prescribed by the Ordinances.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-40.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No member of the Alumni Association shall be entitled to vote  or stand for election unless he has been a member a. the Association  for at least one year prior to the date of the election and is a  graduate of the University of at least five years' standing:</p>
            <p>Provided that the condition relating to the completion of one  year' s membership shall not apply in the case of the first election.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-41">
        <num>41.</num>
        <heading>Ordinance how made.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-41.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The first Ordinances made under sub-</p>
            <p>section (2) of section 26 may be amended, repealed or added to at any  time by the Executive Council in the manner specified below.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-41.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No Ordinance in respect of the matters enumerated in section</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>, other than those enumerated in clause (n) of subsection (1)</p>
            <p>thereof, shall be made by the Executive Council unless a draft of such</p>
            <p>Ordinance has been proposed by the Academic Council.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-26.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Executive Council shall not have power to amend any draft  of any Ordinance proposed by the Academic Council under clause (2),</p>
            <p>but may reject the proposal or return the draft to the Academic</p>
            <p>Council for reconsideration, either in whole or in part, together with  any amendment which the Executive Council may suggest.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the Executive Council has rejected or returned the  draft of an Ordinance proposed by the Academic Council, the Academic</p>
            <p>Council many consider the question afresh and in case the original  draft is re- affirmed by a majority of not less than two- thirds of the  members present; and voting and more than half the total number of  members of the Academic Council, the draft may be sent back to the</p>
            <p>Executive Council which shall either adopt it or refer it to the</p>
            <p>Visitor whose decision shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Ordinance made by the Executive Council shall come into  effect immediately.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Ordinance made by the Executive Council shall be sub-</p>
            <p>mitted to the Visitor within two weeks from the date of its adoption.</p>
            <p>The Visitor shall have the power to direct the University within four  weeks of the receipt of the Ordinance to suspend the operation of any  such Ordinance and he shall, as soon as possible, inform the Executive</p>
            <p>Council about his objection to the proposed Ordinance. The Visitor  may</p>
            <p>after receiving the comments of the University, either withdraw the  order suspending the Ordinance or disallow the Ordinance, and his  decision shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-42">
        <num>42.</num>
        <heading>Regulations.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-42.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The authorities of the University may make</p>
            <p>Regulations consistent with this Act, and these Statutes and the</p>
            <blockList id="section-42.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Ordinances:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-42.1.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>laying down the procedure to be observed at their  meetings and the number of members required to form a quorum;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-42.1.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>providing for all matters which are required by this Act  these Statutes or the Ordinances to be prescribed by</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-42.1.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Regulations;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-42.1.list5.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>providing for all other matters solely concerning such  authorities or committees appointed by them and not provided  for by this Act, these Statutes or the Ordinances.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-42.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every authority of the University shall make. Regulations  providing for the giving of notice to the members of such authority of  the dates of meetings and of the business to be considered at meetings  and for the keeping of a record of the proceedings of meetings.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-42.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Executive Council may direct the amendment in such manner  as it may specify, of any Regulation made under this Statute or the  annulment of any such Regulation.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-43">
        <num>43.</num>
        <heading>Delegation of powers. Subject to the provisions of this Act  and these Statutes. any officer or authority of the University may  delegate his or its powers to any other officer or authority or person  under his or its respective control and subject to the condition that  overall responsibility for the exercise of the powers so delegated  shall continue to vest in the officer or authority delegating such  powers.</heading>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
