<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1959/46/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1959/46"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Government Savings Certificates Act, 1959"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1959/46/eng@1959-09-18/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1959/46/eng@1959-09-18"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1959-09-18" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1959/46/eng@1959-09-18/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1959/46/eng@1959-09-18"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Government Savings Certificates Act, 1959</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 46 OF 1959</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 18th September, 1959.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to make certain provisions in respect of Government Savings</p>
        <p>Certificates.</p>
        <p>Be it enacted by Parliament in the Tenth Year of the Republic of</p>
        <p>India as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, commencement and application.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be  called the Government Savings Certificates Act, 1959.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date  as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It applies to such class of savings certificates as the</p>
            <p>Central Government may, by notification  in the Official Gazette,</p>
            <p>specify in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" minor" means a person who is not deemed to have  attained his majority under the Indian Majority Act, 1875;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>(9 of 1875.)</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" savings certificate" means a savings certificate to  which this Act applies;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>" transfer" means a transfer inter vivos, and does not  include transfer by operation of law</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Restrictions on transfer savings certificates. Notwithstanding  anything contained in any law for the time being in force, no transfer  of a savings certificate, whether made before or after the  commencement of this Act, shall be valid unless it has been made  with the previous consent in writing of the prescribed authority.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Holdings by or on behalf of minors. Notwithstanding any  provision in any law for the time being in force,-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>a minor may apply for and hold savings certificates and  any other person may apply for and hold savings certificates  on behalf of a minor;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>where any savings certificate is held by or on behalf  of a minor, the minor shall, whether the savings certificate  was applied for and issued before or after the commencement  of this Act, be bound by the provisions of this Act and of  any rules made thereunder applicable to such savings  certificate and by the terms of any declaration made by the  applicant for the savings certificate in pursuance of the  said rules.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Payment where certificate is held by or on behalf of a minor.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Payment of the sum for the time being due on a savings certificate  held by or on behalf of a minor may be made</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to him personally, if he himself applied for the  savings certificate, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>for the use of the minor, if the application for  the savings certificate was made by any person other  than the minor,-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>to any such person, being a parent of the minor or  guardian of his property, as may be specified in that  behalf in the form of application;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>if no such person has been specified, to any  guardian of the property of the minor appointed by a  competent court, or where no such guardian has been so  appointed, to either parent of the minor, or where  neither parent is alive, to any other guardian of the  minor.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Nomination by holders of savings certificates.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time being in  force, or in any disposition, testamentary or otherwise in respect of  any savings certificate, where a nomination made in the prescribed  manner purports to confer on any person the right to receive payment  of the sum for the time being due on the savings certificate on the  death of the holder thereof and before the maturity of the  certificate, or before the certificate having reached maturity has  been discharged, the nominee shall, on the death of the holder of the  savings certificate, become entitled to the savings certificate and to  be paid the sum due thereon to the exclusion of all others</p>
            <p>persons, unless the nomination is varied or cancelled in the  prescribed manner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any nomination referred to in sub- section (1) shall become  void if the nominee predeceases, or where there are two or more  nominees all the nominees predecease, the holder of the savings  certificate making the nomination.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the nominee is a minor, it shall be lawful for the  holder of the savings certificate making the nomination to appoint in  the prescribed manner any person to receive the sum due thereon in  the event of his death during the minority of the nominee.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A transfer of a savings certificate made in the prescribed  manner shall automatically cancel a nomination previously made:</p>
            <p>Provided that where a savings certificate is held by or on behalf  of any person as a pledgee or by way of security for any purpose, such  holding shall not have the effect of cancelling a nomination but the  right of the nominee shall be subject to the right of the person so  holding it.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Payment on death of holder.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the holder of a savings  certificate dies and there is in force at the time of his death a  nomination in favour of any person, payment of the sum due thereon  shall be made to the nominee.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where the nominee is a minor, payment of the sum due thereon  shall be made--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in any case where a person has been appointed to  receive it under sub- section (3) of section 6, to that  person, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>where there is no such person, to any guardian of the  property of the minor appointed by a competent court, or  where no such guardian has been so appointed, to either  parent of the minor, or where neither parent is alive, to any  other guardian of the minor.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the sum due on a savings certificate is payable to two  or more nominees, and either or any of them dies, the sum shall be  paid to the surviving nominee or nominees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If a person dies and is at the time of his death the holder  of a savings certificate and there is no nomination in force at the  time of his death and probate of his will or letters of administration  of his estate or a succession certificate granted under the Indian</p>
            <p>Succession Act, 1925, (39 of 1925.) is not within three months of the  death of the holder produced to the prescribed authority, then, if the  sum due on the savings certificate does not exceed such limit as may  be prescribed the prescribed, authority may pay the same to any person  appearing to</p>
            <p>it to be entitled to receive the sum or to administer the estate of  the deceased.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing contained in this section shall be deemed to require  any person to receive payment of the sum due on a savings certificate  before it has reached maturity or otherwise than in accordance with  the terms of the savings certificate.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Payment to be a full discharge.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any payment made in  accordance with the foregoing provisions of this Act to a minor or to  his parent or guardian or to a nominee or to any other person shall be  a full discharge from all further liability in respect of the sum so  paid.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in sub- section (1) shall be deemed to preclude any  executor or administrator or other representative of a deceased holder  of a savings certificate from recovering from the person receiving the  same under section 7 the amount remaining in his hands after deducting  the amount of all debts or other demands lawfully paid or discharged  by him in due course of administration.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any creditor or claimant against the estate of a holder of a  savings certificate may recover his debt or claim out of the sum paid  under this Act to any person and remaining in his hands un-</p>
            <p>administered, in the same manner and to the same extent as if the  latter had obtained letters of administration to the estate of the  deceased.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Security for due administration. The prescribed authority may  take such security as it thinks necessary from any person to whom any  money is paid under sub- section (4) of section 7 for the due  administration of the money so paid and may assign the said security  to any person interested in such administrations.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Power to administer oath.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of ascertaining  the right of a person claiming to be entitled to payment under sub-</p>
            <p>section (4) of section 7, the prescribed authority may take evidence  on oath or affirmation according to the law for the time being in  force relating to oaths and affirmation.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person who upon such oath or affirmation makes any  statement which is false and which he either knows or believes to be  false or does not believe to be true shall be deemed guilty of an  offence under section 193 of the Indian Penal Code. (45 of 1860.)</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit or other  legal proceeding shall lie against any officer of the Government or  any prescribed authority in respect of</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this</p>
            <p>Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules  to carry out the  purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-12.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the form of application for savings certificates and  the issue and discharge of such certificates;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the maximum limits of holdings;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the conditions as to payment of interest or discount  relating to any class of savings certificates and the  recovery of any interest paid on any amount held in excess of  the maximum limits in the same manner as an arrear of land  revenue or in any, other manner;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the transfer and conversion of savings certificates and  the fees to be levied in respect thereof;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the replacement of savings certificates mutilated, lost  or destroyed and the fees payable in respect thereof;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the form of nominations, the manner in which and the  conditions subject to which nominations may be made and the  registration of nominations;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the manner in which any person may be appointed for the  purposes of sub- section (3) of section 6;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the variation or cancellation of nominations and the  registration of such variations or cancellations;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <blockList id="section-12.2.list1.i.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>the fees that may be levied for registration, variation  or cancellation of nominations</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-12.2.list1.i.list0.ia">
                    <num>(ia)</num>
                    <p>the limit under sub- section (4) of section 7;"]</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.2.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>any other matter which has to be, or may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as  may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is in  session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in  one session or  in two or more successive sessions, and if, before  the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the  successive sessions aforesaid"] both- Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not  be made, the rule shall</p>
            <p>thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</p>
            <p>as the case may be, so however that any such modification or annulment  shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done  under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Repeal and savings.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Post Office National Savings</p>
            <p>Certificates Ordinance, 1944 (42 of 1944), is hereby repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding the repeal of the said Ordinance, any rules  made or deemed to have been made or anything done or any action, taken  in exercise of any of the powers conferred by or under the said</p>
            <p>Ordinance shall be deemed to have been made, done or taken in exercise  of the powers conferred by or under this Act, as if this Act were in  force on the day on which such rules were made, such thing was done or  such action was taken.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
