<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-uth/act/2013/21/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-uth/act/2013/21"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Uttarakhand Medicare Service Persons And Institutions (Prevention Of Violence And Damage To Property) Act, 2013"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-uth/act/2013/21/eng@2017-01-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-uth/act/2013/21/eng@2017-01-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-24" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-uth/act/2013/21/eng@2017-01-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-uth/act/2013/21/eng@2017-01-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-12-29" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Uttarakhand Medicare Service Persons And Institutions (Prevention Of Violence And Damage To Property) Act, 2013</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[Act No. 21 of 2013]</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>An Act to prohibit violence against Medicare Service Persons and damage to Property Medicare Service Institutions</p>
      <p>Enacted by the Uttarakhand State Legislative Assembly in the Sixty-fourth Year of the Republic of India, as follows--</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Uttarakhand Medicare Service Persons and Institutions (Prevention of Violence and Damage to Property) Act, 2013.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Uttarakhand.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force at once.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>'Medicare Service Institutions' means all institutions providing medicare to people or through mobile medical unit or by arranging medical camps, which are under the control of State or Central Government or Local Bodies etc. including any private hospital having facilities for treatment of the sick and used for their reception or stay, any private material home where women are usually received and accommodated for the purpose of confinement and ante-natal and post-natal care in connection with child birth or anything connected therewith, and any private nursing home used or intended to be used for the reception and accommodation of persons suffering any sickness, injury or infirmity whether of body or mind, and providing treatment or nursing or both of them and includes a maternity home or convalescent home, etc. and an ambulance;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>'Medicare Service Persons' in relation to a Medicare Service Institutions, shall include-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>Registered Medical Practitioner, working in Medicare Institutions (including those having provisional registration);</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>Registered Nurses;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>Auxiliary Nurse Mid-wife and General Nursing Midwife;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>Trained Dai;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.v">
                    <num>(v)</num>
                    <p>Medical Students;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.vi">
                    <num>(vi)</num>
                    <p>Nursing Students; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.vii">
                    <num>(vii)</num>
                    <p>Para medical and other auxiliary workers employed and working in Medicare Service Institutions;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>'Offender' means any person, who either by himself or as a member or as a leader of a group of persons or organisation commits or attempts to commit or abets or incites the commission of violence under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>'Property' shall include both movable and immovable property;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>'Violence' means activities of causing any harm, injury or endangering the life or intimidation, obstruction or hindrance to any medicare service person in discharge of duty in the Medicare Service Institution or patient or damage to property in the Medicare Service Institution,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition of violence</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any act of violence against, Medicare Service Persons or damage to property in the Medicare Service Institutions is hereby prohibited.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Penalty</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever commit or attempts to commit any violence under Section 3, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years or with fine which may extend to fifty thousand rupees or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person in addition to the punishment specified in sub-section (1), shall be also liable to a penalty of double of the amount of purchase price of medical equipments damaged and loss caused to the property.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever, having been convicted of an offence under any provision of this Act is again convicted of an offence under the same provision, shall be punished, for the second and for each subsequent offence, with double the penalty provided for that offence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the complaint is frivolous or has been made with malafide intention, the competent court after trial may proceed against the complainant under the relevant provisions of the Indian Penal Code, 1860.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If such persons does not pay the penal amount under sub-section (2), the said sum shall be recoverable as arrears of land revenue.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Cognizance of offence</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any offence committed under Section 3, shall be cognizable and non-bailable and shall be triable by the Court of Judicial Magistrate of the First Class.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Act not in derogation of any other law</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of this Act shall be in addition to and not in derogation of the provisions of any other law, for the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Savings</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding the lapse of the Uttarakhand Medicare Service Persons and Institutions (Prevention of Violence and Damage to Property) Ordinance, 2011 anything done or any action taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
