<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1963/45/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1963/45"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Administrators- General Act, 1963"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1963/45/eng@1963-12-11/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1963/45/eng@1963-12-11"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1963-12-11" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1963/45/eng@1963-12-11/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1963/45/eng@1963-12-11"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Administrators- General Act, 1963</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 45 OF 1963</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 11th December, 1963.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fourteenth year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to consolidate and amend the law relating to the office and  duties of Administrator- General.</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:--</p>
        <p>CHAP</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be  called the Administrators- General Act, 1963.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It extends to the whole India .</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on such date  as the Central</p>
              <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" assets" means all the property, movable and immovable,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>of a deceased person, which is chargeable with and  applicable to the payment of his debts and legacies, or  available for distribution among his heirs and next- of-</p>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>kin;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" letters of administration" includes any letters of  administration whether general or with a copy of the  will annexed or limited in time or otherwise;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" next- of- kin" includes a widower or widow of a deceased  person, or any other person who by law would be  entitled to letters of administration in preference to  a creditor or legatee of the deceased; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Act.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>THE OFFICE OF THE ADMINISTRATOR- GENERAL</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>THE OFFICE OF THE ADMINISTRATOR- GENERAL</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Appointment of Administrator- General.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government  shall appoint an Administrator- General for the State:</p>
              <p>Provided that nothing herein contained shall be deemed to bar the  appointment of the same person as Administrator- General for two or  more States.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No person shall be appointed to the office of Administrator-</p>
              <blockList id="section-3.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>General unless he has been for at least--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.2.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>seven years an advocate; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.2.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>seven years an attorney of a High Court; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.2.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>ten years a member of the judicial service of a State;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.2.list4">
                <listIntroduction>or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.2.list4.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>five years a Deputy Administrator- General.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Appointment and powers of Deputy Administrator- General.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may appoint a Deputy or Deputies to assist the</p>
              <p>Administrator- General; and any Deputy so appointed shall, subject to  the control of the State Government and the general or special orders  of the Administrator- General, be competent to discharge any of the  duties and to exercise any of the powers of the Administrator- General,</p>
              <p>and when discharging such duties or exercising such powers shall have  the same privileges and be subject to the same liabilities as the</p>
              <p>Administrator- General.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-4.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>No person shall be appointed as a Deputy under this section  unless he has been for at least three years--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>an advocate; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>an attorney of a High Court; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>a member of the judicial service of a State.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Incorporation. The Administrator- General shall be a  corporation sole by the name of the Administrator- General of the State  for which he is appointed, and, as such Administrator- General, shall  have perpetual succession and an official seal, and may sue and be  sued in his corporate name.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>RIGHTS, POWERS AND DUTIES OF THE ADMINISTRATOR- GENERAL</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="chapter-III.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>RIGHTS, POWERS AND DUTIES OF THE ADMINISTRATOR- GENERAL</listIntroduction>
              <item id="chapter-III.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>Grant of letters of administration and probate</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Jurisdiction of High Court for the whole State. So far as  regards the Administrator- General of any State, the High Court shall  be deemed to be a Court of competent jurisdiction for the purpose of  granting probate or letters of administration under</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>any law for the time being in force, wheresoever within the State the  estate to be administered is situate:</p>
              <p>Provided that nothing in this section shall be construed as  affecting the jurisdiction of any district court.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Administrator- General entitled to letters of administration,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>unless granted to next- of- kin. Any letters of administration granted  by the High Court shall be granted to the Administrator- General of the</p>
              <p>State unless they are granted to the next- of- kin of the deceased.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Administrator- General, entitled to letters of administration  in preference to creditors, certain legatees or friends. The</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Administrator- General of the State shall be deemed by all the courts  in the State to have a right to letters of administration other than  letters pendente lite in preference to that of--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>a creditor; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>a legatee, other than a universal legatee or a residuary  legatee or the representative of a residuary legatee;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>a friend of the deceased.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Right of Administrator- General to apply for administration of  estates.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-9.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>If--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-9.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>any person has died leaving within any State assets  exceeding rupees   fifty thousand]] in value, and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>whether the obtaining of probate of his will or letters  of administration to his estate is or is not  obligatory, no person to whom any court would have  jurisdiction to commit administration of such assets  has, within one month after his death, applied in such</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>State for such probate, or letters of administration,</p>
              <blockList id="section-9.1.list4">
                <listIntroduction>and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-9.1.list4.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>(in cases where the obtaining of such probate or letters  of administration is not obligatory under the  provisions of the Indian Succession Act, 1925 (39 of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1925">
          <num>1925.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1925.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>),) no person has taken other proceedings for the  protection of the estate,</p>
              <p>the Administrator- General of the State in which such assets  are, may, subject to any rules made by the State</p>
              <p>Government, within a reasonable time after he has had  notice of the death of such person, and of his having  left such assets, take such proceedings as may be  necessary to obtain from the High Court letters of  administration of the estate of such person.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-1925.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Administrator- General shall not take proceedings under  this section unless he is satisfied, that there is apprehension of  misappropriation, deterioration or waste of such assets if such  proceedings are not taken by him or that such proceedings are  otherwise necessary for the protection of the assets.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Power of Administrator- General to collect and hold assets  where immediate action is required.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Whenever any person has died  leaving assets within any State exceeding rupees  fifty thousand]</p>
              <blockList id="section-10.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>in value, and the High Court for that State is satisfied that there is  imminent danger of misappropriation, deterioration or waste of such  assets, requiring immediate action, the High Court may, upon the  application of the Administrator- General or of any person interested  in such assets or in the due administration thereof, forthwith direct  the Administrator- General--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.1.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to collect and take possession of such assets, and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.1.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>to hold, deposit, realise, sell or invest the same  according to the directions of the High Court, and, in  default of any such directions, according to the  provisions of this Act so far as the same are  applicable to such assets.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-10.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Any order of the High Court under sub- section (1) shall  entitle the Administrator- General--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to maintain any suit or proceeding for the recovery of  such assets;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>if he thinks fit, to apply for letters of administration  of the estate of such deceased person;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>to retain out of the assets of the estate any fees  chargeable under rules made under this Act; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>to reimburse himself for all payments made by him in  respect of such assets which a private administrator  might lawfully have made.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Grant of probate or letters of administration to person  appearing in the course of proceedings taken by Administrator- General.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>If, in the course of proceedings to obtain letters of administration  under the provisions of section 9 or section 10,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>any person appears and establishes his claim--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>to probate of the will of the deceased;</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list3.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>to letters of administration as next- of-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>kin of the deceased, and gives such security as  may be required of him by law; or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list5.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>any person satisfies the High Court that he has taken  and is prosecuting with due diligence other proceedings  for the protection of the estate, the case being one in  which the obtaining of such probate or letters of  administration is not obligatory under the provisions  of the Indian Succession Act, 1925 (39 of 1925); or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list5.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the High Court is satisfied that there is no  apprehension of misappropriation, deterioration, or  waste of the assets and that the grant of letters of  administration in such proceedings is not otherwise  necessary for the protection of the assets;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>the High Court shall--</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>in the case mentioned in clause (a), grant probate of  the will or letters of administration accordingly;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>in the case mentioned in clause (b) or clause (c), drop  the proceedings; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>in all the cases award to the Administrator- General the  costs of any proceedings taken by him under those  sections to be paid out of the estate as part of the  testamentary or intestate expenses thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Grant of administration to Administrator- General in certain  cases. If, in the course of proceedings to obtain letters of  administration under the provisions of section 9 or section 10, and  within such period as to the High Court seems reasonable, no person  appears and establishes his claim to probate of a will, or to a grant  of letters of administration as next- of- kin of the deceased, or  satisfies the High Court that he has taken and is prosecuting with due  diligence other proceedings for the protection of the estate, the case  being one in which the obtaining of such probate or letters of  administration is not obligatory under the provisions of the Indian</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Succession Act, 1925 (39 of 1925), and the High Court is satisfied  that there is apprehension of misappropriation, deterioration, or  waste of the assets or that the grant of letters of administration in  such proceedings is otherwise necessary for the protection of the  assets;</p>
              <p>or if a person who has established his claim to a grant of  letters of administration as next- of- kin of the deceased fails to give  such security as may be required of him by law;</p>
              <p>the High Court may grant letters of administration to the</p>
              <p>Administrator- General.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Administrator- General not precluded from applying for letters  within one month after death. Nothing in this Act shall be deemed to  preclude the Administrator- General from applying to the High Court for  letters of administration in any case within the period of one month  from the death of the deceased.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>Revocation of grants</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Recall of Administrator- General' s administration and grant of  probate, etc., to executor or next- of- kin. If an executor or next- of-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>kin of the deceased, who has not been personally served with a  citation or who has not had notice thereof in time to appear pursuant  thereto, establishes to the satisfaction of the High Court a claim to  probate of will or to letters of administration in preference to the</p>
              <p>Administrator- General, any letters of administration granted in  accordance with the provisions of this Act to the Administrator-</p>
              <blockList id="section-14.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>General--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list3.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>shall be revoked, if a will of the deceased is proved in  the State;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>may be revoked, in other cases, if an application for  that purpose is made within six months after the grant  to the Administrator- General and the High Court is  satisfied that there has been no unreasonable delay in  making the application, or in transmitting the  authority under which the application is made;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>and probate or letters of administration may be granted to such  executor or next- of- kin as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Cost of obtaining administration, etc., may, on revocation,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>be ordered to be paid to Administrator- General out of estate. If any  letters of administration granted to the Administrator- General in  accordance with the provisions of this Act are revoked, the High Court  may order the costs of obtaining such letters of administration, and  the whole or any part of any fees which would otherwise have been  payable under this Act, together with the costs of the Administrator-</p>
              <p>General in any proceedings taken to obtain such revocation, to be paid  to or retained by the Administrator- General out of the estate:</p>
              <p>Provided that nothing in this section shall affect the provisions  of clauses (c) and (d) of sub- section (2) of section 10.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>After revocation letters granted to Administrator- General to  be deemed, as to him, to have been voidable only. If any letters of  administration granted to the Administrator- General in accordance with  the provisions of this Act are revoked,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>the same shall, so far as regards the Administrator- General and all  persons acting under his authority in pursuance thereof, be deemed to  have been only voidable, except as to any act done by any such</p>
              <p>Administrator- General or other person as aforesaid, after notice of a  will or of any other fact which would render such letters void:</p>
              <p>Provided that no notice of a will or of any other fact which  would render any such letters void shall affect the Administrator-</p>
              <p>General or any person acting under his authority in pursuance of such  letters unless, within the period of one month from the time of giving  such notice, proceedings are commenced to prove the will, or to cause  the letters to be revoked, and such proceedings are prosecuted without  unreasonable delay.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Payments made by Administrator- General prior to revocation.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>If any letters of administration granted to the Administrator- General  in accordance with the provisions of this Act are revoked, upon the  grant of probate of a will, or upon the grant of letters of  administration with a copy of the will annexed, all payments made or  acts done by or under the authority of the Administrator- General in  pursuance of such letters of administration, prior to the revocation,</p>
              <blockList id="section-17.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>which would have been valid under any letters of administration  lawfully granted to him with a copy of such will annexed, shall be  deemed valid notwithstanding such revocation.</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>General</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Administrator- General' s petition for grant of letters of  administration. Whenever any Administrator- General applies for letters  of administration in accordance with the provisions of this Act, it  shall be sufficient if the petition required to be presented for the  grant of such letters states,--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-18.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list0.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the time and place of the death of the deceased to the  best of the knowledge and belief of the petitioner;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list0.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>the names and addresses of the surviving next- of- kin of  the deceased, if known;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list0.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>the particulars and value of the assets likely to come  into the hands of the petitioner;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list0.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>particulars of the liabilities of the estate, if known.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Name in which probate or letters to be granted. All probates  or letters of administration granted to any Administrator- General  shall be granted to him by that name.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Effect of probate or letters granted to Administrator-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>General.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-20.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Probate or letters of administration granted by the High</p>
              <p>Court to the Administrator- General of any State shall have effect over  all the assets of the deceased throughout  India] and shall be  conclusive as to the representative title against all debtors of the  deceased and all persons holding such assets, and shall afford full  indemnity to all debtors paying their debts and all persons delivering  up such assets to such Administrator- General.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Whenever a grant of probate or letters of administration is  made by a High Court to the Administrator- General, the High Court  shall send to the High Courts for the other States a certificate that  such grant has been made, and such certificate shall be filed by the</p>
              <p>High Court receiving the same.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any probate or letters of administration granted by the</p>
              <p>High Court for the State of Jammu and Kashmir before the commencement  of the Central Laws (Extension to Jammu and Kashmir) Act, 1968 shall,</p>
              <p>after such commencement, be as effective as if such probate or letters  of administration had been granted under this section.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Effect of grant by the High Court of Jammu and Kashmir.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Effect of grant by the High Court of Jammu and Kashmir. Rep. by the</p>
              <p>Central Laws (Extension to Jammu and Kashmir) Act, 1968 (25 of 1968),</p>
              <p>s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 15- 8- 1968).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Transfer by private executor or administrator of interest  under probate or letters.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-22.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any private executor or administrator  may, with the previous consent of the Administrator- General of the</p>
              <p>State in which any of the assets of the estate, in respect of which  such executor or administrator has obtained probate or letters of  administration, are situate, by an instrument in writing under his  hand notified in the Official Gazette, transfer the assets of the  estate, vested in him by virtue of such probate or letters to the</p>
              <p>Administrator- General by that name or any other sufficient  description.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As from the date of such transfer, the transferor shall be  exempt from all liability as such executor or administrator, as the  case may be, except in respect of acts done before the date of such  transfer, and the Administrator- General shall have the rights which he  would have had, and be subject to the liabilities to which he would  have been subject, if the probate or letters of administration, as the  case may be, had been granted to him by that name at the date of such  transfer.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Distribution of assets.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-23.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When the Administrator- General  has given the prescribed notice to creditors and others to send in to  him their claims against the estate of the deceased, he shall, at the  expiration of the time therein named for sending in claims, be at  liberty to distribute the assets or any part thereof in discharge of  such lawful claims as he has notice of.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Administrator- General shall not be liable for the assets  so distributed to any person of whose claims he had not notice at the  time of such distribution.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No notice of any claim which has been sent in and has been  rejected or disallowed in part by the Administrator- General shall  affect him, unless proceedings to enforce such claim are commenced  within one month after notice of the rejection or disallowance of such  claim has been given in the prescribed manner and unless such  proceedings are prosecuted without unreasonable delay.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in this section shall prejudice the right of any  creditor or other claimant to follow the assets or any part thereof in  the hands of the persons who may have received the same respectively.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In computing the period of limitation for any suit, appeal or  application under the provisions of any law for the time being in  force, the period between the date or submission of the claim of a  creditor or other claimant to the Administrator- General and the date  of the final decision of the Administrator- General on such claim shall  be excluded.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Appointment of Official Trustee as trustee of assets after  completion of administration.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-24.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When the Administrator- General has,</p>
              <p>so far as may be, discharged all the liabilities of an estate  administered by him, he shall notify the fact in the Official Gazette,</p>
              <p>and he may, by an instrument in writing, with the consent of the</p>
              <p>Official Trustee and subject to any rules made by the State</p>
              <p>Government, appoint the Official Trustee to be the trustee of any  assets then remaining in his hands.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-24.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Upon such appointment, such assets shall vest in the Official</p>
              <p>Trustee as if he had been appointed trustee in accordance with the  provisions of the Official Trustees Act, 1913 (2 of 1913), and shall  be held by him upon the same trusts as the same were held immediately  before such appointment.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Power of High Court to give directions regarding  administration of estate. The High Court may, on application made to  it by the Administrator- General or any person interested in the assets  or in the due administration thereof, give to the Administrator-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>General of</p>
              <p>the State any general or special directions as to any estate in his  charge or in regard to the administration of any such estate.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>No security to be required from Administrator- General. No</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Administrator- General shall be required by any Court to enter into any  administration bond, or to give other security to the Court, on the  grant of any letters of administration to him by that name.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Manner in which petition to be verified by Administrator-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>General. No Administrator- General shall be required to verify,</p>
              <p>otherwise than by his signature, any petition presented by him under  the provisions of this Act, and, if the facts stated in any such  petition are not within his own personal knowledge, the petition may  be subscribed and verified by any person competent to make  verification.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Entry of Administrator- General not to constitute notice of a  trust. The entry of the Administrator- General by that name in the  books of a company shall not constitute notice of a trust, and a  company shall not be entitled to object to entering the name of the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Administrator- General on its register by reason only that the</p>
              <p>Administrator- General is a corporation, and in dealing with assets the  fact that the person dealt with is the Administrator- General shall not  of itself constitute notice of a trust.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>GRANT OF CERTIFICATE</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>GRANT OF CERTIFICATE</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>In what cases Administrator- General may grant certificate.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-29.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Whenever any person has died leaving assets within any State and  the Administrator- General of such State is satisfied that such assets,</p>
              <p>excluding any sum of money deposited in a Government Savings Bank or  in any provident fund to which the provisions of the Provident Fund</p>
              <p>Act, 1925 (19 of 1925) apply, did not at the date of death exceed in  the whole   fifty thousand] rupees in value, he may grant to any  person, claiming otherwise than as a creditor to be interested in such  assets or in the due administration thereof, a certificate under his  hand entitling the claimant to receive the assets therein mentioned  left by the deceased within the State, to a value not exceeding in the  whole   fifty thousand] rupees.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No certificate under this section shall be granted before the  lapse of one month from the death unless before the lapse of the said  one month the Administrator- General is requested so to do by</p>
              <p>writing under the hand of the executor or the widow or other person  entitled to administer the estate of the deceased and he thinks fit to  grant it.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-29.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>No certificate shall be granted under this section,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-29.3.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>where probate of the deceased' s will or letters of  administration of his estate has or have been granted;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-29.3.list3">
                <listIntroduction>or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-29.3.list3.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>in respect of any sum of money deposited in a</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Government Savings Bank or in any provident fund to  which the provisions of the Provident Funds Act, 1925</p>
              <p>(19 of 1925), apply.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading>Grant of certificate to creditors and power to take charge of  certain estates.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-30.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If, in cases falling within section 29, no person  claiming to be interested otherwise than as a creditor in such assets  or in the due administration thereof obtains, within three months of  the death of the deceased, a certificate from the Administrator-</p>
              <p>General under that section, or probate of a will or letters of  administration of the estate of the deceased, the Administrator-</p>
              <p>General may administer the estate without letters of administration,</p>
              <p>in the same manner as if such letters had been granted to him.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-30.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the Administrator- General neglects or refuses to  administer such estate, he shall, upon the application of a creditor,</p>
              <p>grant a certificate to him in the same manner as if he were interested  in such assets otherwise than as a creditor; and such certificate  shall have the same effect as a certificate granted under the  provisions of section 29, and shall be subject to all the provisions  of this Act which are applicable to such certificate.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-30.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Administrator- General may, if he thinks fit, before  granting a certificate under sub- section (2), require the creditor to  give reasonable security for the due administration of the estate of  the deceased.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading>Administrator- General not bound to grant certificate unless  satisfied of claimant' s title, etc. The Administrator- General shall  not be bound to grant any certificate under section 29 or section 30  unless he is satisfied after making such inquiry as he thinks fit of  the title of the claimant and of the value of the assets left by the  deceased within the State.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>Effect of certificate. The holder of a certificate granted in  accordance with the provisions of section 29 or section 30 shall have  in respect of the assets specified in such certificate the same powers  and duties, and</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-32.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>be subject to the same liabilities as he would have had or been  subject to if letters of administration had been granted to him:</p>
              <blockList id="section-32.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that nothing in this section shall be deemed to require  any person holding such certificate,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to file accounts or inventories of the assets of the  deceased before any court or other authority; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>save as provided in section 30, to give any bond for the  due administration of the estate.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading>Revocation of certificate.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-33.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-33.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Administrator- General may  revoke a certificate granted under the provisions of section 29 or  section 30 on any of the following grounds, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-33.1.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>that the certificate was obtained by fraud or  misrepresentation made to him;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-33.1.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>that the certificate was obtained by means of an untrue  allegation of a fact essential in law to justify the  grant though such allegation was made in ignorance or  inadvertently.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-33.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No certificate shall be revoked under this section unless the  holder of the certificate has been given a reasonable opportunity of  showing cause why the certificate should not be so revoked.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-34">
          <num>34.</num>
          <heading>Surrender of revoked certificate.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-34.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When a certificate is  revoked in accordance with the provisions of section 33, the holder  thereof shall, on the requisition of the Administrator- General,</p>
              <p>deliver it up to such Administrator- General, but shall not be entitled  to the refund of any fee paid thereon.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-34.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If such person wilfully and without reasonable cause omits to  deliver up the certificate, he shall be punishable with imprisonment  which may extend to three months, or with fine which may extend to one  thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading>Payment to holder of certificate before it is revoked. When a  certificate is revoked in accordance with the provisions of section</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-33.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>, all payments made in good faith under such certificate to the  holder thereof before such revocation, shall, notwithstanding such  revocation, be a legal discharge to the person making the payment and  the holder of such certificate may retain, and reimburse himself in  respect of, any payments made by him which the person to whom a  certificate or probate or letters of administration may afterwards be  granted might lawfully have made.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-36">
          <num>36.</num>
          <heading>Administrator- General not bound to take out administration on  account of assets for which he has granted certificate. The</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-36.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Administrator- General shall not be bound to take out letters of  administration of the estate of any deceased person on account of the  assets in respect of which he grants any certificate under section 29  or section 30, but he may do so if he revokes such certificate under  section 33, or ascertains that the value of the estate exceeded     fifty thousand] rupees.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-37">
          <num>37.</num>
          <heading>Transfer of certain assets to executor or administrator in  country of domicile for distribution. Where--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-37.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-37.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-37.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>a person not having his domicile in any State  in</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-37.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>India] has died leaving assets in any State and in the  country in which he had his domicile at the time of his  death, and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-37.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>proceedings for the administration of his estate with  respect to assets in any such State have been taken  under section 29 or section 30, and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-37.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>there has been a grant of administration in the country  of domicile, with respect to the assets in that  country,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>the holder of the certificate granted under section 29 or section 30,</p>
              <p>or the Administrator- General, as the case may be, after having given  the prescribed notice for creditors and others to send in to him their  claims against the estate of the deceased, and after having  discharged, at the expiration of the time therein named, such lawful  claims as he has notice of, may, instead of himself distributing any  surplus or residue of the deceased' s property to persons residing out  of India  who are entitled thereto, transfer, with the consent of  the executor or administrator, as the case may be, in the country of  domicile, the surplus or residue to him for distribution to those  persons.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>LIABILITY</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-V.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>LIABILITY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-38">
          <num>38.</num>
          <heading>Liability of Government. The Government shall be liable to  make good all sums required to discharge any liability which the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-38.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Administrator- General, if he were a private administrator, would be  personally liable to discharge, except when the liability is one to  which neither the Administrator- General nor any of his officers has in  any way contributed, or which neither he nor any of his officers  could, by the exercise of reasonable diligence, have averted, have  averted, and in either of those</p>
              <p>cases the Administrator- General shall not, nor shall the Government,</p>
              <p>be subject to any liability.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-39">
          <num>39.</num>
          <heading>Creditor' s suit against Administrator- General.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-39.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any  suit be brought by a creditor against any Administrator- General, such  creditor shall be liable to pay the costs of the suit unless he proves  that not less than one month previous to the institution of the suit  he had applied in writing to the Administrator- General, stating the  amount and other particulars of his claim, and had given such evidence  in support thereof as, in the circumstances of the case, the</p>
              <p>Administrator- General was reasonably entitled to require.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-39.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any such suit is decreed in favour of the creditor, he  shall, nevertheless, unless he is a secured creditor, be only entitled  to payment of the amount decreed or ordered by the court to be paid  out of the assets of the deceased equally and rateably with the other  creditors.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-40">
          <num>40.</num>
          <heading>Notice of suit not required in certain cases. Nothing in  section 80 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), shall  apply to any suit against the Administrator- General in which no relief  is claimed against him personally.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-40.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>FEES</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VI">
        <num>VI</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-VI.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>FEES</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-41">
          <num>41.</num>
          <heading>Fees.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-41.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>There shall be charged in respect of the duties of  the Administrator- General such fees, whether by way of percentage or  otherwise, as may be prescribed by the State Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-41.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The fees under this section may be at different rates for  different estates or classes of estates or for different duties, and  shall, so far as may be, be arranged so as to produce an amount  sufficient to discharge the salaries and all other expenses incidental  to the working of this Act, (including such sum as the State</p>
              <p>Government may determine to be required to insure the Government   against loss under this Act).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-42">
          <num>42.</num>
          <heading>Disposal of fees.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-42.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any expenses which might be retained or  paid out of any estate in the charge of the Administrator- General, if  he were a private Administrator of such estate shall be so retained or  paid and the fees described under section 41 shall be retained or paid  in like manner as and in addition to such expenses.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-42.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Administrator- General shall transfer and pay to such  authority in such manner and at such time as the State Govern-</p>
              <p>ment may prescribe, all fees received by him under this Act, and the  same shall be carried to the account and the credit of the Government.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>AUDIT OF THE ADMINISTRATOR- GENERAL' S ACCOUNTS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VII">
        <num>VII</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-VII.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>AUDIT OF THE ADMINISTRATOR- GENERAL' S ACCOUNTS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-43">
          <num>43.</num>
          <heading>Audit. The accounts of every Administrator- General shall be  audited at least once annually and at any other time if the State</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-43.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government so directs, by the prescribed person and in the prescribed  manner.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-44">
          <num>44.</num>
          <heading>Auditors to examine accounts and report to Government. The  auditors shall examine the accounts and forward to the State</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-44.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-44.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Government a statement thereof in the prescribed form, together with a  report thereon and a certificate signed by them showing--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-44.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>whether the accounts have been audited in the prescribed  manner;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-44.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>whether, so far as can be ascertained by such audit, the  accounts contain a full and true account of everything  which ought to be inserted therein;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-44.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>whether the books which by any rules made under this Act  are directed to be kept by the Administrator- General,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-44.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>have been duly and regularly kept; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-44.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>whether the assets and securities have been duly kept  and invested and deposited in the manner prescribed  by this Act, or by any rules made thereunder;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>or (as the case may be) that such accounts are deficient, or that the</p>
              <p>Administrator- General has failed to comply with this Act or the rules  made thereunder, in such respects as may be specified in such  certificate.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-45">
          <num>45.</num>
          <heading>Power of auditors to summon and examine witnesses, and to  call for documents.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-45.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every auditor shall have all the powers vested  in a civil court under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908),</p>
              <blockList id="section-45.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>when trying a suit, in respect of the following matters, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-45.1.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>summoning and enforcing the attendance of witnesses and  examining them on oath;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-45.1.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>discovery and inspection;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-45.1.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>compelling the production of documents; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-45.1.list2.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person who when summoned refuses, or, without reasonable  cause, neglects to attend or to produce any document or thing or  attends and refuses to be sworn, or to be examined, shall be deemed to  have committed an offence within the meaning of, and punishable under,</p>
              <p>section 188 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860), and the auditor  shall report every case of such refusal or neglect to the State</p>
              <p>Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-46">
          <num>46.</num>
          <heading>Costs of audit, etc. The costs of and incidental to such  audit and examination shall be determined in accordance with rules  made by the State Government, and shall be defrayed in the prescribed  manner.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-46.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VIII">
        <num>VIII</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-VIII.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-47">
          <num>47.</num>
          <heading>General powers of administration. The Administrator- General  may, in addition to, and not in derogation of, any other powers of  expenditure lawfully exercisable by him, incur expenditure--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-47.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-47.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-47.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>on such acts as may be necessary for the proper care and  management of any property belonging to any estate in  his charge; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-47.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>with the sanction of the High Court, on such religious,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>charitable and other objects, and on such improvements,</p>
              <p>as may be reasonable and proper in the case of such  property.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-48">
          <num>48.</num>
          <heading>Power to summon and examine witnesses.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-48.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Administrator-</p>
              <p>General may, whenever he desires, for the purposes of this Act, to  satisfy himself regarding any question of fact, exercise all the  powers vested in a civil court under the Code of Civil Procedure,</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1908">
          <num>1908.</num>
          <heading>(5 of 1908), when trying a suit, in respect of the following  matters, namely:--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-1908.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1908.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-1908.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>summoning and enforcing the attendance of witnesses and  examining them on oath;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1908.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>discovery and inspection;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1908.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>compelling the production of documents; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1908.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-1908.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of sub- section (2) of section 45 shall apply  in relation to a person summoned by the Administrator- General under  this section as they apply in relation to a person summoned under that  section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-49">
          <num>49.</num>
          <heading>Power of person beneficially interested to inspect</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-49.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Administrator- General' s account, etc., and take copies. Any person  interested in the administration of any estate which is in the charge  of the Administrator- General shall, subject to such conditions and  restrictions as may be prescribed, be entitled at all reasonable times  to inspect the accounts relating to such estate and the reports and  certificates of the auditor, and on payment of the prescribed fee, to  copies thereof and extracts therefrom.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-50">
          <num>50.</num>
          <heading>False evidence. Whoever, during any examination authorised by  this Act, makes upon oath a statement which is false and which he  either knows or believes to be false or does not believe to be true,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-50.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>shall be deemed to have intentionally given false evidence in a stage  of a judicial proceeding.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-51">
          <num>51.</num>
          <heading>Assets unclaim for twelve years to be transferred to</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-51.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government. All assets in the charge of the Administrator- General  which have been in his custody for a period of twelve years or  upwards, whether before or after the commencement of this Act, without  any application for payment thereof having been made and granted by  him shall be transferred, in the prescribed manner, to the account and  credit of the Government:</p>
              <p>Provided that this section shall not authorise the transfer of  any such assets as aforesaid, if any suit or proceeding is pending in  respect thereof in any court.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-52">
          <num>52.</num>
          <heading>Mode of proceeding by claimant to recover principal money so  transferred.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-52.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any claim is hereafter made to any part of the  assets transferred to the account and credit of the Government under  the provisions of this Act, or any Act hereby repealed, and if such  claim is established to the satisfaction of the prescribed authority,</p>
              <p>the State Government shall pay to the claimant the amount of the  principal so transferred to its account and credit or so much thereof  as has been found by the said authority to be due to the claimant.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-52.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the claim is not established to the satisfaction of the  prescribed authority, the claimant may, without prejudice to his right  to take any other proceedings for the recovery of such assets, apply  by petition to the High Court against the State Government and</p>
              <p>such Court, after taking such evidence as it thinks fit, shall make  such order in regard to the payment of the whole or any part of the  said principal sum as it thinks fit, and such order shall be binding  on all parties to the proceedings.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-52.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The High Court may further direct by whom the whole or any  part of the costs of each party shall be paid.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-53">
          <num>53.</num>
          <heading>Succession Act or Companies Act not to affect Administrator-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-53.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>General. Nothing contained in the Indian Succession Act, 1925 (39 of</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1925">
          <num>1925.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1925.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>), or the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), shall be taken to  supersede or affect the rights, duties and privileges of any</p>
              <p>Administrator- General.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-54">
          <num>54.</num>
          <heading>Savings of provisions of Police Acts for presidency- towns.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-54.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Nothing contained in the Indian Succession Act, 1925 (39 of 1925), or  in this Act, shall be deemed to affect, or to have affected, any law  for the time being in force relating to the movable property under  four hundred rupees in value of persons dying intestate within any of  the presidency- towns which shall be or has been taken charge of by the  police for the purpose of safe custody.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-55">
          <num>55.</num>
          <heading>Order of court to be equivalent to decree. Any order made  under this Act by any court shall have the same effect as a decree.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-56">
          <num>56.</num>
          <heading>Provision for administration by Consular Officer in case of  death in certain circumstances of foreign subject. Notwithstanding  anything in this Act, or in any other law for the time being in force,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-56.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>the Central Government may, by general or special order, direct that,</p>
              <p>where a subject of a foreign State dies in  India], and it appears  that there is no one in  India], other than the Administrator-</p>
              <p>General, entitled to apply to a court of competent jurisdiction for  letters of administration of the estate of the deceased, letters of  administration shall, on the application to such court by any Consular</p>
              <p>Officer of such foreign State, be granted to such Consular Officer on  such terms and conditions as the Court may, subject to any rules made  in this behalf by the Central Government, think fit to impose.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-57">
          <num>57.</num>
          <heading>Letters of administration not necessary in respects of small  estates administered by Administrator- General in accordance with  certain Acts. It shall not be necessary for the Administrator- General  to take out letters of administration of the estate of any deceased  person which is being administered by him in accordance with the  provisions of the Army and Air Force (Disposal of Private Property)</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-57.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Act, 1950 (40 of 1950),</p>
              <p>or the Navy Act, 1957 (62 of 1957), if the value of such estate does  not, on the date when such administration is committed to him, exceed  rupees two thousand, but he shall have the same power in regard to  such estate as he would have had if letters of administration had been  granted to him.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-58">
          <num>58.</num>
          <heading>Powers to grant Administrator- General letters limited for  purpose of dealing with assets in accordance with the Army and Air</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-58.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Force (Disposal of Private Property) Act, 1950, or the Navy Act, 1957.</p>
              <p>If the Administrator- General applies in accordance with the provisions  of the Army and Air Force (Disposal of Private Property) Act, 1950</p>
              <p>(40 of 1950), or the Navy Act, 1957 (62 of 1957), for letters of  administration of the estate of any person subject to the Army Act,</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1950">
          <num>1950.</num>
          <heading>(46 of 1950), or the Air Force Act, 1950 (45 of 1950), or the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-1950.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Navy Act, 1957, the Court may grant to him letters of administration  limited to the purpose of dealing with such estate in accordance with  the provisions of the Army and Air Force (Disposal of Private</p>
              <p>Property) Act, 1950, or, as the case may be, the Navy Act, 1957.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-59">
          <num>59.</num>
          <heading>Act not to affect Army and Air Force (Disposal of Private</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-59.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Property) Act, 1950, or the Navy Act, 1957. Nothing in this Act shall  be deemed to affect the provisions of the Army and Air Force (Disposal   of Private Property) Act, 1950 (40 of 1950), or the Navy, Act, 1957</p>
              <p>(62 of 1957).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-60">
          <num>60.</num>
          <heading>Saving of provisions of Indian Registration Act, 1908.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-60.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in this Act shall be deemed to affect the provisions of the</p>
              <p>Indian Registration Act, 1908 (16 of 1908).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-61">
          <num>61.</num>
          <heading>Power of Central Government to make rules. The Central</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-61.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules as  to the terms and conditions on which letters of administration may be  granted to Consular Officers under section 56.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-62">
          <num>62.</num>
          <heading>Power of State Government to make rules.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-62.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State</p>
              <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules  for carrying out the purposes of this Act, and for regulating the  proceedings of the Administrator- General.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-62.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-62.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-62.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the accounts to be kept by the Administrator- General and  the audit and inspection thereof;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-62.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the safe custody, deposit and investment of assets and  securities which come into the hands of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-62.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Administrator- General;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-62.2.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the remittance of sums of money in the hands of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-62.2.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Administrator- General in cases in which such  remittances are required;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-62.2.list5.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>subject to the provisions of this Act, the fees to be  paid under this Act and the collection and accounting  for any such fees;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-62.2.list5.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the statements, schedules and other documents to be  submitted to the State Government or to any other  authority by the Administrator- General, and the  publication thereof;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-62.2.list5.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the realization of the cost of preparing any such  statements, schedules or other documents;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-62.2.list5.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which and the person by whom the costs of  and incidental to any audit under the provisions of  this Act are to be determined and defrayed;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-62.2.list5.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which summonses issued under this Act are  to be served and the payment of the expenses of any  person summoned or examined under the provisions of  this Act, and of any expenditure incidental to such  examination; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-62.2.list5.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>any other matter which is required to be, or may be,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>prescribed under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-62.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made by the State Government under this Act  shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before the State</p>
              <p>Legislature.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-63">
          <num>63.</num>
          <heading>Laying of rules made by Central Government before Parliament.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-63.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act shall be  laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of</p>
              <p>Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty days,</p>
              <p>which may be comprised in one session or  in two or more successive  sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately  following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid] both</p>
              <p>Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses  agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have  effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may  be; so however that any such modification or annulment shall be  without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under  that rule.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-64">
          <num>64.</num>
          <heading>Repeal and savings.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-64.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Administrator- General' s Act,</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1913">
          <num>1913.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1913.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>, (3 of 1913) is hereby repealed.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-1913.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Without prejudice to the generality of the provisions of the</p>
              <p>General Clauses Act, 1897 (10 of 1897), relating to the effect of  repeals, the repeal effected by this section shall not affect the  incorporation of any person holding the office of Administrator-</p>
              <p>General at the commencement of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1913.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, the  provisions of section 59B of the Administrator- General' s Act, 1913</p>
              <p>(3 of 1913), shall continue to apply as if that Act had not been  repealed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
