<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-chg/act/2005/17/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-chg/act/2005/17"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Chhattisgarh Tonahi Pratadna Nivaran Act, 2005"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-chg/act/2005/17/eng@2017-01-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-chg/act/2005/17/eng@2017-01-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-chg/act/2005/17/eng@2017-01-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-chg/act/2005/17/eng@2017-01-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-24" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Chhattisgarh Tonahi Pratadna Nivaran Act, 2005</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 17 OF 2005</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[30th September, 2005.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by the Chhattisgarh Legislature in the Fifty-sixth year of the Republic of India as follows:-</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Chhattisgarh Tonahi Pratadna Nivaran Adhiniyam, 2005.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Chhattisgarh.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force from the date of its publication in the Official Gazette.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“Tonahi” means person indicated by any person or persons that he will harm or possesses power to harm or thereby he intends to harm any other person or persons or society or animal or living things by black magic, evil eye or by any other means, whether known as Dayan, Tonaha or by any other names.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“Identifier” means person who indicates any person as Tonahi or induces other person to indicate or by his deed, words, gesture or behavior helps to indicate or knowingly does anything so thereby on the basis of such indication that person may be harmed or apprehended to be harmed or his security and honour may be adversely affected.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“Ojha” may be known by any other name whatsoever means person who claims to possess power to control, cure, treat Tonahi or any person or animal or living things alleged to be affected by Tonahi and make him powerless, by jharphook, totka, tantra-mantra or by any means.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“Damage” includes physical, mental and economic harm and harm to reputation.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“Code” means the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (No. 2 of 1974).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Act not in derogation of any other law.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Provisions of this Act shall be in addition to and not in derogation of any other law for the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Punishment for Identifying Tonahi.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever identifies any person as tonahi by any means shall be punished with rigorous imprisonment for a term which may extend to 3 years and also with fine.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Punishment for harassment.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever causes physical or mental harassment or damage to any person identified by him or any person as tonahi shall be punished with rigorous imprisonment for a term which may extend to 5 years and also with fine.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Punishment for alleged curing.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever does any act of jharphook, totka, use of tantra-mantra or anything as Ojha upon any person indicated as a tonahi or any other person or animal or living thing alleged to be affected by such tonahi, under any claim or treatment or control shall punished with rigorous imprisonment for a term which may extend to 5 years and also with fine.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Punishment for claiming to be tonahi.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever claims to have power to harm any person or animal or living things by black magic, evil eye or by any other means and publicizes it and tries to disturb the public tranquility or peace or causes annoyance or harms others shall be punished with rigorous imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year and also with fine.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Punishment for attempt to commit offence.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever attempts to commit any offence punishable under this Act or to cause such offence to be committed and in such attempt does any act towards the commission of the offence shall be punished with the punishment provided for the offence.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Trial of offences under the Act.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every offence under this Act shall be triable by the Judicial Magistrate First Class.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Offences to be cognizable and non-bailable.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (No. 2 of 1974) -</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>every offence punishable under this Act shall be cognizable and non-bailable.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>no person accused of an offence punishable under this Act shall be released on bail or on his own bond unless, the public prosecutor has been given an oppor¬tunity to oppose the application for such release.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Application of Section 360 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 and of the Probation of Offenders Act, 1958.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Nothing contained in section 360 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (No. 2 of 1974) or in the Probation of Offenders Act, 1958 (No. 20 of 1958) shall apply to a person convicted of an offence under this Act unless such person is under eighteen years of age.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Matters to be taken into consideration for fixing fine.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where a sentence of fine is imposed under Sections 4, 5 and 6, the court in fixing the amount of the fine shall take into consideration the physical and mental damage caused to victim including any cost of treatment.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Order for compensation.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>When a court imposes sentence of fine, the court shall when passing judgment, order the whole or part of the fine recovered to be awarded as compensation to the victim.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Bar of jurisdiction.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No civil court shall entertain any suit or proceeding against any decision made or order passed by any officer or authority under this Act or any rule made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the State Government or any officer of the State Government or any other person exercising any power or discharging any function or performing any duty under this Act, for anything done in good faith or intended to be done under this Act or any rule made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification, make the rules to carry out the provisions of this Act. Every rule made under this Act by the State Government shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before the State legislature.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
