<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2007/5/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2007/5"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Central Educational Institutions (Reservation In Admission) Act, 2006"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2007/5/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2007/5/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2007/5/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2007/5/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Central Educational Institutions (Reservation In Admission) Act, 2006</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Central Educational Institutions (Reservation in Admission) Act, 2006.</p>
            <p>The Central Educational Institutions (Reservation in Admission) Act, 2006</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“academic session” means the period in a calendar year, or a part thereof, during which a Central Educational Institution is open for teaching or instruction in any branch of study or faculty;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“annual permitted strength” means the number of seats, in a course or programme for teaching or instruction in each branch of study or faculty authorised by an appropriate authority for admission of students to a Central Educational Institution;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“appropriate authority” means the University Grants Commission, the Bar Council of India, the Medical Council of India, the All India Council for Technical Education or any other authority or body established by or under a Central Act for the determination, coordination or maintenance of the standards of higher education in any Central Educational Institution;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>“Central Educational Institution” means—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>a university established or incorporated by or under a Central Act;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>an institution of national importance set up by an Act of Parliament;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>an institution, declared as a deemed University under section 3 of the University Grants Commission Act, 1956 (3 of 1956) and maintained by or receiving aid from the Central Government;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>an institution maintained by or receiving aid from the Central Government, whether directly or indirectly, and affiliated to an institution referred to in clause (i) or clause (ii), or a constituent unit of an institution referred to in clause (iii);</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0.v">
                    <num>(v)</num>
                    <p>an educational institution set up by the Central Government under the Societies Registration Act, 1860 (21 of 1860);</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>“faculty” means the faculty of a Central Educational Institution;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>“Minority Educational Institution” means an institution established and administered by the minorities under clause (1) of article 30 of the Constitution and so declared by an Act of Parliament or by the Central Government or declared as a minority educational institution under the National Commission for Minority Educational Institutions Act, 2004 (2 of 2005);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>“Other Backward Classes” means the class or classes of citizens who are socially and educationally backward, and are so determined by the Central Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>“Scheduled Castes” means the Scheduled Castes notified under article 341 of the Constitution;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>“Scheduled Tribes” means the Scheduled Tribes notified under article 342 of the Constitution;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>“teaching or instruction in any branch of study” means teaching or instruction in a branch of study leading to three principal levels of qualifications at bachelor (undergraduate) masters (postgraduate) and doctoral levels.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>The Central Educational Institutions (Reservation in Admission) Act, 2006</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Reservation of seats in Central Educational Institutions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The reservation of seats in admission and its extent in a Central Educational Institution shall be provided in the following manner, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>out of the annual permitted strength in each branch of study or faculty, fifteen per cent. seats shall be reserved for the Scheduled Castes;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>out of the annual permitted strength in each branch of study or faculty, seven and one-half per cent. seats shall be reserved for the Scheduled Tribes;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>out of the annual permitted strength in each branch of study or faculty, twenty-seven per cent. seats shall be reserved for the Other Backward Classes.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>The Central Educational Institutions (Reservation in Admission) Act, 2006</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Act not to apply in certain cases.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The provisions of section 3 of this Act shall not apply to—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>a Central Educational Institution established in the tribal areas referred to in the Sixth Schedule to the Constitution;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the institutions of excellence, research institutions, institutions of national and strategic importance specified in the Schedule to this Act:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that the Central Government may, as and when considered necessary, by notification in the Official Gazette, amend the Schedule;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>a Minority Educational Institution as defined in this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>a course or programme at high levels of specialisation, including at the post-doctoral level, within any branch of study or faculty, which the Central Government may, in consultation with the appropriate authority, specify.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>The Central Educational Institutions (Reservation in Admission) Act, 2006</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Mandatory increase of seats.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in clause (iii) of section 3 and in any other law for the time being in force, every Central Educational Institution shall, with the prior approval of the appropriate authority, increase the number of seats in a branch of study or faculty over and above its annual permitted strength so that the number of seats, excluding those reserved for the persons belonging to the Scheduled Castes, the Scheduled Tribes and the Other Backward Classes, is not less than the number of such seats available for the academic session immediately preceding the date of the coming into force of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where, on a representation by any Central Educational Institution, the Central Government, in consultation with the appropriate authority, is satisfied that for reasons of financial, physical or academic limitations or in order to maintain the standards of education, the annual permitted strength in any branch of study or faculty of such institution cannot be increased for the academic session following the commencement of this Act, it may permit by notification in the Official Gazette, such institution to increase the annual permitted strength over a maximum period of three years beginning with the academic session following the commencement of this Act; and then, the extent of reservation for the Other Backward Classes as provided in clause (iii) of section 3 shall be limited for that academic session in such manner that the number of seats available to the Other Backward Classes for each academic session are commensurate with the increase in the permitted strength for each year.</p>
            <p>The Central Educational Institutions (Reservation in Admission) Act, 2006</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Reservation of seats in admissions to begin in calendar year, 2007.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Central Educational Institutions shall take all necessary steps, which are required in giving effect to the provisions of sections 3, 4 and 5 of this Act, for the purposes of reservation of seats in admissions to its academic sessions commencing on and from the calendar year, 2007.</p>
            <p>The Central Educational Institutions (Reservation in Admission) Act, 2006</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Laying of notifications before Parliament.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every notification made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the notification or both Houses agree that the notification should not be made, the notification shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that notification.</p>
            <p>The Central Educational Institutions</p>
            <p>(Reservation in Admission) Act, 2006</p>
            <p>THE SCHEDULE</p>
            <p>See section 4(b)</p>
            <p>S. No. Names of the Institutions of Excellence, etc.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Homi Bhabha National Institute, Mumbai and its constituent units, namely:—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-1.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list0.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>Bhabha Atomic Research Centre, Trombay;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list0.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>Indira Gandhi Centre for Atomic Research, Kalpakkam;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list0.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>Raja Ramanna Centre for Advanced Technology, Indore;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list0.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>Institute for Plasma Research, Gandhinagar;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list0.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>Variable Energy Cyclotron Centre, Kolkata;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list0.vi">
                <num>(vi)</num>
                <p>Saha Institute of Nuclear Physics, Kolkata;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list0.vii">
                <num>(vii)</num>
                <p>Institute of Physics, Bhubaneshwar;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list0.viii">
                <num>(viii)</num>
                <p>Institute of Mathematical Sciences, Chennai;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list0.ix">
                <num>(ix)</num>
                <p>Harish-Chandra Research Institute, Allahabad;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list0.x">
                <num>(x)</num>
                <p>Tata Memorial Centre, Mumbai.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Tata Institute of Fundamental Research, Mumbai.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>North-Eastern Indira Gandhi Regional Institute of Health and Medical Science, Shillong.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>National Brain Research Centre, Manesar, Gurgaon.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Jawaharlal Nehru Centre for Advanced Scientific Research, Bangalore.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Physical Research Laboratory, Ahmedabad.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Space Physics Laboratory, Thiruvananthapuram.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Indian Institute of Remote Sensing, Dehradun.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>—————</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
