<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1888/8/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1888/8"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Indian Tolls Act, 1888"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1888/8/eng@1888-09-05/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1888/8/eng@1888-09-05"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1888-09-05" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1888/8/eng@1888-09-05/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1888/8/eng@1888-09-05"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Indian Tolls Act, 1888</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 8 OF 1888</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 5th September, 1888.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to remove doubts as to the legality of the levy of certain</p>
        <p>Tolls.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS doubts have been raised as to the operation of the Acts  of the Governor General in Council, No. VIII of 1851 (an Act for   enabling Government to levy Tolls on Public Roads and Bridges) and No.</p>
        <p>XV of 1864 (an Act to amend Act VIII of 1851); It is hereby enacted as  follows:--</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Enforcement of Acts VIII of 1851 and XV of 1864 in the Punjab.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Act VIII of 1851 and XV of 1864 shall be deemed to be in force  throughout the territories now administered by the Lieutenant- Governor  of the Punjab, and from the twenty- first day of August, 1857, and the  twenty- fourth day of March, 1864, respectively, to have been in force  in the territories for the time being administered as part of the</p>
            <p>Punjab  as it existed immediately before the 1st November, 1956].</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Operation of the Act in the Punjab and certain other parts of  the States.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In any part of India] beyond the limits of the  territories administered by the Governor of Fort St. George in</p>
            <p>Council, and the Lieutenant- Governors of Bengal and the North- Western</p>
            <p>Provinces, to or in which Acts VIII of 1851 and XV of 1864 may be or  have been extended, or may be or have been declared to be in force,</p>
            <p>under the latter of those Acts or by this Act or by or under any other  enactment, the State Government shall be deemed to have and, where the</p>
            <p>Acts have been in force the passing of this Act, to have had the same  authority as if it had been included among the State Governments  specified in section 2 of Act VIII of 1851.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Validation of past levy of tolls. All tolls levied, or  purporting to have been levied, under Acts VIII of 1851 and XV of</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1864">
        <num>1864.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1864.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>, or either of those Acts, before the passing of this Act, shall  be deemed to have been lawfully levied.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Saving. Nothing in the foregoing sections shall affect any  proceedings commenced in any Civil Court before the first day of July,</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1888">
        <num>1888.</num>
        <heading/>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of section 2, Act VIII, 1851. Rep. by the A. O.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1937">
        <num>1937.</num>
        <heading/>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
