<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1985/82/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1985/82"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Inland Waterways Authority Of India Act, 1985"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1985/82/eng@1985-12-30/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1985/82/eng@1985-12-30"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1985-12-30" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1985/82/eng@1985-12-30/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1985/82/eng@1985-12-30"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Inland Waterways Authority Of India Act, 1985</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 82 OF 1985</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 30th December, 1985.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty- sixth Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the constitution of an Authority for the  regulation and development of inland waterways for purposes of  shipping and navigation and for matters connected therewith or  incidental thereto.</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:--</p>
        <p>CHAP</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the</p>
              <p>Inland Waterways Authority of India Act, 1985.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on such date  as the Central</p>
              <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" appurtenant land" means all lands appurtenant to a  national waterway, whether demarcated or not;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" Authority" means the Inland Waterways Authority of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>India constituted under section 3;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" channel" means any waterway, whether natural or  artificial;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" conservancy" includes dredging, training, closure,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>diversion or abandoning channels;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>" conservancy measures" means measures for purposes of  conservancy, but does not include measures for protection of  banks against floods or for restricting banks which have become  eroded mainly on account of reasons not connected with shipping  and navigation;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>" infrastructure" includes structures such as docks,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>wharves, jetties, landing stages, locks, buoys, inland ports,</p>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list7">
                <listIntroduction>cargo handling equipment, road and rail access and cargo storage  spaces, and the expression" infrastructural facilities" shall be  construed accordingly;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list7.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>" member" means a member of the Authority appointed under  sub- section (3) of section 3;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list7.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>" national waterway" means the inland waterway declared  by section 2 of the National Waterway (Allahabad- Haldia Stretch   of the Ganga- Bhagirathi- Hooghly River) Act, 1982 (49 of 1982),</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>to be a national waterway.</p>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10">
                <listIntroduction>Explanation.-- If Parliament declares by law any other  waterway to be a national waterway, then from the date on which  such declaration takes effect, such other waterway--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>shall be deemed also to be a national waterway  within the meaning of this clause; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>the provisions of this Act shall, with necessary  modifications (including modification for construing any  reference to the commencement of this Act as a reference to   the date aforesaid), apply to such national waterway;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>" navigable channel" means a channel navigable during the  whole or a part of the year;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list12">
                <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list12.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>" regulations" means regulations made by the Authority  under this Act; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list12.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>" rules" means rules made by the Central Government under  this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>INLAND WATERWAYS AUTHORITY OF INDIA</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>INLAND WATERWAYS AUTHORITY OF INDIA</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Constitution and incorporation of the Inland Waterways</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Authority of India.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>With effect from such date  as the Central</p>
              <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint in  this behalf, there shall be constituted for the purposes of this Act  an Authority, to be called the Inland Waterways Authority of India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Authority shall be a body corporate by the name  aforesaid, having perpetual succession and a common seal with power,</p>
              <p>subject to the provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of  property, both movable and immovable, and to contract and shall by the  said name sue and be sued.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Authority shall consist of the following members,</p>
              <blockList id="section-3.3.list2">
                <listIntroduction>namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.3.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>a Chairman;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.3.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>a Vice- Chairman; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.3.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>such number of persons, not exceeding five, to be  appointed by the Central Government.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Authority may associate with itself, in such manner and  for such purposes as may be determined by regulations, any person  whose assistance or advice it may desire in complying with any of the  provisions of this Act and a person so associated shall have the right  to take part</p>
              <p>in the discussions of the Authority relevant to the purpose for which  he has been associated, but shall not be entitled to vote.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Conditions of service of members. The term of office and other  conditions of service of the members shall be such as may be  prescribed.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Powers of Chairman and Vice- Chairman.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chairman of the</p>
              <p>Authority shall, in addition to presiding over the meetings of the</p>
              <p>Authority, exercise and discharge such powers and duties of the</p>
              <p>Authority as may be delegated to him by the Authority and such other  powers and duties as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Vice- Chairman of the Authority shall exercise and  discharge such of the powers and duties of the Chairman as may be  prescribed or as may be delegated to him by the Authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Removal, etc., of members.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-6.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Central Government may  remove from the Authority any member who, in its opinion,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>refuses to act,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>has become incapable to act,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>has so abused his office as to render his continuance in  office detrimental to the public interest, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>is otherwise unsuitable to continue as a member.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may suspend any member pending an  inquiry against him.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No order of removal under this section shall be made unless  the member concerned has been given an opportunity to submit his  explanation to the Central Government and when such order is passed,</p>
              <p>the seat of the member removed shall be declared vacant.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A member who has been removed under this section shall not be  eligible for re- appointment as a member or in any capacity under the</p>
              <p>Authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Vacancy, etc., not to invalidate proceedings of the Authority.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>No act or proceeding of the Authority shall be invalidated merely by  reason of--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>any vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution of,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>the Authority; or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>any defect in the appointment of a person acting as a  member of the Authority; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>any irregularity in the procedure of the Authority not  affecting the merits of the case.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Secretary and other officers.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Authority may appoint  the Secretary and such other officers and employees as it considers  necessary for the efficient discharge of its functions under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The terms and conditions of service of the Secretary and  other officers and employees of the Authority shall be such as may be  determined by regulations.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Advisory Committees.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to any rules made in this  behalf, the Authority may from time to time constitute such Advisory</p>
              <p>Committees as may be necessary for the efficient discharge of its  functions.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every Advisory Committee shall consist of such number of  persons connected with shipping and navigation and allied aspects as  the Authority may deem fit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Authority to act on business principles. In the discharge of  its functions under this Act, the Authority shall act, so far as may  be, on business principles.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>PROPERTY AND CONTRACTS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PROPERTY AND CONTRACTS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Transfer of assets and liabilities of the Central Government  to the Authority.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-11.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>As from such day  as the Central Government  may, appoint by notification in the official Gazette,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>all properties and other assets vested in the Central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Government for the purposes of Inland Water Transport</p>
              <p>Directorate, and administered by the Chief Engineer- cum-</p>
              <blockList id="section-11.1.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Administrator, Inland Water Transport Directorate, immediately  before such day shall vest in the Authority;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.1.list5.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>all debts, obligations and liabilities incurred, all  contracts entered into and all matters and things engaged to be  done by, with, or for the Central Government immediately before  such day for or in connection with the purposes of Inland Water</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Transport Directorate shall be deemed to have been incurred;</p>
              <p>entered into and engaged to be done by, with, or for the</p>
              <blockList id="section-11.1.list9">
                <listIntroduction>Authority;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.1.list9.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>all non- recurring expenditure incurred by the Central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Government for or in connection with the purposes of Inland Water</p>
              <p>Transport Directorate up to such day and declared to be capital  expenditure by the Central Government shall, subject to such  terms and conditions as may be determined by the Central</p>
              <p>Government, be treated as capital provided by the Central</p>
              <blockList id="section-11.1.list14">
                <listIntroduction>Government to the Authority;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.1.list14.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>all sums of money due to the Central Government in  relation to Inland Water Transport Directorate immediately before  such day shall be deemed to be due to the Authority;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.1.list14.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>all suits and other legal proceedings with respect to  any matter in relation to Inland Water Transport Directorate  which having been instituted by or against the Central Government  are pending, or which could have been so instituted, immediately  before such date shall on and after such date be continued or  instituted by or against the Authority; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.1.list14.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>every employee holding any office under the Central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Government immediately before such day solely or mainly for or in  connection with such affairs of Inland Water Transport</p>
              <p>Directorate as are relevant to the functions of the Authority  under this</p>
              <p>Act shall be treated as on deputation with the Authority but  shall hold his office in the Authority by the same tenure and  upon the same terms and conditions of service as respects  remuneration, leave, provident fund, retirement or other terminal  benefits as he would have held such office, if the Authority had  not been constituted and shall continue to do so until the</p>
              <p>Central Government, either on its own motion or at the request of  the Authority, recalls such employee to its service or until the</p>
              <p>Authority, with the concurrence of the Central Government, duly  absorbs such employee in its regular service, whichever is  earlier:</p>
              <p>Provided that during the period of deputation of any such  employee with the Authority, the Authority shall pay to the</p>
              <p>Central Government in respect of every such employee, such  contribution towards his leave salary, pension and gratuity as  the Central Government may, by order, determine:</p>
              <p>Provided further that any such employee, who has, in respect  of the proposal of the Authority to absorb him in its regular  service, intimated within such time as may be specified in this  behalf by the Authority his intention of not becoming a regular  employee of the Authority, shall not be absorbed by the Authority  in its regular service.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any dispute or doubt arises as to which of the properties,</p>
              <p>rights or liabilities of the Central Government have been transferred  to the Authority or as to which of the employees serving under the</p>
              <p>Central Government are to be treated as on deputation with the</p>
              <p>Authority, under this section, such dispute or doubt shall be decided  by the Central Government in consultation with the Authority and the  decision of the Central Government thereon shall be final.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial Disputes</p>
              <p>Act, 1947 (14 of 1947) or in any other law for the time being in  force, the absorption of any employee by the Authority in its regular  service under this section shall not entitle such employee to any  compensation under that Act or other law and no such claim shall be  entertained by any court, tribunal or other authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Contracts by the Authority. Subject to the provisions of  section 13, the Authority shall be competent to enter into and perform  any contract necessary for the discharge of its functions under this</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Mode of executing contracts on behalf of the Authority.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-13.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every contract shall, on behalf of the Authority, be made by the</p>
              <p>Chairman or such other member or such officer of the Authority as may  be generally or specially empowered in this behalf by the Authority  and such contracts or class of contracts as may be specified in the  regulations shall be sealed with the common seal of the Authority:</p>
              <p>Provided that no contract exceeding such value or amount as the</p>
              <p>Central Government may, from time to time, by order, fix in this  behalf shall be made unless it has been previously approved by the</p>
              <p>Authority:</p>
              <p>Provided further that no contract for the acquisition or sale of  immovable property or for the lease of any such property for a term  exceeding thirty years and no other contract exceeding such value or</p>
              <p>amount as the Central Government may, from time to time, by order, fix  in this behalf shall be made unless it has been previously approved by  the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (1), the form and  manner in which any contract shall be made under this Act shall be  such as may be prescribed by regulations.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No contract which is not in accordance with the provisions of  this Act and the regulations shall be binding on the Authority.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>FUNCTIONS AND POWERS OF THE AUTHORITY</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>FUNCTIONS AND POWERS OF THE AUTHORITY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Functions of the Authority.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-14.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Authority may--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-14.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>carry out surveys and investigations for the  development, maintenance and better utilisation of the national  waterways and the appurtenant land for shipping and navigation  and prepare schemes in this behalf;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>provide or permit setting up of infrastructural  facilities for national waterways;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>carry out conservancy measures and training works and do  all other acts necessary for the safety and convenience of  shipping and navigation and improvement of the national  waterways;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>control activities such as throwing rubbish, dumping or  removal of material, in or from the bed of the national waterways  and appurtenant land, in so far as they may affect safe and  efficient, shipping and navigation, maintenance of navigable  channels, river training and conservancy measures;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.1.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>remove or alter any obstruction or impediment in the  national waterways and the appurtenant land which may impede the  safe navigation or endanger safety of infrastructural facilities  or conservancy measures where such obstruction or impediment has  been lawfully made or has become lawful by reason of long  continuance of such obstruction or impediment or otherwise, after  making compensation to person suffering damage by such removal or  alteration;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.1.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>provide for the regulation of navigation and traffic</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-14.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>(including the rule of the road) on national waterways;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-14.1.list3.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>regulate the construction or alteration of structures  on, across or under the national waterways;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.1.list3.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>disseminate navigational meteorological information  about national waterways;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.1.list3.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>ensure co- ordination of inland water transport on  national waterways with other modes of transport; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.1.list3.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>establish and maintain pilotage on national waterways.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-14.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Authority may also--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-14.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>advise the Central Government on matters relating to  inland water transport;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>study the transport requirement with a view to co-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-14.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>ordinating inland water transport with other modes of transport;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-14.2.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>carry out hydrographic surveys and publish river charts;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.2.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>assist, on such terms and conditions as may be mutually  agreed upon, any State Government in formulation and  implementation of scheme for inland water transport development;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.2.list3.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>develop consultancy services and provide such services,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>on such terms and conditions as may be mutually agreed upon, in</p>
              <blockList id="section-14.2.list6">
                <listIntroduction>India and abroad in relation to planning and development of  waterways for shipping and navigation or any facility thereat;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-14.2.list6.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>conduct research in matters relating to inland water  transport including development of craft design, mechanisation of  country crafts, technique of towage, landing and terminal  facilities, port installations and survey techniques;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.2.list6.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>lay down standards for classification of inland  waterways;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.2.list6.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>arrange programme of technical training for inland water  transport personnel within and outside the country; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.2.list6.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>perform such other functions as may be necessary to  carry out the provisions of this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any dispute arising out of or concerning the compensation  referred to in clause (e) of sub- section (1) shall be determined  according to the law relating to like disputes in the case of land  required for public purposes.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every scheme, prepared by the Authority to carry out  functions under sub- sections (1) and (2), involving capital  expenditure exceeding the amount as may be prescribed, shall be  submitted to the Central Government for approval.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may either approve the scheme  submitted to it under sub- section (4) without modification or with  such modifications as it may consider necessary or reject the scheme  with directions to the Authority to prepare a fresh scheme according  to such directions.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Amendment of schemes. The Authority shall not make any  material change in the scheme approved under sub- section (5) of  section 14 without the prior approval of the Central Government.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section," material change"</p>
              <p>means an increase in the cost of the scheme by more than twenty per  cent. of its cost or a change in the benefit and cost ratio which  either makes the cost component in the ratio exceeds the benefit or  reduces the benefit component by more than twenty per cent.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-V.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Levy and collection of fees and charges.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Authority  may, with the previous approval of the Central Government, levy fees  and charges at such rates as may be laid down by regulations made in  this behalf for services or benefits rendered in relation to the use  of the national waterways for the purposes of shipping, navigation,</p>
              <p>infrastructural facilities, including facilities for passengers and  facilities relating to the berthing of vessels, handling of cargoes  and storage of cargoes.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The fees and charges levied under sub- section (1) shall be  collected in such manner as may be determined by regulations.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Grants and loans by the Central Government. The Central</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in  this behalf, make to the Authority grants and loans of such sums of  money as that Government may consider necessary.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Constitution of the Fund.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-19.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>There shall be constituted a</p>
              <blockList id="section-19.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Fund to be called the Inland Waterways Authority of India Fund and  there shall be credited thereto--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-19.1.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>any grants and loans made to the Authority by the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-19.1.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Central Government under section 18;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-19.1.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>all fees and charges received by the Authority under  this Act; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.1.list4.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>all sums received by the Authority from such other  sources as may be decided upon by the Central Government.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-19.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Fund shall be applied for meeting--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-19.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>salary, allowances and other remuneration of the  members, officers and other employees of the Authority;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Omitted by Act 8 of 1994, s. 2.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>expenses of the Authority in the discharge of its  functions under section 14; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>expenses on objects and for purposes authorised by this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Budget. The Authority shall prepare, in such form and at such  time each financial year as may be prescribed, its budget for the next  financial year, showing the estimated receipts and expenditure of the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Authority and forward the same to the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Investment of funds. The Authority may invest its funds</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>(including any reserve fund) in the securities of the Central</p>
              <p>Government or in such other manner as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Annual report. The Authority shall prepare, in such form and  at such time each financial year as may be prescribed, its annual  report, giving a full account of its activities during the previous  financial year, and submit a copy thereof to the Central Government.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Accounts and audit. The accounts of the Authority shall be  maintained and audited in such manner as may, in consultation with the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Comptroller and Auditor- General of India, be prescribed and the</p>
              <p>Authority shall furnish, to the Central Government, before such date  as may be prescribed, its audited copy of accounts together with the  auditors' report thereon.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Annual report and auditors' report to be laid before</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Parliament. The Central Government shall cause the annual report and  auditors' report to be laid, as soon as may be after they are  received, before each House of Parliament.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VI">
        <num>VI</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-VI.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Power of Central Government to issue directions.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-25.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Without  prejudice to the foregoing provisions of this Act, the Authority  shall, in the discharge of its functions and duties under this Act, be  bound by such directions on questions of policy as the Central</p>
              <p>Government may give in writing to it from time to time:</p>
              <p>Provided that the Authority shall, as far as practicable, be  given opportunity to express its views before any direction is given  under this sub- section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The decision of the Central Government whether a question is  one of policy or not shall be final.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Compulsory acquisition of land for the Authority. Any land  required by the Authority for discharging its functions under this Act  shall be deemed to be needed for a public purpose and such land may be  acquired for the Authority under the provisions of the Land</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Acquisition Act, 1894 (1 of 1894.) or of any other corresponding law  for the time being in force.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Application, etc., of certain laws.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-27.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of  this Act shall be in addition to the provisions of the Indian Ports</p>
              <p>Act, 1908 (15 of 1908) and the Major Port Trusts Act, 1963 (38 of</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1963">
          <num>1963.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1963.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>) and in particular nothing in this Act shall affect any  jurisdiction, functions, powers or duties required to be exercised,</p>
              <blockList id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>performed or discharged by--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the conservator of any port or by any officer or  authority under the Indian Ports Act, 1908 (15 of 1908) or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the Board of Trustees for any major port or by any  officer or authority under the Major Port Trusts Act, 1963 (38 of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1963">
          <num>1963.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1963.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>) in or in relation to any portion of an inland waterway</p>
              <p>(including the national waterway) falling within the limits of  such port or major port.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-1963.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in this Act shall affect the operation of the Inland</p>
              <p>Vessels Act, 1917 (1 of 1917) or any other Central Act other than  the Indian Ports Act, 1908 (15 of 1908) and the Major Port Trusts</p>
              <p>Act, 1963 (38 of 1963) or any State or provincial Act in force  immediately before the commencement of this Act with respect to  shipping and navigation on any national waterway .</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Power to enter. Subject to any rules made in this behalf, any  person, generally or specially authorised by the Authority in this  behalf, may, whenever it in necessary so to do for any of the purposes  of this Act, at all reasonable times, enter upon any land or premises  and--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-28.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-28.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>make any inspection, survey, measurement, valuation or  inquiry;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>take levels;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>dig or bore into sub- soil;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>set out boundaries and intended lines of work;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.paragraph-0.list0.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>mark such level boundaries and lines by placing marks  and cutting trenches; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.paragraph-0.list0.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>do such other acts or things as may be prescribed:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that no such person shall enter any building or any  enclosed court or garden attached to a dwelling- house (unless with the   consent of the occupier thereof) without previously giving such  occupier at least twenty- four hours' notice in writing of his  intention to do so.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Delegation. The Authority may, by general or special order in  writing, delegate to the Chairman or any other member or to any  officer of the Authority, subject to such conditions and limitations,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-29.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>if any, as may be specified in the order such of its powers and  functions under this Act (except the powers under section 35) as it  may deem necessary.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Certain words omitted by Act 8 of 1994, s. 3.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Authentication of orders and other instruments of the Authority.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading>Authentication of orders and other instruments of the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-30.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Authority. All orders and decisions of the Authority shall be  authenticated by the signature of the Chairman or any other member  authorised by the Authority in this behalf and all other instruments  executed by the Authority shall be authenticated by the signature of  an officer of the Authority authorised by the Authority in this  behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading>Members, officers and employees of the Authority to be public  servants. All members, officers and other employees of the Authority  shall be deemed, when acting or purporting to act in pursuance of any  of the provisions of this Act, to be public servants within the  meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-32.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No suit,</p>
              <p>prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against the</p>
              <p>Government or any officer of the Government or any member, officer or  employee of the Authority for anything which is in good faith done or  intended to be done under this Act or the rules or regulations made  thereunder.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No suit or other legal proceedings shall lie against the</p>
              <p>Authority for any damage caused or likely to be caused by anything in  good faith done or purported to be done under this Act or the rules or  regulations, and in particular, it shall not be the responsibility of  the Authority to provide for relief measures necessitated by floods or  by breaches and failures of works.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading>Power of Central Government to supersede the Authority.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-33.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-33.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>If, at any time, the Central Government is of opinion--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-33.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>that on account of a grave emergency, the Authority is  unable to discharge the functions and duties imposed on it by or  under the provisions of this Act; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-33.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>that the Authority has persistently made default in  complying with any direction issued by the Central Government  under this Act or in the discharge of the functions and duties  imposed on it by or under the provisions of this Act and as a  result of which default the financial position of the Authority  or the administration of any national waterway has deteriorated;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-33.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-33.1.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>that circumstances exist which render it necessary in  the public interest so to do, the Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, supersede the Authority for  such period, not exceeding six months, as may be specified in the  notification:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that before issuing a notification under this sub-</p>
              <p>section for the reasons mentioned in clause (b), the Central</p>
              <p>Government shall give a reasonable opportunity to the Authority to  show cause why it should not be superseded and shall consider the  explanations and objection, if any, of the Authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-33.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Upon the publication of a notification under sub- section (1)</p>
              <blockList id="section-33.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>superseding the Authority,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-33.2.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>all the members shall, as from the date of supersession,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-33.2.list4">
                <listIntroduction>vacate their offices as such;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-33.2.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>all the powers, functions and duties which may, by or  under the provisions of this Act, be exercised or discharged by  or on behalf of the Authority, shall, until the Authority is  reconstituted under sub- section (3), be exercised and discharged  by such person or persons as the Central Government may direct;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-33.2.list4.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>all property owned or controlled by the Authority shall,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>until the Authority is reconstituted under sub- section (3), vest  in the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-33.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-33.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>On the expiration of the period of supersession specified in  the notification issued under sub- section (1), the Central Government  may--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-33.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>extend the period of supersession for such further term,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-33.3.list3">
                <listIntroduction>not exceeding six months, as it may consider necessary; or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-33.3.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>reconstitute the Authority by fresh appointment and in  such case any persons who vacated their offices under clause (a)</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>of sub- section (2) shall not be deemed disqualified for  appointment:</p>
              <p>Provided that the Central Government may, at any time before the  expiration of the period of supersession, whether as originally  specified under sub- section (1) or as extended under this sub- section,</p>
              <p>take action under clause (b) of this sub- section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-33.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government shall cause a notification issued  under sub- section (1) and a full report of any action taken under this  section and the circumstances leading to such action to be laid before  such House of Parliament at the earliest opportunity.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-34">
          <num>34.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-34.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the  purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-34.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power,</p>
              <p>such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters,</p>
              <blockList id="section-34.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-34.2.list3.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the term of office and other conditions of service of  the members of the Authority under section 4;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-34.2.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the powers and duties of the Chairman and Vice- Chairman  under section 5;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-34.2.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the matters with respect to the Advisory Committee  referred to in sub- section (1) of section 9;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-34.2.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the amount required to be prescribed under sub- section</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-34.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-34.4.list1">
                <listIntroduction>of section 14;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-34.4.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the form in which, and the time at which, the Authority  shall prepare its budget under section 20 and its annual report  under section 22;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-34.4.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which the Authority may invest its funds  under section 21;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-34.4.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which the accounts of the Authority shall  be maintained and audited under section 23;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-34.4.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>the conditions and restrictions with respect to exercise  of the power to enter under section 28 and the matters referred  to in clause (f) of that section; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-34.4.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>any other matter which is to be, or may be, prescribed  or in respect of which provision is to be, or may be, made by  rules.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading>Power to make regulations.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-35.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Authority may, with the  previous approval of the Central Government, by notification in the</p>
              <p>Official Gazette, make regulations consistent with this Act and the  rules generally to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-35.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-35.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such regulations may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-35.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which and the purposes for which, the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Authority may associate with itself any person under sub- section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-35.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-35.4.list1">
                <listIntroduction>of section 3;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-35.4.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the terms and conditions of service of the Secretary and  other officers and employees of the Authority under sub- section</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-35.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-35.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>of section 8;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-35.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the contracts or class of contracts which are to be  sealed with the common seal of the Authority and the form and  manner in which a contract may be made by the Authority;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-35.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which, and the conditions subject to  which, any functions in relation to the matters referred to in  sub- sections (1) and (2) of section 14 may be performed;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-35.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the rule of the road on a national waterway;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-35.2.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the safe, efficient and convenient use, management and  control of the infrastructures and infrastructural facilities;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-35.2.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the reception, porterage, storage and removal of goods  brought on a national waterway, and the procedure to be followed  for taking charge of goods which may have been damaged before  landing, or may be alleged to have been so damaged;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-35.2.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>regulating, declaring and defining the docks, wharfs,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-35.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>jetties, landing stages on which goods shall be landed from  vessels and shipped on board vessels;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-35.2.list3.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>regulating the manner in which and the conditions under  which the loading and unloading of vessels on a national waterway  shall be carried out; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-35.2.list3.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>the exclusion from a national waterway of disorderly or  other undesirable persons and of trespassers.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-35.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any regulation made under any of the clauses (c) to (j) of  sub- section (2) may provide that a contravention thereof shall be  punishable with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees and in  the case of a continuing contravention with an additional fine which  may extend to twenty rupees for every day during which such  contravention continues after conviction for the first such  contravention.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-36">
          <num>36.</num>
          <heading>Rules and regulations to be laid before Parliament. Every  rule and every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon  as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it  is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be  comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and  if, before the expiry of the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or  regulation or both House agree that the rule or regulation should not  be made, the rule or regulation shall thereafter have effect only in  such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-36.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without  prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule  or regulation.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-37">
          <num>37.</num>
          <heading>Power to remove difficulties.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-37.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any difficulty arises in  giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government  may, by order, published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions  not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act as may appear to be  necessary for removing the difficulty:</p>
              <p>Provided that no order shall be made under this section after the  expiry of five years from the commencement of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-37.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every order made under this section shall be laid, as soon as  may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-38">
          <num>38.</num>
          <heading>Amendment of Act 49 of 1982. In the National Waterway</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-38.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>(Allahabad- Haldia Stretch of the Ganga- Bhagirathi- Hooghly River) Act,</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1982">
          <num>1982.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1982.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1982.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1982.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>in section 3, for the words" Central Government", the  word" Union" shall be substituted, and for the words" to the  extent hereinafter provided", the words and figures" to the  extent provided in the Inland Waterways Authority of India Act,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1985">
          <num>1985.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1985.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1985.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>" shall be substituted;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1985.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>sections 4 to 15 shall be omitted.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
