<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1950/30/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1950/30"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Union Territories (Laws) Act, 1950"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1950/30/eng@1950-04-15/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1950/30/eng@1950-04-15"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1950-04-15" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1950/30/eng@1950-04-15/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1950/30/eng@1950-04-15"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Union Territories (Laws) Act, 1950</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 30 OF 1950</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 15th April, 1950.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the extension of laws to certain  Union  territories].</p>
      </longTitle>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament as follows:--</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Union territories] (Laws) Act, 1950.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on the 16th day of April, 1950.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Power to extend enactments to certain Union territories. The</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette,</p>
            <p>extend to  the Union territory of Delhi, Himachal Pradesh, Manipur  or Tripura or to any part of such territory], with such restrictions  and modifications as it thinks fit, any enactment which is in force in  a  State] at the date of the notification; .</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Extension of laws to Tripura, Vindhya Pradesh, and Manipur.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Acts and Ordinances specified in the Schedule to the Merged</p>
            <p>States (Laws) Act, 1949 (59 of 1949.), are hereby extended to, and  shall be in force in, the States of Tripura and Vindhya Pradesh, as  they are generally in force in the territories to which they extend  immediately before the commencement of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions contained in sub- section (2A),</p>
            <p>the Acts and Ordinances referred to in sub- section (1)], are hereby  extended to, and shall be in force in, the State of Manipur as they  are generally in force in the territories to which they extend  immediately before the commencement of this Act:</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860), in its  application to the State of Manipur shall have effect as if--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in section 361, for the word" eighteen" the word</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list5">
              <listIntroduction>" fifteen" had been substituted, and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list5.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in section 375, for the word" sixteen" in clause Fifthly  the word" fourteen" had been substituted, and for the  word" fifteen" in the Exception the word" thirteen" had  been substituted.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2A">
          <num>(2A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Acts specified in Part A of the Schedule to this Act  shall not extend to the State of Manipur, and the Acts specified in</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <part id="part-B">
        <num>B</num>
        <heading>thereof shall extend to, and be in force in, that State only as  from the date of commencement of the Union Territories (Laws)</heading>
        <paragraph id="part-B.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Amendment Act, 1956 (68 of 1956), and shall, with effect from that  date, be amended in the manner and to the extent specified in the said</p>
            <p>Part.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="part-B.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of facilitating the application in the said</p>
            <p>States of any such Act or Ordinance as aforesaid, any Court or other  authority may construe the Act or Ordinance with such alterations not  affecting the substance as may be necessary or proper to adapt it to  the matter before the Court or other authority.</p>
            <p>Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section and section 4,</p>
            <p>any reference to the State of Manipur or Tripura in relation to any  period after the 31st October, 1956, shall be construed as a reference  to the Union territory of Manipur or Tripura as the case may be.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Repeals and savings. Section 7 of the Delhi Laws Act, 1912 (13   of 1912.), the Ajmer- Merwara (Extension of Laws) Act, 1947 (52 of</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1947">
          <num>1947.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1947.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>), and any law which immediately  before the coming into force  of any Act or Ordinance extended by this Act to any of the States of</p>
              <p>Manipur, Tripura and Vindhya Pradesh is in force in that State and  corresponds to the Act or Ordinance as so extended], are hereby  repealed:</p>
              <blockList id="section-1947.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that the repeal shall not affect--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1947.paragraph-0.list3.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the previous operation of any such law, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1947.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>any penalty, forfeiture or punishment incurred in  respect of any offence committed against any such law,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1947.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1947.paragraph-0.list5.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>any investigation, legal proceeding or remedy in respect  of any such penalty, forfeiture or punishment,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>and any such investigation, legal proceeding or remedy may be  instituted, continued or enforced, and any such penalty, forfeiture or  punishment may be imposed, as if this Act had not been passed:</p>
              <p>Provided further that, subject to the preceding proviso, anything  done or any action taken, including any appointment or delegation  made, notification, order, instruction or direction issued, rule,</p>
              <p>regulation, form, bye- law or scheme framed, certificate, patent,</p>
              <p>permit or licence granted or registration effected, under such law  shall be deemed to have been done or taken under section 2 or, as the  case may be, under the corresponding provision of the Act or Ordinance    as extended] to the State by section 3, and shall continue in force  accordingly, unless and until superseded by anything done or any  action taken under the said section 2 or, as the case may be, under  the said Act or Ordinance.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
