<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1993/69/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1993/69"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Public Records Act, 1993"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1993/69/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1993/69/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1993/69/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1993/69/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Public Records Act, 1993</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Public Records Act, 1993.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“Board” means the Archival Advisory Board constituted under sub-section (1) of section 13;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“Director General” means the Director General of Archives appointed by the Central Government and includes any officer authorised by that Government to perform the duties of the Director General;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“head of the Archives” means a person holding the charge of the Archives of the Union territory Administration;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>“public records” includes—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>any document, manuscript and file;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>any microfilm microfiche and facsimile copy of a document;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>any reproduction of image or images embodied in such microfilm (whether enlarged or not); and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e.list0.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>any other material produced by a computer or by any other device.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>of any records creating agency;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.f.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>records creating agency includes,—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.f.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>in relation to the Central Government, any ministry, department or office of that Government;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.f.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>in relation to any statutory body or corporation wholly or substantially controlled or financed by the Central Government or commission or any committee constituted by that Government, the offices of the said body, corporation, commission or committee;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.f.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>in relation to a Union territory Administration, any department or office of that Administration;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.f.list0.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>in relation to any statutory body or corporation wholly or substantially controlled or financed by Union territory Administration or commission or any committee constituted by that Administration, the offices of the said body, corporation commission or committee;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>“record officer” means the officer nominated by the records creating agency under sub-section (1) of section 5.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Power of the Central Government to co-ordinate, regulate and supervise operations connected with administration, management etc. of public records.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government shall have the power to coordinate, regulate and supervise the operations connected with the administration, management, preservation selection, disposal and retirement of public records under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government in relation to the public records of the records creating agencies specified in sub-clauses (i) and (ii) of clause (f) of section 2 and the Union territory Administration in relation to the public records of the records creating agencies specified in sub-clauses (iii) and (iv) of the said clause, may, by order, authorise the Director General or the head of the Archives, as the case may be, subject to such conditions as may be specified in the order, to carry out all or any of the following functions, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>supervision, management and control of the Archives;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>acceptance for deposit of public records of permanent nature after such period as may be proscribed;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>custody, use and withdrawal of public records;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>arrangement, preservation and exhibition of public records;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>preparation of inventories, indices catalogues and other reference media of public records;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>analysing, developing, promoting and coordinating the standards, procedures and the techniques for improvement of the records management system;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>ensuring the maintenance, arrangement and security of public records in the Archives and in the offices of the records creating agency;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>promoting utilisation of available space and maintenance of equipments for preserving public records;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>tendering advice to records creating agencies on the compilation, classification and disposal of records and application of standards, procedures and techniques of records management;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>survey and inspection of public records;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>organising training programmes in various disciplines of Archives administration and records management;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>accepting records from any private source;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>regulating access to public records;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>receiving records from defunct bodies and making arrangement for securing public records in the event of national emergency;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>receiving reports on records management and disposal practices from the records officer;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.p">
                <num>(p)</num>
                <p>providing authenticated copies of, or extracts from, public records;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.q">
                <num>(q)</num>
                <p>destroying or disposal of public records;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.r">
                <num>(r)</num>
                <p>obtaining on lease or purchasing or accepting as gift any document of historical or national importance.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition against taking of public records out of India.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No person shall take or cause to be taken out of India any public records without the prior approval of the Central Government:</p>
            <p>Provided that no such prior approval shall be required if any public records are taken or sent out of India for any official purpose.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Records officer.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every records creating agency shall nominate one of its officers as records officer to discharge the functions under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every records creating agency may set up such number of record rooms in such places as it deems fit and shall place each record room under the charge of a records officer.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Responsibilities of records officer.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The records officer shall be responsible for—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>proper arrangement, maintenance and preservation of public records under his charge;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>periodical review of all public records and weeding out public records of euphemeral value;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>appraisal of public records which are more than twenty-five years old in consultation with the National Archives of India or, as the case may be, the Archives of the Union territory with a view to retaining public records of permanent value;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>destruction of public records in such manner and subject to such conditions as may be prescribed under sub-section (1) of section 8;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>compilation of a schedule of retention for public records in constitution with the National Archives of India or, as the case may be, the Archives of the Union territory;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>periodical review for downgrading of classified public records in such manner as may be prescribed;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>adoption of such standards, procedures and techniques as may be recommended from time to time by the National Archives of India for improvement of record management system and maintenance of security of public records;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>compilation of annual indices of public records;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>compilation of organisational history and annual supplement thereto;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>assisting the National Archives of India or, as the case may be, the Archives of the Union territory for public records management;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>submission of annual report to the Director General or, as the case may be, head of the Archives in such manner as may be prescribed;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list1.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>transferring of records of any defunct body to the National Archives of India or the Archives of the Union territory, as the case may be, for preservation.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The records officer shall act under the direction of the Director General or, as the case may be, head of the Archives while discharging the responsibilities specified in sub-section (1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Records officer to take appropriate action in the event of unauthorised removal, destruction, etc., of public records in his custody.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The records officer shall, in the event of any unauthorised removal destruction, defacement or alteration of any public records under his charge, forthwith take appropriate action for the recovery or restoration of such public records.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The records officer shall submit a report in writing to the Director General or, as the case may be, the head of the Archives without any delay on any information about any unauthorised removal, destruction, defacement or alteration of any public records under his charge and about the action initiated by him and shall take action as he may deem necessary subject to the directions, if any, given by the Director General or, as the case may be, head of the Archives.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The records officer may seek assistance from any government officer or any other person for the purpose of recovery or restoration of public records and such officer or person shall render all assistance to the records officer.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Destruction or disposal of public records.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Save as otherwise provided in any law for the time being in force, no public record shall be destroyed or otherwise disposed of except in such manner and subject to such conditions as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No record created before the year 1892 shall be destroyed except where in the opinion of the Director General or, as the case may be, the head of the Archives, it is so defaced or is in such condition that it cannot be put to any archival use.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for contraventions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever contravenes any of the provisions of section 4 or section 8 shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years or with fine which may extend to ten thousand rupees or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Public records bearing security classification.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No public records bearing security classification shall be transferred to the National Archives of India or the Archives of the Union territory.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Receipt of records from private sources.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The National Archives of India or the Archives of the Union territory may accept any record of historical or national importance from any private source by way of gift, purchase or otherwise.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The National Archives of India or, as the case may be, the Archives of any Union territory may, in such manner and subject to such conditions as may be prescribed, make any record referred to in sub-section (1) available to any bona fide research scholar.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Access to public records.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All unclassified public records as are more than thirty years old and are transferred to the National Archives of India or the Archives of the Union territory may be, subject to such exceptions and restrictions as may be prescribed made available to any bona fide research scholar.</p>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <p>For the purposes of this sub-section, the period of thirty years shall be reckoned from the year of the opening of the public record.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any records creating agency may grant to any person access to any public record in its custody in such manner and subject to such conditions as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Archival Advisory Board.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute an Archival Advisory Board for the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Board shall consists of the following members, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>Secretary to the Government of India in the Ministry</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Chairman, ex officio;</p>
            <blockList id="section-13.2.list4">
              <listIntroduction>of Central Government dealing with culture</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.2.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>one officer not below the rank of Joint Secretary</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Members, ex officio;</p>
            <p>the Government of India, each from the Cabinet</p>
            <blockList id="section-13.2.list8">
              <listIntroduction>Secretariat Ministry of Home Affairs, Ministry of Defence, Ministry of External Affairs, Ministry of Finance and Ministry of Personnel, Public Grievances and Pension.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.2.list8.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>two representatives not below the rank of Joint</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Members;</p>
            <blockList id="section-13.2.list11">
              <listIntroduction>Secretary in the Union territory Administrations to be nominated by the Central Government.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.2.list11.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>three persons to be nominated by the Central</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Members;</p>
            <blockList id="section-13.2.list14">
              <listIntroduction>Government for a period not exceeding three years, one being an Archivist and two being Professors in the Postgraduate Department of History in any recognised University.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.2.list14.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>Director General</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Secretary</p>
            <p>Member-, ex Officio.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The members nominated under clause (d) of sub-section (2) shall be paid such allowances as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Functions of the Board.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Board shall perform the following functions, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>advise the Central Government and Union territory Administrations on matters concerning the administration, management, conservation and use of public records;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>lay down guidelines for training of Archivists;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>give directions for acquisition of records from private custody;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>deal with such other matters as may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Power of the Director General to lay down norms and standards for courses in archival science.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Director General shall have the power to lay down norms and standards for courses curricula, assessment and examinations relating to the training in archival science and other ancillary subjects.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against any person in respect of anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or the rules made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-17.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the period after which public records of permanent nature may be accepted under clause (b) of sub-section (2) of section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the manner in which and the conditions subject to which public records can be destroyed under clause (d) of sub-section (1) of section 6;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the manner in which periodical review of classified public records for downgrading shall be undertaken under clause (f) of sub-section (1) of section 6;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the manner in which the records officer will report to the Director General or the head of the Archives under clause (k) of sub-section (1) of section 6;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the manner in which and the conditions subject to which public records may be destroyed or disposed of under sub-section (1) of section 8;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the manner in which and the conditions subject to which records of historical or national importance may be made available to research scholar under sub-section (2) of section 11;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>exceptions and restrictions subject to which public records may be made available to a research scholar under sub-section (1) of section 12;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the manner in which and the conditions subject to which any records creating agency may grant to any person access to public records in its custody under sub-section (2) of section 12;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the allowances payable to members of the Board under sub-section (3) of section 13;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>the matters with respect to which the Board may perform its functions under clause (d) of section 14;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>any other matter which is required to be, or may be, prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Laying of rules before Parliament.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
