<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kl/act/1962/6/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kl/act/1962/6"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Kerala Relief Undertakings (Special Provisions) Act, 1961"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kl/act/1962/6/eng@2017-03-23/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kl/act/1962/6/eng@2017-03-23"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-23" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-kl/act/1962/6/eng@2017-03-23/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-kl/act/1962/6/eng@2017-03-23"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-03-23" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Kerala Relief Undertakings (Special Provisions) Act, 1961</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>ACT 6 OF 1962</p>
        <p>An Act to make temporary provisions for industrial relation and other matters to enable the Government to conduct, or provide loan, guarantee or financial assistance for the conduct of, certain industrial undertakings as a measure of preventing unemployment or of unemployment relief.</p>
        <p>Preamble.-</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to make temporary provisions for industrial relations and other matters to enable the Government to conduct, or provide loan, guarantee or financial assistance for the conduct of, certain industrial undertakings as a measure of preventing unemployment or of unemployment relief;</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>BE it enacted in the Twelfth Year of the Republic of India as follows:-</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Kerala Relief Undertakings (Special Provisions) Act, 1961.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Kerala.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Government may, by notification in the Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“Industry” means any business, trade, udertaking, manufacture or calling of employers and includes any plantation and any calling, service, employment, handicraft or industrial occupation or avocation of workmen and the word “industrial” shall be construed accordingly;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“Relief undertaking” means an industrial undertaking in respect of which a declaration under section 3 is in force.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Declaration of relief undertaking.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If at any time, it appears to the Government necessary to do so, the Government may, by notification in the Gazette, declare that an industrial undertaking specified in the notification, whether started, acquired or otherwise taken over by the Government, and carried on or proposed to be carried on by themselves or under their authority, or to which any loan, guarantee or other financial assistance has been provided by the Government, shall, with effect from the date specified for the purpose in the notification be conducted to serve as a measure of preventing unemployment or of unemployment relief and the undertaking shall accordingly be deemed to be a relief undertaking for purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A notification under sub-section (1) shall have effect for such period not exceeding two years as may be specified in the notification; but it shall be renewable by like notifications from time to time for further periods not exceeding twelve months at a time, so however that all the periods in the aggregate do not exceeded ten years</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Power to prescribe industrial relations and other facilities temporarily for relief undertaking.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding any law, usage, custom, contract, instrument, decree, order, award, submission, settlement, standing order or other provision whatsoever, the Government may, by notification in the Gazette, direct that-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>in relation to any relief undertaking and in respect of the period of which the relief undertaking continues as such under sub-section (2) of section 3—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>all the provisions of the laws specified in the Schedule to this Act, which involve any financial commitment or expenditure shall not apply (and such relief undertaking shall be exempt therefrom), or all or any of such provisions shall, if so directed by the Government, be applied with such modifications (which do not however affect the policy of the said laws) as may be specified in the notification;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>all or any of the agreements, settlements, or awards made under any of the laws specified in the Schedule to this Act, which may be applicable to the undertaking immediately before it was acquired or taken over by the Government, or before any loan, guarantee, or other financial assistance was provided to it by or with the approval of the Government for being run as a relief undertaking, shall be suspended in operation, or shall, if so directed by the Government, be applied with such modifications as may be specified in the notification;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.aa">
                    <num>(aa)</num>
                    <p>during the period in which the relief undertaking continues as such under sub-section (2) of section 3, any liability of the undertaking to pay tax under the Kerala General Sales Tax Act, 1963 (15 of 1963), incurred before the undertaking was declared a relief undertaking and any remedy for enforcing the payment thereof shall be suspended and all proceedings relating to the levy, assessment, collection and recovery of such tax pending before any court, tribunal, officer or authority shall be stayed;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>during the period in which the relief undertaking continues as such under sub¬section (2) of section 3 any liability or obligation of the undertaking accrued or incurred before the undertaking was declared a relief undertaking and any remedy for the enforcement thereof shall be suspended and all proceedings relative thereto pending before any court, Tribunal, Officer or authority shall be stayed;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that the provisions in this clause shall not apply to the liabilities or obligations accrued or incurred in favour of the national financial institutions and banks and to any remedy for the enforcement thereof.</p>
            <p>Explantion.-</p>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list5">
              <listIntroduction>For the purposes of this clause,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list5.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>“national financial institution’ means any financial institution with jurisdiction all over India, set up by enacting Special Acts in the Parliament with the objective of providing financial assistance to the industrial units.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list5.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>“bank” means a banking company as defined in clause (c) of section 5 of the banking Regulation Act, 1949 (Central Act 10 of 1949);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list5.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the right, privilege, obligation or liability referred to in clause (aa) or clause (b)] shall, on the notification ceasing to have force, revive and be enforceable and the proceedings referred to therein shall be continued.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that in computing the period of limitation for the enforcement of such right, privilege, obligation or liability, the period during which it was suspended under clause (aa) or clause (b) shall be excluded notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Utilisation of profits.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Such percentage of the profits, if any, made by the Government, as may be prescribed, in carrying on any relief undertaking shall be utilized for the benefit of the persons employed in the undertaking in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action under the Act.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit or other legal proceedings shall lie against the Government for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Government may, by notification in the Gazette, make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the rates of wages payable to the workmen and their work loads and the salary payable to the staff, the payment of bonus, gratuity compensation, etc.;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the manner in which the relief undertaking should be run on behalf of the Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the strength of staff and labour to be employed for running the relief undertaking economically;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the manner in which the net profits or net losses or surplus funds should be appropriated or disposed of; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the percentage of profits to be utilized for the benefit of the persons employed in the undertaking and the manner of its utilization.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All rule made under this section shall, as soon as possible after they are made, be laid before the Legislative Assembly for a period of not less than fourteen days and shall be subject to such modifications as the Legislative Assembly may make during the session in which they are so laid or the session immediately following.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-theschedule">
      <doc name="theschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kl/act/1962/6/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kl/act/1962/6"/>
              <FRBRalias value="THE SCHEDULE"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kl/act/1962/6/eng@2017-03-23/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kl/act/1962/6/eng@2017-03-23"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-kl/act/1962/6/eng@2017-03-23/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-kl/act/1962/6/eng@2017-03-23"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-03-23" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="theschedule">
            <paragraph id="theschedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>Central Acts</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <subsection id="theschedule.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Industrial Disputes Act, 1947.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Minimum Wages Act, 1948,</p>
                <p>State Acts</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.1">
              <num>(1)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Travancore-Cochin Shops and Establishments Act, 1125.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="theschedule.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Madras Shops and Establishments Act, 1947.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
