<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1851/8/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1851/8"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Indian Tolls Act, 1851"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1851/8/eng@1851-07-04/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1851/8/eng@1851-07-04"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1851-07-04" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1851/8/eng@1851-07-04/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1851/8/eng@1851-07-04"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Indian Tolls Act, 1851</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 8 OF 1851</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 4th July, 1851]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act for enabling Government to levy Tolls on Public Roads and</p>
        <p>Bridges.</p>
        <p>Preamble.-- WHEREAS it is expedient to enable Government to levy  tolls upon roads and bridges; It is enacted as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Repeal of Acts. Rep. by the Repealing Act, 1870 (14 of</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1870">
        <num>1870.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1870.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>), s. 1 and Sch, Pt. II.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1A">
        <num>1A.</num>
        <heading>Extent.-- This Act extends to the territories  administered on the fourth of July, eighteen hundred and fifty- one, by  the Governor of the Presidency of Fort William in Bengal, the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Lieutenant- Governor of North- Western Provinces of Bengal and the</p>
            <p>Governor of the Presidency of Fort St. George in Council.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Power to cause levy of tolls on roads and bridges within  certain rates, and to appoint collectors. Collectors'</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>responsibilities.--  The State Government may cause such rates  of toll,  as  it thinks fit], to be levied upon any road or  bridge which has been, or shall hereafter be, made or repaired 4</p>
            <p>at the expense of the Central or any State Government; and may  place the collection of such tolls under the management of such  persons as may appear to  it] proper: and all persons employed in  the management and collection of such tolls shall be liable to the  same responsibilities as would belong to them if employed in the  collection of the land revenue.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Their powers for recovery of toll.-- In case of non- payment of  any such toll on demand, the officers appointed to collect the same  may seize any of the carriages or animals on which it is chargeable,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>or any part of their burden of sufficient value to defray the toll;</p>
            <p>and, if any toll remains undischarged for twenty- four hours, with the  cost arising from such seizure, the case shall be brought before the  officer appointed to superintend the collection of the said toll, who  may sell the property seized for discharge of the toll, and all  expenses occasioned by such nonpayment, seizure and sale, and cause  any balance that may remain to be returned, on demand, to the owner of  the property; and the said officer, on receipt of the property, shall  forthwith issue a notice that, at noon of the next day, exclusive of</p>
            <p>Sunday, or any closed holiday, he will sell the property by auction:</p>
            <p>Release of seized property on tender of dues.-- Provided that, if,</p>
            <p>at any time before the sale has actually begun, the person whose  property, has been seized shall tender the amount of all the expenses  incurred, and of double the toll payable by him, the said officer  shall forthwith release the property seized.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Exemptions from payment of toll.-- No tolls shall be paid for  the passage  of Police- officers on duty, or of any person or  property in their custody, but no other exemption from payment of the  toll levied under this Act shall be allowed.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Assistance of collectors by Police- officers.-- All Police-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>officers shall be bound to assist the toll- collectors, when required,</p>
            <p>in the execution of this Act; and, for that purpose, shall have the  same power which they have in the exercise of their common police-</p>
            <p>duties.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for offences under Act. Compensation to Person  aggrieved. Saving of his right to sue.-- Every person, other than the  persons appointed to collect the tolls under this Act, who shall levy  or demand any toll on any public road or bridge, or for passing  through any bazar situated thereon, and also every person who shall  unlawfully and extortionately demand, or take any other or higher toll  than the lawful toll, or under colour of this Act seize or sell any  property knowing such seizure or sale to be unlawful, or in any manner  unlawfully extort money or any valuable thing from any person under  colour of this Act, shall be liable on conviction before Magistrate to  imprisonment for any term not exceeding six calendar months, or to  fine not exceeding two hundred rupees, any part of which fine may be  awarded by the Magistrate to the person aggrieved; but this remedy  shall not be deemed to bar or affect his right to have redress by suit  in the Civil Court.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Exhibition of table of tolls, and statement of penalties.-- A</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>table of the tolls authorized to be taken at any toll- gate or station  shall be put up in a conspicuous place near such gate or station  legibly written or printed in English words and figures, and also in  those of the vernacular language of the district, to which shall be  annexed, written or printed in like manner, a statement of the  penalties for refusing to pay the tolls and for taking any lawful  toll.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Application of proceeds of tolls.-- The tolls levied under this</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Act shall be deemed public revenue</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
