<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1886/11/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1886/11"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Indian Tramways Act, 1886"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1886/11/eng@1886-03-12/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1886/11/eng@1886-03-12"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1886-03-12" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1886/11/eng@1886-03-12/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1886/11/eng@1886-03-12"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Indian Tramways Act, 1886</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 11 OF 1886</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 12th March, 1886.] W</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to facilitate the construction and to regulate the working of  tramways.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Indian Tramways Act, 1886; and</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force at once.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Local extent.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends in the first instance to  the  whole of India except  the territories which, immediately before the</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1st">
        <num>1st.</num>
        <heading>November, 1956, were comprised in Part B States] and the  territories which were on the 12th March, 1886, respectively],</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1st.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>administered by the Governor of Fort Saint George in Council, the</p>
            <p>Governor of Bombay in Council and the Lieutenant- Governor of Bengal.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-1st.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may by notification in the Official Gazette be  extended to the whole or any part of the said territories by the State</p>
            <p>Government concerned.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless there is something repugnant  in the subject or context,--</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" local authority" means a municipal committee, district  board, body of port commissioners or other authority  legally entitled to, or entrusted by  the Central</p>
            <p>Government or any State Government] with, the control  or management of a municipal or local fund:</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" road" means the way of a road, street, throughfare,</p>
            <p>passage or place along or across which a tramway  authorized under this Act is, or is intended to be,</p>
            <p>laid, and includes the surface- soil and sub- soil of a  road, and the footway, berms, drains and ditches of a  road, and any bridge, culvert or causeway forming part  of a road:</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>" road- authority", in relation to a road, means--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>if a local authority maintains and repairs the  road, then that authority;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>if a local authority does not maintain and  repair the road, and the road is neither vested in</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Government nor maintained and repaired by</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.3.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Government], then the person in whom the road is  vested; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.3.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>if a local authority does not maintain and  repair the road, and the road is vested in Government  or maintained and repaired by   Government], then    the Government for whose purposes a road is so  vested or by which the road is maintained and repaired,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>as the case may be]:</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" circle", in relation to a local authority or road-</p>
            <p>authority, means the area within the control of that  authority:</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.5.list1">
              <listIntroduction>" tramway" means a tramway having one, two or more  rails, and includes--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.5.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any part of a tramway, or any siding, turnout,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.5.list3">
              <listIntroduction>connection, line or track belonging to a tramway;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.5.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any electrical equipment of a tramway; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.5.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any electric supply- line transmitting power  from a generating station or sub- station to a tramway  or from a generating station to a sub- station from  which power is transmitted to a tramway:]</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" order" means an order authorizing the construction of a  tramway under this Act, and includes a further order  substituted for, or amending, extending or varying,</p>
            <p>that order:</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" promoter" means a local authority or person in whose  favour an order has been made, and includes a local  authority or person on whom the rights and liabilities  conferred and imposed on the promoter by this Act and  by the order and any rules made under this Act as to  the construction, maintenance and use of the tramway,</p>
            <p>have devolved:</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" undertaking" includes all moveable and immoveable  property of the promoter suitable to and used by him  for the purposes of the tramway:</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" carriage", in the case of a tramway on which steam-</p>
            <p>power or any other mechanical power  or electrical  power] is used, includes and engine worked on the  tramway for the purpose of producing  or utilizing]</p>
            <p>that power:</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.10">
          <num>(10)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" toll" includes any charge leviable in respect of the  use of a tramway:</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" lessee" means a person to whom a lease has been  granted of the right of user of a tramway and of  demanding and taking the authorized tolls:</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.12">
          <num>(12)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" District Magistrate" includes an officer empowered by  the  Government] by name or by virtue of his office  to discharge within any local area all or any of the  functions of a District Magistrate under this Act:</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.13">
          <num>(13)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" District Court" means a principal Civil Court of  original jurisdiction, and includes a High Court having  ordinary original civil jurisdiction:</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.14">
          <num>(14)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" Collector" means the chief officer in charge of the  revenue- administration of a district, and includes an  officer empowered by the  Government] by name or by  virtue of his office to discharge within any local area  the functions of a Collector under this Act:</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.15">
          <num>(15)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made by the</p>
            <p>Government] under this Act:  and</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.16">
          <num>(16)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" Government" in relation to a tramway which is  wholly within a municipal area or which is declared not  to be  a railway under clause (20) of article 366 of the</p>
            <p>Constitution, means the State Government and, in  relation to any other tramway, means the Central</p>
            <p>Government.]]</p>
            <p>ORDERS AUTHORIZING THE CONSTRUCTION OF TRAMWAYS</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Application for and consent necessary to making of order.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The  Government] may make an order authorizing the construction of a  tramway in a circle on application made--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>by the local authority of the circle with the consent of  the road- authority of any road or part of a road which  is to be traversed by the tramway and of which the  local authority is not itself the road- authority; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>by any person with the consent of the local authority of  the circle, and of the road- authority of any road or  part of a road which is to be traversed by the tramway  and of which the local authority is not the road-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>authority:</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A local authority shall not make an application for an order,</p>
            <p>or be deemed to consent to an application being made by any person for  an order, unless the making of the application or the giving of the  consent has been approved by the local authority in manner prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Consent of local or road- authority not necessary in certain  cases. When it is proposed to lay a tramway in two or more circles,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>and a local authority or road- authority having control in either or  any of the circles does not consent thereto, or attaches conditions to  its consent, the  Government] may, nevertheless, make an order  authorizing the construction of the tramway in the circle, or by the  order impose on the promoter any conditions which it deems fit, if,</p>
            <p>after considering the reasons of the authority for withholding its  consent or attaching the conditions thereto, it is satisfied that the  construction of the tramway in the circle is expedient, or, as the  case may be, that the conditions attached by the authority to its  consent ought not to be imposed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Procedure for making order.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The  Government] on  receiving an application shall consider it, and, if satisfied as to  the propriety of proceeding thereon, publish in the Official Gazette,</p>
            <p>and in such other manner as it deems</p>
            <p>sufficient for giving information to persons interested, a draft of a  proposed order authorizing the construction of the tramway.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A notice shall be published with the draft stating that any  objection or suggestion which any person may desire to make with  respect to the proposed order will, if submitted to the  Government]</p>
            <p>on or before a date to be specified in the notice, be received and  considered.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If, after considering any objections or suggestions which may  have been made with respect to the draft on or before the date so  specified, the  Government] is of opinion that the application  should be granted, with or without addition or modification, or  subject or not to any restriction or condition, it may make an order  accordingly.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every order authorizing the construction of a tramway shall  be published in the Official Gazette in English, and in the other  prescribed language or languages, if any; and that publication shall  be conclusive proof that the order has been made as required by this  section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Contents of order.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An order made under section 6 shall  empower the promoter therein specified to construct and maintain the  tramway therein described in the manner therein provided, and shall  specify the time within which the tramway shall be commenced and the  time within which it shall be completed and opened for public traffic.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The order may also provide, in manner consistent with this</p>
            <blockList id="section-7.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Act, for all or any of the following, among other matters, that is to  say:--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.2.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>a period before the expiration of which the tramway  shall not be commenced, and the conditions subject to  which the local authority, when it is not itself the  promoter, may, within that period elect to be  substituted in the place of the promoter in respect of  the undertaking or of so much thereof as is within its  circle; and the limits of time within which, and the  terms upon which, the local authority may, after the  tramway has been constructed, require the promoter to  sell to it the undertaking or so much thereof as is  within its circle;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the acquisition by the promoter of land for the purposes  of the tramway, and the disposal by him of land which  has been acquired but is no longer required for those  purposes;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the conditions subject to which roads may be opened and  broken up for the purposes of the construction or  maintenance of the tramway or any part thereof, and the  method of, and materials to be used in, the reinstating  of the roads, and the approval of the method and  materials by the  Government] or the road- authority  before the commencement of the work;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the conditions on which the tramway may be constructed  over a bridge or across a railway or tramway when the  carriage- way over the bridge is to form part of the  tramway or when the tramway is to cross a railway or  another tramway on the level;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list2.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <blockList id="section-7.2.list2.e.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>the space which shall ordinarily intervene between  the outside of the carriage- way on either side of a  road whereon the tramway is to be constructed, and--</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-7.2.list2.e.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>in the case of a tramway having one rail, the  rail of the tramway, or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-7.2.list2.e.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>in the case of a tramway having two or more  rails, the nearest rail of the tramway,</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-7.2.list4">
              <listIntroduction>and the conditions on which a smaller space may be  permitted;]</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.2.list4.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the gauge of the tramway, the rails to be used, and the  mode in which, and the level at which, they shall be  laid and maintained; and the adoption and application  by the promoter of such improvements in the rails, and  in their situation, and in the sub- structure upon which  they rest, as the  Government] may from time to time  require;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list4.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the portion of the road or roads traversed by the  tramway to be kept in repair by the promoter; the  maintenance by the promoter to the satisfaction of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Government] or the road- authority, or both, of that  portion of the road or roads; and the liability of the  promoter, on the requisition of the  Government],</p>
            <blockList id="section-7.2.list7">
              <listIntroduction>from time to time to adopt and apply such improvements  in the tramway as the  Government] may consider  necessary or desirable for the safety or convenience of  the public, and to alter the position or level of the  tramway to suit future alterations in the road or  roads;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.2.list7.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the application of material excavated by the promoter in  the construction or maintenance of the tramway;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list7.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the provision of such crossing, passing- places, sidings,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-7.2.list9">
              <listIntroduction>junctions and other works, in addition to those  specified in or authorized by the order, as may from  time to time be necessary or convenient to the  efficient working of the tramway;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.2.list9.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>the powers which may from time to time be exercised by  the  Government], the local authority, the road-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>authority or any person in respect of sewers, drains,</p>
            <blockList id="section-7.2.list12">
              <listIntroduction>telegraph- lines, gas- pipes, water- pipes or other things  in or on land occupied by the tramway; the notice (if   any) to be given of the intended exercise of those  powers; the manner in which the power shall be  exercised; and the extent to which the tramway and the  traffic thereon may be interfered with in the exercise  thereof;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.2.list12.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>the conditions subject to which the promoter may from  time to time interfere with, or alter or require the  alteration of the position of, drains (not being   sewers or main drains), telegraph- lines, gas- pipes,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-7.2.list14">
              <listIntroduction>water- pipes or other things as aforesaid;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.2.list14.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>the provision of a temporary tramway in place of a part  of a tramway which has been removed, or of which the  use has been discontinued by reason of the execution of  any work affecting a road along which the part of the  tramway was laid, or by reason of the use of the road  being interrupted by floods or other cause;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list14.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>the motive power to be used on the tramway, and the  conditions on which steam- power or any other mechanical  power  or electrical power] may be used;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list14.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>the nature, dimensions, fittings, appliances and  apparatus of the carriages to be used on the tramway,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>and the inspection and examination thereof by officers  of the  Government] or the local authority, and the  liabilty of the promoter or lessee, on the requisition  of the  Government], from time to time, to adopt and  apply such improvements in the carriages, and in the  fittings, appliances and apparatus, as the</p>
            <blockList id="section-7.2.list17">
              <listIntroduction>Government] may consider necessary or desirable for  the safety or convenience of the public;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.2.list17.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>the traffic which may be carried on the tramway, the  traffic which the promoter or lessee shall be bound to  carry, and the traffic which he may refuse to carry;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>the tolls to be leviable by the promoter or lessee, and  the periodical revision thereof by the  Government];</p>
            <blockList id="section-7.2.list20">
              <listIntroduction>and the regulation of the traffic and of the levy of  the tolls;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.2.list20.p">
                <num>(p)</num>
                <p>the use of the tramway free of toll by the local  authority, with its own carriages, for specified  purposes, during specified hours, with power to the  local authority to make such sidings and other works as  may be necessary for communication between its premises  and the tramway;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.2.list20.q">
                <num>(q)</num>
                <p>the conditions subject to which the promoter may  transfer the undertaking, or any part thereof, by sale,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-7.2.list22">
              <listIntroduction>mortgage, lease, exchange or otherwise; and the  conditions subject to which the local authority may be  the transferee;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.2.list22.r">
                <num>(r)</num>
                <p>the performance by the  Government] or by the local  authority or road- authority of any work required by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-7.2.list24">
              <listIntroduction>Act or the order to be done by the promoter; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.2.list24.s">
                <num>(s)</num>
                <p>the penalty to be incurred by the promoter or lessee for  failure to observe any condition or direction contained  in the order, and the application of the penalty when  recovered.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The  Government] may, in providing in the order for the  acquisition of land for the purposes of a tramway of which the  promoter is not a company, direct that land may be acquired for the  promoter under the provisions of the Land Acquisition Act, 1870,</p>
            <p>(10 of 1870.) in the same manner and on the same conditions as it  might be acquired for the purposes of the tramway if a company were  the promoter.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The order shall imply the condition--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in the case of a tramway of which a local authority  is the promoter, that a lease thereof shall be granted only  in manner by this Act provided; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.4.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in the case of a tramway of which a local authority  is not the promoter, that a lease thereof shall be only of  the right of user and of demanding and taking the authorized  tolls, and shall not confer or impose on the lessee any of  the powers or duties of the promoter in respect of the  construction or maintenance of the tramway.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Further order.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The  Government] may, on the application  of the promoter, revoke, amend, extend or vary the order by a further  order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An application for a further order shall be made in the same  manner and subject to the same conditions as an application for an  order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The  Government] may, in its discretion, either grant or  reject the application.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If it grants the application, it shall make the further order  in the same manner as an order, except that no addition to, or  modification of, the rights, powers and authorities asked for in the  application, or restriction or condition with respect thereto, shall  be made or imposed by the further order without the consent in writing  of the promoter.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Power to authorize joint work by local authorities.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to, and in accordance with, the provisions of this Act, the</p>
            <p>Government] may, on a joint application, or on two or more  separate applications, make an order empowering two or more local  authorities, respectively, jointly to construst the whole, or  separately to construct parts, of a tramway, and jointly or separately  to own the whole or parts thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All the provisions of this Act which relate to the  construction of tramways shall extend and apply to the construction of  the whole and the separate parts of the tramway, and the form of the  order may be adapted to the circumstances of the case.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Cessation of powers given by an order.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If a promoter  authorized by an order to construct a tramway--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>does not within the time specified in the order  substantially commence the construction of the tramway,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-10.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.1.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>having commenced the construction, suspends it without a  reason sufficient in the opinion of the  Government]</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-10.1.list5">
              <listIntroduction>to warrant the suspension, or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.1.list5.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>does not within the time specified in the order complete  the tramway and open it for public traffic,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-10.1.list7">
              <listIntroduction>the following consequences shall ensue:--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.1.list7.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the powers given by the order to the promoter for  constructing the tramway and otherwise in relation thereto  shall, unless the  Government], by special direction in  writing, prolongs the time or condones the suspension,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-10.1.list9">
              <listIntroduction>cease to be exercised except as to so much of the tramway as  is then completed;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.1.list9.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>as to so much of the tramway as is then completed,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>the  Government] may either permit, or refuse to permit,</p>
            <blockList id="section-10.1.list12">
              <listIntroduction>the powers given by the order to continue;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.1.list12.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>if the  Government] refuses to permit the  powers to continue, then so much of the tramway as is then  completed may be dealt with, under the provisions of this</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Act relating to the discontinuance of tramways, as a tramway  of the working whereof the discontinuance has been proved to  the satisfaction of the  Government].</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A notification published by the  Government] in the</p>
            <p>Official Gazette to the effect that on a date specified in the  notification the construction of a tramway had not been substantially  commenced or a tramway had not been completed and opened for public  traffic, or that the construction of a tramway had been suspended  without sufficient reason, shall, for the purposes of this section, be  conclusive proof of the matter stated therein.</p>
            <p>CONSTRUCTION AND MAINTENANCE OF TRAMWAYS</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Mode of formation of tramway. A tramway shall be constructed  and maintained in the manner provided by the order.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Inspection of tramway before opening. A tramway, or portion  or extension of, or addition to, a tramway, shall not be opened for  public traffic  until it has been inspected and certified to be fit  for such traffic  by an engineer appointed by Government]].</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Agreement between road- authority and promoter as to repair of  roadway. Subject to the provisions of any order for the time being in  force with respect to the matters mentioned in section 7, sub- section</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>, clause (g), the road- authority and the promoter may from time to  time enter into agreements as to the keeping in repair of the whole or  a part of a road traversed by a tramway, and as to the proportion to  be paid by either of them of the expense of keeping the road or part  in repair.</p>
            <p>TRAFFIC ON TRAMWAYS.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Rights of promoters and the public over tramways.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The  promoter of a tramway shall, subject to the provisions of sub- section</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>and to the other provisions of this Act and of the order, have the  exclusive use of the tramway for carriages with flange- wheels or other  wheels suitable to run on the rail described in the order as the rail  to be used on the tramway:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing in this Act or in the order or any rule  made under this Act shall affect the right of any person authorized to  use a tramway or railway to pass across a tramway constructed under  this Act with carriages having wheels suitable to run on the rail  thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The public shall have a right to pass along or across any  part of a road along or across which a tramway is constructed, whether  on or off the tramway, with carriages not having flange- wheels or  other wheels suitable to run on the rail of the tramway:</p>
            <blockList id="section-14.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.2.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>that this sub- section shall not apply where the tramway  is constructed on land the right to the exclusive  possession of which has been acquired by the promoter;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-14.2.list4">
              <listIntroduction>and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.2.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>that the  Government] may by an order authorize the  construction of a tramway on any part of a road with  rails raised above the surface of the road, if it is  satisfied that the convenience of the public will not  be injuriously affected thereby.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Tolls leviable by promoter or lessee.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The promoter or  lessee may demand and take, in respect of the tramway, tolls not  exceeding the limits specified in or determinable under the order, or,</p>
            <p>if the order contains no provision in this behalf, then such sums as  may from time to time be fixed by the promoter or lessee with the  previous sanction of the  Government].</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A list of all the tolls authorized to be levied shall be  exhibited, in such languages as the District Magistrate may direct, in  a conspicuous place inside and outside each of the carriages used upon  the tramway.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Carriage of dangerous or offensive goods.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-16.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A person shall  not be entitled to carry or to require to be carried, on a tramway  constructed under this Act, any goods of a dangerous or offensive  nature.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A person taking such goods with him on the tramway shall,</p>
            <p>before entering the carriage, give notice of their nature to the  servant of the promoter or lessee in charge of the carriage.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A person sending such goods by the tramway shall distinctly  mark their nature on the outside of the package containing them, or  otherwise give notice thereof in writing to the servant of the  promoter or lessee with whom he leaves them for the purpose of their  being sent by the tramway.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any servant of the promoter or lessee may refuse to carry  upon the tramway a parcel which he suspects to contain goods of a  dangerous or offensive nature, and, if any such parcel has been  received for the purpose of being carried upon the tramway, may stop  the transit thereof until he is satisfied as to the nature of its  contents.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a servant of the promoter or lessee refuses under sub-</p>
            <p>section (4) to carry a parcel which has been received for the purpose  of being carried upon the tramway, he shall, as soon as may be, give  notice of his refusal to the consignor or consignee if he refuses at a  time when neither of them is present.</p>
            <p>LICENSES TO USE TRAMWAYS</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Grant to third parties of licenses to use tramway in certain  events. If, at any time after a tramway or part of a tramway has been  for three years opened for public traffic in a circle, the local  authority of the circle represents in writing to the  Government]</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-17.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>that the public is deprived of the full benefit of the tramway or of  the part thereof, the  Government] may, if after considering any  statement which the promoter or lessee or both may desire to make, and  after such further enquiry as it deems necessary, it is satisfied as  to the truth of the representation, grant a license to any person to  use the tramway conformably to this Act and to the order and the rules  made under this Act, subject to the following provisions, namely:--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the license shall be for a period not less than one year  or more than three years from the date of the license,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-17.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>but the  Government] may in its discretion renew it;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the license shall be to use the whole of the tramway for  the time being opened for public traffic, or such part  or parts of the tramway as the  Government], having  regard to the cause for granting the license, thinks  fit;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the license shall specify the number of carriages which  the licensee shall run upon the tramway, the mode in  which, and times at which, the carriages shall be run,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>the tolls to be paid to the promoter or lessee by the  licensee for the use of the tramway, and the tolls,</p>
            <blockList id="section-17.paragraph-0.list6">
              <listIntroduction>being those for the time being leviable by the promoter  or lessee, which the licensee may demand and take for  the use of his carriages;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.paragraph-0.list6.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the licensee and his officers and servants shall permit  one person, duly authorized for that purpose by the  promoter or lessee, to travel free of toll in or upon  each carriage of the licensee run upon the tramway for  the whole or any part of a journey;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.paragraph-0.list6.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>any provision of this Act, or of the order or rules made  under this Act, relating to the functions of a servant  of a promoter or lessee shall be construed, so far as  may be, as referring to a servant of the licensee; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.paragraph-0.list6.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the  Government] may revoke, alter or modify the  license for any cause sufficient in its opinion to  warrant the revocation, alteration or modification  thereof.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Licensee to give to promoter or lessee an account of traffic.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A licensee shall, on demand, give to an officer or servant authorized  in that behalf by the promoter or lessee an exact account in writing,</p>
            <p>signed by the licensee, of the number of passengers, or number or  quantity of goods, conveyed by any and every carriage used by him on  the tramway.</p>
            <p>DISCONTINUANCE OF TRAMWAYS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Cessation of powers of promoter and lessee on discontinuance  of tramway. If it is proved to the satisfaction of the  Government],</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>at any time after the opening of a tramway for public traffic, that  the working of the tramway, or any part thereof, has been practically  discontinued, for the space of three months, without a reason  sufficient, in the opinion of the  Government], to warrant the  discontinuance, the  Government], if it thinks fit, may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, declare that the powers of the  promoter and of the lessee, if any, in respect of the tramway or the  part thereof of which the working has been so discontinued, shall,</p>
            <p>from the date of the notification, be at an end; and thereupon the said  powers shall cease and determine, except in so far as they may be  purchased by a local authority in manner by this Act provided.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Powers of road- authority on cessation of powers of promoter.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-20.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a notification has been published under section 19, the  road- authority may, at any time after the expiration of two months  from the date of the notification, remove the tramway or part of the  tramway of which the working has been so discontinued, and use the  materials thereof in reinstating the road.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The promoter shall pay to the road- authority the cost  incurred by that authority in removing the tramway or the part thereof  and in reinstating the road.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The cost shall be certified by an officer of the road-</p>
            <p>authority, and his certificate, countersigned by the District</p>
            <p>Magistrate, shall be conclusive proof as to the cost incurred.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the promoter does not pay the amount so certified within  one month after the delivery to him of the certificate or of a copy  thereof, the road- authority may, without any previous notice to the  promoter and without prejudice to any other remedy which it may have  for the recovery of the amount, sell and dispose of such materials of  the tramway or part thereof removed as it has not used in reinstating  the road, either by public auction or by private sale, and for such  sum or sums, and to such person or persons, as it thinks fit, and may,</p>
            <p>out of the proceeds of the sale, pay and reimburse itself the amount  of the cost aforesaid and of the expenses of the sale, and shall pay  over the residue (if any) of the proceeds of the sale to the promoter.</p>
            <p>INSOLVENCY OF PROMOTER</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Proceedings in case of insolvency of promoter.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-21.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If, at any  time after the opening of a tramway in a circle for public traffic, it  appears to the road- authority or local authority of the circle that  the promoter of the tramway is insolvent, so that he is unable to  maintain the tramway, or to work it with advantage to the public, and  either of those authorities makes a representation to that effect to  the  Government], the  Government], may, if after considering any  statement which the promoter may desire to make, and after such  further enquiry as it deems necessary, it is satisfied as to the truth  of the representation, declare, by notification in the Official</p>
            <p>Gazette, that the powers of the promoter shall, at the expiration of  six months from the publication of the notification, be at an end; and  the powers of the promoter shall cease and determine at the expiration  of that period, except in so far as they may be purchased by a local  authority in manner by this Act provided.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-21.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a notification has been published under sub- section</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-21.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>, the road- authority may, at any time after the expiration of six  months from the date thereof, remove the tramway in the same manner,</p>
            <p>and subject to the same provisions as to the payment of the cost of  the removal and to the same remedy for recovery of the cost, in every  respect as in cases of removal under section 20.</p>
            <p>PURCHASE OF TRAMWAYS</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Future purchase of undertaking by local authority.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-22.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-22.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where  the promoter of a tramway in a circle is not the local authority, with  the previous sanction of the  Government], may--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-22.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>within such limits of time as may be specified in this  behalf in the order, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-22.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>if a time was not specified in the order, then within  six months after the expiration of a period of twenty-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-22.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>one years from the date of the order, and within six  months after the expiration of every subsequent period  of seven years, or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-22.1.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>within two months after the publication of a  notification under section 19 or within six months  after the publication of a notification under section</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>,</p>
            <p>by notice in writing, require the promoter to sell to the local  authority his undertaking or the part thereof which is within the  circle of the local authority; and thereupon the promoter shall sell  the same upon the terms specified in the order, or, if the terms were  not specified in the order, then upon the terms of paying the then  value of the undertaking or of the part thereof, exclusive of any  allowance for past or future profits of the undertaking or any  compensation for compulsory sale or other consideration whatsoever.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-21.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A requisition shall not be made under sub- section (1) unless  the making thereof has been approved by the local authority in manner  prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-21.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When a sale has been made under this section, all the rights,</p>
            <p>powers and authorities of the promoter in respect of the undertaking  or part thereof sold, or, where a notification has been published  under section 19 or section 21, all the rights, powers and authorities  of the promoter previous to the publication of the notification in  respect of the undertaking or part thereof sold, shall be transferred  to the authority to whom the undertaking or part has been sold, and  shall vest in, and may be exercised by, that authority in the same  manner</p>
            <p>as if the tramway had been constructed by it under an order made under  this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-21.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to, and in accordance with, the preceding provisions  of this section, two or more local authorities may jointly purchase an  undertaking or so much thereof as is within their circles.</p>
            <p>WORKING OF TRAMWAYS OWNED BY LOCAL AUTHORITIES</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Lease of, or working of, tramway by local authority.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-23.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When  a local authority has under the authority of an order completed a  tramway, or has under the provisions of this Act or of an order  acquired possession of a tramway, it may, by a lease to be approved by  the  Government], let to any person the right of user of the tramway  and of demanding and taking the authorized tolls.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On the determination of a lease the local authority may from  time to time let the right for such further term and on such  conditions as the  Government] may approve.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every lease made under this section shall imply a condition  of re- entry if at any time after the making thereof it is proved to  the satisfaction of the  Government] that the lessee has practically  discontinued the working of the tramway leased, or of any part  thereof, for the space of one month without a reason sufficient, in  the opinion of the  Government], to warrant the discontinuance.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notice of the intention of the local authority to make a  lease shall be given in manner prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the local authority cannot by means of a lease obtain what  it deems to be a fair rent for the tramway, it may itself, with the  previous sanction of the  Government] and for such term as the</p>
            <p>Government] directs, place and run carriages upon the tramway, and  demand and take the authorized tolls in respect of the use of the  carriages.</p>
            <p>RULES</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-24.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In addition to any other power to  make rules expressly or by implication conferred by this Act, the</p>
            <blockList id="section-24.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Government] may make rules consistent with this Act--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-24.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>as to the form in which an application for an order  shall be made;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.1.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>as to the costs to be paid by an applicant in respect of  an order, and the time when, and the place where, those  costs shall be paid;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.1.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>as to the payment of money or lodgment of securities, by  way of deposit, by the applicant for an order before  the order is published under section 6, sub- section</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-24.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>, or a further order is made under section 8; the  investment of money so paid; the disposal of interest  or dividends from time to time accruing due on money or  securities so paid, lodged or invested; the application  of the money or securities or the produce thereof to  the discharge of any liability incurred by the  promoter; and the forfeiture, repayment or return of  the money or securities;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-24.4.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>as to the plans and sections of any works to be  deposited by applicants for orders or by promoters;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.4.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>for regulating the use of steam- power or any other  mechanical power  or electrical power] on a tramway;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.4.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>as to any matter specified in section 7, sub- section</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-24.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>, clauses (c), (d), (e), (j) and (k), as a matter  which may be provided for in an order, when that matter  has not been so provided for, or has not, in the  opinion of the  Government], been effectually so  provided for;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-24.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>as to the periodical submission, by promoters, lessees  and licensees, of accounts of traffic and receipts to  the  Government] or as that Government directs, and  as to the forms in which those accounts are to be  submitted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>as to the accidents of which report is to be made to the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-24.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Government] or as that Government directs;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-24.2.list3.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>as to any matter respecting which rules may be made  under this section by a local authority or a promoter  or lessee; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.2.list3.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>generally, as to any other matter or thing in respect of  which it may seem to the  Government] to be expedient  to make rules for carrying out the purposes of this</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A local authority may, from time to time, with the previous  sanction of the  Government], make rules consistent with this Act</p>
            <p>and with the order and any rules made by the  Government] under this</p>
            <blockList id="section-24.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Act, for regulating--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-24.2.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the rate of speed to be observed in travelling upon a  tramway within the circle of the local authority;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.2.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the use of animal power on the tramway;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.2.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the distances at which carriages using the tramway are  to be allowed to follow one after the other;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.2.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the stopping of carriages using the tramway, and the  notice to be given to the public of their approach;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.2.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the manner in which carriages using the tramway after  sunset and before sunrise are to be lighted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.2.list3.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the traffic on roads along or across which the tramway  is laid;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.2.list3.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the number of passengers which may be carried in any  carriage;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.2.list3.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the licensing and control of drivers, conductors and  other persons having charge of the carriages of the  promoter or lessee or a licensee; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.2.list3.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>generally, the mode of use of the tramway.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The promoter or lessee of a tramway may, from time to time,</p>
            <blockList id="section-24.3.list2">
              <listIntroduction>with the previous sanction of the  Government], make rules   consistent with this Act and with the order and any rules made under  this Act--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-24.3.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for preventing the commission of any nuisance in or upon  any carriage, or in or against any premises, belonging  to him; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.3.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>for regulating the travelling in any carriage belonging  to him.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-24.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The  Government] may cancel any rule made by a local  authority or by a promoter or lessee under this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Power to impose penalty by rule. The authority making any  rule under section 24 may direct that a breach of it shall be  punishable with fine which may extend--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-25.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>if the authority making the rule is the  Government],</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-25.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>to two hundred rupees, and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>if that authority is a local authority or a promoter or  lessee, to twenty rupees;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-25.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>and when the breach is a continuing breach, with a further fine which  may extend--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>if the authority making the rule is the  Government],</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-25.paragraph-0.list6">
              <listIntroduction>to fifty rupees, and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list6.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>if that authority is a local authority of a promoter or  lessee, to five rupees,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>for every day after the first during which the breach continues.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Procedure for making, and publication of, rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-26.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every  authority having power to make rules under any section of this Act  shall, before making the rules, publish a draft of the proposed rules  for the information of persons likely to be affected thereby.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The publication shall be made, in the case of rules made by  the  Government], in such manner as may in its opinion be sufficient  for giving information to persons interested, and, in the case of  rules made by a local authority or by a promoter or lessee, in manner  prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be published with the draft a notice specifying a  date, not earlier than the expiration of one month after the date of  publication, at or after which the draft will be taken into  consideration.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The authority shall receive and consider any objection or  suggestion which may be made by any person with respect to the draft  before the date so specified.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The publication in the Official Gazette of a rule purporting  to be made under this Act shall be conclusive proof that it has been  duly made.</p>
            <p>OFFENCES</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for failure of promoter, lessee or licensee to comply  with act or order. If a promoter--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-27.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>constructs or maintains a tramway otherwise than in  accordance with the order, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>opens the tramway for traffic or permits it to be so  opened, before it has been inspected and certified in  manner required by section 12, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>fails to observe any requirement or condition of the  order for neglect or breach whereof no penalty has been  expressly provided in the order,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>or if a promoter, lessee or licensee runs a carriage on a tramway  otherwise than in accordance with the order,</p>
            <p>he shall (without prejudice to the enforcement or specific  performance of the requirements of this Act or of the order, or to any  other remedy which may be obtained against him in a Court of Civil</p>
            <p>Judicature), on complaint made by the  Government] or by the local  authority or road- authority or by the District Magistrate or, with the  previous sanction of the District Magistrate, by any person  injuriously affected by the act or omission, be punished with fine  which may extend to two hundred rupees, and in the case of a  continuing offence to a further fine which may extend to fifty rupees  for every day after the first during which the offence continues to be  committed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28">
        <num>28.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for obstructing promoter in exercise of his powers.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any person without lawful excuse, the burden of proving which shall  lie upon him, wilfully obstructs any person acting under the authority  of the promoter in the lawful exercise of his powers in constructing  or maintaining a tramway, or injures or destroys any mark made for the  purpose of setting out the line of the tramway, he shall be punished  with fine which may extend to fifty rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29">
        <num>29.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for interfering with tramway. If any person without  lawful excuse, the burden of proving which shall lie upon him,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-29.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-29.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>wilfully does any of the following things, namely:--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-29.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>interferes with, removes or alters any part of a tramway  constructed under this Act, or of the works connected  therewith, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-29.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>places or throws upon or across any such tramway any  wood, stone, refuse or other thing, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-29.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>does anything in such a manner as to obstruct any  carriage using any such tramway, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-29.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>abets within the meaning of the Indian Penal Code (45 of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1860">
        <num>1860.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1860.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>) the doing of, or attempts to do, anything  mentioned in clause (a), clause (b) or clause (c),</p>
            <p>he shall (without prejudice to any other remedy which may be obtained   against him in a Court of Civil Judicature) be punished with fine  which may extend to one hundred rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-30">
        <num>30.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for using tramway with carriage having flange- wheels.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-30.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any person, except under a lease from, or by agreement with, the  promoter, or under license from the  Government] granted under this</p>
            <p>Act, uses on a tramway, otherwise than as permitted by section 14, a  carriage having flange- wheels or other wheels suitable to run on the  rail of the tramway, he shall be punished with fine which may extend  to two hundred rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-31">
        <num>31.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for evading payment of proper toll.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-31.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person  travelling or having travelled in a carriage of the promoter or lessee  or of a licensee evades or attempts to evade payment of toll, or if  any person having paid toll for a certain distance wilfully proceeds  in any such carriage beyond that distance and does not pay the  additional toll for the additional distance or attempts to evade  payment thereof, or if any person wilfully refuses or neglects on  arriving at the point to which he has paid toll to quit the carriage,</p>
            <p>he shall be punished with fine which may extend to ten rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-31.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When a person commits an offence under this section and  refuses on demand of a servant of the promoter, lessee or licensee to  give his name and residence, or gives a name or residence which the  servant has reason to believe to be false, he may be arrested and  taken to the nearest police- station by the servant or any person whom  the servant may call to his aid.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-31.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When the person is taken to the police- station he shall with  the least possible delay be forwarded to the nearest Magistrate,</p>
            <p>unless his true name and residence are ascertained, in which case he  shall be released on his executing a bond for his appearance before a</p>
            <p>Magistrate if so required.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-32">
        <num>32.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for taking or sending dangerous or offensive goods  without giving notice. If any person takes or sends by a tramway any  goods of a dangerous or offensive nature without giving the notice  required by section 16, he shall be punished with fine which may  extend to fifty rupees.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-33">
        <num>33.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for licensee not giving to promoter or lessee an  account of traffic or giving false account.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-33.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If a licensee fails on  demand to give the account mentioned in section 18, or, with intent to  evade the payment of tolls, gives a false account when he is called  upon to give an account under that section, he shall be punished with  fine which may extend to fifty rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-33.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The fine shall be in addition to any tolls payable by the  licensee to the promoter or lessee in respect of the passengers or  goods conveyed by the carriage or carriages used by the licensee on  the tramway.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-34">
        <num>34.</num>
        <heading>Saving of prosecutions under other laws. Nothing in this Act  shall prevent a person from being prosecuted under any other law for  an act or omission which constitutes an offence against this Act or  the rules made under it, or from being liable under that other law to  any other or higher punishment or penalty than that provided by this</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-34.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Act or the rules made under it:</p>
            <p>Provided that a person shall not be punished twice for the same  offence.</p>
            <p>SETTLEMENT OF DIFFERENCES</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-35">
        <num>35.</num>
        <heading>Differences between promoters or lessees and authorities.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-35.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any difference arises between the promoter or lessee on the one  hand and the  Government], or the local authority, or the road-</p>
            <p>authority, or a person having the charge of any sewers, drains,</p>
            <p>telegraph- lines, gas- pipes, water- pipes or other things in or on land  occupied by the tramway, on the other hand, with respect to any  interference or control exercised or claimed to be exercised by, or on  behalf of, either party by virtue of this or any other Act, or of the  order or the rules made under this Act, or with respect to the  propriety of, or the mode of, the execution of any work, or with  respect to any compensation to be made by or to the promoter or  lessee, or on the question whether any work is such as ought  reasonably to satisfy the  Government] or the road- authority or  both, or with respect to any other subject or thing regulated by, or  comprised in, this Act or the order or the rules made under this Act,</p>
            <p>and not otherwise expressly provided for therein, the matter in  difference shall, except where the parties elect to proceed under  section 523 of the Code of Civil Procedure,  (14 of 1882.) be  settled, on the application of either party, by a referee.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-35.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-35.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where the difference is--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-35.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>between the promoter or lessee on the one hand and the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Government], either as such or as the road-</p>
            <blockList id="section-35.2.list4">
              <listIntroduction>authority, on the other, or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-35.2.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>between the promotor on the one hand and the local  authority on the other, with respect to the sum to be  paid by the local authority for an undertaking or part  of an undertaking which that authority has required the  promoter to sell under section 22,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>the referee shall be the District Court within the jurisdiction of  which the tramway is situate, or, where the tramway is within the</p>
            <p>jurisdiction of more than one District Court, the District Court with  in the jurisdiction of which the greater part of the tramway is  situate.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-35.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In other cases the referee shall be appointed by the</p>
            <p>Government].</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-35.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Except where the referee is the District Court, the powers  and procedure of the referee may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-35.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the case of a difference between a promoter on the one  hand and a local authority on the other, with respect to the sum to be  paid by the local authority for an undertaking or part of an  undertaking which that authority has required the promoter to sell  under section 22, an appeal shall lie to the High Court from the award  of the referee as from an original decree of the District Court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-35.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the case of every other difference the award of the  referee shall be final.</p>
            <p>RECOVERY OF TOLLS</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-36">
        <num>36.</num>
        <heading>Recovery of moneys due from promoters and, in certain cases,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-36.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>from lessees. Any of the following moneys, namely, any rent due to a  local authority from a lessee, any penalty recoverable from a promoter  or lessee under an order, any sum payable by a promoter or lessee  under an award of a referee, the cost of the performance under this</p>
            <p>Act by the  Government] or by a local authority or road- authority of  any work required by this Act or by an order to be done by a promoter,</p>
            <p>and the cost incurred by a road- authority in removing a tramway and  reinstating a road under this Act, may, without prejudice to any other  remedy that the authority to which the money is due may have by suit  or otherwise, be recovered by that authority, on application made in  this behalf to the Collector, as if the sum due were an arrear of  land- revenue due by the promoter or lessee or his surety (if any):</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing in this section shall authorize the arrest  of the promoter or lessee or his surety in execution of any process  issued by the Collector.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-37">
        <num>37.</num>
        <heading>Recovery of tolls from licensees.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-37.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If a licensee fails to  pay on demand the tolls due for the use of a tramway, the promoter or  lessee to whom the tolls are due may, without prejudice to the remedy  which he may have by suit, apply to a Magistrate to recover the amount  of the tolls, and the Magistrate may, after giving notice to the  licensee, if possible, and</p>
            <p>allowing him an opportunity of being heard, proceed to recover the  amount by distress and the sale of any carriages or other moveable  property of the licensee which may be found on the tramway or on  premises connected therewith.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-37.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When a licensee has failed to pay on demand the tolls due  from him, the promoter or lessee to whom the tolls are due may seize  any carriage or other moveable property of the licensee on the tramway  or on premises connected therewith, and detain the same for forty-</p>
            <p>eight hours unless the tolls are sooner paid.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-37.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When application is made to a Magistrate under sub- section</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-37.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>, he may make an interim order of distraint pending his final  decision.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-38">
        <num>38.</num>
        <heading>Recovery of tolls from passengers. Any toll due to a  promoter, lessee or licensee from a passenger may be recovered either  by suit or, on application to a Magistrate having jurisdiction within  any local area in which any part of the tramway is laid, by distress  and sale of any moveable property belonging to the passenger within  the local limits of the jurisdiction of the Magistrate.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-38.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>SAVINGS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-39">
        <num>39.</num>
        <heading>Promoter to have right of user only.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-39.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding  anything contained in this Act, or in an order or any rule made under  this Act, a promoter shall not acquire any right other than that of  user only over a road along or across which he lays a tramway, nor  shall anything contained in this Act, or in an order or any rule made  under this Act, exempt the promoter of a tramway, or any other person  using the tramway, from the payment of such charges as may lawfully be  levied in respect of the use of a road or bridge along or across which  the tramway is laid.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-39.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, if it thinks fit, fix rates at  which a promoter, lessee or licensee may compound for the charges  payable in respect of the use of a road or bridge.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-40">
        <num>40.</num>
        <heading>Saving of power over roads traversed by tramways.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-40.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing  in this Act, or in an order or any rule made under this Act, shall  take away or abridge any power which a road- authority, local authority  or other person has by law to break up, widen, alter, divert or improve  a road, railroad or tramway along or across which a tramway is laid.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-40.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The road- authority, local authority or other person executing  any work referred to in sub- section (1) shall not be liable to pay</p>
            <p>to a promoter, lessee or licensee any compensation for injury done to  a tramway by the execution of the work or for loss of traffic  occasioned by the reasonable use of any power lawfully exercised for  the execution thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-41">
        <num>41.</num>
        <heading>Saving of power of local authority and police to regulate  traffic on roads. Nothing in this Act, or in an order or any rule made  under this Act, shall affect the powers of a local authority or of a</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-41.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Magistrate or police- officer to regulate the passage of traffic along  or across a road along or across which a tramway is laid; and the  authority, Magistrate or officer aforesaid may exercise its or his  powers as well on as off the tramway and with respect as well to the  traffic of a promoter, lessee or licensee as to the traffic of other  persons.</p>
            <p>SUPPLEMENTAL PROVISIONS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-42">
        <num>42.</num>
        <heading>Promoters, lessees and licensees to be responsible for all  injuries. A promoter, lessee or licensee shall be answerable for all  injuries happening through his act or default, or through the act or  default of any person in his employment, by reason or in consequence  of any of his carriages or works, and shall save harmless all  authorities and persons collectively and individually, and their  officers and servants, from all damages and costs in respect of  injuries so happening.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-43">
        <num>43.</num>
        <heading>Want of funds not a sufficient reason for default. For the  purposes of this Act want of funds shall not be deemed to be a  sufficient reason for the suspension of the construction, or the  discontinuance of the working, of a tramway by a promoter or lessee.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-44">
        <num>44.</num>
        <heading>Power to exempt from municipal taxation. When a tramway is  constructed under this Act within the limits of a municipality, the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-44.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>State Government may exempt the animals, plant, rolling- stocks, yards,</p>
            <p>workshops, engine- sheds,  electrical generating stations or sub-</p>
            <p>stations] and depots of the promoter, lessee or licensee, for such  period as it thinks fit, from all or any municipal taxes leviable  within those limits.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-45">
        <num>45.</num>
        <heading>Application by local authorities of local funds to tramways.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-45.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The fund to or with the control or management of which the local  authority of a municipality, cantonment or district is entitled or  entrusted shall, notwithstanding anything in any enactment respecting  the purposes to which that fund may be applied, be applicable, subject  to the control of the  appropriate Government], to the payment of  expenses incidental to the exercise of the</p>
            <p>powers and functions which may be vested in or exercised by a local  authority under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-45.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The fund shall also be applicable, with the previous sanction  of the  appropriate Government], to a guarantee of the payment of  interest on money to be applied, with the concurrence in writing of  the local authority, within the limits of the local area under its  control, to any of the purposes to which the fund might be applied by  the local authority under sub- section (1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-45.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In this section" the appropriate Government" means the</p>
            <p>Government, Central or State, whose executive authority extends over  the local authority in question.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-46">
        <num>46.</num>
        <heading>Extension of Act to existing tramways. The  Government]</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-46.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>may, with the consent of the local authority and road- authority and of  the promoter and his lessee (if any), extend any part of this Act, or  any rules made under this Act, either with or without modification, to  the whole or any part of a tramway constructed, or authorized by the</p>
            <p>Government] to be constructed, before the passing of this Act, and  may withdraw any part of the Act or any rules so extended.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-47">
        <num>47.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition of construction of tramways except under this</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-47.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-47.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A tramway of which the construction has not been authorized  by the  Government] before the passing of this Act shall not, after  the passing of this Act, be constructed for public traffic in any  place to which this Act extends, except in pursuance of an order made  under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-47.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A person constructing a tramway in contravention of sub-</p>
            <p>section (1) of this section,</p>
            <p>or after the passing of this Act maintaining or using for public  traffic, otherwise than in pursuance of an order made under this Act,</p>
            <p>a tramway which was not constructed, or authorized by the</p>
            <p>Government] to be constructed, before the passing of this Act,</p>
            <p>shall be liable, on the complaint of the  Government] or local  authority, to double the penalty to which a promoter acting otherwise  than in accordance with an order is liable under section 27.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-48">
        <num>48.</num>
        <heading>Transfer of control on exclusion of local area from circle of  local authority. If at any time a local area comprising a tramway to  which this Act or any part thereof or any rule thereunder applies  ceases to be</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-48.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>included in the circle of a local authority, the functions of that  authority under this Act or the part thereof or the rule thereunder,</p>
            <p>and under the order (if any), shall, in respect of that local area,</p>
            <p>devolve on the  Government] or, if that Government so directs, on  the local authority of the circle in which the tramway has been  included.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-49">
        <num>49.</num>
        <heading>Explanation and amendment of section 54 of Railway Act.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-49.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Rep. by the Indian Railways Act, 1890 (9 of 1890), s. 2 and Sch. I.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-50">
        <num>50.</num>
        <heading>Powers of Government exercisable from time to time. All  powers conferred by this Act on  any Government] may be exercised  from time to time as occasion requires.</heading>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
