<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1955/22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1955/22"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Protection Of Civil Rights Act, 1955"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1955/22/eng@1955-05-08/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1955/22/eng@1955-05-08"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1955-05-08" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1955/22/eng@1955-05-08/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1955/22/eng@1955-05-08"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Protection Of Civil Rights Act, 1955</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 22 OF 1955</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 8th May, 1955.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Sixth Year of the Republic of</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to prescribe punishment for the  preaching and practice of</p>
        <p>" Untouchability"], for the enforcement of any disability arising  therefrom and for matters connected therewith.</p>
        <p>India as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be  called  the Protection of Civil Rights Act], 1955.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date  as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>" civil rights" means any right accruing to a person by  reason of the abolition of" untouchability" by article 17  of the Constitution;]</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a.list0.aa">
                    <num>(aa)</num>
                    <p>" hotel" includes a refreshment room, a boarding house,</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>lodging house, a coffee house and a cafe;]</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" place" includes a house, building and other structure  and premises; and also includes a tent, vehicle and vessel;]</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" place of public entertainment" includes any place to  which the public are admitted and in which an entertainment  is provided or held.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Explanation.-" Entertainment" includes any, exhibition,</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5">
              <listIntroduction>performance, game, sport and any other form of amusement;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.d.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>" place of public worship" means a place, by whatever  name known, which is used as a place of public religious  worship or which is dedicated generally to, or is used  generally by, persons professing any religion or belonging to  any religious denomination or any section thereof, for the  performance of any religious service, or for offering prayers  therein;  and includes-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.d.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>all lands and subsidiary shrines appurtenant or  attached to any such place,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.d.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>a privately owned place of worship which is, in  fact, allowed by the owner thereof to be used as a  place of public worship, and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.d.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.d.list0.iii.list0">
                      <listIntroduction>such land or subsidiary shrine appurtenant to such  privately owned place of worship as is allowed by the  owner thereof to be used as a place of public religious  worship;]</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.d.list0.iii.list0.da">
                        <num>(da)</num>
                        <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list7">
              <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list7.db">
                <num>(db)</num>
                <p>" Scheduled Castes" has the meaning assigned to it in  clause (24) of article 366 of the Constitution;]</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list7.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>" shop" means any premises where goods are sold either  whole- sale or by retail or both wholesale and by retail  and  includes-</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list7.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>any place from where goods are sold by a hawker or  vendor or from a mobile van or cart,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list7.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>a laundry and a hair cutting saloon,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list7.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>any other place where services are rendered to  customers].</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Punishment for enforcing religious disabilities. Whoever on the  ground of" untouchability" prevents any person-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>from entering any place of public worship which is open  to other persons professing the same religion  or any  section thereof, as such person; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>from worshipping or offering prayers or performing any  religious service in any place of public worship, or bathing  in, or using the waters of, any sacred tank, well, spring or</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>water- course,  river or lake or bathing at any ghat of such  tank, water- course, river or lake] in the same manner and to  the same extent as is permissible to other persons professing  or any section thereof, as such the same religion,</p>
            <p>or any section there of, as such person;</p>
            <p>shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term of not less than  one month and not more than six months and also with fine which shall  be rot less than one hundred rupees and not more than five hundred  rupees].</p>
            <p>Explanation.- For the purposes of this section and section 4  persons professing the Buddhist, Sikh or Jaina religion or persons  professing the Hindu religion in any of its forms or developments  including Virashaivas, Lingayats, Adivasis, followers of Brahmo,</p>
            <p>Prarthana, Arya Samaj and the Swaminarayan Sampraday shall be deemed  to be Hindus.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Punishment for enforcing social disabilities. Whoever on the  ground of" untouchability" enforces against any person any disability  with regard to-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>access to any shop, public restaurant, hotel or place  of public entertainment; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>the use of any utensils, and other articles kept in any  public restaurant, hotel, dharmshala, sarai or  musafirkhana for the use of the general public or of  any  section thereof]; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>the practice of any profession or the carrying on of  any occupation, trade or business  or employment in any job]</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>; or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list2.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>the use of, or access to, any river, stream, spring,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>well, tank, cistern, water- tap or other watering place, or  any bathing ghat, burial or cremation ground, any sanitary  convenience, any road, or passage, or any other place of  public resort which other members of the public, or  any  section thereof, have a right to use or have access to; or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list4.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>the use of, or access to, any place used for a  charitable or a public purpose maintained wholly or partly  out of State funds or dedicated to the use of the general  public, or  any section thereof]; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list4.vi">
                <num>(vi)</num>
                <p>the enjoyment of any benefit under a charitable trust  created for the benefit of the general public or of  any  section thereof; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list4.vii">
                <num>(vii)</num>
                <p>the use of, or access to, any public conveyance; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list4.viii">
                <num>(viii)</num>
                <p>the construction, acquisition, or occupation of  any residential premises in any locality, whatsoever; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list4.ix">
                <num>(ix)</num>
                <p>the use of any dharmshala, sarai or musafirkhana which  is open to the general public, or to  any section thereof];</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list6">
              <listIntroduction>or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list6.x">
                <num>(x)</num>
                <p>the observance of any social or religious custom, usage  or ceremony or  taking part in, or taking out, any  religious social or cultural procession; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list6.xi">
                <num>(xi)</num>
                <p>the use of jewellery and finery;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term of not less than  one month and not more than six months and also with fine which shall  be not less than one hundred rupees and not more than five hundred  rupees.</p>
            <p>Explanation.- For the purposes of this section," enforcement of  any disability" includes any discrimination on the ground of" untouch-</p>
            <p>ability".]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Punishment for refusing to admit persons to hospitals etc.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Whoever on the round of" untouchability"-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>refuses admission to any person to any hospital,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>dispensary, educational institution or any hostel , if  such hospital, dispensary, educational institution or hostel  is established or maintained for the benefit of the general  public or any section thereof; or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>does any act which discriminates against any such  person after admission to any of the aforesaid institutions;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term of not less than  one month and not more than six months and also with fine which shall  be not less than one hundred rupees and not more than five hundred  rupees].</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Punishment for refusing to sell goods to render services.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever on the ground of" untouchability" refuses to sell any goods or  refuses to render any- service to any person at. the same time and  place and on the same terms and conditions at or on which such goods  are sold or services are rendered to other persons in the ordinary</p>
            <p>course of business  shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term  of not less than one month and not more than six months and also with  fine which shall be not less than one hundred rupees and not more than  five hundred rupees].</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Punishment for other offences arising out of</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>" untouchability".</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Whoever-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>prevents any person from exercising any right accruing  to him by reason of the abolition of" untouchability" under  article 17 of the Constitution; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>molests, injures, annoys, obstructs or causes or  attempts to cause obstruction to any person in the exercise  of any such right or molests, injures, annoys or boycotts any  person by reason of his having exercised any such right; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>by words, either spoken or written, or by signs or by  visible representations or otherwise, incites or encourages  any person or class of persons or the public generally to  practise" untouchability" in any form whatsoever;  or]</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>insults or attempts to insult, on the ground of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>" untouchability", a member of a Scheduled Caste;]</p>
            <p>shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term of not less than  one month and not more than six months and also with fine which shall  be not less than one hundred rupees and not more than five hundred  rupees].</p>
            <blockList id="section-7.1.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation 1].- A person shall be deemed to boycott another  person who-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.1.list5.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>refuses to let to such other person or refuses to  permit such other person, to use or occupy any house or land  or refuses to deal with, work for hire for, or do business  with, such other person or to render to him or receive from  him any customary service, or refuses to do any of the said  things on the terms on Which such things would be commonly  done in the ordinary course of business; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list5.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>abstains from such social, professional or business  relations as he would ordinarily maintain with such other  person.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-7.1.list7">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation II.- For the purpose of clause (c) a person shall be  deemed to incite or encourage the practice of" untouchability"-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.1.list7.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>if he, directly or indirectly, preaches" untouchability"</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-7.1.list9">
              <listIntroduction>or its practice in any form; or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.1.list9.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>if he justifies, whether on historical, philosophical  or religious grounds or on the ground of any tradition of the  caste system or on any other ground, the practice of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>" untouchability" in any form.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.1A">
          <num>(1A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever commits any offence against the person or property  of any individual as a repraisal or revenge for his having exercised  any right accruing to him by reason of the abolition of</p>
            <p>" untouchability" under article 17 of the Constitution, shall, where  the offence is punishable with imprisonment for a term exceeding two  years, be punishable with imprisonment for a term which shall not be  less than two years and also with fine.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Whoever-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>denies to any person belonging to his community or any  section thereof any right or privilege to which such person  would be entitled as a member of such community or section,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-7.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.2.list3.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>takes any part in the ex- communication of such person,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>on the ground that such person has refused to practise</p>
            <p>" untouchability" or that such person has done any act in  furtherance of the objects of this Act,  shall be  punishable with imprisonment for a term of not less than one  month and not more than six months, and also with fine which  shall be not less than one hundred rupees and not more than  five hundred rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7A">
        <num>7A.</num>
        <heading>Unlawful compulsory labour when to be deemed to be a  practice of untouchability.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever compels any person, on the  ground of" untouchability", to do any scavenging or sweeping or to  remove any carcass or to flay any animal or to remove the umbilical  cord or to do any other job of a similar nature, shall be deemed to  have enforced a disability arising out of" untouchability".</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever is deemed under sub- section (1) to have enforced a  disability arising out of" untouchability" shall be punishable with  imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than three months and  not more than six months and also with fine which shall not be less  than one hundred rupees and not more than five hundred rupees.</p>
            <p>Explanation.- For the purposes of this section," compulsion"</p>
            <p>includes a threat of social or economic boycott.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Cancellation or suspension of licences in certain cases. When a  person who is convicted of an offence under section 6 holds any  licence under any law for the time being in force in respect of any  profession, trade, calling or employment in relation to which the  offence is committed, the court trying the offence may, without  prejudice to any other penalty to which such person may be liable  under that section, direct that the licence shall stand cancelled or  be suspended for such period as the court may deem fit, and every  order of the court so cancelling or suspending a licence shall have  effect as if it had been passed by the authority competent to cancel  or suspend the licence under any such law.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Explanation.- In this section," licence" includes a permit or a  permission.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Resumption or suspension of grants made by Government. Where  the manager or trustee of a place of public worship  or any  educational institution or hostel] which is in receipt of a grant of  land or money from the Government is convicted of an offence under  this Act and such conviction is not reversed or quashed in any appeal  or revision, the Government may, if in its opinion the circumstances  of the case warrant such a course, direct the suspension or resumption  of the whole or any part of such grant.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Abetment of offence. Whoever abets any offence under this Act  shall be punishable with the punishment provided for the offence.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Explanation.- A public servant who wilfully neglects the  investigation of any offence punishable under this Act shall be deemed  to have abetted an offence punishable under this Act.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10A">
        <num>10A.</num>
        <heading>Power of State Government to impose collective fine.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If, after an inquiry in the prescribed manner, the State Government is  satisfied that the inhabitants of an area are concerned in, or  abetting the commission of, any offence punishable under this Act, or  harbouring persons concerned in the commission of such offence or  failing to render all the assistance in their power to discover or  apprehend the offender or offenders or suppressing material evidence  of the commission of such offence, the State Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, impose a collective fine on such  inhabitants and apportion such fine amongst the inhabitants who are  liable collectively</p>
            <p>to pay it, and such apportionment shall be made according to the State</p>
            <p>Government' s judgment of the respective means of such inhabitants and  in making any such apportionment the State Government may assign a  portion of such fine to a Hindu undivided family to be payable by it:</p>
            <p>Provided that the fine apportioned to an inhabitant shall not be  realised until the petition, if any, filed by him under sub- section</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>is disposed of.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The notification made under sub- section (1) shall be  proclaimed in the area by beat of drum or in such other manner as  the State Government may think best in the circumstances to bring the  imposition of the collective fine to the notice of the inhabitants of  the said area.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10A.3.list0">
              <item id="section-10A.3.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>Any person aggrieved by the imposition of the collective  fine under sub- section (1) or by the order of apportionment, may,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>within the prescribed period, file a petition before the State</p>
            <p>Government or such other authority as that Government may specify in  this behalf for being exempted from such fine or for modification of  the order of apportionment:</p>
            <blockList id="section-10A.3.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that no fee shall be charged for filing such petition.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10A.3.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>The State Government or the authority specified by it shall,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>after giving to the petitioner a reasonable opportunity of being  heard, pass such order as it may think fit:</p>
            <p>Provided that the amount of the fine exempted or reduced under  this section shall not be realisable from any person, and the total  fine imposed on the inhabitants of an area under sub- section (1) shall  be deemed to have been reduced to that extent.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10A.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (3), the</p>
            <p>State Government may exempt the victims of any offence punishable  under this Act or any person who does not, in its opinion, fall within  the category of persons specified in sub section (1), from the  liability to pay the collective fine imposed under sub- section (1) or  any portion thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10A.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The portion of collective fine payable by any person</p>
            <p>(including a Hindu undivided family) may be recovered in the manner  provided by the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), for the  recovery of fines imposed by a Court as if such portion were a fine  imposed by a Magistrate.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Enhanced penalty on subsequent conviction. Whoever having  already been convicted of an offence under this Act or of an abetment  of such offence is again convicted of any such offence or abetment,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>shall, on convection, be punishable-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for the second offence, with imprisonment for a term  of not less than six months and not more than one year, and  also</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>with fine which shall be not less than two hundred rupees and  not more than five hundred rupees;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>for the third offence or any offence subsequent to the  third offence, with imprisonment for a term of not less than  one year and not more than two years, and also with fine  which shall be not less than five hundred rupees and not more  than one thousand rupees].</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Presumption by courts in certain cases. Where any act  constituting an offence under this Act is committed in relation to a  member of a Scheduled Caste , the court shall presume,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>unless the contrary is proved, that such act was committed on the  ground of" untouchability".</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Limitation of jurisdiction of civil courts.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No civil  court shall entertain or continue any suit or proceeding or shall  pass any decree or order or execute wholly or partially any decree or  order if the claim involved in such suit or proceeding or if the  passing of such decree or order or if such execution would in any way  be contrary to the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No court shall, in adjudicating any matter or executing any  decree or order, recognise any custom or usage imposing any  disability on any person on the ground of" untouchability".</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Offences by companies.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the person committing an  offence under this Act is a company, every person who at the time the  offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible to, the  company for the conduct of the business of the company, shall be  deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded  against and punished accordingly:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render  any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the  offence was committed without his knowledge or that he exercised all  due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where  an offence under this Act has been committed with the consent of any  director or manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such  director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to  be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against  and punished accordingly.</p>
            <blockList id="section-14.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.2.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm  or other association of individuals; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.2.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" director" in relation to a firm means a partner in the  firm.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14A">
        <num>14A.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No suit,</p>
            <p>prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central</p>
            <p>Government or a State Government for anything which is in good faith  done or intended to be done under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the</p>
            <p>Central Government or a State Government for any damage caused or  likely to be caused by anything which is in good faith done or  intended to be done under this Act.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Offences to be cognizable and triable summarily.</p>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure,</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1973">
        <num>1973.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1973.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>, every offence punishable under this Act shall be 2 cognizable  and every such offence, except where it is punishable with  imprisonment for a minimum term exceeding three months, may be tried  summarily by a Judicial Magistrate of the first class or in a metro-</p>
            <p>politan area by a Metropolitan Magistrate in accordance with the  procedure specified in the said Code.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-1973.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal</p>
            <blockList id="section-1973.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Procedure 1973, when any public servant is alleged to have committed 2  the offence of abetment of an offence punishable under this Act, while  acting or purporting to act in the discharge of his official duty, no  court shall take cognizance of such offence of abetment except with  the previous sanction-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1973.2.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>of the Central Government, in the case of a person  employed in connection with the affairs of the Union; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1973.2.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>of the State Government, in the case of a person  employed in connection with the affairs of a State.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15A">
        <num>15A.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-15A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Duty of State Government to ensure that the rights  accruing from the abolition of" untouchability may be availed of by  the concerned persons. Subject to such rules as the Central Government  may make in this behalf, the State Government shall take such measures  as may be necessary for ensuring that the rights arising from the  abolition of" untouchability" are made available to, and are availed  of by, the persons subjected to any disability arising out of</p>
            <p>" untouchability".</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-15A.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of  the provisions of sub- section (1), such measures may include-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15A.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the provision of adequate facilities, including legal  aid, to the persons subjected to any disability arising out  of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-15A.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>" untouchability" to enable them to avail themselves of such  rights;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15A.2.list3.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>the appointment of officers for initiating or  exercising supervision over prosecutions for the  contravention of the provisions of this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15A.2.list3.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>the setting up of special courts for the trial of  offences under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15A.2.list3.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>the setting up of Committees at such appropriate levels  as the State Government may think fit to assist the State</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-15A.2.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Government in formulating or implementing such measures;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15A.2.list5.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>provision for a periodic survey of the working of the  provisions of this Act with a view to suggesting measures for  the better implementation of the provisions of this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15A.2.list5.vi">
                <num>(vi)</num>
                <p>the identification of the areas where persons are under  any disability arising out of" untouchability" and adoption  of such measures as would ensure the removal of such  disability from such areas.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government shall take such steps as may be  necessary to co- ordinate the measures taken by the State Governments  under sub- section (1).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15A.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government shall, every year, place on the Table  of each House of Parliament, a report on the measures taken by itself  and by the State Governments in pursuance of the provisions of this  section.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Act to override other laws. Save as otherwise expressly  provided in this Act, the provisions of this Act shall have effect  notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained in any other  law for the time being in force, or any custom or usage or any  instrument having effect by virtue of any such law or any decree or  order of any court or other authority.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16A">
        <num>16A.</num>
        <heading>Probation of Offenders Act, 1958, not to apply to persons  above the age of fourteen years. The provisions of the Probation of</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Offenders Act, 1958 (20 of 1958), shall not apply to any person above  the age of fourteen years who is found guilty of having committed any  offence punishable under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16B">
        <num>16B.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-16B.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Power to make rules. The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the  provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16B.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act shall  be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of</p>
            <p>Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty days  which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive  sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately  following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both</p>
            <p>Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses  agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have  effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may  be; so however, that any such modification or annulment shall be  without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under  that rule.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Repeal. The enactments specified in the Schedule are hereby  repealed to the extent to which they or any of the provisions  contained therein correspond or are repugnant to this Act or to any of  the provisions contained therein.</heading>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
