<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1998/13/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1998/13"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The National Institute Of Pharmaceutical Education And Research Act, 1998"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1998/13/eng@1998-06-26/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1998/13/eng@1998-06-26"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1998-06-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1998/13/eng@1998-06-26/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1998/13/eng@1998-06-26"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The National Institute Of Pharmaceutical Education And Research Act, 1998</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>NO. 13 OF 1998</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 26th June, 1998]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- ninth Year of the Republic of</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to declare the institution known as the National Institute of</p>
        <p>Pharmaceutical Education and Research to be an institution of national  importance and to provide for its incorporation and matters connected  therewith.</p>
        <p>India as follows:-</p>
        <p>CHAP</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
        <p>Chapter</p>
        <p>Preliminary</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>National Institute of Pharmaceutical Education and Research Act, 1998.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government  may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint and different  dates may be appointed for different provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Declaration of National Institute of Pharmaceutical Education and</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Research as an institution of national importance.- Whereas the objects  of the institution known as the National Institute of Pharmaceutical</p>
            <p>Education and Research, Sector- 67, S. A. S. Nagar (Mohali), District</p>
            <p>Ropar, Punjab are such as to make the institution one of national  importance, it is hereby declared that the institution known as the</p>
            <p>National Institute of Pharmaceutical Education and Research is an  institution of national importance.</p>
            <p>CHAP</p>
            <p>THE INSTITUTE</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <heading>The Institute.</heading>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Establishment of Institute.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>With effect from such date as the</p>
              <p>Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette,</p>
              <p>appoint, the National Institute of Pharmaceutical Education and</p>
              <p>Research shall be constituted as a body corporate by the name  aforesaid.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Institute shall have perpetual succession and a common seal  with power, subject to the provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold  and dispose of property and to contract, and shall, by that name, sue  and be sued.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-4.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Institute shall consist of the Board of Governors having the  following persons, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>a Chairperson, who shall be an eminent academician, scientist or  technologist or professional, to be nominated by the Visitor;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.3.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the Director of the Institute, ex officio;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.3.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the Joint Secretary, incharge of Pharmaceutical Industries in the  concerned Ministry or Department of the Government of India, ex  officio;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.3.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the Secretary, Technical Education, Government of Punjab,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-4.3.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Chandigarh, ex officio;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.3.list3.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the Financial Adviser of the Ministry or Department of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-4.3.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Government of India dealing with the pharmaceutical industries, ex  officio;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.3.list5.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the Drug Controller General of India, Ministry of Health and</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-4.3.list7">
                <listIntroduction>Family Welfare of the Government of India, ex officio;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.3.list7.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the Member Secretary, All India Council for Technical Education,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-4.3.list9">
                <listIntroduction>ex officio;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.3.list9.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>the Director of any one of the national laboratories of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Council of Scientific and Industrial Research to be nominated by the</p>
              <p>Director General of Council of Scientific and Industrial Research, New</p>
              <blockList id="section-4.3.list13">
                <listIntroduction>Delhi;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.3.list13.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the Director of either the All- India Institute of Medical</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Sciences, New Delhi or the Post- Graduate Institute of Medical</p>
              <p>Education and Research, Chandigarh, to be nominated by rotation by the</p>
              <blockList id="section-4.3.list17">
                <listIntroduction>Ministry of Health and Family Welfare of the Government of ndia;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.3.list17.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>the President, Indian Drugs Manufacturers' Association, ex  officio;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.3.list17.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>the President, Organisation of Pharmaceutical Producers of India,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-4.3.list19">
                <listIntroduction>ex officio;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.3.list19.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>three eminent pharmaceutical experts, one of whom shall be an  educationist, a research scientist and a biotechnologist, to be  nominated by the Central Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.3.list19.m">
                  <num>(m)</num>
                  <p>three eminent public persons or social workers one of whom shall  be either from the Scheduled Castes or the Scheduled Tribes to be  nominated by the Visitor out of a panel prepared by the Central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-4.3.list21">
                <listIntroduction>Government;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.3.list21.n">
                  <num>(n)</num>
                  <p>two pharmaceutical industrialists to be nominated by the Visitor  out of a panel prepared by the Central Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.3.list21.o">
                  <num>(o)</num>
                  <p>three Members of Parliament, two from Lok Sabha to be nominated by  the Speaker of Lok Sabha and one from Rajya Sabha to be nominated by  the Chairman of Rajya Sabha.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The term of office of the Chairperson and Governors other than ex  officio Governors shall be three years and they shall be entitled for  such allowances as may be determined by the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The term of office of Governor nominated to fill a casual vacancy  shall continue for the remainder of the term of the Governor in whose  place he has been nominated.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall meet at least three times in a year at such place  and time and observe such rules of procedure in regard to the  transaction of business at its meetings as may be determined by the</p>
              <p>Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Vesting of properties.- On and from the appointed day, subject to  the other provisions of this Act, all properties which had vested in  the Society, immediately before the commencement of this Act, shall,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>on and from such commencement, vest in the In titute.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Effect of incorporation of Institute.- On and from the appointed  day,-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>any reference to the Society in any contract or other instrument  shall be deemed as a reference to the Institute;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>all the rights and liabilities of the Society shall be transferred  to, and be the rights and liabilities of, the Institute; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>every person employed by the Society immediately before the  appointed day shall hold office or service in the Institute by the  same tenure, at the same remuneration and upon the same terms and  conditions and with the same rights and privileges as to ension,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>leave, gratuity, provident fund and other matters as he would have  held the same if this Act had not been passed, and shall continue to  be so unless and until his employment is terminated or until such  tenure, remuneration and terms and condition are duly altered by the</p>
              <p>Statutes:</p>
              <p>Provided that if the alteration so made is not acceptable to such  employee, his employment may be terminated by the Institute in  accordance with the terms of the contract with the employee or, if no  provision is made therein in this behalf, on payment to him by the</p>
              <p>Institute of compensation equivalent to three months' remuneration in  the case of permanent employee and one month' s remuneration in the  case of other employee.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Functions of Institute.- The functions of the Institute shall be-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list0.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>to nurture and promote quality and excellence in pharmaceutical  education and research;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list0.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>to concentrate on courses leading to master' s degree, doctoral  and post- doctoral courses and research in pharmaceutical education;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list0.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>to hold examinations and grant degrees;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list0.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>to confer honorary awards or other distinctions;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list0.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>to cooperate with educational or other institutions having objects  wholly or partly similar to those of the Institute by exchange of  faculty members and scholars and generally in such manner as may be  conducive to their common objective;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list0.vi">
                  <num>(vi)</num>
                  <p>to conduct courses for teachers, pharmaceutical technologists,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>community and hospital pharmacists and other professionals;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list2.vii">
                  <num>(vii)</num>
                  <p>to collect and maintain world literature on pharmaceutical and  related sciences and technology so as to develop an information centre  of its own kind for other institutions within the country and in the  developing world;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list2.viii">
                  <num>(viii)</num>
                  <p>to create a central faculty of pharmaceutical instrumentation  and analysis for use by the researchers within and outside the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Institute;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list4.ix">
                  <num>(ix)</num>
                  <p>to have a centre to experiment and innovate and to train teachers  and other workers in the art or science of pharmaceutical teaching;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list4.x">
                  <num>(x)</num>
                  <p>to develop a world level centre for creation of new knowledge and  transmission of existing information in pharmaceutical areas, with  focus on national, educational, professional and industrial  commitments;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list4.xi">
                  <num>(xi)</num>
                  <p>to develop a multi- disciplinary approach in carrying out research  and training of pharmaceutical manpower so that the larger interests  of the profession, academia and pharmaceutical industry are better  served and a pharmaceutical work culture is evo ved which is in tune  with the changing world trends and patterns of pharmaceutical  education and research;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list4.xii">
                  <num>(xii)</num>
                  <p>to organise national or international symposia, seminars and  conferences in selected areas of pharmaceutical education, from time  to time;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list4.xiii">
                  <num>(xiii)</num>
                  <p>to arrange courses catering to the special needs of the  developing countries;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list4.xiv">
                  <num>(xiv)</num>
                  <p>to act as a nucleus for interaction between academic and  industry by encouraging exchange of scientist and other technical  staff between the Institute and the industry and by undertaking  sponsored and funded research as well as consultancy projects by the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Institute; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list6.xv">
                  <num>(xv)</num>
                  <p>to pay due attention to studies on the distribution and usage of  drugs by the rural masses, taking into account the socio- economic</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Opectrum in the country.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Powers of Board.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the</p>
              <p>Board shall be responsible for the general superintendence, direction  and control of the affairs of the Institute and shall exercise all the  powers not otherwise provided for by this Act, the Statutes and the</p>
              <p>Ordinances, and shall have the power to review the acts of the Senate.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-8.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Without prejudice to the provisions of sub- section (1), the Board  shall-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>take decisions on questions of policy relating to the  administration and working of the Institute;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>fix, demand and receive fees and other charges;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>supervise and control the residence and regulate the discipline of  students of the Institute and to make arrangements for promoting their  health, general welfare and cultural and corporate life;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>institute academic and other posts and to make appointments  thereto (except in the case of the Director);</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>frame Statutes and Ordinances and to alter, modify or rescind the  same;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.2.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>institute and award fellowship, scholarship, prizes and medals;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.2.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>consider and pass resolutions on the annual report, the annual  accounts and the budget estimates of the Institute for the next  financial year as it thinks fit together with a statement of its  development plans; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.2.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>do all such things as may be necessary, incidental or conducive to  the attainment of all or any of the aforesaid powers.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall have the power to appoint such committees as it  considers necessary for the exercise of its powers and the performance  of its duties under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (2) of section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>, the Board shall not dispose of in any manner any immovable property  without the prior approval of the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Institute to be open to all races, creeds and classes.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The</p>
              <p>Institute shall be open to persons of either sex and of whatever race,</p>
              <p>creed, caste or class, and no test or condition shall be imposed as to  religious belief or profession in admitting or appointing members,</p>
              <p>students, teachers or workers or in any other connection whatsoever.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No bequest, donation or transfer of any property shall be accepted  by the Institute which in the opinion of the Board involves conditions  or obligations opposed to the spirit and object of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Teaching at Institute.- All teaching at the Institute shall be  conducted by or in the name of the Institute in accordance with the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Statutes and the Ordinances made in this behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Visitor.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The President of India shall be the Visitor of the</p>
              <p>Institute.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Visitor may appoint one or more persons to review the work and  progress of the Institute and to hold inquiries into the affairs  thereof and to report thereon in such manner as the Visitor may  direct.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Upon receipt of any such report, the Visitor may take such action  and issue such directions as he considers necessary in respect of any  of the matters dealt with in the report and the Institute shall be  bound to comply with such directions.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Authorities of Institute.- The following shall be the other  authorities of the Institute, namely:-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>a Senate;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>such other authorities as may be declared by the Statutes to be  the authorities of the Institute.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Senate.- The Senate of the Institute shall consist of the  following persons, namely:-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the Director, ex officio, who shall be the Chairperson of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Senate;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the Dean, ex officio;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>five professors of the Institute, to be nominated by the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Chairperson in consultation with the Director, by rotation;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list4.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>three persons, not being employees of the Institute, to be  nominated by the Chairperson in consultation with the Director, from  among educationists of repute, one each from the fields of science,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>engineering and humanities and one of them shall be ei her from the</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-scheduled">
      <doc name="scheduled">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1998/13/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1998/13"/>
              <FRBRalias value="Castes or from the Scheduled Tribes; and"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1998/13/eng@1998-06-26/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1998/13/eng@1998-06-26"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1998/13/eng@1998-06-26/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1998/13/eng@1998-06-26"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduled">
            <paragraph id="scheduled.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <blockList id="scheduled.paragraph-0.list0">
                  <item id="scheduled.paragraph-0.list0.e">
                    <num>(e)</num>
                    <p>such other members of the staff as may be laid down in the</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <p>Statutes.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <section id="section-14">
              <num>14.</num>
              <heading>Functions of Senate.- Subject to the provisions of this Act, the</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Statutes and the Ordinances, the Senate of the Institute shall have  the control and general regulation, and be responsible for the  maintenance of standards of instruction, education and xamination in  the Institute and shall exercise such other powers and perform such  other duties as may be conferred or imposed upon it by the Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-15">
              <num>15.</num>
              <heading>Functions, powers and duties of Chairperson.-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-15.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Chairperson  shall ordinarily preside at the meetings of the Board and at the</p>
                  <p>Convocations of the Institute.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-15.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>It shall be the duty of the Chairperson to ensure that the  decisions taken by the Board are implemented.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-15.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Chairperson shall exercise such other powers and perform such  other duties as may be assigned to him by this Act or the Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-16">
              <num>16.</num>
              <heading>Director.-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-16.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Director of the Institute shall be appointed by  the Board with the prior approval of the Visitor.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-16.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Director shall be the principal academic and executive officer  of the Institute and shall be responsible for the proper  administration and academic performance of the Institute and for  imparting of instruction and maintenance of discipline therein.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-16.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Director shall submit annual reports and accounts to the</p>
                  <p>Board.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-16.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Director shall exercise such other powers and perform such  other duties as may be assigned to him by this Act or the Statutes or  the Ordinances.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-17">
              <num>17.</num>
              <heading>Dean.-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-17.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Dean of the Institute shall be appointed on such  terms and conditions as may be laid down by the Statutes and shall  exercise such powers and perform such duties as may be assigned to him  by this Act or the Statutes or the Director.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-17.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Dean shall report to the Director.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-18">
              <num>18.</num>
              <heading>Registrar.-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-18.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Registrar of the Institute shall be appointed  on such terms and conditions as may be laid down by the Statutes and  shall be the custodian of records, the common seal, the funds of the</p>
                  <p>Institute and such other property of the Instit te as the Board shall  commit to his charge.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-18.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Registrar shall act as the Secretary of the Board, the Senate  and such committees as may be prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-18.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Registrar shall be responsible to the Director for the proper  discharge of his functions.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-18.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Registrar shall exercise such other powers and perform such  other duties as may be assigned to him by this Act or the Statutes or  the Director.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-19">
              <num>19.</num>
              <heading>Powers and duties of other authorities and officers.- The powers  and duties of authorities and officers, other than those hereinbefore  mentioned, shall be determined by the Statutes.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-20">
              <num>20.</num>
              <heading>Grants by Central Government.- For the purpose of enabling the</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Institute to discharge its functions efficiently under this Act, the</p>
                  <p>Central Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by  law in this behalf, pay to the Institute in each financial year such  sums of money and in such manner as it may think fit.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-21">
              <num>21.</num>
              <heading>Fund of Institute.-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-21.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-21.1.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>The Institute shall maintain a Fund to  which shall be credited-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-21.1.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>all moneys provided by the Central Government;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-21.1.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>all fees and other charges;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-21.1.list1.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>all moneys received by the Institute by way of grants, gifts,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-21.1.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>donations, benefactions, bequests or transfers; and</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-21.1.list3.d">
                      <num>(d)</num>
                      <p>all moneys received by the Institute in any other manner or from  any other source.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-21.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>All moneys credited to the Fund shall be deposited in such banks  or invested in such manner as the Institute may, with the approval of  the Central Government, decide.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-21.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Fund shall be applied towards meeting the expenses of the</p>
                  <p>Institute including expenses incurred in the exercise of its powers  and discharge of its duties under this Act.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-22">
              <num>22.</num>
              <heading>Setting up of endowment fund.- Notwithstanding anything contained  in section 21, the Central Government may direct the Institute to-</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-22.paragraph-0.list0">
                    <item id="section-22.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>set up an endowment fund and any other fund for specified purpose;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-22.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>transfer money from its Fund to endowment fund or any other fund.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-23">
              <num>23.</num>
              <heading>Accounts and audit.-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-23.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Institute shall maintain proper  accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual statement of  accounts, including the balance- sheet, in such form as may be  specified, in accordance with such general directions as ay be issued  by the Central Government in consultation with the Comptroller and</p>
                  <p>Auditor- General of India.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-23.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The accounts of the Institute shall be audited by the Comptroller  and Auditor- General of India and any expenditure incurred by him in  connection with such audit shall be payable by the Institute to the</p>
                  <p>Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-23.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any person  appointed by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the</p>
                  <p>Institute shall have the same rights, privileges and authority in  connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Audit r- General of</p>
                  <p>India has in connection with the audit of the Government accounts,</p>
                  <p>and, in particular, shall have the right to demand the production of  books, accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and  to inspect the offices of the Inst tute.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-23.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The accounts of the Institute as certified by the Comptroller and</p>
                  <p>Auditor- General of India or any other person appointed by him in this  behalf together with the audit report thereon shall be forwarded  annually to the Central Government and that Gover ment shall cause the  same to be laid before each House of Parliament.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-24">
              <num>24.</num>
              <heading>Pension and provident fund.-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-24.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Institute shall constitute,</p>
                  <p>for the benefit of its employees, including the Director, in such  manner and subject to such conditions as may be prescribed by the</p>
                  <p>Statutes, such pension, insurance and provident funds s it may deem  fit.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-24.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where any such provident fund has been so constituted, the Central</p>
                  <p>Government may declare that the provisions of the Provident Funds Act,</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-1925">
              <num>1925.</num>
              <heading>(19 of 1925) shall apply to such fund as if it were a Government  provident fund.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-25">
              <num>25.</num>
              <heading>Appointments.- All appointments of the staff of the Institute,</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-25.paragraph-0.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>except that of the Director, shall be made in accordance with the  procedure laid down in the Statutes-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>by the Board, if the appointment is made on the academic staff in  the post of Assistant Professor or above or if the appointment is made  on the non- academic staff in any cadre, the maximum of the pay- scale  for which is the same or higher than that of Assistant Professor; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>by the Director, in any other case.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-26">
              <num>26.</num>
              <heading>Statutes.- Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Statutes may  provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:-</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-26.paragraph-0.list0">
                    <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the formation of departments of teaching;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>the institution of fellowships, scholarships, exhibitions, medals  and prizes;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>the classification, the method of appointment and the  determination of the terms and conditions of service of officers,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-26.paragraph-0.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>teachers and other staff of the Institute;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                      <num>(d)</num>
                      <p>the reservation of posts for the Scheduled Castes, the Scheduled</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Tribes and other categories of persons as may be determined by the</p>
                  <blockList id="section-26.paragraph-0.list5">
                    <listIntroduction>Central Government, from time to time;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list5.e">
                      <num>(e)</num>
                      <p>the constitution of pension, insurance and provident funds for the  benefit of the officers, teachers and other staff of the Institute;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list5.f">
                      <num>(f)</num>
                      <p>the constitution, powers and duties of the authorities of the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-26.paragraph-0.list7">
                    <listIntroduction>Institute;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list7.g">
                      <num>(g)</num>
                      <p>the establishment and maintenance of halls and hostels;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list7.h">
                      <num>(h)</num>
                      <p>the manner of filling vacancies among members of the Board;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list7.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>the authentication of the orders and decisions of the Board;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list7.j">
                      <num>(j)</num>
                      <p>the meetings of the Senate, the quorum at such meetings and the  procedure to be followed in the conduct of their business; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list7.k">
                      <num>(k)</num>
                      <p>any other matter which by this Act is to be, or may be, prescribed  by the Statutes.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-27">
              <num>27.</num>
              <heading>Statutes how made.-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-27.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The first Statutes of the Institute shall  be framed by the Board with the previous approval of the Visitor and a  copy of the same shall be laid as soon as may be before each House of</p>
                  <p>Parliament.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-27.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Board may, from time to time, make new or additional Statutes  or may amend or repeal the Statutes in the manner hereafter in this  section provided.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-27.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A new Statute or addition to the Statutes or any amendment or  repeal of a Statute shall require the previous approval of the Visitor  who may assent thereto or withhold assent or remit it to the Board for  consideration.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-27.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A new Statute or a Statute amending or repealing an existing</p>
                  <p>Statute shall have no validity unless it has been assented to by the</p>
                  <p>Visitor.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-28">
              <num>28.</num>
              <heading>Ordinances.- Subject to the provisions of this Act and the</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-28.paragraph-0.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>Statutes, the Ordinances of the Institute may provide for all or any  of the following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-28.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the admission of the students to the Institute;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-28.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>the reservation for the Scheduled Castes, the Scheduled Tribes and  other categories of person;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-28.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>the courses of study to be laid down for all degrees of the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-28.paragraph-0.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>Institute;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-28.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                      <num>(d)</num>
                      <p>the conditions under which students shall be admitted to the  degree courses and to the examinations of the Institute and shall be  eligible for degrees;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-28.paragraph-0.list3.e">
                      <num>(e)</num>
                      <p>the conditions of award of the fellowships, scholarships,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-28.paragraph-0.list5">
                    <listIntroduction>exhibitions, medals and prizes;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-28.paragraph-0.list5.f">
                      <num>(f)</num>
                      <p>the conditions and mode of appointment and duties of examining  bodies, examiners and moderators;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-28.paragraph-0.list5.g">
                      <num>(g)</num>
                      <p>the conduct of examinations;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-28.paragraph-0.list5.h">
                      <num>(h)</num>
                      <p>the maintenance of discipline among the students of the Institute;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-28.paragraph-0.list5.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>the fees to be charged for courses of study in the Institute and  for admission to the examinations of degrees of the Institute;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-28.paragraph-0.list5.j">
                      <num>(j)</num>
                      <p>the conditions of residence of students of the Institute and the  levying of the fees for residence in the halls and hostels and of  other charges; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-28.paragraph-0.list5.k">
                      <num>(k)</num>
                      <p>any other matter which by this Act or the Statutes is to be, or  may be, provided for by the Ordinances.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-29">
              <num>29.</num>
              <heading>Ordinances how made.-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-29.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Save as otherwise provided in this  section, Ordinances shall be made by the Senate.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-29.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>All Ordinances made by the Senate shall have effect from such date  as it may direct, but every Ordinance so made shall be submitted, as  soon as may be, to the Board and shall be considered by the Board at  its next succeeding meeting.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-29.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Board shall have power by resolution to modify or cancel any  such Ordinances and such Ordinances shall from the date of such  resolution stand modified accordingly or cancelled, as the case may  be.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-30">
              <num>30.</num>
              <heading>Tribunal of Arbitration.-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-30.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Any dispute arising out of a  contract between the Institute and any of its employees shall, at the  request of the employee concerned or at the instance of the Institute,</p>
                  <p>be referred to a Tribunal of Arbitration consisting of one member  appointed by the Institute, one member nominated by the employee, and  an umpire appointed by the Visitor.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-30.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The decision of the Tribunal of Arbitration shall be final and  shall not be questioned in any court.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-30.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>No suit or proceeding shall lie in any court in respect of any  matter which is required by sub- section (1) to be referred to the</p>
                  <p>Tribunal of Arbitration.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-30.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Tribunal of Arbitration shall have power to regulate its own  procedure.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-30.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Nothing in any law for the time being in force relating to  arbitration shall apply to arbitrations under this section.</p>
                  <p>CHAP</p>
                  <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <chapter id="chapter-III">
              <num>III</num>
              <heading>Miscellaneous</heading>
              <section id="section-31">
                <num>31.</num>
                <heading>Acts and proceedings not to be invalidated by vacancies.- No act  of the Institute or Board or Senate or any other body set up under  this Act or the Statutes, shall be invalid merely by reason of-</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-31.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-31.paragraph-0.list0">
                      <item id="section-31.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>any vacancy in, or defect in, the constitution thereof, or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-31.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>any defect in the election, nomination or appointment of person  acting as a member thereof, or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-31.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>any irregularity in its procedure not affecting the merits of the  case.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-32">
                <num>32.</num>
                <heading>Grant of degrees, etc., by Institute.- Notwithstanding anything  contained in the University Grants Commission Act, 1956 (3 of 1956) or  in any other law for the time being in force, the Institute shall have  power to grant degrees and other academic dis inctions and titles  under this Act.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-33">
                <num>33.</num>
                <heading>Sponsored schemes.- Whenever the Institute receives funds from any</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-33.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-33.paragraph-0.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>Government, the University Grants Commission or any other agency  sponsoring a scheme to be executed by the Institute, notwithstanding  anything in this Act,-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-33.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>the amount received shall be kept by the Institute separately from  the Fund of the Institute and utilised only for the purpose of the  scheme;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-33.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>the staff required to execute the same shall be recruited in  accordance with the terms and conditions stipulated by the sponsoring  organisation:</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Provided that any money remaining unutilised under clause (a) shall be  transferred to the endowment fund created under section 22 of this</p>
                    <p>Act.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-34">
                <num>34.</num>
                <heading>Power to remove difficulties.-</heading>
                <subsection id="section-34.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>If any difficulty arises in  giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government  may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions  or give such directions not inconsistent with the rovisions of this</p>
                    <p>Act, as appears to it to be necessary or expedient for removing the  difficulty:</p>
                    <p>Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of two  years from the appointed day.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-34.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every order made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may  be after it is made, before each House of Parliament.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-35">
                <num>35.</num>
                <heading>Transitional provisions.- Notwithstanding anything contained in  this Act,-</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-35.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-35.paragraph-0.list0">
                      <item id="section-35.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>the Board of Governors of the Society functioning as such  immediately before the commencement of this Act shall continue to so  function until a new Board is constituted for the Institute under this</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-35.paragraph-0.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>Act, but on the constitution of a new Board under th s Act, the  members of the Board holding office before such constitution shall  cease to hold office;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-35.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>until the first Statutes and the Ordinances are made under this</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Act, the Statutes and the Ordinances of the National Institute of</p>
                    <blockList id="section-35.paragraph-0.list5">
                      <listIntroduction>Pharmaceutical Education and Research, Sector- 67, S. A. S. Nagar</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-35.paragraph-0.list5.Mohali">
                        <num>(Mohali)</num>
                        <p>, District Ropar, Punjab as in force, immediately before the  commencement of this Act, shall continue to apply to the Institute in  so far as they are not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-36">
                <num>36.</num>
                <heading>Statutes and Ordinances to be published in the Official Gazette  and to be laid before Parliament.-</heading>
                <subsection id="section-36.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every Statute or Ordinance made  under this Act shall be published in the Official Gazette.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-36.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every Statute or Ordinance made under this Act shall be laid, as  soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament,</p>
                    <p>while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be  comprised in one session or in two or more succe sive sessions, and  if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session  or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the Statute or Ordinance or both Houses agree that the</p>
                    <p>Statute or Ordinance sh uld not be made, the Statute or Ordinance  shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no  effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification  or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previous y done under that Statute or Ordinance.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-36.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The power to make the Statutes or the Ordinances shall include the  power to give retrospective effect from a date not earlier than the  date of commencement of this Act to the Statutes or the Ordinances or  any of them but no retrospective effect shall be given to any Statute  or Ordinance so as to prejudicially affect the interests of any person  to whom such Statute or Ordinance may be applicable.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-37">
                <num>37.</num>
                <heading>Repeal and saving.-</heading>
                <subsection id="section-37.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The National Institute of Pharmaceutical</p>
                    <p>Education and Research Ordinance, 1998 is hereby repealed.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-37.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken  under the said Ordinance, shall be deemed to have been done or taken  under this Act.</p>
                    <p>RAGHBIR SINGH, Secy. to the Govt. of India</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
            </chapter>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
