<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1991/11/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1991/11"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Chief Election Commissioner And Other Election Commissioners (Conditions Of Service) Act, 1991"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1991/11/eng@1991-01-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1991/11/eng@1991-01-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1991-01-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1991/11/eng@1991-01-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1991/11/eng@1991-01-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Chief Election Commissioner And Other Election Commissioners (Conditions Of Service) Act, 1991</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>NO. 11 OF 1991</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 25th January, 1991.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- first Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to determine the conditions of service of the Chief Election</p>
        <p>Commissioner and other Election Commissioners  and to provide for  the procedure for transaction of business by the Election Commission  and for matters"] connected therewith or incidental thereto.</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:-</p>
        <p>CHAP</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title. This Act may be called the  the Election</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Commission (Conditions of Service of Election Commissioners and</p>
              <p>Transaction of Business)"] Act, 1991.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" Chief Election Commissioner" means the Chief Election</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Commissioner appointed under article 324 of the Constitution;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" Election Commission" means the Election Commission  referred to in article 324 of the Constitution;'.]</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>]" Election Commissioner" means any other Election</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Commissioner appointed under article 324 of the Constitution.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>SALARY AND OTHER CONDITIONS OF SERVICE OF THE CHIEF</p>
              <p>ELECTIONCOMMISSIONER AND ELECTION COMMISSIONERS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>SALARY AND OTHER CONDITIONS OF SERVICE OF THE CHIEF ELECTION</p>
            <p>COMMISSIONER AND ELECTION COMMISSIONERS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Salary.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>There shall be paid to the Chief Election</p>
              <p>Commissioner a salary which is equal to the salary of a Judge of the</p>
              <p>Supreme Court.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>There shall be paid to an Election Commissioner a salary  which is equal to the salary of a Judge of a High Court:</p>
              <p>Provided that if a person who, immediately before the date of  assuming office as the Chief Election Commissioner or, as the case may  be, an Election Commissioner, was in receipt of, or, being eligible so  to do, had election to draw, a pension (other than a disability or   wound pension) in respect of any previous service under the Government  of the Union or under the Government of a State, his salary in respect  of service as the</p>
              <p>Chief Election Commissioner or, as the case may be, an Election</p>
              <blockList id="section-3.2.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Commissioner shall be reduced--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.2.list4.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>by the amount of that pension; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.2.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>if he had, before assuming office, received, in lieu of  a portion of the pension due to him in respect of such previous  service, the commuted value thereof, by the amount of that  portion of the pension.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Term of office. The Chief Election Commissioner or an Election</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Commissioner shall hold office for a term of six years from the date  on which he assumes his office:</p>
              <p>Provided that where the Chief Election Commissioner or an</p>
              <p>Election Commissioner attains the age of sixty- five years before the  expiry of the said term of six years, he shall vacate his office on  the date on which he attains the said age:".]</p>
              <p>Provided further that the Chief Election Commissioner or an</p>
              <p>Election Commissioner may, at any time, by writing under his hand  addressed to the President, resign his office.</p>
              <p>Explanation.-- For the purpose of this section, the term of six  years in respect of the Chief Election Commissioner or an Election</p>
              <p>Commissioner holding office immediately before the commencement of  this Act, shall be computed from the date on which he had assumed  office.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Leave.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A person who, immediately before the date of  assuming office as the Chief Election Commissioner or an Election</p>
              <p>Commissioner, was in service of Government may be granted during his  tenure of office but not thereafter, leave in accordance with the  rules for the time being applicable to the Service to which he  belonged before such date and he shall be entitled to carry forward  the amount of leave standing at his credit on such date,</p>
              <p>notwithstanding anything contained in section 6.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any other person who is appointed as the Chief Election</p>
              <p>Commissioner or an Election Commissioner may be granted leave in  accordance with such rules as are for the time being applicable to a  member of the Indian Administrative Service.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The power to grant or refuse leave to the Chief Election</p>
              <p>Commissioner or an Election Commissioner and to revoke or curtail  leave granted to him, shall vest in the President.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Pension payable to Election Commissioners.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A person who,</p>
              <p>immediately before the date of assuming office as the Chief Election</p>
              <p>Commissioner or an Election Commissioner was in service of Government,</p>
              <p>shall be deemed to have retired from service on the date on which he  enters upon office as the Chief Election Commissioner or an Election</p>
              <p>Commissioner but his subsequent service as the Chief Election</p>
              <p>Commissioner or an Election Commissioner shall be reckoned as  continuing approved service counting for pension in Service to which  he belonged.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-6.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Where the Chief Election Commissioner demits office whether  in any manner specified in sub- section (4) or by resignation, he  shall, on such demission be entitled to--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>a pension which is equal to the pension payable to a</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Judge of the Supreme Court in accordance with the provisions of</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <part id="chapter-II.part-III">
          <num>III</num>
          <heading>of the Schedule to the Supreme Court Judges (Conditions   of Service) Act, 1958, (41 of 1958.) as amended from time to  time; and</heading>
          <paragraph id="chapter-II.part-III.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="chapter-II.part-III.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="chapter-II.part-III.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>such pension (including commutation of pension), family  pension and gratuity as are admissible to a Judge of the Supreme</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Court under the said Act and the rules made thereunder, as  amended from time to time.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="chapter-II.part-III.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>] Except where the Chief Election Commissioner or an</p>
              <p>Election Commissioner demits office by resignation, he shall be  deemed, for the purpose of this Act, to have demitted his office if,</p>
              <blockList id="chapter-II.part-III.3.list3">
                <listIntroduction>and only if,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="chapter-II.part-III.3.list3.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>he has completed the term of office specified in section</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <section id="section-4">
            <num>4.</num>
            <heading/>
            <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>, or</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>he has attained the age of sixty- five years,  xxx or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <p>his demission of office is medically certified to be  necessitated by ill- health.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </section>
          <section id="section-7">
            <num>7.</num>
            <heading>Right to subscribe to General Provident Fund. Every person  holding office as the Chief Election Commissioner or an Election</heading>
            <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>Commissioner shall be entitled to subscribe to the General Provident</p>
                <p>Fund (Central Services).</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </section>
          <section id="section-8">
            <num>8.</num>
            <heading>Other conditions of service. Save as otherwise provided in  this Act, the conditions of service relating to travelling allowance,</heading>
            <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>provision of rent- free residence and exemption from payment of income-</p>
                <p>tax on the value of such rent- free residence, conveyance facilities,</p>
                <p>sumptuary allowance, medical facilities and such other conditions of  service as are,  for the time being, applicable to a Judge of the</p>
                <p>Supreme Court under Chapter IV of the Supreme Court Judges (Conditions   of Service) Act, 1958 (41 of 1958) and the rules made thereunder,</p>
                <p>shall, so far as may be, apply to the Chief Election Commissioner and  other Election Commissioners"]</p>
                <p>CHAP</p>
                <p>TRANSACTION OF BUSINESS OF ELECTION COMMISSION</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </section>
        </part>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>TRANSACTION OF BUSINESS OF ELECTION COMMISSION]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Transaction of business of Election Commission. The business  of the Election Commission shall be transacted in accordance with the  provisions of this Act.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Disposal of business by Election Commission.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Election</p>
              <p>Commission may, by unanimous decision, regulate the procedure for  transaction of its business as also allocation of its business amongst  the Chief Election Commissioner and other Election Commissioners.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Save as provided in sub- section (1), all business of the</p>
              <p>Election Commission shall, as far as possible, be transacted  unanimously.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (2), if the Chief</p>
              <p>Election Commissioner and other Election Commissioners differ in  opinion on any matter, such matter shall be decided according to the  opinion of the majority."]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
