<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-wbg/act/2007/24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-wbg/act/2007/24"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The West Bengal Unorganised Sector Workers Welfare Act, 2007"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-wbg/act/2007/24/eng@2017-06-06/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-wbg/act/2007/24/eng@2017-06-06"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-06-06" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-wbg/act/2007/24/eng@2017-06-06/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-wbg/act/2007/24/eng@2017-06-06"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-06-06" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The West Bengal Unorganised Sector Workers Welfare Act, 2007</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[Act XXIV of 2007]</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for social security and welfare of certain unorganised sector workers and to provide other measures connected therewith or incidental thereto.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for social security measures and welfare schemes with a view to improving the standard of living and to ameliorate the social conditions of certain unorganised sector workers;</p>
        <p>It is hereby enacted in the Fifty-eighth Year of the Republic of India, by the Legislature of West Bengal, as follows :—</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <heading>Preliminary</heading>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the West Bengal Unorganised Sector Workers Welfare Act, 2007.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It extends to the whole of West Bengal.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on such date as the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint, provided, however, that different dates may be appointed for different provisions of this Act and for different employments mentioned in the Schedule appended to this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Non-application of the Act.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>This Act shall not apply to any person who receives any benefit under the Employees' Provident Funds and Miscellaneous Provisions Act, 1952.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>"beneficiary" means an Unorganised Sector Worker registered under section 15;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>"Board" means the West Bengal Unorganised Sector Workers Welfare Board constituted under sub-section (I) of section 4;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>"Family" means and includes the Unorganised Sector Worker, his or her spouse and minor legitimate, illegitimate and adopted children dependent upon the beneficiary, and his or her dependent parents;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>"Fund" means a fund constituted under sub-section (1) of section 11;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>"Notification" means a notification published in the Official Gazette;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>"Prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>"Schedule" means a Schedule to this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>"Scheme" means a scheme introduced under sub-section (1) of section 9;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>"Self-employed person" means any person who is not employed by any employer by directly engaged in any occupation specified in Part B of the Schedule relating to unorganised Sector subject to a monthly earning with such a limit as the State Government may, by notification, declare;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>"Unorganised Sector" means the Unorganised Sector specified in Part A and Part B of the Schedule and includes any process or branch of work forming a part of such Unorganised Sector;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>"Unorganised Sector Worker" means a wage earner and also includes a self-employed person in the Unorganised Sector;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>"Wage" means a remuneration paid, directly by the employer or through any agency or contractor whether exclusively by one employer or more employers, in cash or in kind to any unorganised sector worker with such monthly limit as the State Government may, from time to time, notify.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <heading>Board, Executive Council, Fund and Schemes.</heading>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Constitution of the Board and the terms and conditions of appoint-ment, and salaries and allowances payable to the Chairman, Vice-Chairman, and other members of the Board.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute a Board to be called "The West Bengal Unorganised Workers Welfare Board" for the purpose of administering the "Fund" created herein and for implementing the schemes introduced under this Act:</p>
              <p>Provided that the State Government may set up regional offices under the Board for the purpose of implementing the objects of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall be a body corporate with perpetual succession and a common seal and shall sue and be sued by the name of the West Bengal Unorganised Workers Welfare Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall consist of a Chairperson and a Vice-Chairperson to be nominated by the State Government and such number of other members representing the employers, the unorganised sector workers and shall include other officials of the Government, as the State Government may, by order, decide.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may appoint an officer of the Labour Department as the Secretary of the Board, who shall not be a member of the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The terms and conditions of the appointment and the salaries and other allowances payable the Chairperson, the Vice-Chairperson and the other members of the Board and the manner of filling of casual vacancies by reason of death, resignation or inability to discharge functions owing to illness or other incapacity or for and other reason by, the Chairperson, the Vice-Chairperson and the other members of the Board shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Officers and employees to be appointed by the Board and their terms and conditions of appointment.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall, with the approval of the State Government, appoint its own officers and employees as it considers necessary for the efficient discharge of its functions under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The terms and conditions of appointment and the salary and other allowances payable to the officers and employees of the Board shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Meetings of the Board.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall meet at such time and places, and shall observe such rules of procedures in regard to the transaction of business at its meetings (including the quorum) as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chairperson shall preside over the meeting of the Board. If for any reason, the Chairperson is unable to attend the meeting of the Board, the Vice-Chairperson shall preside over the meeting.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All questions which come up before a meeting of the Board shall be decided by majority of votes of the members present and in the event of equality of votes, the chairperson or in his absence, the Vice Chairperson presiding shall have a second or a casting vote.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Vacancies amongst members or defect in Constitution not to invalidate acts or proceedings of the Board.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>No act or proceeding of the Board shall be deemed to be invalid by reason of—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>any vacancy in or any defect in the Constitution of the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>any defect in the appointment of a person acting as a Chairperson, the Vice-Chairperson and the members of the Board; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>any irregularity in the procedure of the Board not affecting the merit of the case.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Executive Council.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall function through an Executive Council set up by it.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-8.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Executive Council set up under sub-section (1) shall consist of—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>a Chairperson to be nominated by the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>and Officer of the State Government not below the rank of Joint Secretary to that Government as Chief Executive Officier of the Board who shall be the Member-Secretary of the Executive Council;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>a person to be nominated by the Board having expertise in Banking transactions; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>a person to be nominated by the Board having expertise in audit and accounts.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Scheme—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-9.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Board may introduce—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-9.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>any Health Insurance Scheme and Accident Insurance Scheme for the beneficiaries;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>any scheme for providing pension to the beneficiaries who have completed the age of sixty years and to the members of the family in case the beneficiary dies;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>any scheme for house building loans and advance to the beneficiaries;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>any scheme to provide financial assistance for education of the children of the beneficiaries;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.1.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>any scheme to provide maternity benefit to the female beneficiaries;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.1.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>any scheme to provide such other welfare measures and facilities as may be decided by the Board with the approval of the State Government.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The existing schemes run under the direct financial assistance by the State Government, shall, henceforth, be taken over by, and transferred to, the Board. The State Government shall transfer all the accumulated fund under the existing schemes (including the employees' contributions and the Government contributions therein) to the Board on a date to be notified by the State Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every scheme introduced under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before the State Legislature.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>State Government to provide grants and loans to the Board.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, after due appropriation made by the State Legislature by law in this behalf, make to the Board grants and loans of such sums of money as the State Government may consider necessary.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Fund of the Board.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-11.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>There shall be constituted by the Board a fund to be called "the West Bengal Unorganised Sector Workers Welfare Fund" and there shall be credited thereto—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>any grants and loans made to the Board by the State Government under section 10;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>all the contributions made by the beneficiaries;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>contributions by the employers, if any;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>all sums received by the Board from such other sources as may be</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>determined by the State Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-11.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Fund shall be applied for meeting—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the expenses of the Board in discharge of its function under section 9;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>Salaries, allowances and other remuneration of the Chairperson, the Vice-Chairperson, members, officers and other employees of the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the expenses to be incurred for the accomplishment of the objects and for the purposes authorized by this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall incur, in any financial year, expenditure towards salaries, allowances and other remuneration to its Chairperson, Vice-Chairperson, members, officers and other employees and for meeting the other administrative expenses within such limits as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Budget.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall prepare, in such form and at such time of each financial year as may prescribed, its budget for the next financial year showing the estimated receipts and expenditure of the Board and forward the same to the State Government.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Annual report.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-13.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall prepare in every financial year, in such form and at such time as may be prescribed, an annual report giving a full account of its activities during the previous financial year and a copy thereof shall be forwarded to the State Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government shall cause the annual report to be laid, as soon as may be after its receipt, before the State Legislature.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Accounts and Audit.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall cause to be maintained such books of account and other books and records in relation to its accounts, and prepare an annual Statement of accounts, in such form and in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The accounts of the board shall be audited by a person or agency authorised by the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (2), the accounts of the Board shall be audited annualy by the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India and any expenditure incurred by him in connection with such audit shall be payable by the Board to the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Comptroller and Auditor-General of India and any person appointed by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the Board under this Act shall have the same rights and privileges .and authority in connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor General has, in connection with the audit of Government accounts, and in particular, shall have the right to demand the production of books, accounts, Connected Vouchers, documents and papers and inspect any of the offices of the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall furnish to the State Government on such date as may be prescribed its audited copy of accounts together with the Auditor's report.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government shall cause the annual report and Auditors report to be laid, as soon as may be after their receipt, before the State Legislature.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <heading>Registration of Unorganised Sector Workers as Beneficiaries.</heading>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Registration of Unorgnised Sector Worker.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-15.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every Unorganised Sector Worker who has completed eighteen years of age but has not complete sixty years of age, shall be eligible for registration as a beneficiary under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An application for registration shall be made in such form, as may be prescribed along with the fees for registration not exceeding twenty rupees, to the officer authorized by the Board in this behalf:</p>
              <p>Provided that every Unorganised Sector Worker who have already been enrolled in the scheme under the assistance of the State Government shall be deemed to be registered as a beneficiary under this Act and they do not need to make any fresh application for registration.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the Board may decide upon the fees for registration within the limits specified in sub-section (2).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the officer authorised by the Board is satisfied that the applicant has complied with the provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder, he shall register the name of the Unorganised Sector Worker as beneficiary under this Act :</p>
              <p>Provided that an application for registration cannot be rejected without giving the applicant an opportunity of being heard.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person aggrieved by the decision under sub-section (4) may, within thirty days from the date of such decision, prefer and appeal to the Chief Executive Officer of the Board, or any other officier specified by the Board in this behalf and the decision of the Chief Executive Officer or such other officer on such appeal shall be final :</p>
              <p>Provided that the Chief Executive Officer, or other officier specified by the Board in this behalf, may entertain an appeal after the expiry of the said period of thirty days if he is satisfied that the Unorganised Sector Worker was prevented by sufficient cause for filling the appeal in time.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chief Executive Officier of the Board shall cause to maintain a register of the beneficiaries and such other registers as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall give to every beneficiary an identity card with his photograph duly affixed thereon with necessary entries about the details of the beneficiary.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A beneficiary who has been issued an identity card under this Act shall present the same whenever demanded by any officer of the Government or of the Board, for inspection.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Cessation as beneficiary.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-16.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An Unorganised Sector Worker who has been registered as a beneficiary under this Act shall cease to be as such when he dies and when he attains the age of sixty years or when he is not engaged in the occupation of, or in the employment of, the Unorganised Sector or when he voluntarily expresses his intention, in writing, to the Registration Officer that he is not to be governed by or under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), if a person had been a beneficiary for at least five years continuously immediately before attaining the age of sixty years, he shall be eligible to get the benefit of pension under section 9 and such other benefits as may be prescribed subject to the provision of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <heading>Registration of Establishment.</heading>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Registration of Establishment.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-17.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The State Government may, on the recommendation of the Board, by an order notified in the Official Gazette—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>require every employer in respect of Unorganised Sector to get his establishment, as is specified in Part A of the Schedule, registered under this Act, with such registration fees and with such monthly contribution or annual contribution to the fund of the Board, as may be prescribed; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>appoint such number of persons being officers of the State Government, as it thinks fit, as Registering Officers for the purpose of this section and define the limits within which a Registering Officer shall exercise his powers conferred on him by or under this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Application for registration.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-18.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every employer shall, in relation to an establishment in respect of which a notification has been issued by the State Government under clause (a) of section 17, within a period of sixty days from such notification, make an application to the Registering Officer for the Registering of such establishment:</p>
              <p>Provided that the Registering Officer may entertain any such application after the expiry of the said period of sixty days, if he is satisfied that the applicant is prevented by sufficient cause from making the application within the stipulated period.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every application under sub-section (1) shall be in such form and contain such particulars as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>After receipt of an application under sub-section (1), the Registering Officer shall register the establishment and issue certificate of registration of the establishment to the employer thereof in such form an within such time subject to such conditions as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <heading>Inspection</heading>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Inspectors.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-19.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint any person in the employment of the State Government or of the Board to be Inspectors for the purposes of this Act and define the local limits within which they will exercise their powers under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-19.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Subject to any rules made under this Act, and Inspector appointed under sub-section (1) may, within the local limit for which he is appointed—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-19.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>enter, at any reasonal time and with such assistance may be deemed necessary viz. with the assistance of the persons in the service of the Board or any legal authority or public authority as he thinks fit, in the premises or place where any trade or business connected with the Unorganised Sector is carried on, for the purpose of examining any record, register etc. and require the production thereof for inspection;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>examine any person whom he finds in any such premises or place and who, he has reasonable cause to believe, is a worker employed therein;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>require any person in charge of the premises at the time of inspection to give information regarding names and address of the workers employed therein and also such other information in connection with, and relevant to, the provisions of this Act or schemes or rules made thereunder;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>seize or take copies of register, record of wages or any other documents or portions thereof as he may consider relevant in respect of an offence in this Act which, he has reason to believe, has been committed by an employer; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>exercise such other powers as may be prescribed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person who is required to produce any document or to furnish any information required by an Inspector under sub-section (2), shall be bound to do so.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973, shall, so far as may be, apply to any search or seizure under sub-section (2) as they apply to any search or seizure made under an authority of a warrant issued under section 94 of the said Code.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VI">
        <num>VI</num>
        <heading>Penalties And Prosecution.</heading>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Offence and penalties.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-20.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-20.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Any person, who wilfully obstructs an Inspector in the exercise of his powers or discharge of his duties under this Act, or intentionally omits to produce or deliver up, for inspection on demand by an Inspector appointed under this Act, any register, records or other documents, or intentionally omits to furnish any information required under this Act shall, on conviction be punished—</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-20.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>for the first offence, with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three months or with a fine which may extend to one thousand rupees or with both; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-20.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>for second and subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months or with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If an employer of the Unorganised Sector fails to get his establishment registered under this Act or fails to pay and contribution which under this Act he is liable to pay shall, on conviction, be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year or with a fine which may extend to five thousand rupees, or with both;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Previous Sanction of the State Government necessary.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No prosecution shall be instituted against any person in respect of any offence under this Act without the previous sanction of the State Government.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VII">
        <num>VII</num>
        <heading>Miscellaneous</heading>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-22.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, after previous publication, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before the State Legislature.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Power to amend Schedule.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Government, after giving by notification in the Official Gazette not less than three months' notice of its intention so to do, may, by like notification, add to either part of the Schedule any employment to be covered under this Act and thereupon the Schedule shall be deemed to be amended accordingly.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Directions by the State Government.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may give the Board such directions as in its opinion are necessary or expedient in connection with expenditure from the fund or for carrying out any of the purpose of this Act and it shall be the duty of the Board to comply with such directions.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Powers of the Board.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Board may introduce any scheme for the Unorganised Sector Workers under section 9 with such conditions as may be incorporated in the scheme regarding the rate of contribution by the beneficiary, the mode and the manner of deposit, collection or contribution made by the beneficiary, forfeiture of the right of the beneficiary under such circumstances as may be incorporated in the scheme, deposit of the employers' contribution, if any, to the fund by the employer, maintenance of necessary forms and registers, for any scheme and nomination of the beneficiary.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Chairperson, Vice-Chairperson, Members, Officers, and employees to be public servants.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Chairperson, the Vice-Chairperson, the members, and all the Officers and other employees including the Chief Executive Officers shall, while acting, or purporting to act, in pursuance of, or in exercise of any power conferred by or under, any provision of this Act or the rules made thereunder, to be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code, 1860.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Protection for acts done in good faith.—</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No suit or other Legal Proceedings shall lie against any person in respect of anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Power to remove difficulties.—</heading>
          <subsection id="section-28.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the State Government may make such order, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as appears to it to be necessary or expedient for the removal of the difficulty:</p>
              <p>Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a period of three years from the date of commencement of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-28.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every order made under sub-section (1) shall, as soon as may be after it is made, be laid before the State Legislature.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-theschedule">
      <doc name="theschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-wbg/act/2007/24/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-wbg/act/2007/24"/>
              <FRBRalias value="THE SCHEDULE"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-wbg/act/2007/24/eng@2017-06-06/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-wbg/act/2007/24/eng@2017-06-06"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-wbg/act/2007/24/eng@2017-06-06/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-wbg/act/2007/24/eng@2017-06-06"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-06-06" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="theschedule">
            <heading>[SEE CLAUSES (g), AND (j), OF SECTION 3.]</heading>
            <paragraph id="theschedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>PART—A</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <section id="section-1">
              <num>1.</num>
              <heading>Stone Breaking and Stone Crushing;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-2">
              <num>2.</num>
              <heading>Brick or Tile Manufacturing;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-3">
              <num>3.</num>
              <heading>Hotel and Restaurants;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-4">
              <num>4.</num>
              <heading>Security Agencies;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-5">
              <num>5.</num>
              <heading>Cinema;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-6">
              <num>6.</num>
              <heading>Rice Mill;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-7">
              <num>7.</num>
              <heading>Public Motor Transport;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-8">
              <num>8.</num>
              <heading>Hired Motor Vehicles Service;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-9">
              <num>9.</num>
              <heading>Boatman Service;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-10">
              <num>10.</num>
              <heading>Tailoring Industry;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-11">
              <num>11.</num>
              <heading>Printing Press;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-12">
              <num>12.</num>
              <heading>Book Binding;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-13">
              <num>13.</num>
              <heading>Hand-loom;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-14">
              <num>14.</num>
              <heading>Power-loom;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-15">
              <num>15.</num>
              <heading>Sericulture;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-16">
              <num>16.</num>
              <heading>Forestry and Timber Operation;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-17">
              <num>17.</num>
              <heading>Bangle Making;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-18">
              <num>18.</num>
              <heading>Fire-works;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-19">
              <num>19.</num>
              <heading>Embroidery Works;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-20">
              <num>20.</num>
              <heading>Shops;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-21">
              <num>21.</num>
              <heading>Chakki Mills;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-22">
              <num>22.</num>
              <heading>Leather and Leather goods;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-23">
              <num>23.</num>
              <heading>Hosiery;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-24">
              <num>24.</num>
              <heading>Bakery;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-25">
              <num>25.</num>
              <heading>Rubber and Rubber Products;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-26">
              <num>26.</num>
              <heading>Saw Mill;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-27">
              <num>27.</num>
              <heading>Bone Mill;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-28">
              <num>28.</num>
              <heading>Plastic Industry;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-29">
              <num>29.</num>
              <heading>Ceramic Industry;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-30">
              <num>30.</num>
              <heading>Small Scale Chemical Units;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-31">
              <num>31.</num>
              <heading>Cashew Processing;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-32">
              <num>32.</num>
              <heading>Coir Industry;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-33">
              <num>33.</num>
              <heading>Khadi;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-34">
              <num>34.</num>
              <heading>Small Scale Engineering Units;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-35">
              <num>35.</num>
              <heading>Clinical Nursing Home;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-36">
              <num>36.</num>
              <heading>Silk Printing</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-37">
              <num>37.</num>
              <heading>Dal Mill;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-38">
              <num>38.</num>
              <heading>Oil Mill;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-39">
              <num>39.</num>
              <heading>Decoration;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-40">
              <num>40.</num>
              <heading>Lac Industry;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-41">
              <num>41.</num>
              <heading>Medical plants other than Cinchona;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-42">
              <num>42.</num>
              <heading>Iron Foundry;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-43">
              <num>43.</num>
              <heading>Paper Board and Straw Board Manufactories;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-44">
              <num>44.</num>
              <heading>Garments Making;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-45">
              <num>45.</num>
              <heading>Motor Garage;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-46">
              <num>46.</num>
              <heading>Deed or Copy Writing Work in Court or Registration Office;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-47">
              <num>47.</num>
              <heading>Kite and Kite Stick Manufacturing;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-48">
              <num>48.</num>
              <heading>Slaughter House;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-49">
              <num>49.</num>
              <heading>Type Copying Work;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-50">
              <num>50.</num>
              <heading>Earthen Pottery Work;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-51">
              <num>51.</num>
              <heading>Bidi Making;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-52">
              <num>52.</num>
              <heading>Brassware;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-53">
              <num>53.</num>
              <heading>Footware (leather, rubber, plastic);</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-54">
              <num>54.</num>
              <heading>Hand-broken quarried stones.</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-54.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>PART-B</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-1">
              <num>1.</num>
              <heading>Auto-rickshaw Operator;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-2">
              <num>2.</num>
              <heading>Rickshaw and Van Pullar including Hand-pulled Cart ones;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-3">
              <num>3.</num>
              <heading>Mason;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-4">
              <num>4.</num>
              <heading>Carpenter;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-5">
              <num>5.</num>
              <heading>Painter;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-6">
              <num>6.</num>
              <heading>Electrician;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-7">
              <num>7.</num>
              <heading>Plumber;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-8">
              <num>8.</num>
              <heading>Cobbler;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-9">
              <num>9.</num>
              <heading>Head-load Workers;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-10">
              <num>10.</num>
              <heading>Fisherman;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-11">
              <num>11.</num>
              <heading>Street Hawkers including Newspapers Hawkers;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-12">
              <num>12.</num>
              <heading>Railway Hawker;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-13">
              <num>13.</num>
              <heading>Aya or Attendent engaged in Hospital or Nursing Homes by patients;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-14">
              <num>14.</num>
              <heading>Weaver and others in Hand-loom;</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-15">
              <num>15.</num>
              <heading>Domestic workers.</heading>
            </section>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
