<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1956/49/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1956/49"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The River Boards Act, 1956"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1956/49/eng@1956-09-12/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1956/49/eng@1956-09-12"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1956-09-12" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1956/49/eng@1956-09-12/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1956/49/eng@1956-09-12"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The River Boards Act, 1956</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 49 OF 1956</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 12th September, 1956.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Seventh Year of the Republic  of India as follows:-</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the establishment of River Boards for the  regulation and development of inter- State rivers and river valleys.</p>
        <p>CHAP</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the</p>
              <p>River Boards Act, 1956.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on such date  as the Central</p>
              <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Declaration as to expediency of control by Central Government. It is hereby  declared that it is expedient in the public interest th</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context  otherwiserequires,- (a)" Board" means a River Board established  under section 4; (b)" Gover</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>ESTABLISHMENT OF RIVER BOARDS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>ESTABLISHMENT OF RIVER BOARDS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Establishment of Boards.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, on a  request received in this behalf from a State Government or otherwise,</p>
              <p>by notification in the Official Gazette, establish a River Board for  advising the Governments interested in relation to such matters  concerning the regulation or development of an inter- State river or  river valley or any specified part thereof and for performing such  other functions</p>
              <p>as may be specified in the notification, and different Boards may be  established for different inter- State rivers or river valleys:</p>
              <p>Provided that no such notification shall be issued except after  consultation with the Governments interested with respect to the  proposal to establish the Board, the persons to be appointed as  members thereof and the functions which the Board may be empowered to  perform.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A Board may be established under such name as may be  specified in the notification under sub- section (1).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every Board so established shall be a body corporate having  perpetual succession and a common seal, and shall by the said name sue  and be sued.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every Board shall exercise its jurisdiction within such  limits of the river (including its tributaries, if any) or river  valley as may be specified in the notification under sub- section (1)</p>
              <p>and the area so specified shall be called the area of operation of the</p>
              <p>Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Composition of Board.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall consist of a</p>
              <p>Chairman and such other members as the Central Government thinks fit  to appoint.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A person shall not be qualified for appointment as a member  unless, in the opinion of the Central Government, he has special  knowledge and experience in irrigation, electrical engineering, flood  control, navigation, water conservation, soil conservation,</p>
              <p>administration or finance.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Terms and conditions of service of members.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A member  shall, unless his appointment is terminated earlier by the Central</p>
              <p>Government, hold office for such period as may be notified in this  behalf by the Central Government in the Official Gazette and shall, on  the expiry of the term of his office, be eligible for re- appointment.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A member may resign his office by writing under his hand  addressed to the Central Government, but he shall continue in office  until the appointment of his successor is notified in the Official</p>
              <p>Gazette.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A casual vacancy created by the resignation of a member under  sub- section (2) or for any other reason shall be filled by fresh  appointment.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A member may be appointed either as a whole- time or part- time  member as the Central Government thinks fit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The terms and conditions of service of the Chairman and other  members shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Temporary absence of any member. If any member is by infirmity  or otherwise rendered temporarily incapable of carrying out his duties  or is absent on leave or otherwise in circumstances not involving the  vacation of his appointment, the Central Government may appointment,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>the Central Government may appoint another person to act in his place.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Meetings of Board. The Board shall meet at such times and  places and shall observe such rules of procedure in regard to the  transaction of business at its meetings as may be provided by  regulations made under this Act.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Vacancy in Board, etc., not to invalidate acts or proceedings.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No act or proceeding of the Board shall be deemed to be invalid by  reason only of the existence of any vacancy in the Board or any defect  in the appointment of a member thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Appointment of advisory committee. The Board may, from time  to time, appoint one or more advisory committee or committees for the  purpose of enabling it to carry out its functions under this Act.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Temporary association of persons with Board for particular  purposes.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board may associate with itself in such manner and  for such purposes as may be determined by regulations made under this</p>
              <p>Act any person whose assistance or advice it may desire in performing  any of its functions under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A person associated with the Board under sub- section (1) for  any purpose shall have a right to take part in the discussions of the</p>
              <p>Board relevant to that purpose, but shall not have a right to vote at  a meeting of the Board, and shall not be a member for any other  purpose.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Staff of Board. Subject to such rules as may be made by the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Central Government in this behalf, the Board may, for the purpose of  enabling it to efficiently perform its functions or exercise its  powers under this Act, appoint such officers as it may think fit and  determine their functions and terms and conditions of service.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>POWERS AND FUNCTIONS OF THE BOARD</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>POWERS AND FUNCTIONS OF THE BOARD</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Matters in respect of which a Board may be authorised to  tender advice. A Board may be empowered under sub- section</heading>
          <subsection id="section-13.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-13.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>of  section 14 to perform all or any of the following functions, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-13.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>advising the Governments interested on any matter  concerning the regulation or development of any  specified</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-13.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>inter- State river or river valley within its area of  operation and in particular, advising them in relation  to the co- ordination of their activities with a view to  resolve conflicts among them and to achieve maximum  results in respect of the measures undertaken by them  in the inter- State river or river valley for the  purpose of-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-13.1.list3.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>conservation, control and optimum utilisation  of water resources of the inter- State river;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.1.list3.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>promotion and operation of schemes for  irrigation, water supply or drainage;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.1.list3.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>promotion and operation of schemes for the  development of hydro- electric power;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.1.list3.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>promotion and operation of schemes for flood  control;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.1.list3.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>promotion and control of navigation;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.1.list3.vi">
                  <num>(vi)</num>
                  <p>promotion of afforestation and control of  soil erosion;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.1.list3.vii">
                  <num>(vii)</num>
                  <p>prevention of pollution of the waters of the  inter- State river;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.1.list3.viii">
                  <num>(viii)</num>
                  <p>such other matters as may be prescribed;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.1.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>preparing schemes, including multi- purpose schemes, for  the purpose of regulating or developing the inter- State  river or river valley and advising the Governments  interested to undertake measures for executing the  scheme prepared by the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.1.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>allocating among the Governments interested the costs  of executing any scheme prepared by the Board and of  maintaining any works undertaken in the execution of  the scheme;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.1.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>watching the progress of the measures undertaken by the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-13.1.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Governments interested;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-13.1.list5.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>any other matter which is supplemental, incidental or  consequential to any of the above functions.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Functions of Board.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government, after  consultation with the Governments interested, may, by notification in  the Official Gazette,</p>
              <p>empower the Board to perform all or such of the functions under  section 13 as may be specified in the notification.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall exercise its powers and perform all the  functions which it is empowered to do by or under this Act within its  area of operation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In performing its functions under this Act, the Board shall  consult the Governments interested at all stages and endeavour to  secure, as far as may be practicable, agreement among such</p>
              <p>Governments.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Preparation of schemes by Board and their execution.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-15.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-15.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Where any Board has been empowered to perform functions under clause</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-15.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>of section 13, the Board may, from time to time, prepare schemes,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>not inconsistent with its functions under this Act, for the purpose of  regulating or developing any inter- State river or river valley within  its area of operation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>After preparing any such scheme, the Board shall consult the</p>
              <p>Governments interested and the Central Government in respect of the  scheme and after considering their suggestion, if any, the Board may  confirm, modify or reject the scheme.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The scheme as confirmed or modified under sub- section (2)</p>
              <p>shall thereupon become final and shall be called the approved scheme.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Before any scheme is approved, the Board shall take into  account the costs likely to be incurred in undertaking measures for  executing the scheme and in maintaining any works to be undertaken in  the execution of the scheme and the costs shall be allocated among the</p>
              <p>Governments interested in such proportion as may be agreed or, in  default of agreement, as may be determined by the Board having regard  to the benefits which will be received from the scheme by them.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every approved scheme shall be forwarded to the Governments  interested and the Board may advise them to undertake measures for  executing the scheme and a copy of the approved scheme shall also be  forwarded to the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, on a request received in this  behalf from any Government interested or otherwise, assist the</p>
              <p>Governments interested in taking such steps as may be necessary for  the execution of the scheme.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>General Powers of Board. For the purpose of efficiently  performing its functions under this Act, every Board may, within its  area of operation,-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-16.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>acquire, hold and dispose of such property, both  movable and immovable, as it deems necessary;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>undertake such preliminary investigation or surveys or  other measures as it deems necessary;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>inspect or cause to be inspected any works undertaken  by any Government interested concerning the regulation  or development of the inter- State river or river  valley;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>conduct and co- ordinate research on various aspects of  the conservation, regulation or utilisation of water  resources, such as water power generation, irrigation,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-16.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>navigation, flood control, soil conservation, land use  and connected structural and design features:</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list2.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>collect such topographical, meteorological,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-16.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>hydrological and sub- soil water data as it deems  necessary;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list4.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>publish statistics or other information relating to the  various aspects of the regulation or development of the  inter- State river or river valley;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list4.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-16.paragraph-0.list4.g.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>require any Government interested to furnish such  information as the Board may require in relation to-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list4.g.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>the measures undertaken by that Government for  the regulation or development of the inter- State river  or river valley;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list4.g.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>the topographical, meteorological,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-16.paragraph-0.list6">
                <listIntroduction>hydrological and sub- soil water data;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list6.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>such other matters as may be prescribed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Payment to Board. The Central Government may, after due  appropriation made by Parliament by law in this behalf, pay to the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Board in each financial year such sums as the Central Government may  consider necessary for the performance of the functions of the Board  under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Fund of Board.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-18.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall have its own fund, and all  sums which may, from time to time, be paid to it by the Central</p>
              <p>Government or a State Government and all other receipts of the Board  shall be carried to the fund of the Board and all payments by the</p>
              <p>Board shall be made therefrom.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board may expend such sums as it thinks fit for  performing its functions under this Act, and such sums shall be  treated as expenditure payable out of the fund of the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Budget. The Board shall prepare, in such form and at such  time each year as may be prescribed, a budget in respect of the  financial year next ensuing showing the estimated receipts and  expenditure, and copies thereof shall be forwarded to the Central</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government and the Governments interested.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Annual report. The Board shall prepare, in such form and at  such time each year as may be prescribed, an annual report giving a  true and full account of its activities during the previous year and  copies thereof shall be forwarded to the Central Government and the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Governments interested; and the Central Government shall cause every  such report to be laid before both Houses of Parliament.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Accounts and audit.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-21.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall cause to be  maintained such books of account and other books in relation to its  accounts in such form and in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-21.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The accounts of the Board shall be audited at such time and  in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Arbitration.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-22.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-22.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Where any dispute or difference arises  between two or more Governments interested with respect to-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-22.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>any advice tendered by the Board under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-22.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>any measures undertaken by any Government interested in  pursuance of any advice tendered by the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-22.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the refusal or neglect of any Government interested to  undertake any measures in pursuance of any advice  tendered by the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-22.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the sharing of benefits or financial liabilities  arising out of any advice tendered by the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-22.1.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>any other matter covered by this Act or touching or  arising out of it,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>any of the Governments interested may, in such form and in such manner  as may be prescribed, refer the matter in dispute to arbitration.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The arbitrator shall be a person to be appointed in this  behalf by the Chief Justice of India from among persons who are, or  have been, Judges of the Supreme Court or are Judges of a High Court.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The arbitrator may appoint two or more persons as assessors  to assist him in the proceeding before him.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The decision of the arbitrator shall be final and binding on  the parties to the dispute and shall be given effect to by them.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in the Arbitration Act, 1940 (10 of 1940), shall  apply to arbitrations under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Returns and reports. The Board shall furnish to the Central</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government such returns, statistics, accounts and other information  with respect to its fund or activities as the Central Government may  from time to time require.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Delegation of powers. The Board may, by general or special  order in writing, delegate to the Chairman or any other member or any  officer of the Board, subject to such conditions and limitations, if  any, as may be specified in the order, such of its powers and  functions under this Act as it may deem necessary for the efficient  funning of the day- to- day administration of the Board.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Members and officers of Board to be public servants. All  members and officers of a Board shall, when acting or purporting to  act in pursuance of any of the provisions of this Act, be deemed to be  public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Code (45 of 1860).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit or other  legal proceeding shall lie against any member or officer of a Board in  respect of anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done  in pursuance of this Act.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Dissolution of Board and transfer of assets and liabilities.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-27.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When the Central Government is of opinion that a Board has  performed its functions under this Act, the Central Government, after  consultation with the Governments interested, may, by notification in  the Official Gazette, declare that the Board shall be dissolved from  such date as may be specified in this behalf in such notification; and  the Board shall be deemed to have been dissolved accordingly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On the dissolution of the Board by a notification under sub-</p>
              <blockList id="section-27.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>section (1),-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.2.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>all properties, funds and dues which are vested in, or  realisable by, the Board shall vest in, and be  realisable by, such Government or authority as may be  specified in the said notification; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>all liabilities which are enforceable against the Board  shall be enforceable only against the Government or  authority specified in the said notification.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-28.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the  purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-28.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-28.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely;-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-28.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the salaries, allowances and conditions of service of  members of the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-28.2.list1.b.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>the matters in respect of which the Board may tender  advice to the Governments interested under sub- clause</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-28.2.list1.b.list0.viii">
                      <num>(viii)</num>
                      <p>of clause (a) of section 13;</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the matters in respect of which the Board may require a</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-28.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Government interested to furnish information;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-28.2.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which the Central Government may assist  the Government interested to execute any scheme  prepared by the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.2.list3.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the form in which, and the time within which, the  budget and annual report of the Board may be prepared  and forwarded to the Central Government and the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-28.2.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Governments interested:</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-28.2.list5.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the form and manner in which the accounts of the Board  may be maintained, and the time at which, and the  manner in which, such accounts may be audited;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.2.list5.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the returns and information which the Board may be  required to furnish to the Central Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.2.list5.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>the form and manner in which a dispute may be referred  to arbitration under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.2.list5.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the procedure to be followed in arbitration proceedings  under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.2.list5.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>the manner of recruitment of the officers of a Board  and the terms and conditions of service of such  officers;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.2.list5.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>any other matter which has to be, or may be,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-28.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon  as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it  is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be  comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and  if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session  or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not  be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified  form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any  such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the  validity of anything previously done under that rule.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-29.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Power to make regulations. The Board may,</p>
              <p>with the previous approval of the Central Government, by notification  in the Gazette of India, make regulations, not inconsistent with this</p>
              <blockList id="section-29.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Act or the rules made thereunder--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-29.1.list3.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>regulating the meetings of the Board and the procedure  for conducting business thereat;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-29.1.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>regulating the manner in which, and the purposes for  which, advisory committees may be appointed;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-29.1.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>regulating the manner in which and the purposes for  which persons may be associated with the Board under  section 11;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-29.1.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>determining the terms and conditions of service of the  members of advisory committees, of persons associated  with the Board under section 11 and of all officers  appointed by the Board.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every regulation made under this section shall be laid,</p>
              <p>as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament,</p>
              <p>while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be  comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and  if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session  or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the regulation or both Houses agree that the  regulation should not be made, the regulation shall thereafter have  effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may  be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be  without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under  that regulation.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
