<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1903/7/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1903/7"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Works Of Defence Act, 1903"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1903/7/eng@1903-03-20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1903/7/eng@1903-03-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1903-03-20" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1903/7/eng@1903-03-20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1903/7/eng@1903-03-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Works Of Defence Act, 1903</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 7 OF 1903</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 20th March, 1903.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for imposing restrictions upon the use and enjoyment  of land in the vicinity of works of defence in order that such land  may be kept free from buildings and other obstructions, and for  determining the amount of compensation to be made on account of such  imposition.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for imposing restrictions upon  the use and enjoyment of land in the vicinity of works of defence in  order that such land may be kept free from buildings and other  obstructions, and for determining the amount of compensation to be  made on account of such imposition; It is hereby enacted as follows:-</p>
        <p>PART</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <part id="part-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="part-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title and extent.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the</p>
              <p>Works of Defence Act, 1903; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It extends to the whole of India.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless there is something repugnant  in the subject or context,-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the expression" land" includes benefits to arise out  of land, and things attached to the earth or permanently  fastened to anything attached to the earth;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the expression" person interested" includes all  persons claiming an interest in compensation to be made on  account of the imposition of restrictions upon the use and  enjoyment of land under this Act; and a person shall be  deemed to be interested in land if he is interested in an  easement affecting the land:</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the expression" District" means one of the Districts  into which India is, for military purposes for the time  being, divided; it includes a Brigade area which does not  form part of any District, and any area which the Central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette,</p>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>declare to be a District for all or any of the purposes of  this Act:</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the expression" General Officer Commanding the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>District" means the officer for the time being in command of  the forces in a District:]</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the expression" Commanding Officer" means the officer  for the time being in command of a work of defence:</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the expression" Collector" includes any officer specially  appointed by the  Central Government] to perform the  functions of a Collector under this Act:</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the expression" Court" means a principal Civil Court of  original jurisdiction, unless the  Central Government] has  appointed (as it is hereby empowered to do) a special  judicial officer within any specified local limits to perform  the functions of the Court under this Act:</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>" maintain", with its grammatical variations and cognate  expressions, does not, when used in relation to a house or  other construction, include the doing of any act necessary  for keeping such house or construction, until the making of  the award referred to in section 12 or until the exercise,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>prior to the making of the award, of the powers of demolition  conferred, in case of emergency, by section 6, sub- sections</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-2.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and (3), in the state in which it was at the time of the  publication of the notice referred to in section 3, sub-</p>
              <blockList id="section-2.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>section (2):</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.1.list2.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the following persons shall be deemed" entitled to act"</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>as and to the extent hereinafter provided, that is to say,-</p>
              <p>trustees for other persons beneficially interested shall be  deemed the persons entitled to act with reference to any  case. and that to the same extent as the</p>
              <p>persons beneficially interested could have acted if free from  disability:</p>
              <p>a married woman, in cases to which the English law is  applicable, shall be deemed the person so entitled to act,</p>
              <p>and, whether of full age or not, to the same extent as if she  were unmarried and of full age: and</p>
              <p>the guardians, of minors and the committees or managers of  lunatics or idiots shall be deemed respectively the persons  so entitled to act, to the same extent as the minors,</p>
              <p>lunatics or idiots themselves, if free from disability, could  have acted:</p>
              <blockList id="section-2.1.list11">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.1.list11.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>no person shall be deemed" entitled to act" whose  interest in the subject- matter is shown to the satisfaction  of the Collector or Court to be adverse to the interest of  the person interested for whom he would otherwise be entitled  to act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list11.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>in every case the person interested may appear by a  next friend or, in default of his appearance by a next  friend, the Collector or Court, as the case may be, shall  appoint a guardian for the case to act on his behalf in the  conduct thereof;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list11.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>the provisions of Chapter XXXI of the Code of Civil</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Procedure (14 of 1882) 1 shall, mutatis mutandis, apply in the  case of persons, interested appearing before a Collector or</p>
              <blockList id="section-2.1.list14">
                <listIntroduction>Court by a next friend, or by a guardian for the case, in  proceedings under this Act; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.1.list14.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>no person" entitled to act" shall be competent to  receive the compensation- money payable to the person for whom  he is entitled to act, unless he would have been competent to  alienate the land upon the use and enjoyment of which  restrictions are to be imposed and receive and give a good  discharge for the purchase- money on a voluntary sale.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2A">
          <num>2A.</num>
          <heading>Construction of references to laws not in force, or any  functionary not in existence, in any area. Any reference in this Act  to any law which is not in force in any area or any reference therein  to any functionary not in existence in any area shall, in relation to  that</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2A.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>area, be construed as a reference to the corresponding law, if any,</p>
              <p>in force, or to the corresponding functionary, if any, in existence,</p>
              <p>in that area.]</p>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>IMPOSITION OF RESTRICTIONS.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="part-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>IMPOSITION OF RESTRICTIONS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Declaration and notice that restrictions will be imposed.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Whenever it appears to the  Central Government] that it Is necessary  to impose restrictions upon the use and enjoyment of land in the  vicinity of any work of defence or of any site intended to be used or  to be acquired for any such work, in order that such land may be kept  free from buildings and other obstructions, a declaration shall be  made to that effect under the signature of a Secretary to such</p>
              <p>Government or of some officer duly authorised to certify its orders.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The said- declaration shall be published in the Official</p>
              <p>Gazette and shall state the district or other territorial division in  which the land is situate and the place where a sketch plan of the  land, which shall be prepared on a scale not smaller than six inches  to the mile and shall distinguish the boundaries referred to in  section 7, may be inspected; and the Collector shall cause public  notice of the substance of the said declaration to be given at  convenient places in the locality.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The said declaration shall be conclusive proof that it is  necessary to keep the land free from buildings and other obstructions.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Power to do preliminary acts after publication of notice under  section 3, sub- section (2). It shall be lawful for such officer as  the  Central Government] may, by general or special order, authorise  in this behalf, and for his servants and workmen, at any time after  publication of the notice mentioned in section 3, sub- section (2), to  enter upon and survey and take levels of any land in such locality,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>to dig or bore into the sub- soil, to do all other acts necessary to  ascertain whether any and, if so, what restrictions should be imposed  on the use and enjoyment of the land, to set out the boundaries of  the land upon the use and enjoyment of which restrictions are to be  imposed, or of any part of such land, to mark such levels, boundaries  and line by placing marks and cutting trenches, and, where otherwise  the survey cannot be completed and the levels taken and the boundaries  and line marked, to cut down and clear away any part of any standing  crop, fence or jungle:</p>
              <p>Provided that no person shall enter into any building or upon any  enclosed court or garden attached to a dwelling- house (unless with</p>
              <p>the consent of the occupier thereof) without previously giving such  occupier at least seven days' notice in writing of his intention to do  so.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Payment for damage. The officer so authorised shall at the time  of such entry pay or tender payment for all necessary damage to be  done as aforesaid, and, in case of dispute as to the sufficiency of  the amount so paid or tendered, he shall at once refer the dispute to  the decision of the Collector or other chief revenue- officer of the  district, and such decision shall be final.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Further powers exercisable after publication of notice under  section 3, sub- section (2).</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Whenever a declaration has been made  and public notice thereof has been given under section 3, it shall,</p>
              <p>subject to the provisions of sub- sections (2) to (4), be lawful for  such officer as the  Central Government] may, by general or special  order, authorise in this behalf, and for his servants and workmen, to  enter and demolish any buildings or other constructions on the  surface, to cut down or grub up all or any of the trees, to remove or  alter all or any of the banks, fences, hedges and ditches, to make  underground and other</p>
              <p>drains, to fill up all excavations, and demolish all buildings and  other constructions below the surface, and generally to level and  clear the said land and do all such acts for levelling and clearing  the same as he may deem necessary or proper, but in such manner  nevertheless that evidence of the boundaries of the lands held by  different owners may be preserved.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The powers conferred by sub- section (1) shall not be exer-</p>
              <blockList id="section-6.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>cised,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.2.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>save as otherwise provided by sub- section (3), before  the making of the award hereinafter referred to in section</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>, nor</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>save as otherwise provided by sub- section (4), after  the expiration of six months from the making of the said  award, or any shorter period on the expiration of which the  officer exercising such powers gives notice to the Collector  that there will be no further exercise of them.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-12.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In case of emergency, the  Central Government]  may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, declare that all or any powers  conferred by sub- section (1) may be exercised at any time within six  months after the publication of the notice referred to in section 3,</p>
              <p>sub- section (2), and such powers may be exercised accordingly, and the  said notification shall be conclusive proof of emergency.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in sub- section (2) shall be deemed to preclude any  such officer or his servants or workmen from exercising at any time  the said powers for the purpose of removing, wholly or in part, any  building or other obstruction maintained, created, added to, altered,</p>
              <p>planted, stacked, stored or otherwise accumulated in contravention of  this Act or of any rule or order made thereunder or of any condition  prescribed in accordance therewith.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Restrictions. From and after the publication of the notice  mentioned in section 3, sub- section (2), such of the following  restrictions as the  Central Government] may in its discretion  declare therein shall attach with reference to such land, namely:-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list0.a.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>Within an outer boundary which, except so far as is  otherwise provided in section 39, sub- section (4), may extend  to a distance of two thousand yards from the crest of the  outer parapet of the work,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list0.a.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>no variation shall be made in the ground- level, and  no building, wall, bank or other construction above</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>the ground shall be maintained, erected, added to or  altered otherwise than with the written approval of the</p>
              <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>General Officer Commanding the District], and on such  conditions as he may prescribe;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list3.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>no wood, earth, stone, brick, gravel, sand or other  material shall be stacked, stored or otherwise  accumulated:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that, with the written approval of the</p>
              <p>General Officer Commanding the District] and on such  conditions as he may prescribe, road- ballast, manure and  agricultural produce may be exempted from the  prohibition:</p>
              <p>Provided also that any person having control of the land  as owner, lessee or occupier shall be bound forthwith to  remove such road- ballast, manure or agricultural  produce, without compensation, on the requisition of the</p>
              <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list8">
                <listIntroduction>Commanding Officer;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list8.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>no surveying operation shall be conducted otherwise  than by or under the personal supervision of a public  servant duly authorised in this behalf, in the case of  land under the control of military authority, by the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list10">
                <listIntroduction>Commanding Officer and, in other cases, by the Collector  with the concurrence of the Commanding Officer; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list10.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>where any building, wall, bank or other con-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>struction above the ground has been permitted under  clause (i) of this sub- section to be maintained,</p>
              <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list13">
                <listIntroduction>erected, added to or altered, repairs shall not, without  the written approval of the  General Officer Commanding  the District], be made with materials different in kind  from those employed in the original building, wall, bank  or other construction.</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list13.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list13.b.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>Within a second boundary which may extend to a distance  of one thousand yards from the crest of the outer parapet of  the work, the restrictions enumerated in clause (a) shall  apply with the following additional limitations, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list13.b.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>no building, wall, bank or other construction of  permanent materials above the ground shall be</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>maintained otherwise than with the written approval of  the General Officer Commanding the District and on such  conditions as he may prescribe, and no such building,</p>
              <p>wall, bank or other construction shall be erected:]</p>
              <p>Provided that, with the written approval of the  General</p>
              <p>Officer Commanding the District] and on such conditions  as he may prescribe, huts, fences or other constructions  of wood or other materials, easily destroyed or removed,</p>
              <p>may be maintained, erected, added to or altered:</p>
              <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list20">
                <listIntroduction>Provided, also, that any person having control of the  land as owner, lessee or occupier shall be bound  forthwith to destroy or remove such huts, fences or  other constructions, without compensation, upon an order  in writing signed by the  General Officer Commanding  the District]; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list20.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>live hedges, rows or clumps of trees or orchards  shall not be maintained, planted, added to or altered  otherwise than with the written approval of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list22">
                <listIntroduction>General Officer Commanding the District] and on such  conditions as he may prescribe.</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list22.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>Within a third boundary which may extend to a distance  of five hundred yards from the crest of the outer parapet of  the work, the restrictions enumerated in clauses (a) and (b)</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>shall apply with the following additional limitation, namely:</p>
              <p>no building or other construction on the surface, and no  excavation, building or other construction below the surface,</p>
              <p>shall be maintained or erected:</p>
              <p>Provided that, with the written approval of the Commanding</p>
              <p>Officer and on such conditions as he may, prescribe,  a  building or other construction on the surface may be  maintained and] open railings and dry brush- wood fences may  be exempted from this prohibition.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Land to be marked out measured, registered and planned. As  soon as may be after the publication of the declaration aforesaid, the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Collector shall cause the land to be marked out and measured, and  shall also prepare a register and a detailed plan, which shall</p>
              <p>be on a scale not smaller than six inches to the mile, showing  accurately every building, tree and other obstruction.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Notice to persons interested.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-9.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>At any time before the  expiration of-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-9.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the period of eighteen months from the publication of  the declaration referred to in section 3, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>such other period not exceeding three years from the  said publication as the  Central Government]  may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, direct in this behalf,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>the Collector shall cause public notice to be given at convenient  places on or near the land, stating the effect of the said declaration  and that claims to compensation for all interests in such land  affected by anything done or ordered in pursuance of such declaration  may be made to him:</p>
              <p>Provided that, where anything has been done in exercise of the  powers conferred, in case of emergency, by section 6, sub- section (3),</p>
              <p>the notice prescribed by this section shall be given as soon as may be  thereafter.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Such notice shall state the particulars of any damage,</p>
              <p>ordered to be done or, in the case referred to in section 6, sub-</p>
              <p>section (3), done in exercise of any of the powers conferred by the  said section, and the particulars of any restrictions attaching to the  land under section 7, and shall require all persons interested in the  land to appear personally or by agent before the Collector at a time  and place therein mentioned (such time not being earlier than fifteen   days after the date of publication of the notice), and to state the  nature of their respective interests in the land and the amount and  particulars of their claims to compensation for damage to such  interests and their objections (if any) to the measurements made under  section 8. The Collector may in any case require such statement to be  made in writing and signed by the party or his agent.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Collector shall also serve notice to the same effect on  the occupier (if any) of such land and on all such persons known or  believed to be interested therein, or to be entitled to act for  persons so interested, as reside or have agents authorised to receive  service on their behalf, within the revenue- district in which the land  is situate.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In case any person so interested resides elsewhere, and has  no such agent, the notice shall be sent to him by post in a letter  addressed to him at his last known residence, address or place of  business.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Power to require and enforce the making of statements as to  names and interests. The Collector may also require any such person to  make or deliver to him, at a time and place mentioned (such time not   being earlier than fifteen days after the date of the requisition), a  statement containing, so far as may be practicable, the name of every  other person possessing any interest in the land or any part thereof  as co- proprietor, sub- proprietor, mortgagee, tenant or otherwise, and  of the nature of such interest, and of the rents and profits (if any)</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>received or receivable on account thereof for three years next pre-</p>
              <p>ceding the date of the statement.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Application of certain sections of the Indian Penal Code.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every person required to make or deliver a statement under section 9  or section 10 shall be deemed to be legally bound to do so within the  meaning of sections 175 and 176 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1860">
          <num>1860.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1860.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>)</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Inquiry and award by Collector. On the day fixed under  section 9 or on any other day to which the inquiry has been adjourned,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>the Collector shall proceed to inquire into the objections (if any)</p>
              <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>which any person interested has stated pursuant to a notice given  under the said section to the measurements made under section 8, and  into the decrease in the value of the land, and into the respective  interests of the persons claiming the compensation, and shall make an  award under his hand of-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the true area of the land and the nature of the  obstructions from which the land is to be kept free;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the compensation which in his opinion should be allowed  for any damage caused or to be caused under section 6 and for  any restrictions imposed under section 7; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the apportionment of the said compensation among all the  persons known or believed to be interested in the land, of  whom or of whose claims he has information, whether they have  respectively appeared before him or not.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Award of Collector when to be final.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-13.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Such award shall be  filed in the Collector' s office and shall, except as hereinafter  provided, be final and conclusive evidence, as between the Collector  and the persons interested, whether they have respectively appeared  before the Collector or not, of the true area of the land, the nature  of the said obstructions from which the land is to be kept free, the  damage caused or to be caused under section 6, the value of the rights  restricted under section 7, and the apportionment of the compensation  among the persons interested.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Collector shall give immediate notice of his award to  such of the persons interested as are not present personally or by  their representatives when the award is made.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Adjournment of inquiry. The Collector may, for any cause he  thinks fit, from time to time adjourn the inquiry to a day to be fixed  by him.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Power to summon and enforce attendance of witnesses and  production of documents. For the purpose of inquiries under this Act  the Collector shall have power to summon and enforce the attendance of  witnesses, including the parties interested or any of them, and to  compel the production of documents, by the same means, and (so far as   may be) in the same manner, as is provided in the case of a Civil</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Court under the Code of Civil Procedure (14 of 1882) 1.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Matters to be considered and neglected. In determining the  amount of compensation, the Collector shall be guided by the  provisions contained in sections 23 and 24.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Supplementary proceedings. Whenever the officer exercising  powers conferred by section 6 considers it necessary that anything in  respect of which any person is or may be entitled to compensation but  of which no notice has been given or compensation awarded, under  sections 9 and 12, respectively, should be done in pursuance of the  said powers, the collector shall cause supplementary notice to be  given, as nearly as may be, in the manner prescribed by section 9 and  subject to the limit of time imposed by sub- section</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of that  section, and the provisions of sections 10 to 16 shall, so far as they  are applicable, be deemed to apply to any further inquiry and award  which may be held or made in consequence of such supplementary notice.</p>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>REFERENCE TO COURT AND PROCEDURE THEREON.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="part-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>REFERENCE TO COURT AND PROCEDURE THEREON</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Reference to Court.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-18.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person interested who has not  accepted the award may, by written application to the Collector,</p>
              <p>require that the matter be referred by the Collector. for the  determination of the Court, whether his objection be to the  measurement of the land, the amount of the compensation, the persons  to whom it is payable, or the apportionment of the compensation among  the persons interested:</p>
              <blockList id="section-18.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that every such application shall be made,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-18.1.list3.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>if the person making it was present or represented before  the Collector at the time when he made his award, within six  weeks from the date of the Collector' s award;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.1.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>in other cases, within six weeks of the receipt of the  notice from the Collector under section 13, sub- section (2),</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>or within six months from the date of the Collector' s award,</p>
              <p>whichever period shall first expire.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The application shall state the grounds on which objection to  the award is taken.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Collector' s statement to the Court.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-19.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In making the  reference the Collector shall state, for the information of the Court,</p>
              <blockList id="section-19.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>in writing under his hand,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-19.1.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the situation and extent of the land with particulars  of any damage caused under section 6 or of restrictions  imposed under section 7;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.1.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the names of the persons whom he has reason to think  interested in such land;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.1.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the amount of compensation awarded under section 12  and,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.1.list2.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>if the objection be to the amount of the compensation,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>the grounds on which the amount of compensation was  determined.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>To the said statement shall be attached a schedule giving  the particulars of the notices served upon, and of the statements in  writing made or delivered by, the parties interested respectively.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Service of notice. The Court shall thereupon cause a notice  specifying the day on which the Court will proceed to determine the  objection, and directing their appearance before the Court on that  day, to be served on the following persons, namely:-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-20.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the applicant;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>all persons interested in the objection, except such</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-20.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>(if any) of them as have consented without protest to receive  payment of the compensation awarded; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>if the objection is in regard to the area of the land,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>the nature of the obstructions or the amount of the compen-</p>
              <p>sation, the Collector.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Restriction on scope of proceedings. The scope of the  inquiry in every such proceeding shall be restricted to a  consideration of the interests of the persons affected by the  objection.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Proceedings to be in open Court. Every such proceeding shall  take place in open Court, and all persons entitled to practise in any</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Civil Court in the State shall be entitled to appear, plead and act,</p>
              <p>as the case may be, in such proceeding.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Matters to be considered in determining compensation.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-23.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In determining the amount of compensation to be awarded for damage  caused, or to be caused, or for restrictions imposed under this Act,</p>
              <blockList id="section-23.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>the Court shall take into consideration-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-23.1.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the actual decrease in market- value of the land owing  to the publication of the declaration relating thereto under  section 3 and any damage caused or to be caused under section</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the damage sustained by the person interested, by  reason of the removal of any standing crops in the exercise  of any power conferred by section 6;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the damage (if any) sustained by the person interested,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>by reason of ceasing to be able to use such land conjointly  with his other land;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the damage (if any) sustained by the person interested,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>by anything done or ordered under sections 6 and 7 injuri-</p>
              <p>ously affecting his other property, movable or immovable,</p>
              <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list7">
                <listIntroduction>in any other manner, or his earnings; and,</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list7.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>if, in consequence of the imposition of restrictions,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>the person interested is compelled to change his residence or  place of business, the reasonable expenses (if. any)</p>
              <p>incidental to such change.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In addition to the amount representing the actual decrease in the  market- value of the land as above provided, the Court shall in  every case award a further sum of fifteen per centum on such amount.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Matters not to be considered in determining compensation.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>In determining the amount of compensation to be awarded for damage  caused, or to be caused, or for restrictions imposed under this Act,</p>
              <blockList id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>the Court shall not take into consideration-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the degree of urgency which has led to the damage or  the imposition of restrictions;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>any disinclination of the person interested to submit  to damage or restrictions;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>any damage sustained by him, which, if caused by a  private person, would not render such person liable to a  suit;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>any increase to the value of the other land of the  person interested, accruing or likely to accrue from anything  done under this Act; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>any outlay or improvements on, or disposal of, the land  commenced, made or effected without the sanction of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Collector after the date of the publication of the  declaration under section 3.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Rules as to amount of compensation.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-25.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When the applicant  has made a claim to compensation, pursuant to any notice given under  section 9, the amount awarded to him by the Court shall not exceed the  amount so claimed or be less than the amount awarded by the Collector  under section 12.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When the applicant has refused to make such claim or has  omitted without sufficient reason (to be allowed by the Judge) to make  such claim, the amount awarded by the Court shall in no case exceed  the amount awarded by the Collector.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When the applicant has omitted for a sufficient reason (to   be allowed by the Judge) to make such claim, the amount awarded to him  by the Court shall not be less than, and may exceed, the amount  awarded by the Collector.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Form of awards. Every award under this Part shall be in  writing signed by the Judge, and shall specify the amount awarded  under section 23, sub- section (1), clause (a), and also the amounts (if   any) respectively awarded under each of the other clauses of the same  sub- section, together with the grounds of awarding each of the said  amounts.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Costs.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-27.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every such award shall also state the amount of  costs incurred in the proceedings under this Part, and by what persons  and in what proportion they are to be paid.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When the award of the Collector is not upheld, the costs  shall ordinarily be paid by the Collector, unless the Court is of  opinion that the claim of the applicant was so extravagant or that he  was so negligent in putting his case before the Collector that some  deduction from his costs should be made or that he should pay a part  of the Collector' s costs.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Collector may be directed to pay interest on excess  compensation. If the sum which, in the opinion of the Court, the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Collector ought to have awarded as compensation is in excess of the  sum which the Collector did award as compensation, the Court may  direct that the Collector shall pay interest on such excess at the  rate of six per centum per annum from the date of his award to the  date of payment of such excess into Court.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <heading>.</heading>
      </part>
      <part id="part-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="part-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>APPORTIONMENT OF COMPENSATION</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Particulars of apportionment to be specified. Where there  are several persons interested, if such persons agree in the  apportionment of the compensation, the particulars of such  apportionment shall be specified in the award, and as between such  persons the award shall be conclusive evidence of the correctness of  the apportionment.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading>Dispute as to apportionment. When the amount of  compensation has been settled under section 12, if any dispute arises  as to the apportionment of the same or any part thereof, or as to the  persons to whom the same or any part thereof is payable, the Collector  may refer such dispute to the decision of the Court.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-30.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>PAYMENT.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <paragraph id="part-V.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PAYMENT</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading>Payment of compensation or deposit of same in Court.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-31.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On  making an award under section 12, the Collector shall tender payment  of the compensation awarded by him to the persons interested entitled  thereto according to the award, and shall pay it to them unless  prevented by some one or more of the contingencies mentioned in sub-</p>
              <p>section (2).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If they do not consent to receive it, or if there is no  person competent to alienate the land, or if there is any dispute as  to the title to receive the compensation or as to the apportionment of  it, the Collector shall deposit the amount of the compensation in  the Court to which a reference under section 18 would be submitted:</p>
              <p>Provided, first, that any person admitted to be interested may  receive such payment under protest as to the sufficiency of the  amount:</p>
              <p>Provided, secondly, that no person who has received the amount  otherwise than under protest shall be entitled to make any application  under section 18:</p>
              <p>Provided, thirdly, that nothing herein contained shall affect the  liability of any person, who may receive the whole or any part of any  compensation awarded under this Act, to pay the same to the person  lawfully entitled thereto.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything in this section, the Collector may,</p>
              <p>with the sanction of the  Central Government], instead of awarding a  money- compensation in respect of any land, make any arrangement with a  person having a limited interest in such land, either by the grant of  other lands in exchange, or by the remission of land- revenue on the  same or on other lands held under the same title, or in such other way  as may be equitable having regard to the interests of the parties  concerned.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in sub- section (3) shall be construed to interfere  with or limit the power of the Collector to enter into any arrangement  with any person interested in the land and competent to contract in  respect thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>Investment of money deposited in respect of lands belonging  to persons incompetent to alienate.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-32.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any money is deposited in</p>
              <blockList id="section-32.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Court under section 31, sub- section (2), and it appears that the land  in respect of which the same was awarded belonged to any person who  had no power to alienate the same, the Court shall order the money to  be invested-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.1.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>in the purchase of other lands to be held under the  like title and conditions of ownership as the land in respect  of which such money was deposited is held, or,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.1.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>if such purchase cannot be effected forthwith, then in  such Government or other approved securities as it thinks  fit;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-32.1.list4">
                <listIntroduction>and shall direct the payment of the interest or other proceeds arising  from such investment to the person or persons who would for the time  being have been entitled to the possession of the said land, and such  moneys shall remain so deposited and invested until the same are  applied-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.1.list4.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>in the purchase of such other lands as aforesaid; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.1.list4.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>in payment to any person or persons becoming absolutely  entitled thereto.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In all cases of moneys deposited to which this section  applies, the Court shall order the cost of the following matters,</p>
              <blockList id="section-32.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>including therein all reasonable charges and expenses incident  thereto, to be paid by the Collector, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.2.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the costs of such investments as aforesaid;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.2.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the costs of the orders for the payment of the interest  or other proceeds of the securities in which such moneys are  for the time being invested, and for the payment out of Court  of the principal of such moneys and the costs of all  proceedings relating thereto, except such as may be  occasioned by litigation between adverse claimants.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading>Investment of money deposited in other cases. If any money  is deposited in Court under this Act for any cause other than that  mentioned in section 32, the Court may, on the application of any  party interested or claiming an interest in such money, order the same  to be invested in such Government or other approved securities as it  thinks fit, and may direct the interest or other proceeds of any such  investment to be accumulated and paid in such manner as well, in its  opinion, give the parties interested therein the same benefit  therefrom as they might have had from the land in respect of which  such money was deposited or as near thereto as may be.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-34">
          <num>34.</num>
          <heading>Payment of interest. When the amount of any compensation  awarded under this Act is not paid or deposited within fifteen days of  making the award, the Collector shall pay the amount awarded with  interest thereon at the rate of six per centum per annum from the date  of the award until it is so paid or deposited.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading>Service of notices.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-35.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Service of any notice under this</p>
              <p>Act shall be made by delivering or tendering a copy thereof signed, in  the case of a notice under section 3, sub- section (2), by the officer  therein mentioned, and, in the case of any other notice, by or by  order of the Collector or the Judge.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-35.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Whenever it may be practicable, the service of the notice  shall be made on the person therein named.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-35.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When such person cannot be found, the service may be made on  any adult male member of his family residing with him; and, if no such  adult male member can be found, the notice may be served by fixing the  copy on the outer door of the house in which the person therein named  ordinarily dwells or carries on business, or by fixing a copy thereof  in some conspicuous place in the office of the officer aforesaid or of  the Collector or in the court- house and also in some conspicuous part  of the land upon which restrictions are to be imposed:</p>
              <p>Provided that, if the Collector or Judge so directs, a notice may  be sent by post in a letter addressed to the person named therein at  his last known residence, address or place of business and service of  it may be proved by the production of the addressee' s receipt.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-36">
          <num>36.</num>
          <heading>Penalties. Whoever wilfully-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-36.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-36.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-36.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>obstructs any person in doing any of the acts  authorised by section 4, section 6 or section 8, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-36.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>destroys, damages, alters or otherwise interferes with  the ground- level or any work done under section 6, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-36.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>contravenes any of the provisions of section 7 or any  condition prescribed thereunder,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to  one month, or with fine which may extend to fifty rupees, or with  both, and, in the case of a continuing offence, with an additional  fine which may extend to five rupees for every day after the  first in regard to which he is convicted of having persisted  in the offence; and any expenses incurred in removing the  effects of his offence may be recovered from him in the  manner provided by the law for the time being in force for  the recovery of fines.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-37">
          <num>37.</num>
          <heading>Magistrate to enforce the terms of the Act. If the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-37.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Collector or officer authorised under section 6 is opposed or impeded  in doing anything directed or permitted by this Act, he shall, if a</p>
              <p>Magistrate, enforce compliance, and, if not a Magistrate,</p>
              <p>he shall apply to a Magistrate  or (within any area for which a</p>
              <p>Commissioner of Police has been appointed) to the Commissioner of</p>
              <p>Police], and such Magistrate or Commissioner (as the case may be) shall  enforce compliance.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-38">
          <num>38.</num>
          <heading>Completion of imposition of restrictions no compulsory but  compensation to be awarded when not completed.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-38.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The  Central</p>
              <p>Government] shall be at liberty to withdraw from the imposition of any  declared restrictions before any of the measures authorised by section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>have been taken.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Whenever the  Central Government] withdraws the imposition  of any declared restrictions, the Collector shall determine the amount  of compensation due for the damage suffered by the owner in  consequence of the notice or of any proceedings thereunder, and shall  pay such amount to the person interested, together with all costs  reasonably incurred by him in the prosecution of the proceedings under  this Act relating to the said restrictions.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of Part III shall apply, so far as may be, to  the determination of the compensation payable under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-39">
          <num>39.</num>
          <heading>Demolition of part of house or building and imposition of  restrictions on part of land.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-39.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Provisions of this Act shall  not be put in force for the purpose of demolishing or acquiring the  right to demolish a part only of any house, manufactory or other  building, if the owner desires that the whole of such house,</p>
              <p>manufactory or building shall be demolished or that the right to  demolish the whole of it shall be acquired:</p>
              <p>Provided that the owner may at any time before the Collector has  made his award under section 12, by notice in writing, withdraw or  modify his expressed desire that the whole of such house, manufactory  or building shall be demolished, or that the right to demolish the  whole of it shall be acquired:</p>
              <p>Provided, also, that, if any question shall arise as to whether  any building or other construction proposed to be demolished under  this Act does or does not form part of a house, manufactory or  building within the meaning of this section, the Collector shall  refer the determination of such question to the Court, and such  building or other construction shall not be demolished until after the  question has been determined.</p>
              <p>In deciding on such a reference the Court shall have regard to  the question whether the building or other construction proposed to be  demolished is reasonably required for the full and unimpaired use of  the house, manufactory or building.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-39.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If, in the case of any claim of the kind referred to in  section 23, sub- section (1), clause (c), by a person interested, on  account of ceasing to be able to use the land, upon the use and  enjoyment of which restrictions are to be imposed conjointly with his  other land, the  Central Government] is of opinion that the claim is  unreasonable or excessive, it may, at any time before the Collector  has made his award, order the imposition of restrictions upon the  whole of the land of which the land upon the use and enjoyment of  which it was first sought to impose restrictions forms a part.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-39.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the case provided for by sub- section (2) no fresh  declaration or other proceeding under sections 3 to 10 shall be  necessary; but the Collector shall without delay furnish a copy of the  order of the  Central Government] to the person interested, and shall  thereafter proceed to make his award under section 12.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-39.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in section 7, clause (a),</p>
              <p>any land, upon the use and enjoyment of which restrictions are imposed  under this section, may be included in the outer boundary, even though  its distance from the crest of the outer parapet of the work exceeds  two thousand yards.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-40">
          <num>40.</num>
          <heading>Exemption from stamp- duty and fees. No award or agreement  made under this Act shall be chargeable with stamp- duty, and no  person claiming under any such award or agreement shall be liable to  pay any fee for a copy of the same.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-41">
          <num>41.</num>
          <heading>Notice in case of suits for anything done in pursuance of</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-41.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Act. No suit or other proceeding shall be commenced or prosecuted  against any person for anything done in pursuance of this Act, without  giving to such person a month' s previous notice in writing of the  intended proceeding, and of the cause thereof, nor after tender of  sufficient amends.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-42">
          <num>42.</num>
          <heading>Code of Civil Procedure to apply to proceedings before</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-42.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Court. Save in so far as they may be inconsistent with anything con-</p>
              <p>tained in this Act, the provisions of the Code of Civil Procedure 2 (14   of 1882) shall apply to all proceedings before the Court under this</p>
              <p>Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-43">
          <num>43.</num>
          <heading>Appeals in proceedings before Court. Subject to the  provisions of the Code of Civil Procedure 2 (14 of 1882) applicable to  appeals from original decrees, an appeal shall lie to the High Court  from the award or from any part of the award of the Court in any  proceeding under this Act.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-44">
          <num>44.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-44.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules] for the guidance of  officers in all matters connected with the enforcement of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-44.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The power to make rules under sub- section (1) shall be  subject to the condition of the rules being made after previous  publication.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-44.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon  as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it  is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be com-</p>
              <p>prised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if,</p>
              <p>before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or  the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not  be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified  form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any  such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the  validity of anything previously done under that rule.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </part>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
