<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/3/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/3"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Part B States (Laws) Act, 1951"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/3/eng@1951-02-22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/3/eng@1951-02-22"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1951-02-22" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/3/eng@1951-02-22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/3/eng@1951-02-22"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Part B States (Laws) Act, 1951</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 3 OF 1951</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 22nd February, 1951.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the extension of certain laws to Part B</p>
        <p>States.</p>
      </longTitle>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament as follows:--</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <part id="part-B">
        <num>B</num>
        <heading>States (Laws) Act, 1951.</heading>
        <subsection id="part-B.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date  as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definition. In this Act," appointed day" means the date on  which this Act comes into force.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Extension and amendment of certain Acts and Ordinances. The</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Acts and Ordinances specified in the Schedule shall be amended in the  manner and to the extent therein specified, and the territorial extent  of each of the said Acts and Ordinances shall, as from the appointed  day and in so far as any of the said Acts or Ordinances or any of the  provisions contained therein relates to matters with respect to which</p>
              <p>Parliament has power to make laws, be as stated in the extent clause  thereof as so amended.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Construction of references to laws not in force in Part B</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>States. Any reference in any Act or Ordinance specified in the</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-scheduleto">
      <doc name="scheduleto">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/3/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/3"/>
              <FRBRalias value="a law which is not in force in a Part B State shall, in  relation to that State, be construed as a reference to the  corresponding law, if any, in force in that State."/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/3/eng@1951-02-22/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/3/eng@1951-02-22"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/3/eng@1951-02-22/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/3/eng@1951-02-22"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduleto">
            <section id="section-5">
              <num>5.</num>
              <heading>Construction of references to authorities where new  authorities have been constituted. Any reference, by whatever form of  words, in any law for the time being in force in a Part B State to any  authority competent at the date of the passing of that law to exercise  any powers or discharge any functions in that State shall, where a  corresponding new authority has been constituted by or under any Act  or Ordinance now extended to that State, have effect as if it were a  reference to that new authority.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-6">
              <num>6.</num>
              <heading>Repeals and savings. If immediately before the appointed day,</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>there is in force in any Part B State any law corresponding to any of  the Acts or Ordinances now extended to that State, that law shall,</p>
                  <p>save as otherwise expressly provided in  this Act] stand repealed:</p>
                  <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>Provided that the repeal shall not affect--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list3.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the previous operation of any law so repealed or  anything duly done or suffered thereunder, or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>any right, privilege, obligation or liability acquired,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list5">
                    <listIntroduction>accrued or incurred under any law so repealed, or</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list5.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>any penalty, forfeiture or punishment incurred in  respect of any offence committed against any law so  repealed, or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list5.d">
                      <num>(d)</num>
                      <p>any investigation, legal proceeding or remedy in respect  of any such right, privilege, obligation, liability,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>penalty, forfeiture or punishment as aforesaid;</p>
                  <p>and any such investigation, legal proceeding or remedy may be  instituted, continued or enforced, and any such penalty, forfeiture or  punishment may be imposed as if this Act had not been passed:</p>
                  <p>Provided further that, subject to the preceding proviso, anything  done or any action taken (including any appointment or delegation  made, notification, order, instruction or direction issued, rule,</p>
                  <p>regulation, form, bye- law or scheme framed, certificate obtained,</p>
                  <p>patent, permit or licence granted or registration effected) under any  such law shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the  corresponding provision of the Act or Ordinace as now extended to that</p>
                  <p>State, and shall continue to be in force accordingly, unless and until  superseded by anything done or any action taken under the said Act or</p>
                  <p>Ordinance.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-7">
              <num>7.</num>
              <heading>Power to remove difficulties.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-7.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>If any difficulty arises in  giving effect in any Part B State to the provisions of any Act or</p>
                  <p>Ordinance now extended to that State, the Central Government may, by  order notified in the Official Gazette, make such provisions or give  such directions as appear to it to be necessary for the removal of the  difficulty.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-7.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-7.2.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, any such notified order may--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-7.2.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>specify the corresponding authorities within the meaning  of section 5;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-7.2.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>provide for the transfer of any matter pending before  any Court, tribunal or other authority, immediately  before the appointed day, to any corresponding Court,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-7.2.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>tribunal or other authority for disposal;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-7.2.list3.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>specify the areas or circumstances in which, or the  extent to which or the conditions subject to which,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>anything done or any action taken including any of the  matters specified in the second proviso to section (6)</p>
                  <p>under any law repealed by that section shall be  recognised or given effect to under the corresponding  provision of the Act or Ordinance as now extended.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
