<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1976/89/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1976/89"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Indian Iron And Steel Company (Acquistion Of Shares) Act, 1976"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1976/89/eng@1976-09-02/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1976/89/eng@1976-09-02"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1976-09-02" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1976/89/eng@1976-09-02/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1976/89/eng@1976-09-02"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Indian Iron And Steel Company (Acquistion Of Shares) Act, 1976</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 89 OF 1976</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 2nd September, 1976.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the acquistion of certain shares of the Indian</p>
        <p>Iron and Steel Company Limited with a view to securing the proper  management of the affairs of the Company and the continuity and  development of the production of goods which are vital to the needs of  the country and for matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.</p>
        <p>CHAP</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the</p>
              <p>Indian Iron and Steel Company (Acquistion of Shares) Act, 1976.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 17th day of</p>
              <p>July, 1976.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" appointed day" means the 17th day of July, 1976;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" bank" means a banking company within the meaning of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Banking Regulation Act, 1949 (10 of 1949.);</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" Company" means the Indian Iron and Steel Company</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Limited, being a company within the meaning of the</p>
              <p>Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956.), and having its  registered office at IISCO House, 50, Chowringhee Road,</p>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Calcutta;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" Commissioner" means the Commissioner of Payments  appointed under section 5;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>" notification" means a notification published in the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list8">
                <listIntroduction>Official Gazette;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list8.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10">
                <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10.g.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>" share" means a share, whether equity or preference, in  the capital of the Company, and includes a share  pledged by any shareholder with any bank or other  creditor, but does not include any share in the capital  of the Company held by--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10.g.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>any State Government;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10.g.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>the State Bank of India, established under  section 3 of the State Bank of India Act, 1955 (23 of</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1955">
          <num>1955.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1955.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1955.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>) and its subsidiary banks;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1955.paragraph-0.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>the Steel Authority of India Limited, a  company formed and registered under the Companies Act,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1956">
          <num>1956.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1956.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>, (1 of 1956.) and having its registered office at</p>
              <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Hindustan Times House, Kasturba Gandhi Marg, New Delhi;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list2.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>the Life Insurance Corporation of India,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>established under section 3 of the Life Insurance</p>
              <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Corporation Act, 1956 (31 of 1956.);</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list5.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>the Unit Trust of India, established under  section 3 of the Unit Trust of India Act, 1963 (52 of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1963">
          <num>1963.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1963.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>);</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list1.vi">
                  <num>(vi)</num>
                  <p>any corresponding new bank, within the  meaning of the Banking Companies (Acquisition and</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Transfer of Undertakings) Act, 1970 (5 of 1970.);</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list3.vii">
                  <num>(vii)</num>
                  <p>any general insurance company nationalised  by the General Insurance Business (Nationalisation)</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Act, 1972 (57 of 1972.);</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list5.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list5.h.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>" shareholder" means,--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list5.h.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>a person who, immediately before the appointed  day, was registered by the Company as the holder of any  share and includes his legal representative; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list5.h.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>a person who, before the appointed day, had  lodged with the Company a proper instrument of transfer  of any share in the form prescribed under section 108  of the Companies Act, 1956, (1 of 1956.) and executed  in accordance with the provisions of that section; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list5.h.list0.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>a person who claims under a proper  instrument of transfer of any share in the form  prescribed under section 108 of the Companies Act,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1956">
          <num>1956.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1956.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>, (1 of 1956.) and delivers such instrument, duly  executed, to the Commissioner  before the expiry of  one hundred and twenty days from the date of  commencement of the Indian Iron and Steel Company</p>
              <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>(Acquistion of Shares) Amendment Act, 1981];]</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list2.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>" specified date" means such date as the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Central Government may, for the purpose of any  provision of this Act, by notification, specify.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>ACQUISITION OF THE SHARES OF THE COMPANY</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>ACQUISITION OF THE SHARES OF THE COMPANY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Transfer and vesting of shares of the Company in the Central</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On the appointed day, all the shares of the Company  shall, by virtue of this Act, stand transferred to, and vested in, the</p>
              <p>Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government shall be deemed, on and from the  appointed day, to have been registered in the Register of members of  the Company as the holder of each share which stands transferred to,</p>
              <p>and vested in, it by virtue of the provisions of sub- section (1).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All the shares which have vested in the Central Government  under sub- section (1), shall, by force of such vesting, be freed and  discharged of all trusts, liabilities, obligations, mortgages,</p>
              <p>charges, liens and other incumbrances affecting them, and any  attachment, injunction or any decree or order of the court, tribunal  or other</p>
              <p>authority restricting the use of such shares in any manner, shall be  deemed to have been withdrawn.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.4.list1">
                <listIntroduction>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that the  provisions of sub- sections (1) and (2) shall not be deemed to affect--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.4.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>any right of the Company subsisting, immediately before  the appointed day, against any shareholder to recover  from such shareholder any sum of money on the ground  that the shareholder has not paid or credited to the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Company the whole or any part of the value of the  shares held by him, or on any other ground whatsoever;</p>
              <blockList id="section-3.4.list4">
                <listIntroduction>or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.4.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>any right of the shareholder subsisting, immediately  before the appointed day, against the Company to  receive any dividend or other payment due from the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Company.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Payment of amounts.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the transfer to, and vesting in,</p>
              <p>the Central Government, under section 3, of the shares of the Company,</p>
              <p>there shall be given by the Central Government to the shareholders of  the Company, in cash and in the manner specified in section 6, an  amount of rupees seven crores, twenty- three lakhs, ninety- five  thousand and one hundred and thirty- seven and fifteen paise.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The amount, referred to in sub- section (1), shall carry  simple interest at the rate of four per cent, per annum for the period  commencing on the appointed day and ending on the date on which  payment of such amount is made by the Central Government to the</p>
              <p>Commissioner.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Appointment of Commissioner, of Payments.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central</p>
              <p>Government shall, for the purpose of disbursing the amounts payable to  the Company under section 4, by notification, appoint a Commissioner  of Payments.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may appoint such other persons as it  may think fit to assist the Commissioner and thereupon the</p>
              <p>Commissioner may authorise one or more of such persons also to  exercise all or any of the powers exercisable by him under this Act,</p>
              <p>and different persons may be authorised to exercise different powers.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person authorised by the Commissioner to exercise any of  the powers exercisable by the Commissioner may exercise those powers  in the same manner and with the same effect as if they have</p>
              <p>been conferred on that person directly by this Act, and not by way of  authorisation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The salaries and allowances of the Commissioner and other  persons appointed under this section shall be defrayed out of the</p>
              <p>Consolidated Fund of India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Payment by the Central Government to the Commissioner.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The</p>
              <p>Central Government shall, within thirty days from the specified date</p>
              <blockList id="section-6.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>, pay, in cash, to the Commissioner, for payment to the shareholders  of the Company,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.1.list3.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>an amount equal to the amount specified in sub- section</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-6.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>of section 4; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>an amount equal to the amount determined under sub-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>section (2) of section 4.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A deposit account shall be opened by the Central Government  in favour of the Commissioner, in the Public Account of India, and  every amount paid under this Act to the Commissioner shall be  deposited by him to the credit of the said deposit account and the  said deposit account shall be operated by the Commissioner.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The interest accruing on the amount standing to the credit of  the deposit account, referred to in sub- section (2), shall enure to  the benefit of the shareholders of the Company.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Claims to be made to the Commissioner.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every shareholder,</p>
              <p>having a claim in relation to any share acquired by this Act, shall  prefer such claim before the Commissioner  before the expiry of one  hundred and twenty days from the date of commencement of the Indian</p>
              <p>Iron and Steel Company (Acquisition of Shares) Amendment Act, 1981]</p>
              <p>Provided that if the Commissioner is satisfied that the  claimant was prevented by sufficient cause from preferring the claim  before the expiry of the said period of one hundred and twenty days,</p>
              <p>he may entertain the claim within a further period of one hundred and  twenty days and not thereafter.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.1A">
            <num>(1A)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every claim preferred under sub- section (1) as it stood  before the commencement of the Indian Iron and Steel Company</p>
              <p>(Acquisition of Shares) Amendment Act, 1981, after the expiry of the  period or date specified therein shall be deemed to have been  preferred under the said sub- section as amended by the said Amendment</p>
              <p>Act and shall be dealt with (even if it had been disallowed before   such commencement) as if it had been preferred within time.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every shareholder of a preference share shall have a  prevential claim with regard to the amount paid by the Central</p>
              <p>Government to the Commissioner.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7A">
          <num>7A.</num>
          <heading>Power of Commissioner to inquire into disputes as to  persons entitled to any amount. Where there is any dispute as to the  person or persons who are entitled to any amount payable under this</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7A.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Act (including any dispute as to who are the legal representatives of  any deceased</p>
              <p>claimant to the amount), the Commissioner may, after making such  inquiry as he may deem fit, make the payment to such person as appears  to him to be best entitled to receive the amount:</p>
              <p>Provided that if the Commissioner is unable to determine as to  who is the person entitled to the amount and considers that the matter  could more appropriately be dealt with by the principal civil court of  original jurisdiction within the local limits of whose jurisdiction  the registered office of the Company is situated, he may refer such  dispute to the said court, whose decision thereon shall be final:</p>
              <p>Provided further that nothing contained herein shall affect the  liability of any person, who may receive the whole or any part of the  amount allowed under this Act, to pay the same to the person lawfully  entitled thereto.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7B">
          <num>7B.</num>
          <heading>Deposit of amount in court. Where any dispute has been  referred under section 7A by the Commissioner to the civil court  referred to therein, he shall deposit the amount in that court.]</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Examination of claims. On receipt of the claims made under  section 7, the Commisioner shall separately arrange the claims in  relation to preference shares and in relation to the equity shares and  examine the claims in relation to each such share.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Admission or rejection of claims.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>After examining the  claims, the Commissioner shall fix a certain date on or before which  every claimant shall file the proof of his claim or be excluded from  the benefit of the disbursements made by the Commissioner.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Not less than fourteen days' notice of the date so fixed  shall be given by advertisement in one issue of the daily newspaper in  the English language and in one issue of such daily newspaper in the  regional language as the Commissioner may consider suitable, and every  such notice shall call upon the claimant to file the proof of his  claim with the Commissioner within the time specified in the  advertisement.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every claimant, who fails to file the proof of his claim  within the time specified by the Commissioner, shall be excluded from  the disbursement made by the Commissioner.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Commissioner shall, after such investigation as may, in  his opinion, be necessary, and after giving the Company an opportunity  of</p>
              <p>refuting the claim and after giving the claimant a reasonable  opportunity of being heard, in writing, admit or reject the claim in  whole or in part.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Commissioner shall have the power to regulate his own  procedure in all matters arising out of the discharge of his  functions, including the place or places at which he will hold his  sittings and shall, for the purpose of making an investigation under  this Act, have the same powers as are vested in a civil court under  the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908, (5 of 1908.) while trying a suit,</p>
              <blockList id="section-9.5.list2">
                <listIntroduction>in respect of the following matters, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-9.5.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the summoning and enforcing the attendance of any  witness and examining him on oath;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.5.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the discovery and production of any document or other  material object producible as evidence;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.5.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the reception of evidence on affidavits;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.5.list2.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the issuing of any commission for the examination of  witnesses.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any investigation before the Commissioner shall be deemed to  be a judicial proceeding within the meaning of sections 193 and 228 of  the Indian Penal Code (65 of 1960.) and the Commissioner shall be  deemed to be a civil court for the purposes of section 345 and Chapter</p>
              <p>XXVI of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974.).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A claimant, who is dissatisfied with the decision of the</p>
              <p>Commissioner, may prefer an appeal against the decision to the  principal civil court of original jurisdiction within the local limits  of whose jurisdiction the registered office of the Company is  situated.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Disbursement of money by the Commissioner to claimants.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>After admitting a claim under this Act, the amount due in respect of  each share acquired by virtue of this Act shall be paid by the</p>
              <p>Commissioner at the rate of rupees thirty- two and paise seventy- five  per preference share, and at the rate of rupees four and paise seventy  per equity share to the person or persons to whom such sums are due,</p>
              <p>and on such payment, the liability of the Central Government in  respect of the share so acquired shall stand discharged.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Commissioner shall also apportion amongst the  shareholders, the amount paid to him by way of interest under sub-</p>
              <p>section (3) of section 6, and such apportionment shall be made on the  basis of the amount due to each shareholder.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Undisburse or unciaimed amount to be deposited to the general  revenue account. Any money paid to the Commissioner which remains  undisbursed or unclaimed for a period of  six months] from the last  day on which the disbursement was made, shall be transferred by the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Commissioner to the general revenue account of the Central Government;</p>
              <p>but a claim to any money so transferred may be preferred to the</p>
              <p>Central Government by the person entitled to such payment and shall be  dealt with as if such transfer had not been made, the order, if any,</p>
              <p>for payment of the claim being treated as an order for the refund of  revenue.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Power of inspection. For the purposes of ascertaining whether  any person claiming payment under this Act is a shareholder, the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Commissioner shall have the right to--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>require any person, having the possession, custody or  control, of any register or record of the Company, to  produce such register or record before the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Commissioner,</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>require any person to make any statement or furnish any  information which may be required by the Commissioner.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Act to have overriding effect. The provisions of this Act  shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith  contained in any law, other than this Act, or in any instrument having  effect by virtue of any law, other than this Act.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Penalties. If any person,--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-14.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>makes any claim for any payment under this Act, knowing  or having reason to believe that such claim is false or  without any basis; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-14.paragraph-0.list0.b.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>when required under this Act so to do,--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list0.b.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>omits or fails to produce any register or  record of the Company; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list0.b.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>makes any statement or furnishes any  information which is false in any material particular  and which he knows or believes to be false or does not  believe to be true; or</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>makes any such statement as aforesaid in any book,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>account, record, register, return or other document.</p>
              <p>he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend  to two years, or with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees, or  with both.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Offences by companies.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-15.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where an offence under this Act  has been committed by a company, every person who, at the time the  offence was committed, was in charge of, and was responsible to, the  company for the conduct of the business of the company as well as the  company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be  liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:</p>
              <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render  any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the  offence was committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised  all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where  any offence under this Act has been committed with the consent or  connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any  director, manager, secretary or other officer, such director, manager,</p>
              <p>secretary or other officer shall be deemed to be guilty of that  offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished  accordingly.</p>
              <blockList id="section-15.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-15.2.list3.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm  or other association of individuals; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-15.2.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner in  the firm.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Limitation of cognizance of offences. No court shall take  cognizance of an offence punishable under this Act, except with the  previous sanction of the Central Government or of an officer  authorised by that Government in this behalf.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, by  notification, make rules to carry out the provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act  shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House  of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty  days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more  successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session  immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or  both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall  thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</p>
              <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that rule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Repeal and saving. The Indian Iron and Steel Company</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>(Acquisition of Shares) Ordinance, 1976 (10 of 1976.), is hereby  repealed:</p>
              <p>Provided that notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any  action taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been  done or taken under the corresponding provision of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
