<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1966/26/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1966/26"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Delhi High Court Act, 1966"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1966/26/eng@1966-09-05/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1966/26/eng@1966-09-05"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1966-09-05" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1966/26/eng@1966-09-05/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1966/26/eng@1966-09-05"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Delhi High Court Act, 1966</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 26 OF 1966 AN ACT TO PROVIDE FOR THE CONSTITUTION OF A HIGH COURT</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 5th September, 1966.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Seventeenth Year of  the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>FOR THE UNION TER</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Delhi High Court Act, 1966.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Section 17 shall come into force on such date 1 as the</p>
            <p>Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette,</p>
            <p>appoint; and the remaining provisions of this Act shall come into  force at once.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" appointed day" means the date appointed under section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" notified order" means order notified in the Official</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Gazette.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>High Court.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>As from such date 2 as the Central Government  may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint, there shall be  a High Court for the Union territory of Delhi (hereinafter referred to   as the High Court of Delhi).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The principal seat of the High Court of Delhi shall be at</p>
            <p>Delhi or at such other place as the President may, by notified order,</p>
            <p>appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (2), the</p>
            <p>Judges and Division Courts of the High Court of Delhi may sit at such  other place or places other than its principal seat as the Chief</p>
            <p>Justice may, with the approval of the President, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3A">
        <num>3A.</num>
        <heading>Salaries and allowances of Judges to be expenditure  charged on Consolidated Fund of India. Expenditure in respect of the  salaries and allowances of Judges of the High Court of Delhi shall be  expenditure charged on the Consolidated Fund of India.]</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Exceptions and modifications subject to which the provisions of</heading>
      </section>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <heading>of Part VI of the Constitution apply to the High Court of</heading>
        <paragraph id="chapter-V.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Delhi.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="chapter-V.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="chapter-V.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The provisions of Chapter V of Part VI of the Constitution  shall, in their application to the High Court of Delhi, have effect  subject to the following exceptions and modifications, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="chapter-V.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in article 217, the words" the Governor of the State"</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall be omitted and in relation to appointments to be made  under sub- section (2), that article shall be construed as if  the words" and, in the case of appointment of a Judge other  than the Chief Justice, the Chief Justice of the High Court,"</p>
            <blockList id="chapter-V.1.list4">
              <listIntroduction>had also been omitted;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="chapter-V.1.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in article 219, the reference to the Governor of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="chapter-V.1.list6">
              <listIntroduction>State, and in the proviso to clause (3) of article 227, the  reference to the Governor, shall be construed as a reference  to the administrator of the Union territory of Delhi</listIntroduction>
              <item id="chapter-V.1.list6.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the provisions of article 225 shall not apply</p>
              </item>
              <item id="chapter-V.1.list6.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <blockList id="chapter-V.1.list6.d.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>in article 229,-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="chapter-V.1.list6.d.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>the references to the Governor of the State shall be  construed as references to the administrator of the</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="chapter-V.1.list8">
              <listIntroduction>Union territory of Delhi;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="chapter-V.1.list8.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>the references to the State Public Service Com-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>mission, the Legislature of the State and the Consoli-</p>
            <p>dated Fund of the State shall be construed,</p>
            <p>respectively, as references to the Union Public Service</p>
            <p>Commission, Parliament and the Consolidated Fund of</p>
            <blockList id="chapter-V.1.list14">
              <listIntroduction>India;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="chapter-V.1.list14.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <blockList id="chapter-V.1.list14.e.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>the provisions of article 230 shall apply subject to  the modifications that-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="chapter-V.1.list14.e.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>in clause (1) thereof, for the words" High Court in  both the places where they occur, the words" High Court  for a Union territory" and for the words" any Union  territory", the words" any other Union territory"</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="chapter-V.1.list16">
              <listIntroduction>shall be substituted;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="chapter-V.1.list16.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>for clause (2) thereof, the following clause shall  be substituted, namely:-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>" (2) Where the High Court for a Union territory  exercises jurisdiction in relation to another Union  territory, the reference in article 227 to the  administrator of the Union territory of Delhi  shall, in relation to any rules, forms or tables  for subordinate courts in that other Union  territory, be construed as a reference to the admi-</p>
            <p>nistrator of that other Union territory."</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="chapter-V.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Between the coming into force of this section and the  appointed day, the President may, after consultation with the Chief</p>
            <p>Justice of India, appoint the Chief Justice of the High Court of Delhi  and</p>
            <p>as many other Judges of the said High Court as he thinks fit, and an  appointments so made shall take effect as from the appointed day.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Jurisdiction of High Court.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The High Court of Delhi  shall have, in respect of the territories for the time being included  in the Union territory of Delhi all such original, appellate and other  jurisdiction as, under the law in force immediately before the  appointed day, is exercisable in respect of the said territories by  the High Court of Punjab.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time  being in force, the High Court of Delhi shall also have in respect of  the said territories ordinary original civil jurisdiction in every  suit the value of which exceeds  rupees five lakhs].</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Power to enrol legal practitioners, etc.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The High Court  of Delhi shall have like powers to approve, admit, enrol, remove and  suspend legal practitioners, and to make rules with respect to them,</p>
              <p>as are, under the law in force immediately before the appointed day  exercisable by the High Court of Punjab.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The right of audience in the High Court of Delhi shall be  regulated in accordance with the like principles, as, immediately  before the appointed day, are in force with respect to the right of  audience in the High Court of Punjab:</p>
              <p>Provided that subject to any rule made or direction given by the</p>
              <p>High Court of Delhi in the exercise of the powers conferred by this  section, any person who immediately before the appointed day is an  advocate entitled to practise or an attorney entitled to act in the</p>
              <p>High Court of Punjab shall be recognised as an advocate or an attorney  entitled to practise or act, as the case may be, in the High Court of</p>
              <p>Delhi.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Practice and procedure in the High Court of Delhi. Subject  to the provisions of this Act, the law in force immediately before the  appointed day with respect to practice and procedure in the High Court  of Punjab shall, with the necessary modifications, apply in relation  to the High Court of Delhi and accordingly the High Court of Delhi  shall have all such powers to make rules and orders with respect to  practice and procedure as are immediately before the appointed day  exercisable by the High Court of Punjab and shall also have powers to  make rules and orders with respect to practice and procedure for the  exercise of its ordinary original civil jurisdiction:</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Provided that any rules or orders which are in force immediately  before the appointed day with respect to practice and procedure in the</p>
              <p>High Court of Punjab shall, until varied or revoked by rules or</p>
              <p>orders made by the High Court of Delhi, apply with the necessary  modifications in relation to practice and procedure in the High Court  of Delhi as if made by that High Court.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Custody of the Seal of the High Court of Delhi. The law in  force immediately before the appointed day with respect to the custody  of the Seal of the High Court of Punjab shall, with the necessary  modifications, apply with respect to the custody of the Seal of the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>High Court of Delhi.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Form of writs and other processes. The law in force  immediately before the appointed day with respect to the form of writs  and other processes used, issued or awarded by the High Court of</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Punjab shall, with the necessary modifications, apply with respect to  the form of writs and other processes used, issued or awarded by the</p>
              <p>High Court of Delhi.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Powers of Judges.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where a single Judge of the High Court  of Delhi exercises ordinary original civil jurisdiction conferred by  sub- section (2) of section 5 on that Court, an appeal shall lie from  the judgment of the single Judge to a Division Court of that High</p>
              <p>Court.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (1), the law in force  immediately before the appointed day relating to the powers of the</p>
              <p>Chief Justice, single Judges and Division Courts of the High Court of</p>
              <p>Punjab and with respect to all matters ancillary to the exercise of  those powers shall, with the necessary modifications, apply in  relation to the High Court of Delhi.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Procedure as to appeals to Supreme Court. The law in force  immediately before the appointed day relating to appeals to the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Supreme Court from the High Court of Punjab and the Judges and</p>
              <p>Division Courts thereof shall, with the necessary modifications, apply  in relation to the High Court of Delhi.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Transfer of proceedings from the High Court of Punjab to the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>High Court of Delhi.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-12.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except as hereinafter provided, the High Court  of Punjab shall, as from the appointed day, have no jurisdiction in  respect of the Union territory of Delhi.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Such proceedings pending in the High Court of Punjab imme-</p>
              <p>diately before the appointed day as are certified, whether before or  after that day, by the Chief Justice of that High Court having regard  to the place of accrual of the cause of action and other circumstances  to be proceedings which ought to be heard and decided by the High</p>
              <p>Court of Delhi, shall, as soon as may be after such certification, be  transferred to the High Court of Delhi.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- sections (l) and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of this section and in section 5, but save as hereinafter  provided,</p>
              <p>the High Court of Punjab shall have, and the High Court of Delhi shall  not have, jurisdiction to entertain, hear or dispose of, appeals  applications for leave to appeal including leave to appeal to the</p>
              <p>Supreme Court, applications for review and other proceedings where any  such proceedings seek any relief in respect of any order passe by the</p>
              <p>High Court of Punjab before the appointed day:</p>
              <p>Provided that if after any, such proceedings have been  entertained by the High Court of Punjab, it appears to the Chief</p>
              <p>Justice of that High Court that they ought to be transferred to the</p>
              <p>High Court of Delhi, he shall order that they shall be so transferred,</p>
              <p>and such proceedings shall thereupon be transferred accordingly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-12.4.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Any order made by the High Court of Punjab-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12.4.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>before the appointed day, in any proceedings  transferred to the High Court of Delhi by virtue of sub-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-12.4.list3">
                <listIntroduction>section (2);</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12.4.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>in any proceedings with respect to which the High</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Court of Punjab retains jurisdiction by virtue of sub-</p>
              <p>section (3),</p>
              <p>shall for all purposes have effect, not only as an order of the High</p>
              <p>Court of Punjab, but also as an order made by the High Court of Delhi.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Right to appear or to act in proceedings transferred to  the High Court of Delhi. Any person who, immediately before the  appointed day, is an advocate entitled to practise or an attorney  entitled to act, in the High Court of Punjab, and was authorised to  appear or to act in any proceedings transferred from that High Court  to the High Court of Delhi under section 12, shall have the right to  appear or to act, as the case may be, in the High Court of Delhi in  relation to those proceedings.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Interpretation. For the purposes of sections 12 and 17,-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-14.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>proceedings shall be deemed to be pending in a  court until that court has disposed of all issues  between the parties, including any issues with respect  to the taxation of the costs of the proceedings and  shall include appeals, applications for leave to appeal  to the Supreme Court, applications for review, petitions  for revision and petitions for writs;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>references to a High Court shall be construed as  including references to a Judge or Division Court  thereof, and references to an order made by a court or a</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Judge shall be construed as including references to a  sentence, judgment or decree passed or made by that  court or Judge.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Savings. Save as provided in section 4, nothing in this Act  shall affect the application to the High Court of Delhi of any  provisions of the Constitution, and this Act shall have effect subject  to any provision that may be made on or after the appointed day with  respect to that High Court by any Legislature or other authority  having power to make such provision.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Pending proceedings before subordinate courts in Delhi. All  proceedings pending immediately before the appointed day in any  subordinate court in the Union territory of Delhi in or in relation to  any such civil suit as is referred to in sub- section (2) of section 5  shall on that day stand transferred to the High Court of Delhi which  shall proceed to try, hear and determine the matter as if it had been  pending therein.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Extension of the jurisdiction of the High Court of Delhi.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As from such date 1 as the Central Government may, by notification  in the Official Gazette, appoint (hereinafter referred to as the   prescribed date), the jurisdiction of the High Court of Delhi shall  extend to the Union territory of Himachal Pradesh.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As from the prescribed date the Court of the Judicial Com-</p>
              <p>missioner for Himachal Pradesh shall cease to function and is hereby  abolished:</p>
              <p>Provided that nothing in this sub- section shall prejudice or  affect the continued operation of any notice served, injunction  issued, direction given, or proceedings taken before the prescribed  date by the Court of the Judicial Commissioner for Himachal Pradesh  abolished by this sub- section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The High Court of Delhi shall have, in respect of the terri-</p>
              <p>tories for the time being included in the Union territory of Himachal</p>
              <blockList id="section-17.3.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Pradesh,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.3.list3.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>all such original, appellate and other jurisdiction as under  the law in force immediately before the prescribed date, is  exercisable in respect of the said territories by the Court  of the Judicial Commissioner for Himachal Pradesh; and also</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.3.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>ordinary original civil jurisdiction in every suit the  value of which exceeds  fifty thousand rupees],</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time  being in force.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All proceedings pending in the Court of the Judicial Commis-</p>
              <p>sioner for Himachal Pradesh before the prescribed date shall stand  transferred to the High Court of Delhi.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any order made before the prescribed date by the Court  referred to in sub- section (4) shall for all purposes have effect not  only as an order of that Court but also as an order of the High Court  of Delhi.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that the  provisions of sections 6 to 11 and 13 shall, with the necessary  modifications, apply to the High Court of Delhi in the exercise of  jurisdiction conferred upon it by this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All proceedings pending immediately before the prescribed  date in any subordinate court in the Union territory of Himachal</p>
              <p>Pradesh in or in relation to any such civil suit as is referred to in  clause (b) of sub- section (3) shall on- that date stand transferred to  the High Court of Delhi which shall proceed to try, hear and determine  the matter as if it had been pending therein.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Rule of construction.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-18.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>References in any law in force in  the Union territory of Delhi to the High Court of Punjab shall, as  from the appointed day, be construed in relation to that Union  territory as references to the High Court of Delhi.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>References in any law in force in the Union territory of</p>
              <p>Himachal Pradesh to the High Court of Punjab or to the Court of the</p>
              <p>Judicial Commissioner for that territory shall, as from the prescribed  ate, be construed in relation to that Union territory as references to  the High Court of Delhi.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Amendment of certain laws. Rep. by the Repealing and</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Amending Act, 1974 (56 of 1974) s. 2 and Sch. 1.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Power to remove difficulties.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-20.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any difficulty arises  in giving effect to the provisions OX this Act, the Central Government  may, by notified order, make such provision as appears to it to be  necessary or expedient for the removal of the difficulty.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every order made under this section shall be laid as soon as  may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is in  session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in  one session or in two successive sessions, and if, before the expiry  of the session in which it is so laid or the session immediately  following both Houses agree in making any modification in the order or  both Houses agree that the order should not be made, the order shall</p>
              <p>thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</p>
              <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annul-</p>
              <p>ment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously  done under that order.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Power to adapt Laws. For the purpose of facilitating the  application of any law in relation to the Union territory of Delhi or</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Himachal Pradesh, the Central Government may, before the expiration of  two years from the appointed,, day in relation to the Union territory  of Delhi and before the expiration of two years from the prescribed  date in relation to the union territory of Himachal Pradesh, by order,</p>
              <p>make such adaptations and modifications of the law, whether by way of  repeal or amendment, as may be necessary or expedient to give effect  to the provisions of this Act and thereupon every such law shall have  effect subject to the adaptions and modifications so made until  altered, repealed or amended by a competent Legislature or other  competent authority.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
