<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1878/6/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1878/6"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Indian Treasure- Trove Act, 1878"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1878/6/eng@1878-02-13/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1878/6/eng@1878-02-13"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1878-02-13" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1878/6/eng@1878-02-13/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1878/6/eng@1878-02-13"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Indian Treasure- Trove Act, 1878</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 6 OF 1878</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 13th February, 1878.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to amend the law relating to Treasure- trove.</p>
        <p>Preamble.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to amend the law relating to  treasuretrove; It is hereby enacted as follows:--</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title. This Act may be called the Indian Treasure- trove</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Act, 1878.</p>
            <p>Extent.</p>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India except  the territories which,</p>
            <p>immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised in Part B</p>
            <p>States].</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Repeal of enactments. Rep. by the Repealing and Amending</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Act, 1891 (12 of 1891), s. 2 and Sch. I.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Interpretation- clause." Treasure." In this Act--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>" treasure" means anything of any value hidden in the soil,</p>
            <p>or in anything affixed thereto:</p>
            <p>" Collector."</p>
            <p>" Collector." means (1) any Revenue- officer in independent  charge of a district, and (2) any officer appointed by  the State Government to perform the functions of a</p>
            <p>Collector under this Act</p>
            <p>" Owner."</p>
            <p>When any person is entitled, under any reservation in an  instrument of transfer of any land or thing affixed thereto, to  treasure in such land or thing, he shall, for the purposes of this</p>
            <p>Act, be deemed to be the owner of such land or thing.</p>
            <p>PROCEDURE ON FINDING TREASURE</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Notice by finder of treasure. Whenever any treasure exceeding  in amount or value ten rupees is found, the finder shall, as soon as  practicable, give to the Collector notice in writing--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>of the nature and amount or approximate value of such  treasure;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>of the place in which it was found;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>of the date of the finding;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>and either deposit the treasure in the nearest Government  treasury, or give the Collector such security as the Collector thinks  fit, to produce the treasure at such time and place as he may from  time to time require.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Notification requiring claimants to appear. On receiving a  notice under section 4, the Collector shall, after making such enquiry</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>(if any) as he thinks fit, take the following steps (namely):--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>he shall publish a notification in such manner as the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>State Government from time to time prescribes in this  behalf, to the effect that, on a certain date</p>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>(mentioning it) certain treasure (mentioning its   nature, amount and approximate value) was found in a  certain place (mentioning it); and requiring all  persons claiming the treasure, or any part thereof, to  appear personally or by agent before the Collector on a  day and at a place therein mentioned, such day not  being earlier than four months, or later than six  months, after the date of the publication of such  notification;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>when the place in which the treasure appears to the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Collector to have been found was at the date of the  finding in the possession of some person other than the  finder,</p>
            <p>the Collector shall also serve on such person a special  notice in writing to the same effect.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Forfeiture of right on failure to appear. Any person having  any right to such treasure or any part thereof, as owner of the place  in which it was found or otherwise, and not appearing as required by  the notification issued under section 5, shall forfeit such right.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Matters to be enquired into and determined by the Collector.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>On the day notified under section 5, the Collector shall cause the  treasure to be produced before him, and shall enquire as to and  determine--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the person by whom, the place in which, and the  circumstances under which, such treasure was found; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>as far as is possible, the person by whom, and the  circumstances under which, such treasure was hidden.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Time to be allowed for suit by person claiming the treasure.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If, upon an enquiry made under section 7, the Collector sees reason to  believe that the treasure was hidden within one hundred years before  the date of the finding, by a person appearing as required by the said  notification and claiming such treasure, or by some other person under  whom such person claims, the Collector shall make an order adjourning  the hearing of the case for such period as he deems sufficient, to  allow of a suit being instituted in the Civil Court by the claimant,</p>
            <p>to establish his right.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>When treasure may be declared ownerless. If upon such enquiry  the Collector sees no reason to believe that the treasure was so  hidden; or if, where a period is fixed under section 8, no suit is  instituted as aforesaid within such period to the knowledge of the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Collector; or</p>
            <p>if such suit is instituted within such period, and the  plaintiff' s claim is finally rejected;</p>
            <p>the Collector may declare the treasure to be ownerless.</p>
            <p>Appeal against such declaration. Any person aggrieved by a declaration made under this section may  appeal against the same within two months from the date thereof to the</p>
            <p>Chief Controlling Revenue- authority .</p>
            <p>Subject to such appeal, every such declaration shall be final and  conclusive.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Proceedings subsequent to declaration. When a declaration has  been made in respect of any treasure under section 9, such treasure  shall, in accordance with the provisions hereinafter contained, either  be delivered to the finder thereof, or be divided between him and the  owner of the place in which it has been found in manner hereinafter  provided.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>When no other person claims as owner of place, treasure to be  given to finder. When a declaration has been made in respect of any  treasure as aforesaid, and no person other than the finder of such  treasure has appeared as required by the notification published under  section 5 and claimed a share of the treasure as owner of the place in  which it has been found, the Collector shall deliver such treasure to  the finder thereof.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>When only one such person claims and his claim is not  disputed, treasure to be divided, and shares to be delivered to  parties. When a declaration has been made as aforesaid in respect of  any treasure, and only one person other than the finder of such  treasure has so appeared and claimed, and the claim of such person is  not disputed by the finder, the Collector shall proceed to divide the  treasure between the finder and the person so claiming according to  the following rule (namely):--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If the finder and the person so claiming have not entered into  any agreement then in force as to the disposal of the treasure,</p>
            <p>threefourths of the treasure shall be allotted to such finder and the  residue to such person. If such finder and such person have entered  into any such agreement, the treasure shall be disposed of in  accordance therwith:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Collector may in any case, if he thinks fit,</p>
            <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>instead of dividing any treasure as directed by this section,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list4.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>allot to either party the whole or more than his share  of such treasure, on such party paying to the Collector  for the other party such sum of money as the Collector  may fix as the equivalent of the share of such other  party, or of the excess so allotted, as the case may  be; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>sell such treasure or any portion thereof by public  auction and divide the sale- proceeds between the  parties according to the rule hereinbefore prescribed:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided also, that when the Collector has by his declaration  under section 9 rejected any claim made under this Act by any person  other than the said finder or person claiming as owner of the place in  which the treasure was found, such division shall not be made until  after the expiration of two months without an appeal having been  presented</p>
            <p>under section 9 by the person whose claim has been so rejected, or,</p>
            <p>when an appeal has been so presented, after such appeal has been  dismissed.</p>
            <p>When the Collector has made a division under this section, he  shall deliver to the parties the portions of such treasure, or the  money in lieu thereof, to which they are respectively entitled under  such division.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>In case of dispute as to ownership of place, proceedings to  be stayed. When a declaration has been made as aforesaid in respect of  any treasure, and two or more persons have appeared as aforesaid and  each of them claimed as owner of the place where such treasure was  found, or the right of any person who has so appeared and claimed is  disputed by the finder of such treasure, the Collector shall retain  such treasure and shall make an order staying his proceedings with a  view to the matter being enquired into and determined by a Civil</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Court.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Settlement of such dispute, Any person who has so appeared  and claimed may, within one month from the date of such order,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>institute a suit in the Civil Court to obtain a decree declaring his  right; and in every such suit the finder of the treasure and all  persons disputing such claim before the Collector shall be made  defendants.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>and division thereupon. If any such suit is instituted and  the plaintiff' s claim is finally established therein, the Collector  shall, subject to the provisions of section 12, divide the treasure  between him and the finder.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If no such suit is instituted as aforesaid, or if the claims of  the plaintiffs in all such suits are finally rejected, the Collector  shall deliver the treasure to the finder.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Power to acquire the treasure on behalf of Government. The</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Collector may, at any time after making a declaration under section 9,</p>
            <p>and before delivering or dividing the treasure as hereinbefore  provided, declare by writing under his hand his intention to acquire  on behalf of the Government the treasure, or any specified portion  thereof, by payment to the persons entitled thereto of a sum equal to  the value of the materials of such treasure or portion, together with  one- fifth of such value, and may place such sum in deposit in his  treasury to the credit of such persons; and thereupon such treasure or  portions shall be deemed to be the property of Government, and the  money so deposited shall be dealt with, as far as may be, as if it  were such treasure or portion.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Decision of Collector final, and no suit to lie against him  for acts done bona fide. No decision passed or act done by the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Collector under this Act shall be called in question by any Civil</p>
            <p>Court, and no suit or other proceeding shall lie against him for  anything done in good faith in exercise of the powers hereby  conferred.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Collector to exercise powers of Civil Court. A Collector  making any enquiry under this Act may exercise any power conferred by  the Code of Civil Procedure  on a Civil Court for the trial of  suits (14 of 1882)].</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules. The State Government may, from time to  time, make rules consistent with this Act, to regulate proceedings  hereunder.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Such rules shall, on being published in the Official Gazette,</p>
            <p>have the force of law.</p>
            <p>PENALTIES</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Penalty on finder failing to give notice, etc. If the finder  of any treasure fails to give the notice, or does not either make the  deposit or give the security, required by section 4, or alters or  attempts to alter such treasure so as to conceal its identity, the  share of such treasure, or the money in lieu thereof to which he would  otherwise be entitled, shall vest in Government,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>and he shall, on conviction before a Magistrate, be punished with  imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or with fine, or  with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Penalty on owner abetting offence under section 20. If the  owner of the place in which any treasure is found abets, within the  meaning of the Indian Penal Code (15 of 1860), any offence under  section 20, the share of such treasure, or the money in lieu thereof  to which he would otherwise be entitled, shall vest in Government,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>and he shall, on conviction before a Magistrate, be punished with  imprisonment which may extend to six months, or with fine, or with  both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
