<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2002/33/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2002/33"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Delimitation Act, 2002"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2002/33/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2002/33/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2002/33/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2002/33/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Delimitation Act, 2002</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Delimitation Act, 2002.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“article” means an article of the Constitution;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“associate member” means a member nominated under section 5;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“Commission” means the Delimitation Commission constituted under section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>“Election Commission“ means the Election Commission referred to in article 324;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>“member” means a member of the Commission and includes the Chairperson; and;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>“State” includes a Union territory having a Legislative Assembly but does not include the State of Jammu and Kashmir.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of Delimitation Commission.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>As soon as may be after the commencement of this Act, the Central Government shall constitute a Commission to be called the Delimitation Commission which shall consist of three members as follows:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>one members, who shall be a person who is or has been a Judge of the Supreme Court, to be appointed by the Central Government who shall be the Chairperson of the Commission;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the Chief Election Commissioner or an Election Commissioner nominated by the Chief Election Commissioner, ex officio:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that after the nomination of an Election Commissioner as a member under this clause, no further nomination under this clause shall be made except to fill the casual vacancy of such member under section 6; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the State Election Commissioner of concerned State, ex officio.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list6">
              <listIntroduction>For the purposes of clause (c), the State Election Commissioner of concerned State,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list6.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>in respect of the duties of the Commission relating to a State (other than the States of Meghalaya, Mizoram and Nagaland), means the State Election Commissioner appointed by the Governor of that State under clause (1) of Article 243K; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list6.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>in respect of the duties of the Commission relating to the State of Meghalaya or the State of Mizoram or the State of Nagaland, as the case may be, means a person nominated by the Governor of that State for such purposes.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Duties of the Commission.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The readjustment made, on the basis of the census figures as ascertained at the census held in the year 1971 by the Delimitation Commission constituted under section 3 of the Delimitation Act, 1972 (76 of 1972) of the allocation of seats in the House of the People to the several States and the total number of seats in the Legislative Assembly of each State shall be deemed to be the readjustment made by the Commission for the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of sub-section (1) and any other law for the time being in force, the Commission shall readjust the division of each State into territorial constituencies for the purpose of elections to the House of the People and to the State Legislative Assembly on the basis of the census figures as ascertained at the census held in the year 2001:</p>
            <p>Provided that where on such readjustment only one seat is allocated in the House of the People to a State, the whole of that State shall form one territorial constituency for the purpose of elections to the House of the People from that State.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Associate members.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commission shall associate with itself for the purpose of assisting it in its duties in respect of each State, ten persons five of whom shall be members of the House of the People representing that State and five shall be members of the Legislative Assembly of that State:</p>
            <p>Provided that where the number of the members of the House of the People representing any State is five or less, then, all such members shall be the associate members for that State and in the latter case the total number of associate members shall be less than ten by such number as by which the total number of members of the House of the People representing that State is less than five.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The persons to be so associated from each State shall be nominated, in the case of members of the House of the People, by the Speaker of that House, and in the case of members of a Legislative Assembly, by the Speaker of that Assembly, having due regard to the composition of the House or, as the case may be, of the Assembly.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The first nominations to be made under sub-section (2)—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>shall be made by the Speakers of the several Legislative Assemblies within one month, and by the Speaker of the House of the People within two months, of the commencement of this Act, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>shall be communicated to the Chief Election Commissioner, and where the nominations are made by the Speaker of a Legislative Assembly, also to the Speaker of the House of the People.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>None of the associate members shall have a right to vote or to sign any decision of the Commission.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.5.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Commission shall have power to call upon—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.5.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the Registrar-General and Census Commissioner, India or his nominee; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.5.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the Surveyor General of India or his nominee; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.5.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any other officer of the Central Government or State Government; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.5.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>any expert in geographical information system; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.5.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>any other person,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>whose expertise and knowledge are considered necessary by the Commission to provide assistance to it in addition to the assistance provided by the persons referred to in sub-section (1) and the officers and persons so called upon shall be duty bound to assist the Commission.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Secretary to the Election Commission shall be the ex officio Secretary of the Commission and shall discharge his functions with the assistance of the employees of the Election Commission under the supervision of the Chairperson of the Commission.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Casual vacancies.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If the office of the Chairperson or of a member or of an associate member falls vacant owing to his death or resignation, it shall be filled as soon as may be practicable by the Central Government or the Speaker concerned under and in accordance with the provisions of section 3 or, as the case may be, of section 5.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Procedure and powers of the Commission.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Commission shall determine its own procedure and shall, in the performance of its functions, have all the powers of a civil court under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), while trying a suit, in respect of the following matters, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>summoning and enforcing the attendance of witnesses;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>requiring the production of any document; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>requisitioning any public record from any court or office.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commission shall have power to require any person to furnish any information on such points or matters as in the opinion of the Commission may be useful for, or relevant to, any matter under the consideration of the Commission.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commission may authorise any of its members to exercise any of the powers conferred on it by clauses (a) to (c) of sub-section (1) and sub-section (2), and any order made or act done in exercise of any of those powers by the member authorised by the Commission in that behalf shall be deemed to be the order or act, as the case may be, of the Commission.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If there is a difference of opinion among the members, the opinion of the majority shall prevail, and acts and orders of the Commission shall be expressed in terms of the views of the majority.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commission as well as any group of associate members shall have power to act notwithstanding the temporary absence of a member or associate member or the existence of a vacancy in the Commission or in that or any other group of associate members; and no act or proceeding of the Commission or of any group of associate members shall be invalid or called in question on the ground merely of such temporary absence or of the existence of such vacancy.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commission shall be deemed to be a civil court for the purposes of sections 345 and 346 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).</p>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <p>For the purposes of enforcing the attendance of witnesses, the local limits of the jurisdiction of the Commission shall be the limits of the territory of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Readjustment of number of seats.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Commission shall, having regard to the provisions of articles 81, 170, 330 and 332 and also, in relation to the Union territories, except National Capital Territory of Delhi, sections 3 and 39 of the Government of Union Territories Act, 1963 (20 of 1963) and in relation to the National Capital Territory of Delhi sub-clause (b) of clause (2) of article 239AA, by order, determine,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>on the basis of the census figures as ascertained at the census held in the year 1971 and subject to the provisions of section 4, the number of seats in the House of the People to be allocated to each State and determine on the basis of the census figures as ascertained at the census held in the year</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2001">
        <num>2001.</num>
        <heading>the number of seats, if any, to be reserved for the Scheduled Castes and for the Scheduled Tribes of the State; and</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2001.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2001.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2001.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>on the basis of the census figures as ascertained at the census held in the year 1971 and subject to the provisions of section 4, the total number of seats to be assigned to the Legislative Assembly of each State and determine on he basis of the census figures as ascertained at the census held in the year 2001 the number seats, if any, to be reserved for the Scheduled Castes and for the Scheduled Tribes of the State:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that the total number of seats assigned to the Legislative Assembly of any State under clause (b) shall be an integral multiple of the number of seats in the House of the People allocated to that State under clause (a).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Delimitation of constituencies.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Commission shall, in the manner herein provided, then distribute the seats in the House of the People allocated to each State and the seats assigned to the Legislative Assembly of each State as readjusted on the basis of 1971 census to single-member territorial constituencies and delimit them on the basis of the census figures as ascertained, at the census held in the year 2001, having regard to the provisions of the Constitution, the provisions of the Acts specified in section 8 and also to the following provisions, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>all constituencies shall, as far as practicable, be geographically compact areas, and in delimiting them regard shall be had to physical features, existing boundaries of administrative units, facilities of communication and public convenience;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>every assembly constituency shall be so delimited as to fall wholly within one parliamentary constituency;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>constituencies in which seats are reserved for the Scheduled Castes shall be distributed in different parts of the State and located, as far as practicable, in those areas where the proportion of their population to the total is comparatively large; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>constituencies in which seats are reserved for the Scheduled Tribes shall, as far as practicable, be located in areas where the proportion of their population to the total is the largest.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Commission shall—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>publish its proposals for the delimitation of constituencies, together with the dissenting proposals, if any, of any associate member who desires publication thereof, in the Gazette of India and in the Official Gazettes of all the States concerned and also in such other manner as it thinks fit;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>specify a date on or after which the proposals shall be further considered by it;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>consider all objections and suggestions which may have been received by it before the date so specified, and for the purpose of such consideration, hold one or more public sittings at such place or places in each State as it thinks fit; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <blockList id="section-9.2.list1.d.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>thereafter by one or more orders determine—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-9.2.list1.d.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>the delimitation of parliamentary constituencies, and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-9.2.list1.d.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>the delimitation of assembly constituencies,</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>of each State.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Publication of orders and their date of operation.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commission shall cause each of its orders made under section 8 or section 9 to be published in the Gazette of India and in the Official Gazettes of the States concerned and simultaneously cause such orders to be published at last in two vernacular newspapers and publicize on radio, television and other possible media available to the public and after such publication in the Official Gazettes of the States Concerned, every District Election Officer shall cause to be affixed, the Gazette version of such orders relating to the area under his jurisdiction, on a conspicuous part of his office for public notice. —(1) The Commission shall cause each of its orders made under section 8 or section 9 to be published in the Gazette of India and in the Official Gazettes of the States concerned and simultaneously cause such orders to be published at last in two vernacular newspapers and publicize on radio, television and other possible media available to the public and after such publication in the Official Gazettes of the States Concerned, every District Election Officer shall cause to be affixed, the Gazette version of such orders relating to the area under his jurisdiction, on a conspicuous part of his office for public notice."</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon publication in the Gazette of India, every such order shall have the force of law and shall not be called in question in any court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>As soon as may be after such publication, every such order shall be laid before the House of the People and the Legislative Assemblies of the States concerned.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of sub-section (5), the readjustment of representation of the several territorial constituencies in the House of the People or in the Legislative Assembly of a State and the delimitation of those constituencies provided for in any such order shall apply in relation to every election to the House or to the Assembly, as the case may be, held after the publication in the Gazette of India of that order and shall so apply in supersession of the provisions relating to such representation and delimitation contained in any other law for the time being in force or any order or notification issued under such law in so far as such representation and delimitation are inconsistent with the provision of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in this section shall affect the representation in the House of the People or in the Legislative Assembly of a State until the dissolution of the House or of the Assembly, as the case may be, existing on the date of publication in the Gazette of India of the final order or orders of the Commission relating to the delimitation of parliamentary constituencies or, as the case may be, of the assembly constituencies of that State and any bye-election to fill any vacancy in such House or in any such Assembly shall be held on the basis of the provisions of the laws and orders superseded by sub-section (4) as if the said provisions had not been superseded.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commission shall endeavour to complete and publish each of its orders referred to in sub-section (1) in the manner provided in that sub-section, within two years of the constitution of the Commission under section 3.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Power to maintain delimitation orders up-to-date.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Election Commission may, from time to time, by notification in the Gazette of India and in the Official Gazette of the State concerned—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>correct any printing mistake in any of the orders made by the Commission under section 9 or any error arising therein from an inadvertent slip or omission; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>where the boundaries or name of any district or any territorial division mentioned in any of the said orders are or is altered, make such amendments as appear to it to be necessary or expedient for bringing the orders up-to-date, so however, that the boundaries or areas or extent of any constituency shall not be changed by any such notification.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every notification under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is issued, before the House of the People and the Legislative Assembly of the State concerned.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Repeal.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Delimitation Act, 1972 (76 of 1972) is hereby repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
