<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1961/28/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1961/28"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Maharashtra Medical Practitioners Act, 1961"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1961/28/eng@2017-04-11/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1961/28/eng@2017-04-11"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-04-11" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1961/28/eng@2017-04-11/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1961/28/eng@2017-04-11"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-04-11" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Maharashtra Medical Practitioners Act, 1961</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>(Act No. 28 of 1961)</p>
      </longTitle>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[10th June, 1961]</docDate>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>An Act to regulate the qualifications and to provide for the registration of practitioners of the Ayurvedic, Siddha and Unani Systems of Medicine, with a view to encourage the study and spread of such systems, and to make certain provisions relating to medical practitioners generally, in the State of Maharashtra; and for that purpose to consolidate and amend the law relating thereto.</p>
      <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to regulate the qualifications and to provide for the registration of practitioners of the Ayurvedic, Siddha and Unani Systems of Medicine, with a view to encourage the study and spread of such systems, and to make certain provisions relating to medical practitioners generally, in the State of Maharashtra; and for that purpose to consolidate and amend the law relating thereto; It is hereby enacted in the Twelfth Year of the Republic of India as follows, namely:-</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <heading>Preliminary</heading>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the Maharashtra Medical Practitioners Act, 1961.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Maharashtra.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The whole Act (except Chapter VI thereof) shall come into force on such date as the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint; and Chapter VI shall come into force on such other date being a subsequent date as that Government, by like notification, appoints.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-2.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires, -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>“appointed day” means the date on which the whole Act except Chapter VI thereof comes into force;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>“by-law” means by-law made under Section 31;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>“Council” means the Maharashtra Council of Indian Medicine established under Section 3;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>“Director of Ayurved” means the Director of Ayurved, Maharashtra State;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>(f-a) “Indian Medicine” means the system of Indian Medicine commonly known as Ashtang Ayurvedic or Siddha or Unani or Unani Tibb, whether supplemented or not by such modern advances as the Central Council from time to time by notification may declare under clause (e) of sub-section (1) of Section 2 of the Indian Medicine Central Council Act, 1970;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.1.list3.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>“Inspector” means an Inspector appointed by the Council.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list3.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>“member” means a member of the Council</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list3.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>“President” means the President of the Council;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list3.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>“recognised institution” means any institution recognised under Section 27;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list3.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>“register’, except in Chapter VI, means the register of practitioners prepared and maintained under Section 17;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list3.m">
                  <num>(m)</num>
                  <p>“registered practitioner” means a practitioner whose name is for the time being entered in the register;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list3.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>“Registrar” means the Registrar appointed under Section 16;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list3.m">
                  <num>(m)</num>
                  <p>“rules” means rules made under Section 30;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list3.n">
                  <num>(n)</num>
                  <p>“Schedule” means the Schedule appended to this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list3.o">
                  <num>(o)</num>
                  <p>“State” means the State of Maharashtra;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list3.s">
                  <num>(s)</num>
                  <p>“Vice-President” means the Vice-President of the Council.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purposes of Chapter VI, a person shall be deemed to practise any system of medicine who holds himself out as being able to diagnose, treat, operate, or prescribe medicine or other remedy or to give medicine for any ailment, disease, injury, pain, deformity or physical condition or who, by any advertisement, demonstration, exhibition or teaching offers or undertakes, by any means or method whatsoever to diagnose, treat, operate or prescribe medicine or other remedy or to give medicine for any ailment, disease, injury, pain, deformity or physical condition :</p>
              <blockList id="section-2.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that a person who -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.2.list2.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>mechanically fits or sells lenses, artificial eyes, limbs or other apparatus of appliances; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.2.list2.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>is engaged in the mechanical examination of eyes for the purpose of constructing or adjusting spectacles, eye-glasses or lenses; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.2.list2.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>practices physio-therapy or electro-therapy or chiripody or naturopathy or hydropathy or yogic healing; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.2.list2.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>without personal gain furnishes medical treatment or does domestic administration of family remedies; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.2.list2.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>being registered under the Dentists Act, 1948, limits his practice to the art of dentistry; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.2.list2.vi">
                  <num>(vi)</num>
                  <p>being a nurse, midwife or health visitor registered or enlisted under the Bombay Nurses, Midwifes and Health Visitors Act, 1954, or any other corresponding law for the time being in force in the State or a Dai attends on a case of labour, shall not be deemed to practise medicine;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.2.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Explanation:- In this sub-section -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.2.list4.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>“advertisement” includes any word, letter, notice, circular, picture, illustration, model, sign, placard, board or other document and any announcement made orally or by any means of producing or transmitting light, sound, smoke or other audible or visible representation; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.2.list4.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>“physio-therapy” means treatment of any ailment, disease, injury, pain, deformity or physical condition, by message or other physical means, but does not include bone-setting.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <heading>Constitution, Functions and Powers of the Council</heading>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Establishment and incorporation of Council and dissolution of existing Board and Faculty; and Director to function as Administrator temporarily.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.1.list0">
                <item id="section-3.1.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>On the date of commencement of the Maharashtra Medical Practitioners (Amendment) Act, 1982, a Council to be called “the Maharashtra Council of Indian Medicine: shall be deemed to have been established.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.1.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>The Council shall be a body corporate by the name aforesaid, and the perpetual succession and a common seal, with power to acquire, hold and dispose of property and to contract and may by the said name sue and be sued.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of Section 41, the existing Board and the Faculty shall stand dissolved on and with effect from the date of commencement of the Maharashtra Medical Practitioners (Amendment) Act, 1982, and all members of the aforesaid Board and Faculty shall vacate office.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, on and with effect from the date of commencement of the Maharashtra Medical Practitioners (Amendment) Act, 1982, the Director of Ayurved shall function as the Administrator, and he shall exercise all the powers and perform all the functions of the Council established under sub-section (1) during the period he holds the office of the Administrator under sub-section (4).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The term of office of the Administrator functioning under sub-section (3) shall expire on the day immediately preceding the date of publication under Section 5 of the names of the members of the Council (including the President and the Vice-President) nominated, or as the case may be, elected in accordance with the provisions of Sections 3A and 4.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3A">
          <num>3A.</num>
          <heading>Constitution of Council</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3A.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3A.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Council shall consist of the following members, including the President and the Vice-President, -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3A.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the Director of Ayurved, ex-officio;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3A.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>five members nominated by the State Government, out of whom two shall be practitioners in Ashtang Ayurvedic or Siddha system of Medicine and two shall be practitioners in Unani or Unani Tibb system of medicine;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3A.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-3A.1.list1.c.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>nine members elected by registered practitioners as follows, that is to say,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-3A.1.list1.c.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>eight members elected by registered practitioners whose names are entered in Part I of the register, from amongst themselves;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3A.1.list1.c.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>one member elected by the registered practitioners whose names are entered in Part II and Part III of the register, from amongst themselves :</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3A.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-3A.1.list1.d.list1">
                    <item id="section-3A.1.list1.d.list1.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>two members elected by the Principals or Heads of Colleges or institutions affiliated to or, as the case may be, recognised by any statutory university in the State of Maharashtra and which are imparting education in Indian Medicine for appearing at the examinations held by any such university, from amongst themselves, and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3A.1.list1.d.list1.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>two members elected by the Teachers (other than Principals or Heads) of such colleges or institutions, from amongst themselves, who are registered practitioners possessing any of the qualifications specified in the Schedule and for a period of not less than three years engaged in teaching in any of the systems of Indian Medicine in any such colleges or institutions :</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that, the members to be elected under sub-clauses (i) and (ii) of this clause shall be persons other than those nominated or elected under the preceding clauses.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3A.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If at any election, the electors fail to elect the requisite number of members to the Council, the State Government shall nominate such registered practitioners as it deems fit, to fill the vacancies which remain unfilled after the election, and the practitioners so nominated shall be deemed to have been duly elected under sub-section (1).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3A.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The President and the Vice-President of the Council shall be elected by the members; from amongst themselves.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Procedure for election of members, President and Vice-President.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The election of members of the Council, under Section 3, shall beheld at such time, and at such place, and in such manner as may be prescribed by rules :</p>
              <p>Provided that, for the purpose of any election under clause (c) of sub-section (1) of Section 3A, the list referred to in sub-section (1) of Section 23 (including any addendum or corrigendum thereto duly printed and published) and for the time being in force on such date as the State Government may, by general or special order, notify in this behalf (being a date not earlier than 30 days from the date of issue of such order) shall be the electoral roll.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-4.2.list0">
                <item id="section-4.2.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>Within seven days after the nomination and election of members under the foregoing provisions, a meeting shall be called for the election of the President and Vice-President on such date as the Direcot of Ayurved may fix. Such election shall be by ballot.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.2.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>The meeting called under clause (a) shall be presided over by the Director of Ayurved, and he shall have the right to vote. The Director presiding over such meeting (hereinafter referred to in this section as “the Presiding officer”) may, for reasons recorded in writing which in his opinion are sufficient, refuse to adjourn such meeting, or as the case may be, adjourn such meeting.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.2.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>If in the election of the President or Vice-President, there is an equality of votes, the result of the election shall be decided by lot to be drawn in the presence of the Presiding Officer, in such manner as he may determine.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.2.list0.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>In the event of a dispute arising as to the validity of the election of a President or Vice-President, the Presiding Officer may, within 30 days from the date of the election, refer the dispute to the State Government for decision. The decision of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>State Government in such dispute shall be final and conclusive and shall not be questioned in any Court.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Term of office.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government shall, as soon as possible after the election held in accordance with the provisions of Section 3A and 4 by notification in the Official Gazette, publish the names of the President, the Vice-President and the members of the Council.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The President and the Vice-President shall hold office for such period as the State Government may specify in the notification published under sub-section (1), provided that, such period shall not exceed the term of office of such President or Vice-President as a member under sub-section (3). The term shall commence from the date of the notification published under sub-section (1).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-5.3.list0">
                <item id="section-5.3.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>A member of the Council whether elected or nominated, shall hold office for a period of five years commencing from the date of notification published under sub-section (1).</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The term of an outgoing President, Vice-President or member shall notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (2) or (3) be deemed to extend to and expire with the day immediately preceding the day on which the name of the successor of such President,</p>
              <p>Vice-President or member is published under sub-section (1).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An outgoing members shall be eligible for re-election or re-nomination.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the sub-section (3), the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, extend from time to time the term of office of</p>
              <p>the members of the Council for a further period not exceeding three years in the aggregate.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Casual vacancies.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any casual vacancy, previous to the expiry of the term, in the office of the President or the Vice-President or a member nominated by the State government due to his death, resignation, removal, disability or disqualification or any other reason shall be filled by nomination by the State Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any such vacancy in the office of a member of the Council elected by registered practitioners, shall be filled by the State Government by nomination of a person from a panel of three registered practitioners recommended by the Council:</p>
              <p>Provided that, if the Council fails to make a recommendation under this sub-section, within such time as the State Government may fix, the State Government may appoint any registered practitioner to fill the vacancy.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person nominated under sub-section (1) or (2) to fill a vacancy shall, notwithstanding anything contained in Section 5, hold office only so long as the person in whose place he is nominated or elected would have held office, if the vacancy had not occurred.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Resignation.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An elected member may at any time resign his office by a notice in writing to the President, A nominated member, may at any time resign his office by a notice in writing to the State Government. Such resignation shall take effect from the date on which the resignation is accepted by the President or the State Government, as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The President or the Vice-President may at any time resign his office by a notice in writing to the State Government. The resignation shall take effect from the date on which such resignation is accepted by the State Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Disqualification, disability and removal from office.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-8.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>No person,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>who is an un discharged insolvent;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>who has been adjudged to be of unsound mind by a competent Court;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>whose name has been removed from the register; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>who is a full time officer or servant of the Council; shall be eligible to be elected or nominated as a member.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-8.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>If any member -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>absents himself from three consecutive meetings of the Council as the case may be, without such reasons as may, in the opinion of the State Government in the case of the President and the Vice-President and in the opinion of the Board or the Faculty, as the case may be, in the case of any other member, be sufficient; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>becomes, or is found to be, subject to any of the disqualifications specified in sub-section (1), the State Government shall declare his office to be vacant.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, on the recommendation of the Council, as the case may be, supported by at least two-thirds of the whole number of members, remove any member elected or nominated under this Act, if such member has been guilty of misconduct in the discharge of his duties as a member, or of any disgraceful conduct, or has become incapable of performing his duties as a member:</p>
              <p>Provided that, no resolution recommending the removal of any member shall be passed by the Council unless the member to whom it relates has been given a reasonable opportunity for showing cause why such recommendation should not be made.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may remove the President or the Vice-President if he has been guilty of misconduct in the discharge of his duties under this Act, or of any disgraceful conduct, or has become incapable of performing his duties as the President or, as the case may be, the Chairman:</p>
              <p>Provided that, no such action shall be taken unless the President or, as the case may be, the Chairman is given a reasonable opportunity of showing cause why he should not be removed from office.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Meeting of the Council.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The meetings of the Council shall be convened, held and conducted in such manner as may be prescribed by rules.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Save as otherwise provided in sub-section (2) of Section 4, the President, when present, shall preside at every meeting of the Council. If at any meeting the President is absent, then the Vice-president, and in the absence of both, some other member elected by the members present, from amongst themselves, shall preside at such meeting.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All questions at a meeting of the Council shall be decided by a majority of the notes of the members present and voting at the meeting.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The presiding authority at a meeting shall have and exercise a second or a casting vote, in case of an equality of votes.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Eight members of the Council including the President and Vice-President shall form a quorum. When a quorum is required but not present, the presiding authority shall adjourn the meeting to such hour on some future day as it may notify on the notice-board at the office of the Council; and the business which would have been brought before the original meeting, had there been a quorum threat, shall be brought before the adjourned meeting, and may be disposed of at such meeting or any subsequent adjournment thereof, whether there be a quorum present or not.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Proceedings of meetings and validity of acts.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The proceedings of the discussions of every meeting of the Council be treated as confidential and no person shall, without the previous resolution of the Council disclose any portion thereof:</p>
              <p>Provided that nothing in this section shall be deemed to prohibit any person from disclosing or publishing the text of any resolution adopted by the Council unless the Council directs such resolution also to be treated as confidential.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No disqualification of or defect in the election, nomination or appointment of any person as a member or as the President or as the Vice-President or as a presiding authority of a meeting shall of itself be deemed to vitiate any act or proceedings the Council in which such person has taken part, whenever the majority of persons, parties to such act or proceedings, were entitled to vote.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>During any vacancy in the Council the continuing members may act as if no vacancies shall at any time not exceed six in number.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Fees and allowances for meetings.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>There shall be paid to the President, the Vice-President and other members of the Council and to the members of their committees and to the Chairman and members of the appellate authority referred to in sub-section (7) of Section 17 such fees and allowances for attendance at meetings, and such reasonable travelling allowances as shall from time to time be prescribed by rules.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Income and Expenditure of the Council.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-12.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-12.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The income of the the Council shall consist of-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>fees received from practitioners;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>(a-1) fees received from examinees;</p>
              <blockList id="section-12.1.list4">
                <listIntroduction>(a-2) any other fees collected by the Council;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12.1.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>grants received from the State Government, if any; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.1.list4.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>donations and any other sums received by the Council;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-12.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>It shall be competent for the Council to incur expenditure for the following purposes namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>salaries and allowances of the Registrar and the staff including the Inspector maintained by the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>fees and allowances paid to the members of Board or a committee including a board of studies thereof or of the appellate authority referred to in sub-section (7) of Section 17;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>(b-1) remuneration paid to paper setters, examiners, moderators and other persons appointed by the Council for the conduct of examinations;</p>
              <blockList id="section-12.2.list4">
                <listIntroduction>(b-2) other expenses for the conduct of examination;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12.2.list4.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>such other expenses as are necessary for performing its duties and functions under this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Omitted</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Powers, duties and functions of the Council.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Subject to such conditions as may be prescribed by or under the provisions of this Act, the powers, duties and functions of the Council shall be,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to provide for registration of practitioners and to maintain the register;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>to hear and decide appeals from any decision of the Registrar;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>to prescribe a code of ethics for regulating the professional conduct of registered practitioners;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>to reprimand a registered practitioner, or to suspend or remove him from the register or to take such other disciplinary action against him as may, in the opinion of the Council be necessary or expedient;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>to hold examinations and to make all the necessary arrangements of such examinations;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>to conduct the course of training which were, immediately before the date of commencement of Maharashtra Medical Practitioners (Amendment) Act, 1982, conducted by the Faculty and such other courses as the Central Council, prescribes by regulations made under clause (i) of Section 36 of the Indian Medicine Central Council Act, 1970, leading to the examinations held by the Council, and to charge fee for such examinations;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>to provide for post-graduate training;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>to grant degrees, diplomas and marks of honour;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>to award stipends, scholarships, medals, prizes and other rewards;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>to recommend recognition of institutions for the purpose of giving instructions for the courses leading to. the examinations held by the Council, or to recommend the cancellation of such recognition;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>to recommend the inclusion of any degree, diploma, certificate or award in the Schedule or to recommend the removal of any degree, diploma, certificate or award from the Schedule;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>to prepare, publish and prescribe text books, and to publish statements of prescribed courses of study;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.m">
                  <num>(m)</num>
                  <p>to provide for the maintenance of an adequate standard of proficiency for the practice of the system of Indian Medicine;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.n">
                  <num>(n)</num>
                  <p>to provide for research in the system of Indian Medicine;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.o">
                  <num>(o)</num>
                  <p>to provide for the inspection of recognised institutions, and to require such institutions to furnish such information as may be necessary;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.p">
                  <num>(p)</num>
                  <p>to provide for the inspection of any other institutions giving instructions for any of the qualifications included in the Schedule;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.q">
                  <num>(q)</num>
                  <p>to appoint boards of studies and committees consisting of persons, who may or may not be members of the Council, but at least half of the number of such persons shall be medical practitioners registered under any of the laws mentioned in sub-section (1) of Section 34, and to lay down the constitution, the duties and the functions of such boards and committees;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.r">
                  <num>(r)</num>
                  <p>subject to the approval of the State Government, to receive donations and to determine the conditions of acceptance of donations;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.s">
                  <num>(s)</num>
                  <p>to exercise such other powers and perform such other duties and functions as are laid down in this Act, or may be prescribed by rules.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Omitted.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Registrar and other employees of the Council.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-16.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government shall, after consulting the Council, appoint a Registrar, who shall be the Executive Officer of the Council. The salary, allowances and other conditions of service of the Registrar shall be such as may be prescribed by the State Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Council may from time to time grant leave to the Registrar :</p>
              <p>Provided that, if the period of leave does not exceed two months, the leave may be granted by the President.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>During any such temporary vacancy in the office of the Registrar due to leave or any other reason. The Council may, with the provisions sanction of the State Government, appoint another person to act in his place, and any person so appointed shall for the period of such appointment, be deemed to be the Registrar for the purposes of this Act:</p>
              <p>Provided that, when the period of such vacancy does not exceed two months, the appointment may be made by the President, who shall forthwith report such appointment to the State Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, after consulting The Council, suspend, dismiss or remove any person appointed as the Registrar, or impose any other penalty upon him.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Council shall, from time to time, appoint such other officers and servants as it deems necessary for carrying out its duties and performing its functions under this Act:</p>
              <p>Provided that, the number and designations and the salaries, allowances and other conditions of service of such officers and servants shall be such as the State Government may from time to time determine.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Registrar and any other officer or servant appointed under this section shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of Section 21 of the Indian Penal Code.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16A">
          <num>16A.</num>
          <heading>Executive Committee of the Council.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-16A.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Council shall, as soon as may be, constitute an Executive Committee consisting of the President, ex-officio and such number of other members, elected by the Council from amongst its members, as may be prescribed by rules.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16A.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The term of office of, the manner of filling casual vacancies among, and the procedure to be followed by, the members of the Executive Committee shall be such as may be prescribed by rules.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16A.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In addition to the powers, duties and functions conferred, imposed and entrusted by this Act, the Executive Committee shall exercise such powers, perform such duties, and discharge such functions, of the Council as may be delegated to it by rules or entrusted to it, from time to time, by the Council.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16B">
          <num>16B.</num>
          <heading>Omitted.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Preparation of Register.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>As soon as maybe after the appointed day, the Registrar shall prepare and maintain thereafter a register of practitioners of Indian Medicine for the State, in accordance with the provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-17.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The register shall be divided into three parts, namely:</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.2.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>Part I containing the names of practitioners who possess any of the qualifications specified in the Schedule;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.2.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>Part II containing the names of practitioners, whose names were included in that part immediately before the 1st day of October, 1976;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.2.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>Part III containing the names of practitioners, who on the 3rd day of September, 1976 were enlisted practitioners and who are on that day deemed to have become registered practitioners under Section 18 ;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Each part shall consist of one or more sections as the State Government may specify in this behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every person who possesses any of the qualifications specified in the Schedule shall, at any time on an application made in the form prescribed by rules, to the Registrar and on payment of a fee of five hundred rupees be entitled to have his name entitled in the register.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.3A">
            <num>(3A)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Not with standing anything contained in any law for the time being in force, every person enrolled on the register maintained under the Indian medicine Central Council Act, 1970, but not enrolled on the register maintained under this Act, shall, on an application and on payment of the fee as provided in sub-section (3), be entitled to have his name entered in the register maintained under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-17.4.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The name of every person who on the day immediately proceeding the appointed day stood registered in any register kept under -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.4.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the Bombay Medical Practitioners’ Act, 1938, as in force in the Bombay area of the State; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.4.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the Central Provinces and Berar Ayurvedic and Unani Practitioner’s Act, 1947 as in force in the Vidarbha region of the State; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.4.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the Medical Act, as in force in the Hyderabad area of the State;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>shall be entered in the register prepared under this Act without such person being required to make an application or to pay any fee.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-17.5.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Any person, not being a person qualified for registration under sub-section (3) or (4), who proves to the satisfaction of the Committee appointed under sub-section (6) -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.5.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>that he had been regularly practising the Ayurvedic or the Unani system of medicine in the Vidarbha region or the Hyderabad area of the State, for a period of not less than ten years immediately before the 23rd day of November, 1960; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.5.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>that he was on the 4th day of November, 1941 regularly practising the Ayurvedic or the Unani system of medicine in the Bombay area of the State, but his name was not entered in the register maintained under the Bombay Medical Practitioners’ Act, 1938; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.5.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>that his name had been entered in the list kept under Section 18 of the Bombay Medical Practitioners’ Act, 1938, by virtue of paragraph (ii) or (iii) of sub-section (1) of Section 31C inserted in that Act by the Bombay Medical Practitioners (Amendment) Act, 1949, and stood included, on the day immediately preceding the date of the commencement of the Maharashtra Medical Practitioners (Amendment) Act, 1964, in the list maintained under this Act, by virtue of clause</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.5.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>of sub-section (2) of Section 18.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>shall, on an application made in the form prescribed by rules, accompanied by a fee of ten of rupees and such documents as may be prescribed by rules, on or before the 31st day of March, 1965, be entitled to have his name entered in the register.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All applications for registration under sub-section (5) shall be considered by a Committee of three members of the Council appointed by the State Government. The Committee shall make enquiry in such manner as may be prescribed by rules. The Committee shall not entertain any further application from a person, if an application made by him under clause (i) or (ii) of sub-section (5) has already been decided by it.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-17.7.list0">
                <item id="section-17.7.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>Any person aggrieved by the decision of the Committee appointed under sub-section (6) may, within a period of one month from the date on which such decision is communicated to him, on payment of a fee of five rupees, appeal to the appellate authority constituted by the State Government in this behalf. The appellate authority shall consist of a Chairman who has for at least seven years held judicial office not lower in rank than that of a District Judge, one member elected by the Council and the Director of Ayurved shall be the ex-officio member. The decision of the appellate authority shall be final.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.7.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in clause (a) any person aggrieved by such decision of the Committee, who has not already appealed to the appellate authority aforesaid before the date of the commencement of the Maharashtra Medical Practitioners (Amendment) Act, 1964, may, on or before the 31st day of March, 1965, on payment of a like fee of five rupees, appeal to the appellate authority.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.7A">
            <num>(7A)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If on an application for registration made under clause (iii) of sub-section (5) or on appeal under sub-section (7), a person is found eligible for registration, then on his name being included in the register the entry of his name in the list shall be cancelled.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-17.8.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The register shall include the following particulars, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.8.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the full name, and residential address of the registered practitioner:</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.8.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the date of his admission to the register maintained under this Act; and if he be a person who was registered on the day immediately preceding the appointed to in sub-section (4), the date of his admission to that register;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.8.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the qualification specified in the Schedule possessed by, him, if any, and the date on which he obtained the qualification and the authority which conferred or granted it; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.8.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>such further particulars as may be prescribed by rules.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When the register is prepared in accordance with the foregoing provision, the Registrar shall publish a notice in the Official Gazette and such newspapers as the Council may select, about the register having been prepared, and the register shall come into force from the date of the publication of such notice in the Official Gazette.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.10">
            <num>(10)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-17.10.list0">
                <item id="section-17.10.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>Every registered practitioner shall be given a certificate of registration in the form prescribed by rules. The registered practitioner shall display the certificate of registration in a conspicuous place in his dispensary, clinic or place of practice.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.10.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>Such certificate shall be valid until it is duly cancelled and the name of the practitioner is removed from the register under the provisions of this Act; and every certificate of registration given before the commencement of the Maharashtra Medical Practitioners (Amendment) Act, 1972 which is valid on such commencement shall, subject to the provisions of Section 23-A, be valid likewise, and shall continue accordingly.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.10.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>Where it is shown to the satisfaction of the Registrar that a certificate of registration has been defaced, lost or destroyed, the Registrar may, on payment of the prescribed fee, issue a duplicate certificate in such form as may be prescribed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Enlisted practitioners deemed to be registered practitioners on 30th September, 1976.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-18.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every person who on the 30th day of September, 1976, that is, the day immediately preceding the date of coming into force of Section 17 of the Indian Medicine Central Council Act, 1970 was an enlisted practitioner under this Act, shall be deemed to have become a registered practitioner under this Act on that day and to have become a person enrolled on the State Register for the purposes of the said Section 17. His name shall be entered by the Registrar in the register maintained under this Act with effect from that day, without such person being required to make any application or to pay any fee.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every person whose name is entered in the register under sub-section (1) shall be given a certificate of registration in the form prescribed by rules, on the payment of a fee of fifteen rupees.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18A">
          <num>18A.</num>
          <heading>Provisional registration for practice.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-18A.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the courses of study to be undergone for obtaining any of the qualifications specified in the Schedule, include a period of training after a person has passed the qualifying examination, and before such qualification is conferred on him, any such person shall, on an application made to the Registrar, in the form prescribed by rules and on payment of a fee of seventy-five rupees, be granted a provisional registration in the register, in order to enable him to practise Ayurvedic or Unani system of medicine in an approved institution for the purpose of such training, and for no other purpose, for the period aforesaid.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18A.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every person who is granted a provisional registration under sub-section (1) shall be given a certificate of provisional registration in the form prescribed by rules, which shall remain in force for such period as may be specified therein.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Persons not entitled to registration.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-19.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in Section 17 no person, whose name has been removed from any register kept under -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the Bombay Medical Practitioners’ Act, 1938, as in force in the Bombay area of the State;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>the Central Provinces and Berar Ayurvedic and Unani Practitioners’ Act, 1947, as in force in the Vidarbha region of the State;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>the Medical Act, as in force in the Hyderabad area of the State;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list1.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>any other law for the time being in force in India or any part thereof regulating the registration of practitioners of medicine.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>for infamous conduct in a professional respect, shall be entitled to have has name entered in the register unless his name is duly restored to the register from which it was so removed.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Removal of names from the register.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-20.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-20.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>If a registered practitioner has been, after due inquiry held by the Council or the Executive Committee in the manner prescribed by rules, found guilty of any misconduct by the Council the Council may -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-20.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>issue a letter of warning to such practitioner; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-20.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-20.1.list1.b.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>direct the name of such practitioner -</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-20.1.list1.b.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>to be removed from the register for such period as may be specified in the direction, or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-20.1.list1.b.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>to be removed from the register permanently.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-20.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Explanation:- For the purposes of this section, “misconduct” shall mean -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-20.1.list3.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the conviction of a registered practitioner by a criminal court for an offence which involved moral turpitude, and which is cognizable within the meaning of the the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-20.1.list3.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>the conviction under the Army Act, 1950, of a registered practitioner subject to military law for an offence which is cognizable within the meaning of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-20.1.list3.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>any conduct which, in the opinion of the Council is infamous in relation to the medical profession particularly under any code of ethics prescribed by the Council.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-20.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>If the name of any such practitioner is entered in -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-20.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the register maintained under the Maharashtra Medical Council Act, 1965;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-20.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the register or list maintained under the Bombay Homoeopathic and Biochemic Practitioners’ Act, 1959 or any other law for the time being in force in relation to the qualifications and registration of Homoeopathic or Biochemic practitioners in any part of the State;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>it shall be the duty of the Registrar to give intimation of such removal to the authority entitled to maintain the said register or the said list.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the name of a registered practitioner is also entered in the register or the list, as the case may be, maintained under any of the laws referred to in sub-section (2) and it is removed from the said register or the said list, the Council shall if such removal comes to its notice also remove his name from the register under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Council may, on sufficient cause being shown, direct at any subsequent date that the name of a practitioner removed under sub-section (1) or (3) shall be re-entered in the register or such conditions and on the payment of such fees, as may be prescribed by rules.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Council may of its own motion, or on the application of any person, after due and proper enquiry and after giving an opportunity to the person concerned of being heard, cancel or alter any entry in the register if in the opinion of the Council such entry was fraudulently or incorrectly made.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-20.6.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In holding any inquiry under this section, the Council or the Executive Committee shall have the same powers as are vested in Civil Courts under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908, when trying a suit, in respect of the following matters namely :-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-20.6.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>enforcing the attendance of any person, and examining him on oath;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-20.6.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>compelling the production of documents;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-20.6.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>issuing of commissions for the examination of witnesses.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All inquiries under this section shall be deemed to be judicial proceedings within the meaning of Sections 193, 219 and 228 of the Indian Penal Code.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-20.8.list0">
                <item id="section-20.8.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-20.8.list0.a.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>For the purpose of advising the Council or the Executive Committee on any question of law arising in any inquiry under this section, there may in all such inquiries be an assessor, who has been for not less than ten years -</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-20.8.list0.a.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>an advocate enrolled under the the Advocates Act, 1961, or;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-20.8.list0.a.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>an attorney of a High Court.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
                <item id="section-20.8.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>Where an assessor advises the Council or the Executive Committee on any question of law as to evidence, procedure or any other matter, he shall do so in the presence of every party, or person representing a party as to the inquiry who appears thereat, or if the advice is tendered after the Council or the Executive Committee has begun to deliberate as to their findings, every such party or person as aforesaid shall be informed what advice the assessor has tendered. Such party or person shall also be informed if in any case of the Council or the Executive Committee does not accept the advice of the assessor on any such question as aforesaid.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-20.8.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>Any assessor under this section may be appointed either generally, or for any particular inquiry or class of inquiries, and shall be paid such remuneration as may be prescribed by rules.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Maintenance of register.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-21.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall be the duty of the Registrar to make entries in the register, from time to time, to revise the same and to issue the certificates of registration in accordance with the provisions of this Act, the rules made thereunder, and the orders of the Council.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-21.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The name of registered practitioners who die or whose names are directed to be removed from the register under Section 20 shall be removed therefrom.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-21.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person whose name is entered in the register and who subsequent to his registration obtains any additional qualification which is specified in the Schedule, or desires to record in the register any change in his name, shall on an application made in this behalf and on payment of such fee as may be prescribed by rules, be entitled to have an entry stating such additional qualification made against his name in the register or such change in his name recorded in the register, as the case may be :</p>
              <p>Provided that, where a registered practitioner whose name is entered in Part II or Part III of the register makes an application for entry on such additional qualification which involves change of his registration from Part II, or as the case may be, Part III, to Part I of the register, such application shall be treated as an application for fresh registration, and it shall be accompanied by a fee of one hundred rupees. After the name of such registered practitioner is entered in Part I of the register, the entry of his name made in any of the other Part of the register earlier shall be cancelled.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Omitted</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Publication of list of registered practitioners.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-23.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>At such time after the publication of the notice under sub-section (9) of section 17 as the Council deems fit, and thereafter at such intervals as may be prescribed by rules, the Registrar shall cause to be printed and published a correct medical list of all persons for the time being entered in the register.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-23.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Except in a year in which a list is published under sub-section (1), the Registrar shall cause to be printed and published annually on or before a date to be prescribed by rules, an addendum and a corrigendum to the list published under sub-section (1) showing -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-23.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the names of all persons for the time being entered or re-entered in the register, and not included in any subsisting list already printed and published; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the names of all practitioners included in any subsisting list, whose names have since been removed on account of any reason whatsoever from and not re-entered in the register; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>any other amendments to the subsisting list.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.2A">
            <num>(2A)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (2), when the election of members of the Council is to be held under clause (c) of sub-section (1) of Section 3A and any general or special order is issued by the State Government under the proviso to sub-section (1) of Section 4 the Registrar shall review the subsisting list and if necessary cause to be printed and published, on the date immediately preceding the date notified under the said proviso, an addendum and corrigendum to the said list.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The form of the list published under sub-section (1), the particulars to be included therein, and the manner of its publication, shall be such as may be prescribed by rules.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A copy of list referred to in sub-section (1) shall be evidence in all Courts, and in all judicial or quasi judicial proceedings, that the persons therein specified are registered according to the provisions of this Act, and the absence of the name of any person from such copy shall be evidence, until the contrary is proved, that such person is not registered according to the provisions of this Act :</p>
              <p>Provided that, in the case of any person whose name does not appear in such copy, a certified copy under the hand of the Registrar of the entry of the name of such person on the register shall be evidence that such person is registered under the-provisions of this Act. Such certified copy may be issued by the Registrar on payment of such fee and in such form as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23A">
          <num>23A.</num>
          <heading>Renewal of Registration.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-23A.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-23A.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in Sections 17 and 23, after the commencement of the Maharashtra Medical Practitioners (Amendment) Act, 1972 -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-23A.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-23A.1.list1.a.list0">
                    <item id="section-23A.1.list1.a.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>the Registrar shall cause two general notices in the prescribed form to be published an interval of not less than sixty days, in the Official Gazette and in such other manner as may be prescribed. The first such general notice shall be published on such date as the Registrar may, with the approval of the President, decide, calling upon all registered practitioners to make an application to the Registrar for the continuance of their names on the register, and drawing attention to their liability to pay to the Council a fee of fifty rupees therefore;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-23A.1.list1.a.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>the Registrar shall, after the publication of the first general notice under sub-clause (i) of this clause, send an individual notice under certificate of posting, enclosing therewith the prescribed form of application, to every registered practitioner at his address as entered in the register calling from him to return the application to the Registrar duly filled in for the continuance of his name on the register along with a fee of fifty rupees, within forty-five days of the receipt of such individual notice.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-23A.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>If any of the registered practitioners fails to return such application within the period specified in the individual notice along with a fee of fifty rupees, the Registrar shall, after the publication of the second general notice under clause (i), issue a further individual notice to such registered practitioner under certificate of posting, enclosing therewith the prescribed form of application calling upon him to return the application to the Registrar for the continuance of his name on the register within thirty days of the receipt of the further individual notice together with a fee of fifty rupees and an additional fee of five rupees;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-23A.1.list3.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>if the application together with the fee is returned within the period specified in such individual notices, the Registrar shall inform the registered practitioner under certificate of posting, that the fee has been received, and that the certificate of his registration shall, subject to the provisions of this section, continue in operation, unless such certificate is duly cancelled under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23A.1.list3.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>if the application together with the fee is not returned within the period specified in the further individual notice, the Registrar shall remove the name of the defaulting practitioner from the register and inform him of such removal under certificate of posting. The fact of such removal shall be published in the Official Gazette and in such other manner as may be prescribed. On such removal, the certificate of registration issued to the defaulting practitioner shall be deemed to have been cancelled, and shall be liable to be withdrawn from the practitioner by the Registrar in the prescribed manner;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-23A.1.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that on an application made to the Registrar in that behalf within the prescribed period, the name so removed may be re-entered in the register on payment of a fee of fifty rupees together with an additional fee of fifteen rupees; and thereupon, the certificate of registration, if withdrawn, shall be returned to the practitioner and shall continue in operation, and if not yet withdrawn, it shall also continue in operation, as provided in sub-clause (iii) of this clause;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-23A.1.list5.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>and thereafter, every five years from the commencement of the Maharashtra Medical Practitioners (Amendment) Act, 1972, the Registrar shall likewise cause two general notices in the prescribed form to be published at an interval of not less than sixty days, in the Official Gazette and in such other manner as may be prescribed calling upon all registered practitioners to make an prescribed calling upon all registered practitioners to make an application to the Registrar for continuance of their names on the register without payment of the fee of fifty rupees referred to in clause (a), and thereupon, the provisions of clause (a) shall, mutatis mutandis, apply for the continuance of the names of registered practitioners on the register.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23A.1.list5.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-23A.1.list5.c.list0">
                    <item id="section-23A.1.list5.c.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>and the Registrar shall, as soon as may be, after the commencement of the Maharashtra Medical Practitioners (Amendment) Act, 1973, send a notice under certificate of posting at the last known address along with the prescribed form of application to every person whose name has been removed from the register during the process of renewal which took place under Section 22 of this Act before the commencement of the Maharashtra Medical Practitioners (Amendment) Act, 1972, and call upon such person to return the application duly filled in for restoration of his name on the register along with a fee of fifty rupees together with arrears of dues, if any, payable to the Board before such commencement and an additional fee of fifteen rupees by way of penalty within sixty days from the date of the receipt of such notice :</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-23A.1.list7">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that, the Registrar may accept an application together with an additional fee of fifteen rupees after the expiry of the said period, if he is satisfied that the applicant was prevented by sufficient cause from returning the application along with fees and dues in time;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-23A.1.list7.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>if the application together with the fees and dues, if any, is returned within the period specified in such notice, the Registrar shall inform such person under certificate of posting, that the fees and dues, if any, have been received, and that his name has been restored to the register and that the certificate of his registration shall, subject to the provisions of this section, continue in operation unless such certificate is duly cancelled under this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23A.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-23A.2.list0">
                <item id="section-23A.2.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>Any registered practitioner to whom a certificate of registration is issued before the 9th day of November, 1972, and such certificate is still in operation, may, at any time, by an application in writing, accompanied by such certificate (in original) and a fee of five rupees, apply to the Registrar for issue of a fresh certificate of registration is lieu of the certificate issued earlier.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23A.2.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>On receipt of such application, the Registrar shall cancel such certificate and issue a fresh certificate of registration in the form prescribed by rules made under sub-section (10) of Section 17.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>No refund of fees.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Fees paid under Sections 17, 18, 18A, 20, 21 and 23A shall not be refunded.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Rights of registered practitioners to practice.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-25.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time being in force,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the expression “legally qualified medical practitioner” or “duly qualified practitioner” or any words importing a person recognized by law as a medical practitioner or member of the medical profession or as having a right to practise any system of medicine shall, in all Acts of the State Legislature and in all Central Acts (in their application to the State of Maharashtra), in so far as such Acts relate to any matters specified in List II or List III in the Seventh Schedule to the Constitution of India, include a practitioner whose name is entered in any part of the register maintained under this Act, whether before or on or after the 1st day of October, 1976, that is, the date of coming into force of Section 17 of the Indian Medicine Central Council Act, 1970;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>it shall be lawful for every practitioner whose name is entered in any part of the register maintained under this Act to use in full after his name the words “Registered Medical Practitioner”;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>a certificate, required by any Act from a medical practitioner or medical officer, shall be valid if such certificate has been given and signed by a practitioner registered under Part I or Part II of the register maintained under this Act.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list1.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>the registered practitioners of the Indian Medicine and holding the qualifications mentioned in Part A, A1, B or D of the Schedule, shall have privilege to practice the modern scientific medicine known as allopathic medicine to the extent of the training they received in that system, alongwith the system of Indian Medicine for which they are registered;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list1.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>the registered practitioners of the Indian Medicine holding the qualifications mentioned in the Part A, A1, B or D of the Schedule and holding post-graduate qualification which is entered as additional qualification in the register prepared under section 17 shall be eligible to pursue and practice the latest knowledge, skill and technological advances to the extent of the training they received in that system during post-graduation.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <heading>Examinations held by Council Courses of Studies, Recognition of Institutions and Recognition of Qualification</heading>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Examination held by Council and courses of studies.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Council shall by by-laws made under Section 31 prescribe the examinations to be held by it, the qualifications for admission to such examinations, the courses of studies for such examinations (including the subjects of medicine, surgery, midwifery and gynaecology), the standard of passing, the degree, diploma, certificate or any other like award to be given to the person who pass the examinations, and such other matters in respect of such examinations as may be necessary or expedient.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Recognition of institutions.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-27.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every institution recognised under this section shall, subject to such conditions as may be prescribed by the Council be entitled to train students for the examinations of the Council.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-27.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Any institution desirous of recognition under this Act shall send application to the Registrar, giving full information in respect of the following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the constitution and personnel of the managing body;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>subjects and courses in which it gives or proposes to give instruction, and the examination for which it seeks recognition;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>accommodation, equipment and the number of students for whom provision has been or is proposed to be made;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the strength of the staff, their salaries, qualifications, and the research work carried out by them;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>fees levied or proposed to be levied, and the financial provision made for capital expenditure on buildings and equipment and for continued maintenance and efficient working of the institution:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that, no application shall be entertained by the Registrar unless the institution agrees in writing to give all facilities to any Inspectors or visitors authorised by the Council to make an inspection or enquiry or to attend any examination under sub-sections (3) to (9).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Registrar shall place the application before the Council and the Council may direct the Registrar to call for any further information which it may deem necessary. The Council may also direct a local inquiry to be made by a competent person or persons authorised by it in this behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>After recording the report of such local inquiry and after making such further inquiry as may be necessary, the Council, shall forward the application together with its report, to the State Government with its recommendations. The State Government may thereupon grant or refuse the recognition, or may grant it subject to such conditions as it deems fit. The State Government shall not grant recognition to any institution which does not provide such facilities for clinical training as may be prescribed under the by-laws. The decision of the State Government shall be final.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall be the duty of the Council to secure the maintenance of an adequate standard of proficiency in the subjects of medicine, surgery, midwifery and gynaecology and for the practice of the Ayurvedic system of medicine or the Unani system of medicine. For the purpose of securing the maintenance of such standard, the Faculty shall have authority to call on the governing body or authorities of any recognised institution to permit Inspectors or visitors appointed by the Faculty in this behalf, who may or may not be members of the Council inspect the recognised institution and the hospitals attached to it, and to attend and be present at all or any of the examinations held by the institution. Every recognised institution shall comply with the directions issued by the Faculty from time to time.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Inspectors, or visitors shall not interfere with the conduct of any examination, but it shall be their duty to report to the Council their opinion as to the sufficiency or insufficiency of every examination which they attend, and any other matters in regard to such institution on which the Council may require them to report.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every recognised institution and every examination held by such institutions shall be inspected by the Faculty through its Inspectors or visitors at least once in five years, and more frequently if the Council so desires.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Council shall forward a copy of every such report to the authorities of the institution in respect of which the report was made, and shall also forward a copy of such report, together with any observations made thereon by the said body, to the State Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An Inspector, or a visitor shall receive such remuneration to be paid as part of the expenses of the Council as maybe prescribed by rules.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Withdrawal of recognition of institutions.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-28.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If it appears to the State Government on the report of the Council or otherwise that any recognised institution is not maintaining an adequate standard of training according to the requirements of the Council, the State Government may ask the Council to direct the institution to take steps within such reasonable time as it may fix to bring the training up to the required standard.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-28.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the institution fails so to do within the stipulated time, the State Government may at any time withdraw the recognition granted to such institution.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Amendment of Schedule.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-29.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If it shall appear to the State Government on the report of the Council or otherwise that the course of study and examinations prescribed by any university, body or institution conferring a degree, diploma, certificate or any other like award not entered in the Schedule, is such as to secure the. possession, by persons obtaining such degree, diploma, certificate or award of, the requisite knowledge and skill for the efficient practice of their profession, including the medicine, surgery, midwifery and gynaecology, it shall be lawful for the State Government from time to time by notification in the Official Gazette, to amend the Schedule and to direct the inclusion therein of any such degree, diploma, certificate or award subject to such conditions (if any) as may be specified in respect of any such degree, diploma, certificate or award.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any university, body or institution desirous of having included in the Schedule any degree, diploma, certificate or award in the Ayurvedic system of medicine or the Unani system of medicine conferred by it, may apply to the Council in the manner provided in sub-section (2) of Section 27 and for the purposes of this section the Council shall have all the powers specified in sub-sections (3) to (9) of Section 27 as if the university, body or institution had applied for recognition under Section 27.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If it appears to the State Government on the report of the Council or otherwise that the course of study or the examinations prescribed by any university, body or institution for any degree, diploma, certificate or award which is entered in the Schedule under this section, are such not as to secure the maintenance of an adequate standard of proficiency for the practice of the Ayurvedic system of medicine or the Unani system of medicine, as the case may be, including the practice of medicine, surgery, midwifery and gynaecology it shall be lawful for the State Government at any time by notification in the Official Gazette, to direct the removal of any such degree, diploma, certificate or award from the Schedule:</p>
              <p>Provided that, no notification under sub-section (1) or this sub-section shall be issued by the State Government without first consulting the Council :</p>
              <p>Provided further that, before making any recommendation to the State Government under this sub-section to remove any degree, diploma, certificate or award from the Schedule, the Council shall require the university, body or institution to take such steps as may be directed by the</p>
              <p>Council and within such reasonable time as the Council may prescribe to bring the course of study examination or such degree, diploma or award to the required standard.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <heading>Miscellaneous</heading>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading>Rules.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-30.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, and subject to the condition of previous publication make rules to carry out the purposes of the Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-30.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-30.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generally of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters namely :-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-30.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the time and place at which and the manner in which election to the Council shall be held under sub-section (1) of Section 4;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which the meetings of the Council shall be convened, held and conducted under sub-section (1) of Section 9;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the fees and other allowances to be paid under Section ill;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the powers, duties and functions of the Council under clause (s) of Section 14;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.2.list1.da">
                  <num>(da)</num>
                  <p>the number and term of office of, the manner of filling casual vacancies among, and the procedure to be followed by, the members of the Executive Committees, and the powers, duties and functions of the Council delegated to the Executive Committee under Section 16A;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>any further particulars to be entered in the register :</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.2.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the forms of application for registration and provisional registration under Sections 17 and 18A, and the documents to accompany such forms;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.2.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the manner of making enquiry by the committee appointed under sub-section</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-30.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-30.6.list1">
                <listIntroduction>of Section 17;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-30.6.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>the forms of Certificate of registration and provisional registration ;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.6.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the manner of holding enquiry under Section 20;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.6.list1.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>the conditions and the fees for re-entering the name of a practitioner removed under Section 20;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.6.list1.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>the remuneration to be paid to the additional qualifications or change of name under sub-section (3) of Section 21;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.6.list1.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>the fee chargeable for the entry of additional qualifications or change of name under sub-section (3) of Section 21;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.6.list1.o">
                  <num>(o)</num>
                  <p>the interval at which the medical list shall be published under sub-section (1) of Section 23;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.6.list1.p">
                  <num>(p)</num>
                  <p>the forms of the medical list, the supplementary list, the particulars to be included therein and the manner of publication under sub-section (3) of Section 23;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.6.list1.q">
                  <num>(q)</num>
                  <p>remuneration to be paid to an Inspector or visitor under sub-section (9) of Section 27;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.6.list1.r">
                  <num>(r)</num>
                  <p>any other matter which is to be or may be prescribed under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-30.6.list1.s">
                  <num>(s)</num>
                  <p>the furtherance of any of the objects of this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-30.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made before each House of the State Legislature while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session in which it is so laid or the session immediately following, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that rule should not be made, and notify such decision in the Official Gazette, the rule shall from the date of publication of such notification have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done or omitted to be done under that rule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading>By-laws.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-31.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-31.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Council may, with the previous sanction of the State Government, make by-laws, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act or the rules made thereunder for the following matters, namely :-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-31.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the examinations to be held by it;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-31.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the qualifications for admission to and the courses of studies for the examinations;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-31.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the standard or passing;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-31.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the degree, diploma, certificate or other like award to be conferred upon those who pass the examinations and the manner of conferring such degree, diploma, certificate or award;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-31.1.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the language in which the examinations shall be conducted;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-31.1.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the conditions of appointment of examiners, paper-setters, moderators and other persons appointed and fees to be paid to them, the conduct of examinations and the fees to be charged for the conduct of examinations;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-31.1.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the conditions for the recognition of teachers in recognised institutions;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-31.1.list1.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>the number of students to be admitted to recognised institutions;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-31.1.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the language in which instructions shall be given in recognised institution;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-31.1.list1.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>such other matters as may be necessary for the exercise of the powers and performance of duties and functions by the Council under this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government on receiving the draft by-laws may sanction or refuse to sanction the same, or sanction subject to such modification as it may think fit or return them to the Council for further consideration.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All by-laws when sanctioned, shall be published in the Official Gazette by the State Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, cancel any by-law.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>Control of State Government.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-32.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If at any time it appears to the State Government that the Council or its President or Vice-President has failed to exercise or has exceeded or abused any of the powers conferred upon it or him by or under this Act or has otherwise ceased to function, or has become incapable of functioning, the State Government may, if it considers such failure, excess or abuse, to be of a serious character, notify the particulars thereof to the Council or the President or the Vice-President as the case may be. If the Council or the President or the Vice-President fails to remedy such failure, excess or abuse within such reasonable time as the State Government may fix in this behalf, the State Government may remove the President or the Vice-President, or dissolve the Council and cause all or any of the powers, duties and functions of the Council to be exercised and performed by such persons and for such period not exceeding two years as it may think fit, and shall take steps to constitute a new Council.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, or in the rules or by-laws, if at any time it at any time it appears to the State Government that the Council or any other authority empowered to exercise any of the powers or to perform any of the duties or functions under this Act, has not been validly constituted or appointed, the State Government may cause any of such powers or functions to be exercised or performed by such person, in such manner and for such period not exceeding six months and subject to such conditions, as it thinks fit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VI">
        <num>VI</num>
        <heading>General Provisions Applicable to all Medical Practitioners</heading>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading>Prohibition of medical practice by persons not registered.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-33.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-33.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time being in force or in any judgment, decree or order of any Court, no person other than a medical practitioner whose name is entered in -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-33.1.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the register maintained under this Act; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-33.1.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>the register or the list prepared and maintained under the Bombay Homoeopathic and Biochemic Practitioners’ Act, 1959 or under any other law for the time being in force in relation to the qualifications and registration of Homoeopathic or Biochemic Practitioners in any part of the State; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-33.1.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>the register prepared and maintained under the Maharashtra Medical Council Act, 1965; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-33.1.list1.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>the Indian Medical Register prepared and maintained under the Indian Medical Council Act, 1956,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>shall practise any system of medicine in the State :</p>
              <p>Provided that, the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that subject to such conditions as it may deem fit to impose and the payment of such fee as may be prescribed by rules, the provisions of this section shall not apply to any class of persons, or to any area, as may be specified in such notification.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-33.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-33.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Any person, who acts in contravention of any of the provisions of sub-section (1) shall, on conviction, be punished,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-33.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>for the first offence, with rigorous imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than two years but which may extend to five years and with fine which shall not be less than two thousand rupees but which may extend to ten thousand rupees; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-33.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>for a second or subsequent offence, with rigorous imprisonment for a term which may extend to ten years and with fine which may extend to twenty-five thousand rupees :</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that, when the contravention is continued after the order of conviction, a further fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, for each day of continuation of such contravention, may be imposed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-33A">
          <num>33A.</num>
          <heading>Unregistered persons not to hold certain appointments.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-33A.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-33A.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Nothwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time being in force, no person, who is not a practitioner registered under any of the Acts referred to in section 33 shall, after the commencement of this Chapter, hold any appointment as-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-33A.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>physician, surgeon, or other medical officer, in any hospital, infirmary or dispensary not supported wholly by voluntary contribution.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-33A.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>medical officer of health of any local authority; teacher in medicine, surgery or midwifery in any public institution.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Explanation:- For the purposes of this sub-section a practitioner registered under this Act shall not include a practitioner registered under Part III of the register maintained under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-33A.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-33A.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Any person who contravenes the provisions of subsection (1) shall, on conviction, be punished, -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-33A.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>for the first offence, with rigorous imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than two years but which may extend to five years and with fine which shall not be less than two thousand rupees but which may extend to ten thousand rupees; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-33A.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>for a second or subsequent offence, with rigorous imprisonment for a term which may extend to ten years and with fine which may extend to twenty-five thousand rupees :</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that, when the contravention is continued after the order of conviction, a further fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, for each day of continuation of such contravention, may be imposed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-34">
          <num>34.</num>
          <heading>Registered practitioners competent to give valid certificates or expert evidence.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-34.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-34.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything in any law for the time being in force, a birth or a death certificate, or a medical or fitness certificate, or any other certificate required by any law to be signed or authenticated by a duly qualified medical practitioner, shall be valid only if it has been signed or authenticated by a practitioner registered under-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-34.1.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>Part I or Part II of the register maintained under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-34.1.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>the Maharashtra Medical Council Act, 1965;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-34.1.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>the Bombay Homoeopathic and Biochemic Practitioners Act, 1959 or any other law for the time being in force in relation to the qualifications and registration of Homoeopathic or Biochemic practitioners in any part of the State; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-34.1.list1.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>the Indian Medical Council Act, 1956.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-34.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time being in force, no</p>
              <p>person other than a practitioner registered under any of the laws specified in sub-section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-34.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>shall be qualified to give evidence at any inquest or in any Court of law as an expert under Section 45 of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872, on any matter relating to medicine, surgery of midwifery.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading>Conferring, granting or issuing colourable imitations of degrees, diplomas or licences to be an offence.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-35.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-35.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>No person other than-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-35.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>a University established by law;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-35.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the Council constituted under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-35.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>an authority specified or notified under the Indian Medical Degrees Act, 1916;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-35.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the Court of Examiners constituted under the Bombay Homoeopathic and Biochemic Practitioners Act, 1959 or any other body constituted under any other law for the time being in force in relation to the qualifications and registration of Homoeopathic or Biochemic Practitioner in any part of the State;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-35.1.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>an authority empowered or recognised as competent, by the State Government, to confer, grant or issue any degree, diploma, licence, certificate or any other like award, shall confer, grant or issue or hold himself out as entitled to confer, grant or issue any degree, diploma, licence, certificate or any other like award which is identical with or is a colourable imitation of any degree, diploma, licence, certificate or award granted by a body or institution specified in clauses</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-35.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>, (b), (c), (d) or (e) of this sub-section or which states or implies that the holder thereof is qualified to practise any system of medicine.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-35.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-35.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Any person who contravenes the provisions of sub-section (1), and if the person so contravening is an association, every member of such association who, knowingly or wilfully authorises or permits the contravention shall, on conviction, be punished -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-35.2.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>for a first offence, with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-35.2.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>for a subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-36">
          <num>36.</num>
          <heading>Prohibition against addition of any title, description, etc., to name of any person unless authorised to do so.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-36.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-36.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>No person shall add to his name any title, description, letters or abbreviations which imply that he holds a degree, diploma, licence or certificate or any other like award as his qualification to practise any system of medicine unless-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-36.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>he actually holds such degree, diploma, licence or certificate or any other like award : and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-36.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-36.1.list1.b.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>such degree, diploma, licence or certificate or any other like award-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-36.1.list1.b.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>is recognised by any law for the time being in force in India or in any part thereof, or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-36.1.list1.b.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>has been conferred, granted or issued by a body or institution referred to in sub-section (1) of Section 35, or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-36.1.list1.b.list0.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>has been recognised by the Medical Council of India; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-36.1.list1.b.list0.iv">
                      <num>(iv)</num>
                      <p>has been recognised by the Central Council of Indian Medicine.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person, who contravenes the provisions of sub-section (1) shall, on conviction, be punished with rigorous imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than one year but which may extend to three years and with fine which shall not be less than one thousand rupees but which may extend to five thousand rupees; and when the contravention is a continuing one/with further fine which may extend to two hundred rupees for every day during which such contravention continues after conviction for the first such contravention.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-38">
          <num>38.</num>
          <heading>Cognizance of offences.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-38.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>All offences under this Act shall be cognizable and non-bailable.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-39">
          <num>39.</num>
          <heading>Indemnity to persons acting under the Act.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-39.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No suit, prosecution, or other legal proceeding shall be instituted against any</p>
              <p>person for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act, or under the rules or by-laws made thereunder.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VII">
        <num>VII</num>
        <heading>Repeal and Transitional Provisions</heading>
        <section id="section-40">
          <num>40.</num>
          <heading>Repeal and saving</heading>
          <subsection id="section-40.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-40.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Subject to the provisions of this Chapter, on the appointed day,––</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-40.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the Bombay Medical Practitioners’ Act, 1938, in its application to the Bombay area of the State;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-40.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the Central Provinces and Berar Ayurvedic and Unani Practitioners Act, 1947, in its application to the Vidarbha region of the State;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-40.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the Medical Act, in its application to the Hyderabad area of the State, shall stand repealed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-40.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of sub-section (2) of section 44 all or any of the rules, by-laws, regulations, orders or any other instruments made or issued under any of the Acts repealed under sub-section (1), relating to any examinations held by any Faculty, Board or Medical Council or like body competent to hold such examinations under the said Acts, as the State Government may by order specify on the appointed day, shall, in so far as they are not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, be deemed to have been made or issued under and for the purposes of the relevant provisions of this Act and be in force accordingly, unless and until superseded by any rules or by-laws or other orders made under this Act. All other rules, by-laws, regulations, orders or any other instruments made or issued under the said Acts shall on and from the appointed day cease to be in force.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-40.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-40.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The register kept or maintained or deemed to be kept and maintained,––</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-40.3.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>under the Bombay Medical Practitioners ‘Act, 1938, in its application to the Bombay area of the State; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-40.3.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>under the Central Provinces and Berar Ayurvedic and Unani Practitioners Act, 1947, in its application to the Vidarbha region of the State,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>which are in force immediately before the appointed day, shall be deemed to be the register under this Act, until the register prepared under section 17comes into force under sub-section (9) thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-40.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The list kept or deemed to be kept under the Act repealed under clause (a) of sub-section (1) which is in force immediately before the appointed day, shall be deemed to be the list under this Act, until the list prepared under section 18 comes into force under sub-section (3) of section 18 read with sub-section (9) of section 17.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-40.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any appointment, notification, notice, order or form made, issued or given under any of the Acts, repealed under sub-section (1) and subsisting immediately before the appointed day shall, in so far as it is not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, be deemed to have been made, issued or given under the relevant provisions of this Act, and be in force throughout the State accordingly unless and until superseded by any appointment, notification, notice, order or form made, issued or given under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-41">
          <num>41.</num>
          <heading>Vesting of rights, dutiesetc. in the Council and saving.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-41.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-41.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>On and with effect from the date of commencement of the Maharashtra Medical Practitioners (Amendment) Act, 1982 (hereinafter in this section referred to as “the commencement date”), the following consequences shall ensue, that is to say,––</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-41.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>all rights of the Board and the Faculty dissolved under sub-section (2) of section 3 (hereinafter in this section referred to as “the dissolved Board and Faculty”) shall on the commencement date vest in the Council established under sub-section (1) of section 3 (hereinafter referred to as “the Council”);</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>all the property movable or immovable which on the day immediately preceding the commencement date vested in the dissolved Board and Faculty shall, subject to all limitations and conditions as were in force on that day, vest in the Council;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>all sums due to the dissolved Board and Faculty on any account shall be recoverable by the Council, which shall be competent to take any measure or institute any proceedings which it would have been open to the dissolved Board and Faculty to take or institute if the Maharashtra Medical Practitioners (Amendment) Act, 1982 had not come into operation;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>all debts, liabilities and obligations incurred by or on behalf of the disolved Board and Faculty, immediately before the commencement date and subsisting on the said day, shall be deemed to have been incurred by the Council in exercise of the powers conferred on it by or under this Act and shall continue in operation accordingly;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>all proceedings and matters pending before any authority or officer immediately before the commencement date shall be deemed to be transferred to and continued before the corresponding authority or officer under this Act as amended by the Maharashtra Medical Practitioners (Amendment) Act, 1982 competent to entertain such proceedings and matters;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>all prosecutions instituted by or on behalf of or against the dissolved Board and Faculty and all suits and other legal proceedings instituted by or against the dissolved Board and Faculty or any officer or any such dissolved Board and Faculty on behalf of the dissolved Board and Faculty pending on the commencement date, shall be continued by or against the Council;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the Registrar and all officers and servants in the employment of the dissolved Board and Faculty immediately before the commencement date shall be the Registrar, officers and servants employed by the Council and shall receive salaries and allowances and be subject to the conditions of service or retirement benefits which they were entitled to or subject to on the commencement date:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-41.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that––</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-41.paragraph-0.list3.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the service rendered by such Registrar, officers and servants before the commencement date shall be deemed to be service rendered under the Council;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.paragraph-0.list3.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>if, in the opinion of the Council, the services of any officer or servant are not necessary as being surplus in view of the State Government sanctioning new pattern of staff with due reference to the volume of work of the Council or are not suitable to the requirements of services under it, it may, with the previous approval of the State Government, discontinue the services of any such officer or servant and any officer or servant whose services are so discontinued shall be entitled to receive from the Council such leave, pension, gratuity or other benefits as he would have, if the Maharashtra Medical Practitioners (Amendment) Act, 1982 had not been enacted been entitled to receive on being invalidated out of service of the dissolved Board or Faculty and may receive such additional amount by way of compensation as the Council may with the sanction of the State Government determine;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.paragraph-0.list3.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.paragraph-0.list3.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>any appointment, notification, notice, order, rule, by-law, register, registration certificate, recognition or form held, made, issued, maintained or granted under this Act and subsisting and in force immediately before the commencement date shall, in so far as it is not incosistent with the provisions of this Act as amended by the Maharashtra Medical Practitioners (Amendment) Act, 1982, con¬tinue to be in force, unless and until superseded by any appointment, notification, notice, order, rule, by-law, register, registration certificate, recognition or form held, made, issued, maintained or granted under this Act as amended by the Maharashtra Medical Practitioners (Amendment) Act,1982</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-42">
          <num>42.</num>
          <heading>Omitted</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-43">
          <num>43.</num>
          <heading>Omitted</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-44">
          <num>44.</num>
          <heading>Omitted</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-45">
          <num>45.</num>
          <heading>Omitted</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-46">
          <num>46.</num>
          <heading>Omitted</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-47">
          <num>47.</num>
          <heading>Power to remove difficulty</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-47.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, as amended by the Maharashtra Medical Practitioners (Amendment) Act, 1982, during the period of one year from the date of commencement of the said amendment Act, the State Government may, as occasion requires, by order do anything which appears to it necessary or expedient for the purpose of removing the difficulty.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-schedule">
      <doc name="schedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1961/28/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1961/28"/>
              <FRBRalias value="Schedule"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1961/28/eng@2017-04-11/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1961/28/eng@2017-04-11"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1961/28/eng@2017-04-11/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1961/28/eng@2017-04-11"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-04-11" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="schedule">
            <heading>(See Sections 18, 17, 21, 29 and 44)</heading>
            <paragraph id="schedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>Qualifications the possession of which entitled a person to registration</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <part id="part-A">
              <num>A</num>
              <heading>Qualifications in the Ayurvedic System of Medicine with a course supplemented by modern advances with -</heading>
              <paragraph id="part-A.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <blockList id="part-A.paragraph-0.list0">
                    <item id="part-A.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the Inter Science (B Group) examination as qualification for admission; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="part-A.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>the Matriculation or section S.C. Examination or is equivalent Examination as qualification for admission, provided the course is of a duration of six or more years.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <table id="part-A.paragraph-0.table1">
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>Sr. No</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Authority</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Qualification</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Abbreviation for registration and conditions for registration, if any.</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>1</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>2</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>3</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>4</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>1</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Benaras Hindu University, Benaras.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>(1) Ayurvedacharya with Bachelor of Medicine and Surgery.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>A.M.B.S. (Ben.). (This qualification shall be recognised only when granted in or after 1952). A.M.S. (Ben.).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p/>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p/>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>(2) Ayurvedacharya with Medicine and Surgery.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>A.M.M.S. (Ben.).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p/>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p/>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>(3) Ayurvedacharya with Modern Medicine and Surgery.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>A.M.M.S. (Ben.).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>2</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>University of Poona</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Bachelor of Ayurvedic Medicine and Surgery.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M.S. (Poona).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>3</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Faculty of Ayurvedic and Unani Systems of Medicine constituted under the Bombay Medical Practitioners Act, 1938 and, on and after the 23rd October, 1961, the Maharashtra Faculty of Ayurvedic and Unani Systems of Medicine constituted under the Maharashtra Medical Practitioners Act, 1961.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Graduate of the Faculty of Ayurvedic Medicine.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>G.F.A.M. (Bom.).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>4</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>College of Indigenous Medicine, Madras.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Graduate of the College of Indigenous Medicine.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>G.C.I.M.(Madras)</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>5</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Tilak Maharashtra Vidyapeeth, Poone.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Ayurvidya-Parangat</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>A.V.P. (Poona).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>6</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Faculty of Ayurvedic and Unani Systems of Medicine, Gujarat.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Graduate of the Faculty of Ayurvedic Medicine.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>G.F.A.M. (Guj.).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>7</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>University of Kerala</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Bachelor in Ayurvedic Medicine</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M. (Kerala).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>8</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>University of Gujarat.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Bachelor in Ayurvedic Medicine and Surgery.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M.S. (Guj.).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>9</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>University of Nagpur.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Bachelor of Ayurvedic Medicine and Surgery.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M.S. (Nag.)</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>10</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Ravishankar University, Raipur</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Bachelor of Ayurvedic Medicine and Supergery (Ayurvedacharya).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M.S. (Ravi). (This qualification shall be recognised only when granted to students admitted by the University on or after the 1st day of June, 1968).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>11</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Maharashtra Faculty of Ayurvedic and Unani Systems of Medicine, Bombay.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Bachelor of Ayurvedic Medicine and Surgery.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M.S. (Mah. Faculty).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>12</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Marathwada University, Aurangabad.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Bachelor of Ayurvedic Medicine and Surgery.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M.&amp; section</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>13</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Shivaji University, Kolhapur</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Bachelor of Ayurvedic Medicine and Surgery.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M. &amp; S.</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>14</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>University of Indore (Madhya Pradesh).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Ayurved Sankaya (Bachelor of Ayurved with Modern Medicine and Surgery).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M.S.</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>15</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>University of Jabalpur (Madhya Pradesh).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Bachelor of Ayurvedic Medicine and Surgery.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M.S.</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>16</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>University of Kanpur (Uttar Pradesh).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>‘Ayurvedacharya’ Bachelor of Ayurved with Modern Medicine and Surgery.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M.S. (Kanpur)</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>17</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>University of Sagar (Madhya Pradesh).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>‘Ayurvedacharya’ Bachelor of Ayurved with Modern Medicine and Surgery.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M.S. (Sagar). (This qualification shall be recognised only when granted in or after 1972).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>18</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Vikram University, Ujjain (Madhya Pradesh).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Bachelor of Ayurved with Modern Medicine and Surgery.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M.S. (This qualification shall be recognised only when granted to students admitted by the University before 1971).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                  </table>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </part>
            <part id="part-A">
              <num>A</num>
              <heading>1</heading>
              <paragraph id="part-A.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Qualification in Indian Syastem of Medicine–Ayurved recommended by the</p>
                  <p>Central Council of Indian Medicine</p>
                  <table id="part-A.paragraph-0.table2">
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>Sr. No.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Authority.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Qualification</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Abbreviation tor registration and conditions for registration, if any</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>1</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>2</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>3</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>4</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>1</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>University of Nagpur</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>“Ayurvedacharya” (Bachelor of Ayurvedic Medicine and Surgery).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M.S. (Nag.) (The 5-1/2 years degree awarded to students admitted in 1971 and 1972 only).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>2</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>University of Poona</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>“Ayurvedacharya” (Bachelor of Ayurvedic Medicine and Surgery).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M.S. (Poona) (The 6-1/2 years degree awarded to students admitted in 1971 and 1972 only).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>3</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>University of Bombay</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>“Ayurvedacharya” (Bachelor of Ayurvedic Medicine and Surgery).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M.S. (Bom.) (The 7-1/2 years degree awarded to students admitted in 1973 and thereafter).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>4</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>University of Napur</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>“Ayurvedacharya” (Bachelor of Ayurvedic Medicine and Surgery).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M.S. (Nag.) (The 7-1/2 years degree awarded to students admitted in 1973 and thereafter).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>5</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>University of Poona</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>“Ayurvedacharya” (Bachelor of Ayurvedic Medicine and Surgery).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M.S. (Poona) (The 7-1/2 years degree awarded to students admitted in 1973 and thereafter).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>6</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Marathwada University Aurangabad</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>“Ayurvedacharya” (Bachelor of Ayurvedic Medicine and Surgery).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M.S. (Marathwada) (The 7-1/2 years degree awarded to students admitted in 1973 and thereafter).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>7</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Shivaji University Kolhapur</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>“Ayurvedacharya” (Bachelor of Ayurvedic Medicine and Surgery).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>BAM.S. (Shivaji) (The 7-1/2 years degree awarded to students admitted in 1973 and thereafter).”</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>8</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Gujarat Ayurved University, Jamnagar (Gujarat).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>“Ayurvedacharya” (Bachelor of Ayurvedic Medicine and Surgery).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M.S. (Jamnagar) (From 1982 onwards).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>9</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Kurukshetra University, Kurukshetra (Haryana).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>“Ayurvedacharya” (Bachelor of Ayurvedic Medicine and Surgery).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M.S. (Kuruk-shetra) (From 1982 onwards).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>10</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Maharshi Dayanand University, Rohtak (Haryana).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>“Ayurvedacharya” (Bachelor of Ayurvedic Medicine and Surgery).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M.S. (Rohtak) (From 1982 onwards.)</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>11</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>University of Mysore, Mysore (Karnataka)</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>“Ayurvedacharya” (Bachelor of Ayurvedic Medicine and Surgery).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M.S. (Mysore) (From 1980 onwards.)</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>12</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Sambalpur University, Burla, Sambalpur, (Orissa).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>“Ayurvedacharya” (Bachelor of Ayurvedic Medicine and Surgery).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M.S. (Sambalpur) (From 1980 onwards.)</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>13</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Gurunanak Dev University, Amritsar (Punjab).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>“Ayurvedacharya” (Bachelor of Ayurvedic Medicine and Surgery).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M.S. (Amritsar) (From 1982 onwards.)</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>14</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Punjab University, Patiala (Punjab)</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>“Ayurvedacharya” (Bachelor of Ayurvedic Medicine and Surgery).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M.S. (Patiala) (From 1976 onwards.)</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>15</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Rajasthan University, Jaipur (Rajasthan)</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>“Ayurvedacharya” (Bachelor of Ayurvedic Medicine and Surgery).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M.S. (Jaipur) (From 1980 onwards.).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>16</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Lucknow University, Lucknow (Uttar Pradesh</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>“Ayurvedacharya” (Bachelor of Ayurvedic Medicine and Surgery).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M.S. (Lucknow) (From 1982 onwards.)</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>17</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>University of Bihar, Muzaffarpur (Bihar)</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>“Ayurvedacharya” (Bachelor of Ayurvedic Medicine and Surgery).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M.S. (Muzaffarpur) (From 1981 onwards).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>18</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Kameshwar Singh Darbhanga Sanskrit University, Darbhanga (Bihar).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>“Ayurvedacharya” (Bachelor of Ayurvedic Medicine and Surgery).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M.S. (Darbhanga) (From 1981 onwards.)</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>19</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>University of Amravati (Maharashtra)</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>“Ayurvedacharya” Bachelor of Ayurvedic Medicine and Surgery.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M.S. (From 1988 onwards.).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>20</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>North Maharashtra University,</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>“Ayurvedacharya”</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B. A. M. S.Jalgaon</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>21</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>The Bharati Vidyapeeth (Deemed University), Pune.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Bachelor of Ayurvedic Medicine and Surgery.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M.S. (from 2000 onwards).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>22</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Madhya Pradesh Board of Ayurvedic and Unani Systems of Medicine and Naturopathy Bhopal, Madhya Pradesh.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Ayurveda Vigyanacharya with Medicine and Surgery.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>A.V.M.S. (from 1971 to 1976 and from 1978 to 1984).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                  </table>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </part>
            <part id="part-B">
              <num>B</num>
              <heading>Qualifications in the Ayurvedic Syatem of Medicine with a course supplemented by modern advances with the Matriculation or S. S. C. Examination or its equivalent Examination as qualification for admission.</heading>
              <paragraph id="part-B.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <table id="part-B.paragraph-0.table0">
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>Sr.No</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Authority</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Qualification</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Abbreviation for registration and conditions for registration, if any</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>1</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>2</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>3</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>4</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>1</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Faculty of Ayurvedic and Unani Systems of Medicine, constituted under the Bombay Medical Practitioners Act, 1938.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Ayurved Visharad</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>D.A.S.F. (Bom.)</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>2</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Vidarbha Board of Ayurvedic and Unani Systems of Medicine constituted under the Central Provinces and Berar Ayurvedic and Unani Practitioners’ Act, 1947 (C.P. &amp; Berar Act IV of 1948)and, on and after the 23rd October, 1961, the Maharashtra Faculty of Ayurvedic and Unani Systems of Medicine constituted under the Maharashtra Medical Practitioners Act, 1961.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Bachelor of Ayurved with Modern Medicine and Surgery Ayurvidnyanacharya</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M.S. (Vid.).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>3</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Board of Indian Medicine, Hyderabad (Deccan), constituted under the rules made under the rules made under the Medical Act (Hyd. I of 1312 Fasli),</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Ayurved Visharad of the Government Ayurvedic College, Hyderabad</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>A.V.V. (Hyd.).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>4</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Tilak Maharashtra</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Ayurved Visharad</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>A.V.V. (Pune) (This qualification shall be recognised only when granted before 1944).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>5</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Ayurved Mahavidya laya, Ahmednagar.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Ayurvedteerth</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>A.T. (Nagar). (This qualification hall be recognised only when granted before 1942).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>6</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Aryangla Vaidyak Mahavidyalaya, Satara.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Ayurvedic Visharad</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>A.V.V. (Satara). (This qualification shall be recognised only when granted before 1942.)</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>7</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>U.P. Ayurvedic Mahavidyalaya, Patan (Baroda State).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Girihit Ayurved-Shastra,</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>L.A.M. (Patan) (This qualification shall be recognised only when granted before 1942).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>8</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Gurukul University, Kangri</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Ayurvedalankar</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>A.L. (Kang.) (This qualification shall be recognised only when -</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p/>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p/>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p/>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>(a) granted after 1926 but before 1952;</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p/>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p/>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p/>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>(b) granted after 1952 to students admitted by the University before June, 1952).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>9</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Board of Examiners in Indian Medicine, Madras.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Licennciate of Indian Medicine</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>L.I.M. (Madras).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>10</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>The ad hoc Committee appointed by Bombay Government Resolution in Local Self-Government and Public Health Department No. AUC-4859/73751/31474/H, dated the 31st December, 1959 and, on and after the 23rd October, 1961, the Maharashtra Faculty of Ayurvedic and Unani Systems of Medicine constituted under the Maharashtra Medical Practitioners Act, 1961.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Ayurved-Visharad (Graduate of College of Ayurvedic Medicine), Nanded.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>A.V.V. (G.C.A.M.) Nanded</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>11 .</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Board of Indian Medicine, U.P.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>1. Bachelor of Indian Medicine and Surgery.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.I.M.S. (U.P.)</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p/>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p/>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>2. Diploma of Indian Medicine and Surgery.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>D.I.M.S. (U.P.)</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>12</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Government Ayurvedic College, Patna.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Ayurvedacharya and Graduate of Ayurvedic</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>G.A.M.S. (Patna)</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>13</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Ayurvedic and Tibbi College, Delhi</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Medicine and Surgeyr</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p/>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p/>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p/>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>1. Ayurvedacharya Dhanwantari</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>……</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p/>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p/>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>2. Bhishagacharya Dhanwantari.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>………</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>14</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Government Ayurvedic and Unani College and Hospital, Mysore.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Licentiate of Ayurved Medicine and Surgery.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>L.A.M.S. (Mysore)</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>15</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Faculty of Ayurvedic Medicine, Bengal.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>1. Member of the Ayurvedic State Faculty.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>M.A.S.F. (Bengal).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p/>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p/>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>2. Fellow of the Ayurvedic State Faculty.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>F.A.S.F. (Bengal).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>16</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>University of Kerala</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Diploma in Ayurvedic Medicine</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>D.A.M. (Kerala)</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>17</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Board of Indian Medicine, Uttar Pradesh.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Ayurvedacharya Bachelor of Medicine and Surgery.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>A.M.B.S., U.P. (This qualification shall be recognised only when granted after 1956).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>18</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>J. B. Ashtang Ayurvedic College, Calcutta.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Diploma of L.A.M.S. (Bhishagratna).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>L.A.M.S. (Bhishagratna, Bengal). This qualification shall be recognised only when granted in or before 1942.</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>19</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Government Ayurvedic School, Raipur.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Diploma of Licentiate Ayurvedic Practitioner (Bhishagwar).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>L.A.P. (Bhishagwar), Madhya Pradesh. (This qualification shall be recognised only when granted in or before 1958).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>20</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Maharashtra Faculty of Ayurvedic and Unani Systems of Medicine, Bombay.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Member of the Faculty of Ayurvedic Medicine.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>MFAM (Maharashtra).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>21</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Board of Studies in Indian Medicine, Mysore, Bangalore.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Graduate Course of Integrated Medicines.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>G.C.I.M. (Mysore). (This qualification shall be recognised only when granted upto 1967).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>22</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>University of Sagar</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Bachelor of Ayurvedic Medicine and Surgery.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M.S. (Sagar). (This qualification shall be recognised only when granted to students admitted by the University before the 1st day of June, 1964).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>23</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Ravishankar University, Raipur.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Bachelor of Ayurvedic Medicine and Surgery.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.A.M.S. (Ravel) (This qualification shall be recognised only when granted to students admitted by the University after the 31st day of May, 1964 but before the 1st day of June, 1968).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>24</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Dayanand Ayurvedic College</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Vaidya Vachaspati</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>V.V. (This qualification shall be recognised only when granted before 1947).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>25</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>The Committee for Shuddha Ayurved Course appointed under Bombay Government Resolution in Local Self-Government and Public Health Department, No. ADR. 1253, dated the 17th September 1953 (and, on an after the 23rd October, 1961, the Maharashtra Faculty of Ayurvedic and Unani Systems of Medicine constituted under the Maharashtra Medical Practitioners Act, 1961) and aforesaid course introduced and conducted by the Government of Maharashtra in the Urban Development and Public Health and Housing Department.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Ayurved Pravin styled ic as such under Bombay Governmentnt Resolution in L.S.G. and P.H.D. No. BMP. 1054-H, dated the o. 12th July, 1956, le granted in 1957 and thereafter AND those of whom who have passed the Short Term Course Certificate in the Modern Scientific System of Medicine (M.S.S.M.) prescribed by Government Resolution, in U.D.P.H. &amp; H.D., No. DRG. 1165/79749/V, dated the 30th November, 1967, introduced and conducted by the Government.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>D.S.A.C. (Bom.) with Certificate in M.S.S.M.</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                  </table>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </part>
            <part id="part-C">
              <num>C</num>
              <heading>Qualification in the Ayurvedic System of Medicine with the Matriculation or S.S.C. Examination or an equivalent Examination with Sanskrit, as qualification for admission.</heading>
              <paragraph id="part-C.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <table id="part-C.paragraph-0.table0">
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>Sr. No.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Authority</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Qualification</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Abbreviation for registration and conditions for registration, if any</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>1</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>2</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>3</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>4</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>1</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>The Committee for Shudha Ayurvedic Course appointed under Bombay Government Resolution, in Local Self-Government and Public Health Department No. ADR-1253, dated the 17th September, 1953 and, on and after the 23rd October, 1961, the Maharashtra Faculty of Ayurvedic and Unani Systems of Medicine constituted under the Maharashtra Medical Practitioners Act, 1961).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Ayurved-Pravin, styled as such under Bombay Government Resolution in L.S.G. and P.H.D. No. BMP-1054-H, dated the 12th July, 1956, granted in 1957 and thereafter.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>D.S.A.C. (Bom.)</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>2</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Board of Studies in Indian Medicine, Mysore.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Ayurved Pravin</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>D.A.S.C. (Mysore).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>3</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Committee of Shuddha Ayurvedic Course, Gujarat State, Ahmedabad.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Ayurved Pravin</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>D.S.A.C. (Gujarat) (This qualification shall be recognised only when granted upto April, 1968).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>4</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Board of Studies in Indian Medicine, Bangalore (Karnataka).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Diploma in Ayurvedic Medicine.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>D.A.M. (This qualification shall be recognised only when granted to students admitted prior to July, 1968).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>5</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Government of Kerala.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Diploma in Ayurvedic Medicine.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>D.A.M. (Kerala) (This qualification shall be recognised only when granted to students admitted in or before July, 1968.)</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>6</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>University of Bombay (Maharashtra).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>‘Ayurvedacharya’ Bachelor of Shuddha Ayurvedic Medicine.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.S.A.M.</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>7</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>University of Poona (Maharashtra).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>‘Ayurvedacharya’ Bachelor of Shuddha Ayurvedic Medicine.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.S.A.M.</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>8</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Shivaji University, Kolhapur (Maharashtra).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>‘Ayurvedacharya’ Bachelor of Shuddha Ayurvedic Medicine.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.S.A.M.</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>9</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Marathwada University, Aurangabad (Maharashtra).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>‘Ayurvedacharya’ Bachelor of Shuddha Ayurvedic Medicine.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.S.A.M.</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                  </table>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </part>
            <part id="part-D">
              <num>D</num>
              <heading>Qualification in the Unani System of Medicine</heading>
              <paragraph id="part-D.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <table id="part-D.paragraph-0.table0">
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>Sr. No.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Authority granting the qualification</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Qualification</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Abbreviation for registration and conditions for registration, if any.</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>1</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>2</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>3</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>4</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>1</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Board of Examiners in Unani.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Mahire-Tib-o-Jarahat</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>M.T.J. (Bom.) (This qualification shall be recognised qualification only when granted in 1942 or 1943).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>2</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Faculty of Ayurvedic and Unani Systems of Medicine constituted under the Bombay Medical Practitioners’Act, 1938 (Bom. XXVI of 1938).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Mahire-Tib-o-Jarahat</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>D.U.S.F. (Bom.)</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>3</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Ayurvedic and Unani Tibbi College, Delhi.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>(i) Fazi’l-e-Tib-o Jarahat</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>F.T.J. (Del.)</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p/>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p/>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>(ii) Kamile-e-Tib-o-Jarahat.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>K.T.J. (Del.)</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>4.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Government Ayurvedic College, Mysore.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Licentiate of Unani Medicine and Surgery.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>L.U.M.S. (Mysore).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>5</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Board of Indian Medicine, U.P.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>1. Bachelor of Indian Medicine and Surgery.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.I.M.S. (U.P.)</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p/>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p/>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>2. Diploma in Indian Medicine and Surgery.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>D.I.M.S. (U.P.)</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>6</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Government Unani Tibbi college, Hyderabad.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Tabeeb-e-Mustanad</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>D.I.M.S. (U.P.)</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>7</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Board of Indian Medicine, Uttar Pradesh.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Fazil-Ul-Tib, Bachelor of Medicine and Surgery.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>F.M.B.S., U.P. (This qualification shall be recognised only when granted after 1956).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>8</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Muslim University, Aligarh.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>(1) Bachelor of Unani Medicine and Surgery.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.U.M.S. (Aligarh).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>9</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Maharashtra Faculty of Ayurvedic and Unani Systems of Medicine, Bombay before the 30th June, 1982 and thereafter the Maharashtra Council of Indian Medicine till the 31st October, 1984.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Diploma in Unani Medicine and Surgery.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>D. U. M. S. (Maharashtra).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>10</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>University of Pune (Maharashtra).</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Kamil-Tib-o-Jarahat (Bachelor of Unani Medicine and Surgery)</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.U.M.S. (From 1987 on wards).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                      <td>
                        <p>11</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Mumbai University, Mumbai.</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>Kamil-e-Tibb-o-Jarahat (Bachelor of Unani Medicine and Surgery)</p>
                      </td>
                      <td>
                        <p>B.U.M.S. (From 1984 onwards).</p>
                      </td>
                    </tr>
                  </table>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </part>
            <part id="part-E">
              <num>E</num>
              <heading>All qualifications specified in the Second, Third and Fourth Schedules to the Indian Medicine Central Council Act, 1970, other than those specified in Parts A to D above.</heading>
            </part>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
