<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1872/4/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1872/4"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Punjab Laws Act, 1872"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1872/4/eng@1872-03-28/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1872/4/eng@1872-03-28"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1872-03-28" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1872/4/eng@1872-03-28/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1872/4/eng@1872-03-28"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Punjab Laws Act, 1872</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 4 OF 1872</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 28th March, 1872.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act for declaring which of certain rules, laws and regulations  have the force of law in the Punjab and for other purposes.</p>
        <p>Preamble.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS certain rules, laws and regulations, made heretofore for  the Punjab, acquired the force of law under the provisions of section</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>of the  Indian Councils Act, 1861; (24 and 25 Vict., c. 67.) and  whereas it is expedient to declare which of the said rules, laws and  regulations shall henceforth be in force in the Punjab, and to amend,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>consolidate or repeal others of the said rules, orders and  regulations; It is hereby enacted as follows:--</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title. This Act may be called the Punjab Laws Act, 1872.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Local extent. It extends to the territories  which,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised in the</p>
            <p>States of Punjab and Delhi], but not so as to alter the effect of any  regulations made for any parts of the said territories under the</p>
            <p>Statute 33 Vict, ch. 3, section 1;</p>
            <p>Commencment.</p>
            <p>and it shall come into force on the first day of June, 1872.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Enactments in force. The Regulations, Acts and Orders  specified in the First Schedule hereto annexed are in force in the    territories to which this Act extends] to the extent specified in  the third column of the said Schedule.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Enactments repealed. Rep. by the Second Repealing and</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Amending Act, 1914 (17 of 1914), s. 3 and Sch. II.</p>
            <p>Civil Judicature</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Decisions in certain cases to be according to Native law.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In questions regarding succession, special property of females,</p>
            <p>betrothal, marriage, divorce, dower, adoption, guardianship, minority,</p>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>bastardy, family relations, wills, legacies, gifts, partitions, or any  religious usage or institution, the rule of decision shall be--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any custom applicable to the parties concerned, which is  not contrary to justice, equity or good conscience, and</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list5">
              <listIntroduction>has not been, by this or any other enactment, altered  or abolished, and has not been declared to be void by  any competent authority;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list5.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the Muhammadan law, in cases where the parties are</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Muhammadans, and the Hindu law, in cases where the  parties are Hindus, except in so far as such law has  been altered or abolished by legislative enactment, or  is opposed to the provisions of this Act, or has been  modified by any such custom as is above referred to.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Decisions in cases not specially provided for. In cases not  otherwise specially provided for, the Judges shall decide according to  justice, equity and good conscience.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Local customs and mercantile usages when valid. All local  customs and mercantile usages shall be regarded as valid, unless they  are contrary to justice, equity or good conscience, or have, before  the passing of this Act, been declared to be void by any competent  authority.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>8, 8A to 8C Repealed.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Pre- emption</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>(Rep. by the Punjab Pre- emption Act, 1905) (Punjab Act 2   of 1905), s. 2 1.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Decrees concerning land</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Copy of decrees affecting land to be forwarded to Deputy</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Commissioner. Rep. by the Punjab Land Revenue Act, 1887 (17 of 1887).</p>
            <p>Insolvency</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>t</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Insolvency Rep. by the Provincial Insolvency Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>to 32. Insolvency Rep. by the Provincial Insolvency Act, 1907</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>(3 of 1907).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-33">
        <num>33.</num>
        <heading>Saving of previous insolvency proceedings. Rep. by the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-33.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Amending Act, 1891 (12 of 1891).</p>
            <p>Minors and the Court of Wards</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-34">
        <num>34.</num>
        <heading>t</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-34.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Rep. by the Punjab Court of Wards Act, 1903</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-34">
        <num>34.</num>
        <heading>to 38. Rep. by the Punjab Court of Wards Act, 1903 (Punjab Act</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>of 1903), s. 2 (1).</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-39">
        <num>39.</num>
        <heading>Indian Penal Code to apply to offences committed previous to</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1st">
        <num>1st.</num>
        <heading>January, 1862. The provisions of the Indian Penal Code, with the  exception of Chapter VI, shall be applicable to all offences committed  before first January, 1862 (45 of 1860), in territory which was, at  the time of the commission of such offence, subject to the State</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1st.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Government of the Punjab:</p>
            <p>Saving of privileges conferred on certain Chiefs.</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing contained in this section shall affect any  privilege conferred on certain Chiefs in the Punjab by the Central</p>
            <p>Government, or by the Board of Administration for the affairs of the</p>
            <p>Punjab, nor any indemnity or pardon granted by competent authority.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-39A">
        <num>39A.</num>
        <heading>Power to establish system of village- watchmen and  municipal- watchmen, and to make rules. The State Government may  establish a system of village- watchmen or municipal watchmen in any  part of the territories under its administration, and in furtherance  of this object may, from time to time, make rules to provide for the  following matters:--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-39A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-39A.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-39A.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the definition of the limits of watchmen' s beats;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39A.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the determination of the several grades of watchmen, and  the number of each grade to be appointed to each beat;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39A.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the appointment, suspension, dismissal and resignation  of watchmen of each grade;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39A.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the equipment and discipline of, and the control and  supervision over, such watchmen;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39A.paragraph-0.list0.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the conferring upon them, and the exercise by them, of  any powers and the enjoyment by them of any protection  or privilege, which may be exercised and enjoyed by a  police- officer under any law for the time being in  force;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39A.paragraph-0.list0.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the performance by them of such duties relating to  police, sanitation or statistics, or for the benefit of  the village communities or municipalities within their  respective beats, as the State Government thinks fit;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39A.paragraph-0.list0.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the exercise of authority over, and the rendering of aid  to, such watchmen by headmen of the villages or members  of the Municipal Committees of the towns comprised in  their respective beats;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39A.paragraph-0.list0.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the performance, by the headmen of villages comprised in  the beat of any watchmen, of any of the duties of a  village- watchman in aid of, or substitution for, such  watchman;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39A.paragraph-0.list0.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the exercise, by such village- headmen for the purposes  referred to in clauses (g) and (h), or by members of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-39A.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Municipal Committees for the purposes referred to in  clause (g) of this section, of any of the powers, and  the enjoyment by such headmen or members of any  privilege or protection, of a village- watchman, or a  municipal- watchman, as the case may be;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-39A.paragraph-0.list2.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>the determination of the rate at which, and the mode in  which, watchmen shall be paid, and, in the case of  village- watchmen, of the mode in which their pay, the  expenses of their equipment, and other charges  connected with the village- watchmen- system shall be  provided for, whether out of cesses or funds already  leviable or available in the villages comprised in the  beat, or by a special tax in money or kind to be  imposed on any class of persons residing or owning  property in, or resorting to, such villages, or partly  in one of these ways and partly in the other;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-39A.paragraph-0.list2.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>the collection with or without the aid of the village-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-39A.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>headmen, and by any process available for the  realisation of the land- revenue, of any tax imposed  under clause (j) of this section, and the application  of, and the mode of accounting for, the same; and  generally for</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-39A.paragraph-0.list4.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>the efficient working of the system of village- watchmen  or municipal watchmen:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided--</p>
            <p>first, that the rules to be made regarding the appointment  of village- watchmen shall allow to the headmen of the  villages comprised in the beat to which such a watchman  is to be appointed a power of nomination to be  exercised in such manner and subject to such reasonable  conditions as may be prescribed by such rules;</p>
            <p>secondly, that the rules to be made under clause (j) of this  section with regard to village- watchmen shall include  provisions for recording and securing due consideration  of the views and opinions on the matters therein  referred to of the headmen of the villages comprised in  each beat.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-39B">
        <num>39B.</num>
        <heading>Obligation to assist watchmen and headmen. Every person is  bound to render to a village- watchman, or municipal watchman, or  village- headman discharging the duties of a police- officer under the  rules made hereunder, all the assistance which he is bound to render  to a police- officer.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-39B.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Person obstructing watchman or headman may be arrested without  warrant.</p>
            <p>Any person who obstructs such watchman or headman in the  discharge of such duties may be arrested without warrant by a police-</p>
            <p>officer or by any watchman or village- headman empowered in this behalf  by the State Government.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-39C">
        <num>39C.</num>
        <heading>Power to direct local taxation for payment of police  enrolled under Act 5 of 1861. Whenever it seems to the State</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-39C.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Government expedient that the duties of watch- and- ward and other  internal police- service of any town or village not comprised within  the limits of a municipality or within the limits of a village-</p>
            <p>watchman' s beat as defined under the power conferred by section 39A</p>
            <p>should be performed by police- officers enrolled under  Act V of 1861,</p>
            <p>the State Government may direct that the said service shall be so  performed, and may also  direct that the charges for the time being  fixed by such Government on account of such service shall be defrayed  by taxes to be levied in such town or village.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-39D">
        <num>39D.</num>
        <heading>Notice of taxes proposed to be levied. When the State</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-39D.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Government has, under section 39C, directed that taxes shall be levied  in any town or village, the Deputy Commissioner may from time to time  issue a public notice in such town or village explaining the nature of  the taxes he proposes to levy.</p>
            <p>Objections to taxation.</p>
            <p>Any inhabitant of such town or village objecting to the taxation  thus proposed may, within fifteen days from the publication of such  notice, send his objection in writing to the Deputy Commissioner.</p>
            <p>Procedure thereon.</p>
            <p>After the expiry of fifteen days from the publication of the  notice, the Deputy Commissioner may submit for the information of the</p>
            <p>State Government a report of the proposal made by him. Such report  shall contain specific mention of the objections (if any) urged to his  proposal and his opinion on such objections.</p>
            <p>No such tax shall be levied until it has, upon such report, been  approved by the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-39E">
        <num>39E.</num>
        <heading>Power to fix rates of tax. When any such tax has been so  approved by the State Government, the Deputy Commissioner may from  time to time, subject to such rules consistent with this Act as the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-39E.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>State Government may from time to time prescribe, determine the rates  at which it is to be levied.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-39F">
        <num>39F.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules for collection of taxes. The State</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-39F.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Government may from time to time make rules to provide for the  collection of such taxes by any process available</p>
            <p>for the realisation of the land- revenue and to regulate the  application and mode of accounting for the same.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-39G">
        <num>39G.</num>
        <heading>Validation clause. Rep. by the Amending Act, 1891 (12 of</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1891">
        <num>1891.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1891.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>).]</p>
            <p>Honorary police- officers</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-40">
        <num>40.</num>
        <heading>State Government may confer powers of police- officer. The</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-40.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>State Government may, if it thinks fit, confer on any person any of  the powers which may be exercised by a police- officer under any Act  for the time being in force,  and may withdraw any powers so  conferred].</p>
            <p>Track law</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-41">
        <num>41.</num>
        <heading>Trackers may call for assistance in carrying on tracks. When  an offence is, has been, or may reasonably be supposed to have been  committed, and the tracks of the persons who may reasonably be  supposed to have committed such offence, or of any animal or other  property reasonably supposed to be connected with such offence, are  followed to a spot within the immediate vicinity of a village, the  person following such tracks may call upon any headman or village-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-41.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>watchman in such village to assist in carrying on the tracks.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-42">
        <num>42.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for withholding assistance or conniving at offence or  escape. If such headman or watchman do not forthwith give such  assistance, or if the inhabitants of such village do not afford full  opportunity for search in their houses for the offenders, or, if from  the circumstances of the case, there shall appear good reason to  believe that the inhabitants of such village, or any of them were  conniving at the offence or at the escape of the offenders, and such  offenders cannot be traced beyond the village, the Magistrate of the  district may, with the previous sanction of the Commissioner of the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-42.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Division inflict a fine upon such village not exceeding five hundred  rupees, except in the case of stolen property over five hundred rupees  in value, in which case the fine shall not exceed the value of such  property.</p>
            <p>Appeal to High Court.</p>
            <p>An appeal against all convictions under this section shall lie to  the High Court of Punjab.</p>
            <p>Fine may be awarded to injured parties, and fee to tracker.</p>
            <p>The Magistrate may direct that the fine imposed under this  section or any part thereof shall be awarded to any persons injured by  such offence in compensation for such injury; and, in the case of  stolen property recovered through the agency of a tracker, may direct  that such property be not restored to its owner until he has paid to  such</p>
            <p>tracker such fee, not exceeding one- fourth part of the value of the  stolen property, as to the said Magistrate seems fit.</p>
            <p>Slaughter of kine</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-43">
        <num>43.</num>
        <heading>Control of slaughter of kine and sale of beef. The slaughter  of kine and the sale of beef shall not take place, except  subject  to rules to be from time to time, either generally or in any  particular instance, prescribed by the State Government.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-43.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Armed men and foreign vagrants</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-44">
        <num>44.</num>
        <heading>Control of entry into towns of bands of armed men. No band of  armed men shall enter into any city or town, except  subject to  rules to be from time to time, either generally or in any particular  instance, prescribed by the State Government.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-45">
        <num>45.</num>
        <heading>Powers of Magistrate of district as to foreign vagrants. The</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-45.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Magistrate of the district may, if he considers that any band of  foreign vagrants is likely to occasion a breach of the peace or to  commit any offence under the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860), prohibit  such band from entering his district; or, if they are already in his  district, may require them within a given time to leave it.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-46">
        <num>46.</num>
        <heading>Surveillance, etc., of band failing to comply with</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-46.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Magistrate' s order. If any such band fail to comply with the orders of  the said Magistrate within the prescribed period, he shall report the  matter to the State Government, and the State Government may give such  directions for the surveillance, control or deportation of such band,</p>
            <p>as to it seems fit.</p>
            <p>Miscellaneous</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-47">
        <num>47.</num>
        <heading>Crossing of streams on buoys or skins. No person shall cross  any river or stream on a buoy or inflated skin, nor shall have in his  possession or custody any buoy or skin for the purpose of being used  in crossing any river or stream, except  subject to rules to be  from time to time, either generally or in any particular instance,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-47.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>prescribed by the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-48">
        <num>48.</num>
        <heading>Use of pasturage or natural product of Government land. No  person shall make use of the pasturage or other natural product of any  land being the property of the Government, except with the consent and  subject to rules to be from time to time, either generally or in any  particular instance, prescribed by  the Government concerned].</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-49">
        <num>49.</num>
        <heading>Growing, selling or keeping opium. Rep. by the Opium Act,</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1878">
        <num>1878.</num>
        <heading>(1 of 1878), s. 2 and Sch.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-50">
        <num>50.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules as to matters mentioned in sections 43  to 48. The State Government may from time to time make rules as to the  matters mentioned in  section 43 to 48] inclusive.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-50.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Existing rules.</p>
            <p>All existing rules upon such matters, which might have been made  under this section had it been in force, shall be deemed to have been  made hereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-50A">
        <num>50A.</num>
        <heading>Conditions of validity of rules hereafter made under this</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-50A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-50A.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Act.  Rules made under this Act shall not be valid unless]:--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-50A.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>they are consistent with the laws for the time being in  force in the  territories to which this Act extends];</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-50A.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>they are published in the Official Gazette;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-50B">
        <num>50B.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for contravention of rules. If any person  contravenes the provisions of any rule made by the State Government  under this Act, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term  which may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to fifty  rupees, or with both.]]</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-51">
        <num>51.</num>
        <heading>Republication of rules and orders. All rules which the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-51.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>State Government is empowered to issue under this Act, and all  circulars issued by the High Court of Punjab, shall be republished  from time to time by the State Government, and upon such  republication, shall be arranged in the order of their subject- matter,</p>
            <p>and all such alterations or amendments as may have been made since the  last preceding publication thereof, or may have become necessary or  advisable, shall be embodied therewith, and upon such republication  all such rules and circulars previously issued shall be repealed.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-52">
        <num>52.</num>
        <heading>Recovery of advances made by Government. Rep. by the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-52.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Northern India Takkavi Act, 1879 (10 of 1879).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
