<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1927/17/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1927/17"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Lighthouse Act, 1927"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1927/17/eng@1927-09-21/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1927/17/eng@1927-09-21"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1927-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1927/17/eng@1927-09-21/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1927/17/eng@1927-09-21"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Lighthouse Act, 1927</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 17 OF 1927</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 21st September, 1927.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to consolidate and amend the law relating to the provision,</p>
        <p>maintenance and control of lighthouses by the Government in</p>
        <p>India].</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be  called the  Lighthouse Act, 1927</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India .</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date  as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant  in the subject or context,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" district" means an area defined as a district for the  purposes of this Act under section 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" general lighthouse" means any lighthouse which the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Central Government may, by notification in the Official</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Gazette, declare to be a general lighthouse for the  purposes of this Act;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>" lighthouse" includes any light- vessel, fog- signal,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5">
              <listIntroduction>buoy, beacon, or any mark, sign or apparatus exhibited  or used for the guidance of ships;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>" local lighthouse" means any lighthouse which is not a  general lighthouse;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Extended to Laccadive, Minicoy and Amindivi Islands (w. e. f.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>10. 1967): vide Reg. 8 of 1965, s. 3 and Sch.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Extended to Goa, Daman and Diu with modifications, by Reg. 12 of 1962,</p>
            <p>s. 3 and Sch.</p>
            <p>The Act comes into force in Pondicherry on 1. 10. 1963 vide Reg. 7 of</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1963">
        <num>1963.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1963.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>, s. 3 and Sch. I.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>" local lighthouse authority" means a State Government,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>local authority or other person having the  superintendence and management of a local lighthouse;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list3.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>" owner" includes any part- owner, charterer, or mortgagee  in possession and any agent to whom a ship is  consigned;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list3.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>" port" means any port, as defined in the Indian Ports</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Act, 1908 (15 of 1908), to which that Act extends;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list5.hh">
                <num>(hh)</num>
                <p>" proper officer", in relation to any functions to be  performed under this Act, means the officer of Customs  who is assigned those functions by the Central Board of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list7">
              <listIntroduction>Excise and Customs constituted under the Central Boards  of Revenue Act, 1963 (54 of 1963), and includes any  person appointed by the Central Government to discharge  the functions of a proper officer under this Act;]</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list7.hha">
                <num>(hha)</num>
                <p>" ship" includes a sailing vessel;]</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list7.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>words and expressions used in this Act and not otherwise  defined have the same meanings respectively as in the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Merchant shipping Act, 1958 (44 of 1958)].</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Appointment of officers. The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>define areas to be district for the purposes of this</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>appoint a person to be the Director of Lighthouses  and Lightships in each district;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>appoint persons to be Deputy Directors- General of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Lighthouses and Lightships; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list4.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>appoint a person to be the Director- General of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Lighthouses and Lightships.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Advisory Committees.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government shall appoint  a Central Advisory Committee and shall consult it in regard to--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the erection or position of lighthouses or of any works  appertaining thereto;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>additions to, or the alteration or removal of,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>lighthouses;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the variation of the character of any lighthouse or of  the mode of use thereof;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the cost of any proposals relating to lighthouses; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the making or alteration of any rules or rates of dues  under this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, if it thinks fit, appoint an</p>
            <p>Advisory Committee for any district for the purpose of advising in  regard to any of the matters specified in sub- section (1) in so far as  the interests of the district are affected thereby.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Advisory Committees shall consist of persons representing  interests affected by this Act or having special knowledge of the  subject- matter thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>No act or proceeding of the Advisory Committee shall be  invalidated merely by reason of--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any vacancy in, or any defect in constitution of, the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-4.4.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Advisory Committee;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.4.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any defect in appointment of a person acting as a member  of the Advisory Committee; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.4.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any irregularity in the procedure of the Advisory</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Committee not affecting the merits of the case.]</p>
            <p>GENERAL LIGHTHOUSES</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Management of general lighthouses by the Central Government  and delegation of management.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The superintendence and management  of all general lighthouses are vested in the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may require any local lighthouse  authority to undertake the superintendence and management of any  general lighthouse situated in or adjacent to the local limits within  which the authority exercises its powers, and shall pay to the  authority such sums to defray the cost of superintendence and  management as the Central Government may determine.</p>
            <p>LOCAL LIGHTHOUSES</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Power to inspect local lighthouses.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The  Director-</p>
            <p>General of Lighthouses and Lightships] may, at any time, and any</p>
            <p>Director or Deputy Director- General of Lighthouses and Lightships]</p>
            <p>may, if authorised in this behalf by a general or special order in  writing of the Central Government, enter upon and inspect any local  lighthouse and make such inquireis in respect thereof or of the  management thereof as he thinks fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every person having the charge of, or concerned in the  management of, any lighthouse shall be bound to furnish to any officer  authorised by or under sub- section (1) to inspect the lighthouse all  such information regarding the same as the officer may require.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every local lighthouse authority shall furnish to the Central</p>
            <p>Government all such returns and other information in respect of the  lighthouses under its supervision and management, or of any of them,</p>
            <p>as the Central Government may require.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Control of local lighthouses by the Central Government.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If, after an inspection under section 6 or such other inquiry as it  thinks fit, the Central Government is satisfied that a direction under  this sub- section is necessary or expedient for the safety, or  otherwise in the interests, of shipping, it may direct any local  lighthouse authority--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to remove or discontinue or to refrain from moving or  discontinuing any lighthouse under its superintendence  and management or to make or refrain from making any  variation in the character or mode of use of any such  lighthouse, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to erect, place or maintain, or to refrain from  erecting, placing or maintaining, any lighthouse within  the local limits within which the local lighthouse  authority exercises its powers.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A local lighthouse authority shall not erect, place, remove  or discontinue any lighthouse or vary the character or mode of use of  any lighthouse, unless it has given to the Central Government at least  one month' s notice in writing of its intention so to do:</p>
            <p>Provided that, in cases of emergency, a local lighthouse  authority may take such action as it deems necessary and shall give  immediate notice of the same to the Central Government and, so far as  is possible, to all shipping approaching or in the vicinity of the  lighthouse.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If a local lighthouse authority--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>fails to comply with any direction made under sub-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-7.3.list3">
              <listIntroduction>section (1), or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.3.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>fails to exercise or perform, or exercises or performs  in an improper, inefficient or unsuitable manner, any  power or duty relating to the superintendence or  management of lighthouses conferred or imposed upon it  by or under any law for the time being in force, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.3.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>fails to make adequate financial provision for the  performance of any such duty,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>the Central Government may, by order in writing, require the local  lighthouse authority to comply with the direction, or to make  arrangements to the satisfaction of the Central Government for the  proper exercise of the power or performance of the duty, or to make  financial provision to the satisfaction of the Central Government for  the performance of the duty, as the case may be, within such period as the</p>
            <p>Central Government may specify.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the local lighthouse authority fails to comply with an  order made under sub- section (3) within the specified period or within  such further time as the Central Government may allow, the Central</p>
            <p>Government may exercise the power or perform the duty or make the  requisite financial provision, as the case may be, and the local  lighthouse authority shall be liable to repay to the Central</p>
            <p>Government any expenditure incurred by it in so doing.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Management of local lighthouses by the Central Government. The</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Central Government may, at the request of a local lighthouse  authority, undertake the superintendence and management of any local  lighthouse on its behalf, and the local lighthouse authority shall pay  to the Central Government such sums to defray the cost of  superintendence and management as may be agreed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8A">
        <num>8A.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to prohibit lights and  regulate heights of buildings, structures and trees.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the</p>
            <blockList id="section-8A.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Central Government is of opinion that it is necessary or expedient so  to do for unobstructed functioning of any lighthouse, it may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, direct that,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8A.1.list2.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>no light shall be established without the prior  permission of the Central Government in case of general  lighthouse and without the prior permission of the local  lighthouse authority in case of local lighthouse on any land  within such radius, not exceeding one kilometre from the  lighthouse, as may be specified in the notification; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8A.1.list2.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>no building or structure higher than such height as may  be specified in the notification shall be constructed or erected,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>or no tree, which is likely to grow or ordinarily grows higher  than such height as may be specified in the notification, shall  be planted, on any land within such radius, not exceeding one  kilometre from the lighthouse, as may be specified in the  notification.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any light has been established without or contrary to  the permission referred to in clause (i) of sub- section (1), the</p>
            <p>Central Government or the local lighthouse authority, as the case may  be, may, in addition to any other action that may be taken under this</p>
            <p>Act, make an order directing that such light shall be removed by the  owner or the person having control of the light, within such period as  may be specified in such order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any building or structure has been constructed or  erected or any tree has been planted in contravention of the  directions contained in clause (ii) of sub- section (1), the Central</p>
            <p>Government or the local lighthouse authority, as the case may be, may,</p>
            <p>in addition to any other action that may be taken under this Act, make  an order directing that the height of such building, structure or tree  shall be reduced to the extent specified in such notification, by the  owner or the person having control of the building or structure or the  tree, as the case may be, within such period as may be specified in  such order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8A.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No order under sub- section (2) or sub- section (3) shall be  made unless the owner or the person has been given, by means of a  notice, a reasonable opportunity of showing cause why such order shall  not be made.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8A.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person fails to remove the light in pursuance of  direction contained in the order issued under sub- section (2) or  reduce the height of the building, structure or tree in pursuance of  any direction contained in the order issued under sub- section (3),</p>
            <p>within the period specified in such order, then, subject to such rules  as the Central Government may make in this behalf, it shall be  competent for any officer authorised by the Central Government or the  local lighthouse authority, as the case may be, in this behalf to  remove such light or to reduce the height of such building, structure  or tree and the expenses of such removal or reduction shall be  recoverable from such person as a land revenue.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8A.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8A.6.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The orders referred to in sub- sections (2) and (3) and the  notice referred to in sub- section (4) shall be served on the owner or  the person having the control of the light, building, structure or  tree, as the case may be,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8A.6.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>by delivering or tendering it to such owner or person;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-8A.6.list3">
              <listIntroduction>or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8A.6.list3.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>if it cannot be so delivered or tendered, by delivering  or tendering it to any officer of such owner or person or any  adult male member of the family of such owner or person or by  affixing a copy thereof on some conspicuous part of the premises  in which such owner or person is known to have last resided or  carried on business or personally worked for gain, or failing  service by these means;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8A.6.list3.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>by post.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8A.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person wilfully fails to comply with any direction  contained in any notification issued under sub- section (1), he shall  be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six  months or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees or with  both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8A.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every notification issued by the Central Government under  sub- section (1) shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is published  in the Official Gazette, before each House of Parliament, while it is  in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised  in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before  the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the  successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree that the notification  should not be made, the notification shall thereafter have effect only  in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so,</p>
            <p>however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without  prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under the  notification.]</p>
            <p>LIGHT- DUES</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Levy and collection of light- dues. For the purpose of  providing or maintaining or of providing and maintaining lighthouses  for the benefit of ships voyaging to or from  India] or between  ports in  India], the Central Government shall, subject to the  provisions of this Act, cause light- dues to be levied and collected in  respect of every ship arriving at or departing from any port in</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>India].</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Rates of light- dues leviable.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government  may, by notification in the Official Gazette, prescribe such rates, as  it may deem necessary to provide for the purpose mentioned in section</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>, at which light- dues shall be payable, and may prescribe different  rates for different classes of ships or sailing vessels, or for ships  or sailing vessels of the same class when in use for different  purposes or in different circumstances.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Light- dues payable in respect of a ship shall be paid by the  owner or master of the ship on its arrival at, and on its departure  from, any port in  India]:</p>
            <p>Provided that, if light- dues have been paid in accordance with  the provisions of this Act in respect of any ship, no further dues  shall become payable in respect of that ship for a period of thirty  days from the date on which the dues so paid became payable.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An order under sub- section (1) imposing, abolishing or  varying light- dues shall not take effect till the expiration of thirty  days from the day on which the order was notified in the Official</p>
            <p>Gazette.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every notification issued by the Central Government under  sub- section (1) shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is published  in the Official Gazette, before each House of Parliament, while it is  in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised  in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before  the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the  successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the notification or both Houses agree that the  notification should not be made, the notification shall thereafter  have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case  may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be  without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under  the notification.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Receipts for light- dues. Light- dues shall be paid to the    proper officer] who shall grant to the person paying the same a  receipt in writing specifying--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the port at which the dues have been paid;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the amount of the payment;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the date on which the dues became payable; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the name, tonnage and other proper description of the  ship in respect of which the payment is made.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Ascertainment of tonnage.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purposes of levy of  light- dues, the tonnage of a ship or sailing vessel shall be reckoned  as under the Merchant Shipping Act, 1958 (44 of 1958.) for dues  payable on a ship' s tonnage including the tonnage of any space added  under the said Act to the tonnage of ships by reason of such space  being utilised for carrying cargo.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-12.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In order to ascertain the tonnage of any ship for the purpose  of levying light- dues, the  proper officer] may--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>if the ship is registered under any law for the time being  in force in India or under the law of any country, other  than India, being a country the ships of which are  recognised or accepted by the Central Government to be of  the tonnage denoted in their certificates of registry or  other national papers under any order made under any  enactment repealed by sub- section (1) of section 461 of  the Merchant Shipping Act, 1958 (44 of 1958), and  continued in force under clause (a) of sub- section (3) of  that section or under any rule made under clause (b) of  sub- section (2) of section 74 of the said Act (any such  ship being hereafter in this section referred to as   registered ship), require the owner or master or other  person having possession of the ship' s register or other  papers denoting her tonnage to produce the same for  inspection and, if such owner, master or other person  refuses or neglects to produce the register or papers, as  the case may be, or otherwise to satisfy the proper  officer as to the tonnage of the ship, cause the ship to  be measured and the tonnage to be ascertained; or]</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>if the ship is not a registered ship and the owner or master  fails to satisfy the  proper officer] as to the true  tonnage thereof according to the mode of measurement  prescribed by the law for the time being in force for  regulating the measurement of registered ships, cause the  ship to be measured and the tonnage thereof to be ascer-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>tained according to such mode.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person refuses or neglects to produce any register or  other papers or otherwise to satisfy the  proper officer] as to the  true tonnage of any ship when required to do so under this section,</p>
            <p>such person shall be liable to pay the expenses of the measurement of  the ship and of the ascertainment of the tonnage, and, if the ship is  a registered ship, shall further, on conviction by a Presidency</p>
            <p>Magistrate or Magistrate of the first class having jurisdiction in the  port where the ship lies or in any port to which she may proceed, be  punishable with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Recovery of light- dues expenses and costs.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the owner  or master of any ship refuses or neglects to pay to the  proper  officer] on demand the amount of any light- dues or expenses payable  under this Act in respect of the ship, the  proper officer] may  seize the ship and the tackle, apparel and furniture belonging  thereto, or any part thereof, and detain the same until the</p>
            <p>amount of the dues or expenses, together with the costs of the seizure  and detention, is paid.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any part of such dues, expenses or costs remains unpaid  after the expiry of five days following the date of the seizure, the    proper officer] may cause the ship or other thing seized to be  sold, and with the proceeds of the sale may satisfy the dues, expenses  or costs remaining unpaid, together with the costs of the sale, and  shall repay the surplus, if any, to the person by whom the same were  payable.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Refusal of port- clearance. The officer whose duty it is to  grant a port- clearance for any ship shall not grant the port- clearance  until the amount of all light- dues, expenses and costs payable in  respect of the ship under this Act and of any fines impose thereunder  has been paid, or until security for the payment thereof has been  given to his satisfaction.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Determination of disputes as to liability for payment. If any  dispute arises as to whether light- dues, expenses or costs are payable  in respect of any ship under this Act or as to the amount of such  dues, expenses or costs, the dispute shall, on application made in  this behalf by either of the disputing parties, be heard and  determined by a Presidency Magistrate or Magistrate of the first class  having jurisdiction at the place where the dispute arises, and the  decision of such Magistrate shall be final.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Light- dues payable at one port recoverable at another.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-16.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If  the master of any ship in respect of which any light- dues are payable  at any port causes the ship to leave such port without having paid the  same, the  proper officer] at that port may by writing require the    proper officer] at any other port in  India] to which the ship  may proceed or in which she may be to recover the dues remaining  unpaid.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any  proper officer] to whom such a requisition is directed  shall proceed to levy such sum as if it were payable under this Act at  the port at which he is the  proper officer], and a certificate by  the  proper officer] at the port at which the light- dues first  became payable, stating the amount payable, shall be sufficient proof  in any proceeding under section 13 or section 15 that such amount is  payable.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for evading payment of light- dues.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the owner  or master of a ship evades or attempts to evade the payment of any  light- dues, expenses or costs payable in respect of the ship under  this Act, he shall, on conviction by a</p>
            <p>Presidency Magistrate or Magistrate of the first class having  jurisdiction in any port to which the vessel may proceed or in which  she may be found, be punishable with fine which may extend to five  times the amount of the sum payable.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In any proceeding before a Magistrate in a prosecution under  sub- section (1), any such certificate as is mentioned in sub- section</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of section 16, stating that the owner or master has evaded such  payment, shall be sufficient proof of the evasion, unless the owner or  master shows to the satisfaction of the Magistrate that the departure  of the vessel without payment of the sum was caused by stress of  weather, or that there was lawful or reasonable grounds for such  departure.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Exemption from payment of light- dues. The following ships  shall be exempted from the payment of light- dues under this Act,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-18.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>namely:--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any ship belonging to Government  or to a foreign</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-18.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Prince or State and not carrying cargo or passengers  for freight or fares; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any ship of a tonnage of less than fifty tons,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>and the Central Government may, by notification in the Official</p>
            <p>Gazette, exempt any other ships, or classes of ships or ships  performing specified voyages from such payment, either wholly or to  such extent only as may be specified in the notification.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Refund of excess payments. Where light- dues have been paid in  respect of any ship in excess of the amount payable under this Act, no  claim to refund of such excess payment shall be admissible, unless it  is made within six months from the date of each payment.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19A">
        <num>19A.</num>
        <heading>Fees. Fees may be charged for providing assistance to  ships for calibrating their Wireless Direction Finders and for  rendering other services to vessels, at such rates as the Central</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-19A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Government may specify in the rules made under this Act.]</p>
            <p>ACCOUNTS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Accounts, etc.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-20.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government shall cause to be  maintained a separate account of all amounts received by way of light-</p>
            <p>dues, expenses, costs and fines under this Act and of all expenditure  incurred for the purposes of this Act, and shall cause such account to  be laid before the Central Advisory Committee as soon as possible  after the close of each financial year.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government shall cause to be laid before the</p>
            <p>Central Advisory Committee before the close of each financial year a</p>
            <p>statement of the estimated receipts under, and expenditure for the  purposes of, this Act during the forthcoming year.</p>
            <p>RULES</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-21.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government  may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules] consistent with this</p>
            <p>Act to carry into effect the purposes thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-21.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-21.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-21.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the powers and duties of the Director- General of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Lighthouses and Lightships and Directors and Deputy</p>
            <blockList id="section-21.2.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Directors- General of Lighhouses and Lightships;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-21.2.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the procedure and conduct of business of Advisory</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-21.2.list6">
              <listIntroduction>Committees constituted under this Act;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-21.2.list6.bb">
                <num>(bb)</num>
                <p>the manner in which the light may be removed and the  height of the building, structure or tree may be  reduced under sub- section (5) of section 8A;]</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-21.2.list6.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the rate of travelling and subsistence allowance payable  to members of Advisory Committees; .</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-21.2.list6.cc">
                <num>(cc)</num>
                <p>the rates of fees for providing assistance to ships  for calibrating their Wireless Direction Finders and  for rendering other services to vessels;]</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-21.2.list6.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the period in respect of which and the form in which the  separate account referred to in sub- section (1) of  section 20 shall be kept and the forms in which that  account and the statement referred to in sub- section</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-21.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of that section shall respectively be presented to  the Central Advisory Committee.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-21.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made by the Central Government under this  section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each</p>
            <p>House of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of  thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more  successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session  immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule,</p>
            <p>or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall  thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</p>
            <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that rule.]</p>
            <p>REPEALS</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Repeals. Rep. by the Repealing Act, 1938 (1 of 1938), s. 2  and Sch.</heading>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
