<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1994/56/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1994/56"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Neyveli Lignite Corporation Limited (Acquisition And Transfer Of Power Transmission System) Act, 1994"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1994/56/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1994/56/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1994/56/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1994/56/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Neyveli Lignite Corporation Limited (Acquisition And Transfer Of Power Transmission System) Act, 1994</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>(AS PASSED BY THE HOUSES OF PARLIAMENT)</p>
      </longTitle>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 56 OF 1994</docNumber>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-14th">
        <num>14th.</num>
        <heading>September, 1994.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14th.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>An Act to provide in the public interest for the acquisition and  transfer of the power transmission system of the Neyveli Lignite</p>
            <p>Corporation Limited and the right, title and interest of the company  in the power transmission system to the Power Grid Corporation of</p>
            <p>India Limited, with a view to developing the National Power Grid to  ensure transmission of power, within and across the different regions  of India, on a more scientific, efficient and economic basis and for  matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.</p>
            <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- fifth Year of the</p>
            <p>Republic of India as follows:--</p>
            <p>CHAP</p>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be  called the Neyveli Lignite Corporation Limited (Acquisition and</p>
              <p>Transfer of Power Transmission System) Act, 1994.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu  and Kashmir.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of sections 8 to 11 and sections 13 to 16  shall come into force at once and the remaining provisions of this Act  shall be deemed to have come into force on the 1st day of April, 1992  and any reference to the commencement of this Act in any provision of  this Act shall be construed as a reference to the commencement of that  provision.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" appointed day" means the 1st day of April, 1992;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" associated personnel" means the employees of the  company associated with its power transmission system;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" company" means the Neyveli Lignite Corporation Limited,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>a company incorporated and registered under the Companies Act,</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1956">
          <num>1956.</num>
          <heading>(1 of 1956) having its registered office at Neyveli- 607801,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-1956.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>South Arcot District, Tamil Nadu;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" Corporation" means the Power Grid Corporation of India</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Limited, being a company within the meaning of the Companies Act,</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1956">
          <num>1956.</num>
          <heading>(1 of 1956) and having its registered office at Hemkunt</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-1956.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Chambers, 89, Nehru Place, New Delhi- 110019;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>" notification" means a notification published in the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Official Gazette;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list3.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>" power transmission system", in relation to the company,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>means the main transmission lines including extra high voltage  alternative current (EHVAC) lines and high voltage direct current</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list5.HVDC">
                  <num>(HVDC)</num>
                  <p>lines and sub- stations owned by the company;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list5.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list7">
                <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list7.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>words and expressions used herein and not defined but  defined in the Electricity (Supply) Act, 1948 (54 of 1948) or,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>as the case may be, the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) shall  have the meanings, respectively, assigned to them in those Acts.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>ACQUISITION AND TRANSFER OF POWER TRANSMISSION SYSTEM</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>ACQUISITION AND TRANSFER OF POWER TRANSMISSION SYSTEM</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Acquisition of rights of company in relation to the power  transmission system.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On the appointed day, the power transmission  system and the right, title and interest of the company in relation to  its power transmission system shall, by virtue of this Act, be deemed  to have been transferred to, and vested in, the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The power transmission system vested in the Central</p>
              <p>Government by virtue of sub- section (1) shall, immediately after it  had so vested, be deemed to have been transferred to, and vested in,</p>
              <p>the Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>General effect of vesting.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The power transmission system  shall be deemed to include all assets, rights, leaseholds, powers,</p>
              <p>authorities and privileges and all property, movable and immovable,</p>
              <p>relating to such system including lands, buildings, workshops,</p>
              <p>projects (whether complete or at any stage of completion or planning),</p>
              <p>stores, spares, instruments, machinery and</p>
              <blockList id="section-4.1.list6">
                <listIntroduction>equipment, construction equipment, unutilised long- term and short- term  loans and all other rights and interests in, or arising out of, such  property as were, immediately before the appointed day, in the  ownership, possession, power or control of the company and all books  of account, registers and all other documents of whatever nature  relating thereto but shall be deemed not to include--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.1.list6.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>book debts due to the company, immediately before the  appointed day;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.1.list6.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>cash balances and bank balances as on the appointed day;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.1.list6.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>income and expenditure on revenue account relating to  any period before the appointed day.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Explanation.-- For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared  that rights in relation to the power transmission system of the  company which have been transferred to, and vested in, the Corporation  under sub- section (2) of section 3 and this sub- section shall include  the right to collect transmission charges for transmission of power  and any monies collected on or after the appointed day by the company  as transmission charges (whether shown separately or not) shall be  payable by the company to the Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Unless otherwise expressly provided by this Act, all deeds,</p>
              <p>bonds, guarantees (other than guarantees given by the Government of</p>
              <p>India), agreements, powers of attorney, grants of legal representation  and other instruments of whatever nature in relation to the power  transmission system of the company, subsisting or having effect  immediately before the appointed day, and to which the company is a  party or which are in favour of the said company shall be of as full  force and effect against or in favour of the Corporation and may be  enforced or acted upon as fully and effectually as if in the place of  the company, the Corporation had been a party thereto or as if they  had been issued in favour of the Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If, on the date of commencement of this Act, any suit, appeal  or other proceeding of whatever nature, in relation to any property or  assets which have been transferred to, and vested in, the Corporation  under sub- section (2) of section 3, instituted or preferred by or  against the company was pending, the same shall not abate, be  discontinued or be, in any way, prejudicially affected by reason of  the transfer of the power transmission system of the company or of  anything contained in this Act, but the suit, appeal or other  proceeding may be continued, prosecuted or enforced, subject to the  provisions of sub- section (1) of section 5, by or against the</p>
              <p>Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Corporation to be liable for certain prior liabilities.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (2), every liability of the  company in relation to its power transmission system, in respect of  any period prior to the appointed day, which has been transferred to,</p>
              <p>and vested in, the Corporation under sub- section (2) of section 3,</p>
              <p>shall be the liability of the Corporation and shall be enforceable  against the Corporation and not against the company:</p>
              <blockList id="section-5.1.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall apply  to--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.1.list4.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the income and expenditure on revenue account relating  to any period before the appointed day and received or, as the  case</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-5.1.list6">
                <listIntroduction>may be, incurred by the company on or after the appointed day;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.1.list6.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>arrears of depreciation, regarding contingent  liabilities on capital account relating to any period before the  appointed day, arising on account of the decision of any court,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>tribunal or other authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where any repayment of a loan or interest, or both, has been  made, on or after the appointed day, by the company to any lending  agency, such repayment shall be deemed to have been made by the</p>
              <p>Corporation and the amount of such repayment shall be reimbursed by  the Corporation to the company on adjustment of transmission charges  or any other amount due to the Corporation from the company.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Corporation to be lessee or tenant.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where any property is  held by the company in relation to its power transmission system under  any lease or right of tenancy, the Corporation shall, on and from the  appointed day, be deemed to have become the lessee or tenant, as the  case may be, in respect of such property as if the lease or tenancy in  relation to such property had been granted to the Corporation and  thereupon all the rights under such lease or tenancy shall be deemed  to have been transferred to, and vested in, the Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On the expiry of the term of any lease or tenancy referred to  in sub- section (1), such lease or tenancy shall, if so desired by the</p>
              <p>Corporation, be renewed on the same terms and conditions on which the  lease or tenancy was held by the company immediately before the  appointed day.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Removal of doubts.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby  declared that the provisions of sections 3, 4, 5 and 6 shall apply to  the extent to which any property appertains to the business relating  to the power transmission system carried on by the company and to the  rights and powers acquired, and to debts, liabilities and obligations  incurred, and to contracts, agreements and other instruments made by  the company and to legal proceedings relating to those matters pending  in any court, tribunal or other authority in India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any question arises as to whether any property  appertained, on the appointed day, to any business of the company in  relation to its power transmission sytem, or whether any rights,</p>
              <p>powers, debts, liabilities or obligations were acquired or incurred or  any contract, agreement or other instrument was made by the company  for the purposes of its said business, or whether any document relates  to those purposes, the question shall be referred to the Central</p>
              <p>Government which shall, after giving a reasonable opportunity of being  heard to the persons interested in the matter, decide it in such  manner as it may think fit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Payment of amount.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the transfer to, and vesting in,</p>
              <p>the Central Government under sections 3 and 4 of the power  transmission system and the right, title and interest of the company  in relation to its power transmission system there shall be paid, in  the prescribed manner, by the Central Government to the company such  amount as is equal to the book value of all the assets and properties  after deduction of liabilities (other than contingent liabilities)</p>
              <p>given in the audited statement of accounts of the company as on the</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-31st">
          <num>31st.</num>
          <heading>day of March. 1992.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-31st.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the transfer to, and vesting in, the Corporation under  sub- section (2) of section 3 of the power transmission system and the  right, title and interest of the company in relation to its power  transmission system, there shall be paid, in the prescribed manner, by  the Corporation to the Central Government, the amount which is paid by  that Government to the company under sub- section (1).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31st.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In case of any dispute relating to the nature of any asset,</p>
              <p>property or liability or the amount payable under sub- section (1), the  dispute shall be referred by the Central Government to such authority  as it may appoint and the decision of that authority in the matter  shall be final.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>DELIVERY OF ASSETS, ETC., TO THE CORPORATION</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>DELIVERY OF ASSETS, ETC., TO THE CORPORATION</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Duty of persons to account for assets, etc., in their  possession.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person who has, on the date of commencement of  this Act, in his possession or under his control, any assets, books  and any other documents relating to the power transmission system  which has been transferred to, and vested in, the Corporation under  sub- section (2) of section 3, shall be liable to account for the said  assets, books and documents to the Corporation and shall deliver them  up to the Corporation or to such person or persons as the Corporation  may specify in this behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Corporation may take or cause to be taken all necessary  steps for securing possession of the power transmission system which  has been transferred to, and vested in, the Corporation under this</p>
              <p>Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The company shall, within such period as the Corporation may  allow in this behalf, furnish to the Corporation a complete inventory  of all its property and assets as on the appointed day pertained to  its power transmission system which has been transferred to, and  vested in, the Corporation under sub- section (2) of section 3.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>PROVISIONS RELATING TO ASSOCIATED PERSONNEL</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PROVISIONS RELATING TO ASSOCIATED PERSONNEL</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Continuance of associated personnel.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On the vesting of  the power transmission system of the company in the Corporation, the  associated personnel who have been, immediately on or before the 1st  day of December, 1992, employed in the company and have not already  become employees of the Corporation shall become, on and from the date  of commencement of this Act, employees of the Corporation and shall  hold office or service under the Corporation on the terms and  conditions which are not in any way less favourable than those which  would have been admissible to them if there had been no such vesting  and shall continue to do so unless and until their employment under  the Corporation is duly terminated or until their remuneration and  other conditions of service are duly altered by the Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial Disputes</p>
              <p>Act, 1947 (14 of 1947) or any other law for the time being in force,</p>
              <p>the transfer of the services of the associated personnel to the</p>
              <p>Corporation, shall not entitle such personnel to any compensation  under this Act or any other law for the time being in force and no  such claim shall be entertained by any court, tribunal or other  authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Provident fund and other funds.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where the company has  established a provident fund or any other fund for the benefit of the  persons employed by it, the monies relatable to the associated  personnel who have already become employees of the Corporation or  whose services have become transferred under this Act to the</p>
              <p>Corporation shall, out of the monies standing, on the date of transfer  of the associated personnel, to the credit of such provident fund or  other fund, stand transferred to, and vest in, the Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The monies which stand transferred under sub- section (1) to  the Corporation shall be dealt with by the Corporation in such manner  as may be prescribed.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-V.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Act to have overriding effect. The provisions of this Act  shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith  contained in any other law for the time being in force or in any  instrument having effect by virtue of any law, other than this Act, or  in any decree or order of any court, tribunal or other authority.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Penalties. Any person who,--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>having in his possession, custody or control any  property forming part of the power transmission system of the  company wrongfully withholds such property from the Corporation;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>wrongfully obtain possession of, or retains, any  property forming part of the power transmission system of the  company; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>wilfully withholds or fails to furnish to the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Corporation or any person or body of persons specified by the</p>
              <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Corporation, any document or inventory relating to the power  transmission system of the company, which may be in his  possession, custody or control; or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list5.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>fails to deliver to the Corporation or any person or  body of persons specified by that Corporation, any assets, books  of account, registers or other documents in his possession,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>custody or control relating to the pnwer transmission system of  the company,</p>
              <p>shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to  two years and also with fine which may extend to ten thousand rupees.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Offences by companies.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where an offence punishable under  this Act has been committed by a company, every person who, at the  time the offence was committed, was in charge of, and was responsible  to, the company for the conduct of the business of the company, as  well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and  shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:</p>
              <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render  any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the  offence was committed without his knowledge and that he had exercised  all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where  any offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is  proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or  connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any  director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such  director, manager, secretary or other officer shall be deemed to be  guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and  punished accordingly.</p>
              <blockList id="section-14.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-14.2.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm  or other association of individuals; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.2.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner in  the firm.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central</p>
              <p>Government or the Corporation or the company or any officer of that</p>
              <p>Government, Corporation or company or any other person authorised by  that Government, Corporation or company for anything which is in good  faith done or intended to be done under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-16.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, by  notification, make rules for carrying out the provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-16.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-16.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which the amount is to be paid under sub-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-16.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>section (1) or sub- section (2) of section 8;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-16.2.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which the monies in any provident fund or  other fund, referred to in sub- section (2) of section 11, shall  be dealt with;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.2.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>any other matter which is required to be, or may be,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act  shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House  of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty  days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more  successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session  immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or  both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall  thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</p>
              <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that rule.</p>
              <p>A. C. C. UNNI,</p>
              <p>Aditional Secretary to the Govt. of India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
