<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1969/43/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1969/43"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Khuda Bakhsh Oriental Public Library Act, 1969"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1969/43/eng@1969-12-26/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1969/43/eng@1969-12-26"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1969-12-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1969/43/eng@1969-12-26/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1969/43/eng@1969-12-26"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Khuda Bakhsh Oriental Public Library Act, 1969</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 43 OF 1969</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 26th December, 1969.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twentieth Year of the Republic  of India as follows:-</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to declare the Khuda Bakhsh Oriental Public Library at Patna to  be an institution of national importance and to provide for its  administration and certain other connected matters.</p>
        <p>CHAP</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the</p>
              <p>Khuda Bakhsh Oriental Public Library Act, 1969.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on such date  as the Central</p>
              <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Declaration of Khuda Bakhsh Oriental Public Library as an  institution of national importance. It is hereby declared that the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Khuda Bakhsh Oriental Public Library at Patna in the State of Bihar is  an institution of national importance.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" Board" means the Board established under section 4;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" Chairman" means the Chairman of the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" deed of trust" means the deed of trust No. 217  executed in the office of the Deputy Registrar of Patna  by the late Maulvi Khuda Bakhsh Khan Bahadur of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Muradpur on the 14th January, 1891;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" Fund" means the Fund referred to in section 19;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>" library" means the Khuda Bakhsh Oriental Public</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Library declared to be an institution of national  importance under this Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list4.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>" member" means a member of the Board and includes the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Chairman;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list6.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list8">
                <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list8.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>" State Government" means the Government of Bihar.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>THE KHUDA BAKHSH ORIENTAL PUBLIC LIBRARY BOARD</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>THE KHUDA BAKHSH ORIENTAL PUBLIC LIBRARY BOARD</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Establishment and incorporation of Board.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>With effect from  such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the</p>
              <p>Official Gazette, appoint, there shall be established for the purposes  of this Act, a Board to be known as the Khuda Bakhsh Oriental Public</p>
              <p>Library Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall be a body corporate with the name aforesaid,</p>
              <p>having perpetual succession and a common seal with power, subject to  the provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of property  and contract, and may, by that name, sue and be sued.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Composition of Board.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-5.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Board shall consist of the  following persons, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the Governor of Bihar, exofficio, Chairman;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-5.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the Accountant General, Bihar, exofficio;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-5.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>a person to be nominated by the Central Government, who  shall be a member of the family of the late Maulvi</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-5.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Khuda Bakhsh Khan Bahadur of Muradpur;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.1.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>eight persons, four each to be nominated by the Central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-5.1.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Government and the State Government, who shall, as far  as possible, be persons having knowledge of, and  experience in, matters relating to the administration  of libraries;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.1.list5.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the Director, Khuda Bakhsh Oriental Public Library, ex-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>officio Member- Secretary.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every nomination under this section shall take effect as soon  as it is notified by the Central Government in the Official Gazette.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Term of office and fresh nomination in certain cases.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The  terms of office of nominated members shall be such as may be  prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any nominated member may resign his office by giving notice  in writing to the Central Government and to the State Government, and  on such resignation being notified by the Central Government in the</p>
              <p>Official Gazette, shall be deemed to have vacated his office.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A casual vacancy created by the resignation of a nominated  member under sub- section (2) or for any other reason may be filled by  fresh nomination by the Central Government or the State Government, as  the case may be, and a member so nominated shall hold office for the  remaining period for which the member in whose place he is nominated  would have held office.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An outgoing member shall be eligible for renomination.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any nominated member is by infirmity or otherwise rendered  temporarily incapable of carrying out his duties or is absent on leave  or otherwise in circumstances not involving the vacation of his  office, the Central Government or the State Government, as the case  may be, may nominate another person to act in his place during his  absence.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Vacancies, etc., not to invalidate acts. No act of the Board  shall be invalid merely by reason of-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>any vacancy in, or defect in the constitution of, the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Board, or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>any defect in the nomination of a person acting as a  member thereof, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>any irregularity in its procedure not affecting the  merits of the case.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Duty of Government nominating persons, etc.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Before  nominating a person to be a member of the Board, the Central</p>
              <p>Government or the State Government, as the case may be, shall satisfy  itself that the person will have no such financial or other interest  as is likely to affect prejudicially the exercise or performance by  him of his functions as a member, and the Central Government or the</p>
              <p>State Government, as the case may be, shall also satisfy itself from  time to time with respect to every member nominated by it that he has  no such interest; and any person who is or whom the Central Government  or the State Government, as the case may be, proposes to nominate and  who has consented to be, a member shall, whenever requested by the</p>
              <p>Central Government or the</p>
              <p>State Government so to do, furnish to it such information as that</p>
              <p>Government considers necessary for the performance by it of its duties  under this sub- section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A nominated member who is in any way, directly or indirectly,</p>
              <p>interested in a contract made or proposed to be made, by the Board  shall, as soon as possible, after relevant circumstances have come to  his knowledge, disclose the nature of his interest at a meeting of the</p>
              <p>Board and the disclosure shall be recorded in the minutes of the Board  and the member shall not take any part after the disclosure in any  deliberation or decision of the Board with respect to that contract.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Meetings of Board.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall meet at such times and  places and shall, subject to the provisions of sub- sections (2), (3)</p>
              <p>and (4), observe such rules of procedure in regard to the transaction  of business at its meetings (including the quorum at meetings) as may  be provided by regulations made under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chairman or, in his absence, any member chosen by the  members present from among themselves, shall preside at a meeting of  the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any nominated member, being an officer of Government, is  unable to attend any meeting of the Board, he may, with the previous  approval of the Chairman, authorise any person in writing to do so.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All questions at a meeting of the Board shall be decided by a  majority of the votes of the members present and voting and in the  case of an equality of votes, the Chairman or, in his absence, the  member presiding, shall have a second or casting vote.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Temporary association of persons with Board for particular  purposes.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board may associate with itself in such manner and  for such purposes as may be provided by regulations made under this</p>
              <p>Act, any person whose assistance or advice it may desire in performing  any of its functions under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A person associated with it by the Board under sub- section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>for any purpose shall have the right to take part in the  discussions of the Board relating to that purpose, but shall not, by  virtue of this section, be entitled to vote.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Authentication of orders and other instruments of Board. All  orders and decisions of the Board shall be authenticated by the  signature of the Chairman or any other member authorised by the Board  in this behalf, and all other instruments issued by the Board shall be  authenticated by the signature of an officer of the Board authorised  in like manner in this behalf.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Staff of Board.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-12.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of sub- section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, the Board may, for the purpose of enabling it efficiently to  perform its functions under this Act, appoint such number of officers  and other employees as it may think fit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The recruitment and conditions of service of such officers  and employees shall be such as may be provided by regulations made  under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Transfer of service of existing employees to Board. Subject  to the provisions of this Act, every person employed in the library  immediately before the date of establishment of the Board shall, on  and from such date, become an employee of the Board with such  designation as the Board may determine and shall hold his office or  service therein by the same tenure, at the same remuneration and upon  the same terms and conditions as he would have held the same on such  date if the Board had not been established and shall continue to do so  unless and until his employment in the Board is terminated or until  such tenure, remuneration and terms and conditions are duly altered by  the Board:</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Provided that the tenure, remuneration and terms and conditions  of service of any such person shall not be altered to his disadvantage  without the previous approval of the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Location of library. The library shall be located at Patna.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>PROPERTY, LIABILITIES AND FUNCTIONS OF THE BOARD</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PROPERTY, LIABILITIES AND FUNCTIONS OF THE BOARD</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Property and liabilities of Board.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-15.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-15.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>On the establishment  of the Board--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-15.1.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>all properties, funds and dues which are vested in, or  realisable by, the trustees of the library constituted  by the deed of trust, in their capacity as such, shall  vest in, and be realisable by, the Board; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-15.1.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>all liabilities in relation to the library which are  enforceable against the said trustees, shall be  enforceable only against the Board.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All properties, which may, after the establishment of the</p>
              <p>Board, be given, bequeathed or otherwise transferred to the library or  acquired by the Board, shall vest in the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Duties of Board.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-16.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of the deed of  trust, it shall be the general duty of the Board to manage the library  and to plan, promote, organise and implement programmes for the  development of the library on modern scientific lines (including the   microfilming of rare manuscripts) and to perform such other functions  as the Central Government may, from time to time, assign to the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-16.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing provision, the Board may take such steps as it thinks fit-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-16.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>for providing for instruction and research in matters  relating to libraries and for the advancement of  learning and dissemination of knowledge in such  matters; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>to do all such other things as may be necessary for the  discharge of its functions under this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Powers of Board.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to such conditions and  restrictions as the Central Government may think fit to impose, the</p>
              <p>Board may exercise all such powers as may be necessary or expedient  for the purpose of carrying out its duties under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to such regulations as may be made by the Board in  this behalf, the Board may from time to time purchase or otherwise  acquire such manuscripts, books, articles or things as may, in the  opinion of the Board, be worthy of preservation in the library.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>FINANCE, ACCOUNTS, AUDIT AND REPORTS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>FINANCE, ACCOUNTS, AUDIT AND REPORTS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Grants by Central Government to Board. For the purpose of  enabling the Board to discharge its functions efficiently under this</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Act, the Central Government may, after due appropriation made by</p>
              <p>Parliament by law in this behalf, pay to the Board in each financial  year such sums of money as that Government considers necessary by way  of grant, loan or otherwise.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Fund of Board.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-19.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-19.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Board shall maintain a Fund to which  shall be credited-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-19.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>all moneys paid by the Central Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>such sums of money as the State Government may pay  annually having regard to its resolution No. V L</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4055">
          <num>4055.</num>
          <heading>60 E 120, dated the 26th September, 1962;</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4055.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-4055.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-4055.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>all fees and other charges levied under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4055.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>all moneys received by the Board by way of grant, gift,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>donation, benefaction, bequest, subscription,</p>
              <blockList id="section-4055.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>contribution or transfer;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4055.paragraph-0.list3.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>all other moneys received by the Board in any other  manner or from any other source.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-4055.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board may expend such sums as it thinks fit for  performing its functions under this Act and such sums shall be treated  as expenditure payable out of the Fund.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4055.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A sum of money not exceeding such amount as may be provided  by regulations made under this Act may be kept in current account with  any scheduled bank as defined in section 2 of the Reserve Bank of</p>
              <p>India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934), or any other bank approved by the Central</p>
              <p>Government in this behalf, but any moneys in excess of that sum shall  be deposited in the Reserve Bank of India or with the agents of the</p>
              <p>Reserve Bank of India or invested in such manner as may be approved by  the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Budget.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-20.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall, by such date in each year as may  be specified by the Central Government, submit to it for approval a  budget for the next financial year in the form specified by it,</p>
              <p>showing the estimated receipts and expenditure, and the sums which  would be required from the Central Government during that financial  year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any sum granted by the Central Government remains wholly  or partly unspent in any financial year, the unspent sum may be  carried forward to the next financial year and taken into account in  determining the sum to be provided by the Central Government for that  year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (4), no sum shall be  expended by or on behalf of the Board, unless the expenditure is  covered by provision in the budget approved by the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to such conditions and restrictions as the Central</p>
              <p>Government may think fit to impose, the Board may sanction any  reappropriation from one head of expenditure to another or from a  provision made for one purpose to that for another purpose.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Accounts and audit.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-21.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall maintain proper  accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual statement of  accounts including the balance- sheet in such form as may be specified,</p>
              <p>and in accordance with such general directions as may be issued by the</p>
              <p>Central Government in consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor-</p>
              <p>General of India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-21.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The accounts of the Board shall be audited annually by the</p>
              <p>Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any expenditure incurred  by him in connection with such audit shall be payable by the Board to  the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-21.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any person  appointed by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the</p>
              <p>Board shall have the same rights, privileges and authority in  connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor- General of</p>
              <p>India has in connection with the audit of Government accounts, and, in  particular, shall have the right to demand the production of books,</p>
              <p>accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and to  inspect the office of the Board, and the library.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-21.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The accounts of the Board as certified by the Comptroller and</p>
              <p>Auditor- General of India or any other person appointed by him in this  behalf, together with the audit report thereon, shall be forwarded  annually to the Central Government and that Government shall cause the  same to be laid before each House of Parliament.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Returns and reports.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-22.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall furnish to the</p>
              <p>Central Government at such time and in such form and in such manner as  the Central Government may direct such returns, statements and  particulars as the Central Government may, from time to time, require.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Without prejudice to the provisions of sub- section (1) the</p>
              <p>Board shall, as soon as possible after the commencement of each  financial year, submit to the Central Government within such time as  may be specified by the Central Government a report giving true and  full account of the activities of the Board during the previous  financial year and an account of activities likely to be undertaken  during the current financial year.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-V.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Power of Central Government to issue directions to Board.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-23.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the discharge of its functions under this Act, the Board shall be  bound by such directions on questions of policy as the Central</p>
              <p>Government may give to it from time to time:</p>
              <p>Provided that the Board shall be given an opportunity to express  its views before any direction is given under this sub- section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The decision of the Central Government whether a question is  one of policy or not shall be final.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Delegation of powers and duties. The Board may, by general or  special order in writing, direct that all or any of the powers or  duties which may be exercised or discharged by it shall, in such  circumstances and under such conditions, if any, as may be specified  in the order, be exercised or discharged also by any member, officer  or employee of the Board specified in this behalf in the order.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Officers and employees of Board to be public servants. All  officers and employees of the Board shall, when acting or purporting  to act in pursuance of the provisions of this Act or of any rule or  regulation made thereunder, be deemed to be public servants within the  meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Protection of action taken under the Act. No suit,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Board or  any member, officer or employee of the Board for any thing which is in  good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or of  any rule or regulation made thereunder.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Power of Central Government to make rules.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-27.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central</p>
              <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to  give effect to the provisions of this Act:</p>
              <p>Provided that when the Board has been established, no such rules  shall be made without consulting the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-27.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the term of office of, and the manner of filling casual  vacancies among, the members nominated under clauses</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>and (d) of sub- section (1) of section 5;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the travelling and other allowances payable to a member  other than the Chairman and to a person associated with  the Board under section 10;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the disqualifications for membership of the Board and  the procedure to be followed in removing a member who  is or becomes subject to any disqualification;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the conditions subject to which, and the mode in which,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>contracts may be entered into by or on behalf of the</p>
              <blockList id="section-27.2.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Board;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.2.list4.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>any other matter which has to be or may be prescribed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as  may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is in  session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in  one session  or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before  the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the  successive sessions aforesaid"] both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not  be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified  form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any  such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the  validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Power of Board to make regulations.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-28.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board may, with  the previous approval of the Central Government, by notification in  the Official Gazette, make regulations, not inconsistent with this Act  and the rules made thereunder, for enabling it to discharge its  functions under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-28.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-28.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such regulations may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-28.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the conditions and restrictions subject to which  manuscripts and books in the library may be used;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which, and the purposes for which,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-28.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>persons may be associated with the Board;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-28.2.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the time and place of meetings of the Board, the  procedure to be followed in regard to the transaction  of business at such meetings and the quorum necessary  for the transaction of business at a meeting;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.2.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the maintenance of minutes of meetings of the Board and  the transmission of copies thereof to the Central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-28.2.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Government;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-28.2.list5.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the recruitment and conditions of service of officers  and other employees of the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.2.list5.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the persons by whom and the manner in which, payments,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>deposits and investments may be made on behalf of the</p>
              <blockList id="section-28.2.list8">
                <listIntroduction>Board;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-28.2.list8.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the maximum amount that may be kept in the current  account;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.2.list8.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>the maintenance of registers and accounts;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.2.list8.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the compilation of catalogues and inventories of the  manuscripts, books and other articles and things in the  library;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.2.list8.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>the steps to be taken for the preservation of the  manuscripts, books and other articles and things in the  library;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.2.list8.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>the general management of the library;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.2.list8.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>the fees and other charges to be levied for the use of  manuscripts and books in the library;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-28.2.list8.m">
                  <num>(m)</num>
                  <p>any other matter in respect of which provision is, in  the opinion of the Board, necessary for the performance  of its functions under this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-28.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, after consultation with the</p>
              <p>Board, by notification in the Official Gazette, amend, vary or rescind  any regulation which it has approved; and thereupon the regulation  shall have effect accordingly, but without prejudice to the exercise  of the powers of the Board under sub- sections (1) and (2).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-28.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every regulation made under this section shall be laid,</p>
              <p>as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament,</p>
              <p>while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be  comprised in one session or in two or more successive session, and if,</p>
              <p>before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or  the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the regulation or both Houses agree that the  regulation should not be made, the regulation shall thereafter have  effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may  be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be  without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under  that regulation."]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
