<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1971/48/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1971/48"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Maharashtra Vexatious Litigation (Prevention) Act, 1971"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1971/48/eng@2017-02-08/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1971/48/eng@2017-02-08"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-02-08" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-mah/act/1971/48/eng@2017-02-08/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-mah/act/1971/48/eng@2017-02-08"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-02-03" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Maharashtra Vexatious Litigation (Prevention) Act, 1971</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[13th December 1971]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Act No. 48 of 1971</p>
        <p>An Act to prevent the institution or continuance of vexatious proceedings in Courts.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS, it is expedient to prevent the institution or continuance of vexatious proceedings in Courts ; It is hereby enacted in the Twenty second Year of the Republic of India as follows :</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short Title, extent and commencement-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Maharashtra Vexatious Litigation (Prevention) Act, 1971.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Maharashtra.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date' as the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Leave of Court necessary for vexatious litigant to institute or continue any civil or criminal proceedings-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If, on an application made by the Advocate General, the High Court is satisfied that any person has habitually and without any reasonable ground instituted vexatious proceedings, civil or criminal, in any Court or Courts, whether against the same person or against different persons, the High Court may, after hearing that person or giving him an opportunity of being heard, order that no proceedings, civil or criminal, shall be instituted by him in any Court (and that any legal proceedings instituted by him in any Court before the order shall not be continued by him),-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in Greater Bombay, without the leave of the High Court ; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>elsewhere in the State, without the leave of the District and Sessions Judge.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>At the hearing of any such application, the Advocate General may appear through a pleader. (2) Such leave shall not be given unless the High Court or the Judge, as the case may be, is satisfied that the proceedings are not an abuse of the process of the Court and that there is prima facie ground for the proceedings.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No appeal shall lie against an order refusing leave for the institution or continuance of any proceedings by a person who is the subject of an order for the time being in force under sub-section (1). Nothing in this sub-section shall apply to any appeal which may lie to or any proceeding before the Supreme Court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If it appears to the High Court that the person against whom an application is made under sub-section (1), is unable, on account of poverty, to engage a pleader, the High Court may engage a pleader to appear for him.</p>
            <p>Explanation- For the purpose of this section “pleader” has the same meaning as in clause (15) of Section 2 of the Civil Procedure Code, 1908.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A copy of every order made under sub-section (1) directing any person to obtain leave before instituting or continuing proceedings shall be published in the Official Gazette and may also be published in such other, manner as the High Court thinks fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Proceedings instituted or continued without leave to be dismissed-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any proceedings instituted or continued in any Court by a person against whom an order under sub-section (I) of the last preceeding section has been made without obtaining the leave referred to in that section, shall be dismissed by the Court.</p>
            <p>Provided that, this section shall not apply to any proceedings instituted for the purpose of obtaining such leave.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3A">
        <num>3A.</num>
        <heading>Exclusion of time required for obtaining leave, for computation of limitation period-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where a person, against whom an order under sub-section (1) of section 2 has been made applies for leave for institution of any proceedings, the time required by the High Court or the Judge, as the case may be, for deciding the application, shall be excluded in computing the period of limitation (if any) prescribed under any law for the time being in force for instituting such proceedings.</p>
            <p>Explanation.—In excluding such time, the date on which the application for leave was made to the proper authority and the date on which such authority made its order on the application shall be counted.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3B">
        <num>3B.</num>
        <heading>Power to make Rules-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3B.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The High Court may make rules to carry out of the purposes of this Act make rules.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Saving-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of this Act shall be in addition to and not in derogation of the provisions of any other law for the time being in force for prevention of vexatious proceedings or other abuse of legal process or which require consent, sanction or approval in any form of any other authority for the ,institution or continuance of any proceedings.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
