<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1956/61/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1956/61"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Khadi And Village Industries Commission Act, 1956"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1956/61/eng@1956-09-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1956/61/eng@1956-09-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1956-09-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1956/61/eng@1956-09-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1956/61/eng@1956-09-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Khadi And Village Industries Commission Act, 1956</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 25th September, 1956.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Seventh Year of the Republic  of India as follows:--</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>ACT NO. 61 OF</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the establishment of a Commission for the  development of Khadi and Village Industries and for matters connected  therewith.</p>
        <p>CHAP</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title and extent.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the Khadi  and Village Industries Commission Act, 1956.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu  and Kashmir.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" the Board" means the Board constituted under  section</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>];</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" chairman" means the chairman of the Commission;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" Commission" means the Khadi and Village Industries</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Commission established under section 4;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list3.cc">
                  <num>(cc)</num>
                  <p>" fixed capital investment" includes investment in  plant and machinery and land and building of an  industry;]</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" khadi" means any cloth woven on handlooms in India from  cotton, silk or woollen yarn handspun in India or from  a mixture of any two or all of such yarns;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list3.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>" member" means a member of the Commission  and  includes the chairman ];</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list3.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list5.ff">
                  <num>(ff)</num>
                  <p>" rural area" means the area comprised in any  village, and includes the area comprised in any town,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list7">
                <listIntroduction>the population of which does not exceed ten thousand or  such other figure as the Central Government may specify  from time to time;]</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list7.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>" village industry" means,--</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list7.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>any industry located in a rural area which produces any goods  or renders any service with or without the use of power and in which  the fixed capital investment per head of an artisan or a worker does  not exceed fifteen thousand rupees or such other sum as may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, be specified from time to time  by the Central Government:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that any industry specified in the Schedule and located  in an area other than a rural area and recognised as a village  industry at any time before the commencement of the Khadi and Village</p>
              <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list10">
                <listIntroduction>Industries Commission (Amendment) Act, 1987 shall, notwithstanding  anything contained in this sub- clause, continue to be a village  industry under this Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list10.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>any other non- manufacturing unit established for the sole  purpose of promoting, maintaining, assisting, servicing (including   mother units) or managing any village industry;]</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Power to add to the Schedule. omitted by Act 12 of 1987, s.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>(w. e. f. 24. 7. 1987).</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>THE KHADI AND VILLAGE INDUSTRIES COMMISSION</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>THE KHADI AND VILLAGE INDUSTRIES COMMISSION</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Establishment and constitution of the Commission.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>With  effect from such date as the Central Government may, by notification  in the Official Gazette, fix in this behalf, there shall be  established a Commission to be called the Khadi and village Industries</p>
              <p>Commission which shall be a body corporate having perpetual succession  and a common seal, with power to acquire, hold and dispose of property  and to contract, and may by the said name sue and be sued.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-4.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Commission shall consist of the following members  appointed by the Central Government, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>six non- official members having specialised knowledge  and experience of khadi and village industries and representing  such six geographical zones of the country, as may be prescribed;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>two non- official members having expert knowledge and  experience in one or more of the following disciplines, namely:--</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Economics, Planning, Rural Development, Science and</p>
              <blockList id="section-4.2.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Technology or Technical Education and Training;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.2.list4.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>one Financial Adviser, who shall also be the Chief</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-4.2.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Accounts Officer of the Commission, ex- officio; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.2.list6.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>a Chief Executive Officer, ex- officio:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that the ex- officio members shall not have the right to  vote in any of the matters discussed at a meeting of the Commission.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may appoint one of the members  appointed under clause (a) of sub- section (2) to be the chairman who  shall be a full- time member.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Powers and functions of the Chief Executive Officer.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chief Executive Officer appointed under clause (d) of sub- section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of section 4 shall exercise powers of general superintendence over  the affairs of the Commission and its day- to- day management under the  direction and control of the chairman.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chief Executive Officer shall be responsible for the  furnishing of all returns, reports and statements required to be  furnished to the Central Government under section 24.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall be the duty of the Chief Executive Officer to place  before the Commission for its consideration and decision any matter of  financial import if the Financial Adviser suggests to him in writing  that such matter be placed before the Commission.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5A">
          <num>5A.</num>
          <heading>Powers and functions of the Financial Adviser. The Financial</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-5A.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Adviser appointed under clause (c) of sub- section (2) of section 4  shall be in charge of all financial matters of the Commission  including its budget, accounts and audit and it shall be the duty of  the Financial Adviser to bring to the notice of the Commission through  the Chief Executive Officer any matter of financial import, which, in  his opinion, requires consideration and decision by the Commission.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Disqualifications for membership of the Commission. A person  shall be disqualified for being appointed as, and for being, a member  of the Commission--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>if he is, or is found to be a lunatic or a person of  unsound mind; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>if he has been adjudged insolvent; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>if he has been convicted of an offence involving moral  turpitude; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>if he has any financial interest in any subsisting  contract made with or in any work being done by the Commission,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>except as a shareholder (other than a Director), in a company as  defined in section 3 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956):</p>
              <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that where he is a shareholder, he shall disclose  to the Central Government, the nature and extent of shares held  by him in such a company; or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list3.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>if he has any financial interest in any business  undertaking dealing with or any other village industry specified  or deemed to be specified in the Schedule to the Act</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6A">
          <num>6A.</num>
          <heading>Removal of Chairman, Member, etc., from the Commission. The</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6A.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette,</p>
              <blockList id="section-6A.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>remove from office any member of the Commission who--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6A.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>is or becomes subject to any of the disqualifications  mentioned in section 6; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6A.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>in the opinion of the Central Government has failed or  is unable to carry out his duties; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6A.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>absents himself from three consecutive meetings of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Commission without the leave of the Commission:</p>
              <p>Provided that before issuing any such notification, the</p>
              <p>Central Government shall give an opportunity to the member  concerned to show cause against such removal.]</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Resignation of office by member. Any member may resign his  office by giving notice in writing to the Central Government and, on  such resignation being notified in the Official Gazette by that</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government, shall be deemed to have vacated his office.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Vacancies, etc., not to invalidate acts and proceedings of the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Commission. No act or proceeding of the Commission shall be invalid by  reason only of the existence of any vacancy amongst its members or any  defect in the constitution thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Temporary association of persons with the Commission for  particular purposes.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Commission may associate with itself in  such manner and for such purposes as may be determined by regulations  made under this Act any persons whose assistance or advice it may  desire in complying with any of the provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A person associated with it by the Commission under sub-</p>
              <p>section (1) for any purpose shall have the right to take part in the  discussions of the Commission relevant to that purpose, but shall not  have the right to vote, and shall not be a member for any other  purpose.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official</p>
              <p>Gazette, depute one or more officers of the Government to attend any  meetings of the Commission and to take part in the discussions of the</p>
              <p>Commission, but such officer or officers shall not have the right to  vote.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Constitution of the Board. For the purpose of assisting the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Commission in the discharge of its functions under this Act, the</p>
              <p>Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette,</p>
              <p>constitute a Board to be called the Khadi and Village Industries Board  consisting of a chairman and such number of other members as the</p>
              <p>Central Government may think fit, chosen from among persons who, in  the opinion of the Central Government, are qualified as having had  experience, and shown capacity, in matters relating to the development  of khadi and village industries.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Commission to consult the Board. The Commission shall  ordinarily consult the Board with respect to the discharge of its  functions under this Act.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Meetings of the Commission.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-12.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Commission shall meet at  such times and places and shall, subject to the provisions of sub-</p>
              <p>sections (2) and (3), observe such rules of procedure in regard to  transaction of business at its meetings (including the quorum at   meetings) as may be provided by regulations made by the Commission  under this Act;</p>
              <p>Provided that the Commission shall meet at least once in every  month.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The chairman or, in his absence, any member (other than   an ex- officio member) chosen by the members present from among  themselves, shall preside at a meeting of the Commission.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All questions at a meeting of the Commission shall be decided  by a majority of the votes of the members present and voting and in  the case of an equality of votes, the chairman or, in his absence the  person presiding, shall have a second or casting vote.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Term of office and conditions of service of the chairman  and other members.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-13.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every members of the Commission, other than an  ex- officio member, shall hold office for a term of five years:</p>
              <p>Provided that the chairman shall, notwithstanding the expiration  of his term, continue to hold office until his successor enters upon  his office.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The terms and conditions of service of the chairman, Chief</p>
              <p>Executive Officer, Financial Adviser and other members shall be such  as may be prescribed.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Officers and servants of the Commission.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Subject to such rules as may be made by the Central</p>
              <p>Government in this behalf, the Commission may appoint such other  officers and servants as it considers necessary for the efficient  performance of its functions:</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>FUNCTIONS OF THE COMMISSION</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>FUNCTIONS OF THE COMMISSION</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Functions of the Commission.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-15.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the  provisions of this Act, the functions of the Commission shall  generally be to plan, promote, organise and assist in the  establishment and development of khadi and village industries in the  rural area in coordination with other agencies engaged in rural  development wherever necessary.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-15.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, the Commission may take such other steps as it may  think fit,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-15.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to plan and organise training of persons employed or  desirous of seeking employment in khadi and village industries;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-15.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>to build up reserves of raw materials and implements and  supply them to persons engaged or likely to be engaged in  production of handspun yarn or khadi or village industries at  such rates as the Commission may decide;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-15.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>to encourage and assist in the creation of common  service facilities for the processing of raw materials or semi-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-15.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>finished goods and for otherwise facilitating production and  marketing of khadi or products of village industries;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-15.2.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>to promote the sale and marketing of khadi or products  of village industries or handicrafts and for this purpose forge  links with established marketing agencies wherever necessary and  feasible;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-15.2.list3.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>to encourage and promote research in the technology used  in khadi and village industries, including the use of non-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-15.2.list5">
                <listIntroduction>conventional energy and electric power with a view to increasing  productivity, eliminating drudgery and otherwise enhancing their  competitive capacity and to arrange for dissemination of salient  results obtained from such research;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-15.2.list5.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>to undertake directly or through other agencies studies  of the problems of khadi or village industries;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-15.2.list5.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>to provide financial assistance to institutions or  persons engaged in the development and operation of khadi or  village industries and guide them through supply of designs,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-15.2.list7">
                <listIntroduction>prototypes and other technical information for the purpose of  producing goods and services for which there is effective demand  in the opinion of the Commission;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-15.2.list7.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>to undertake experiments or pilot projects which in the  opinion of the Commission are necessary for the development of  khadi and village industries;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-15.2.list7.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>to establish and maintain separate organisations for the  purpose of carrying out any or all of the above matters;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-15.2.list7.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>to promote and encourage cooperative efforts among the  manufacturers of khadi or persons engaged in village industries;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-15.2.list7.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>to ensure genuineness and to set up standards of quality  and ensure that products of khadi and village industries do  conform to the said standards, including issue of certificates or  letters of recognition to the concerned persons; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-15.2.list7.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>to carry out any other matters incidental to the  above.]</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Power of Central Government to give directions. In the  discharge of its functions under this Act, the Commission shall be  bound by such directions as the Central Government may give to it.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>FINANCE, ACCOUNTS, AUDIT AND REPORTS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>FINANCE, ACCOUNTS, AUDIT AND REPORTS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Payment to the Commission. The Central Government may, after  due appropriation made by Parliament by law in this behalf, pay to the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Commission in each financial year such sums as may be considered  necessary for the performance of the functions of the Commission under  this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17A">
          <num>17A.</num>
          <heading>Commission to receive gifts, grants, etc. The Commission  may, for the purpose of development of khadi  the development of  village industries or the development of khadi and village  industries], receive gifts, grants donations or benefactions from the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-17A.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government or any other person.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Funds of the Commission.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-18.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Commission shall have  three separate funds to be called the khadi fund, the village  industries fund and the general and miscellaneous fund.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.1A">
            <num>(1A)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-18.1A.list1">
                <listIntroduction>There shall be credited,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-18.1A.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to the khadi fund, all sums received by the Commission  for the purpose relating to khadi;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.1A.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>to the village industries fund, all sums received by the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-18.1A.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Commission for the purposes relating to village industries and  products of handicrafts;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-18.1A.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>to the general and miscellaneous fund, all other sums  received by the Commission:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that if the amount available in any of the said funds is  in excess of the requirements of that fund and the amount available in  any other of the said funds is insufficient to meet the requirements  of that fund, the Commission may, with the previous approval of the</p>
              <p>Central Government, transfer from the first mentioned fund the excess  amount or such part thereof as may be necessary to the other fund.</p>
              <p>Explanation.-- For the purpose of computing the amount in any of  the said funds, the amount received under section 17A shall not be  taken into account.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.1B">
            <num>(1B)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-18.1B.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The sums credited under sub- section (1),--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-18.1B.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to the khadi fund, shall be applied for the purposes  relating to khadi;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.1B.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>to the village industries fund, shall be applied for the  purposes relating to village industries and products of  handicrafts;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.1B.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>to the general and miscellaneous fund, shall be applied  for the purposes relating to khadi and village industries and for  meeting the salary, allowances and other remuneration of the  members, officers and other employees of the Commission and other  administrative expenses of the Commission.]</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except as otherwise directed by the Central Government, all  moneys belonging to such funds shall be deposited in the Reserve Bank  of India or with the agents of the Reserve Bank of India or, where  there is neither an office of the Reserve Bank of India nor an agent  of the Reserve Bank of India, in a Government Treasury, or be invested  in such securities as may be approved by the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Power of the Commission to spend. Subject to the provisions  of section 20 the Commission shall have power to spend such sums as it  thinks fit on purposes authorized by this Act:</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Provided that nothing in this section shall be deemed to prevent  the Commission from spending, with the previous approval of the</p>
              <p>Central Government, such moneys, as it thinks fit on any such purpose  outside the territories to which this Act extends.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19A">
          <num>19A.</num>
          <heading>Standing Finance Committees.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-19A.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>There shall be  constituted from among the members of the Commission in the prescribed  manner, a Standing Finance Committee in respect of each of the three  funds  referred to in section 18.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19A.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Standing Finance Committee shall exercise such of the  powers of the Commission under section 19 as are delegated to it by  the Commission.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19B">
          <num>19B.</num>
          <heading>Recovery of monies due to the Commission as arrears of land-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-19B.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>revenue.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-19B.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any sum payable to the Commission under any agreement  express or implied, or otherwise howsoever, may be recovered in the  same manner as an arrear of land- revenue.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19B.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any question arises whether a sum is payable to the</p>
              <p>Commission within the meaning of sub- section (1), it shall be referred  to a Tribunal constituted by the Central Government for the purpose  which shall, after making such inquiry as it may deem fit and after  giving to the person by whom the sum is alleged to be payable an  opportunity of being heard, decide the question; and the decision of  the Tribunal shall be final and shall not be called in question by any  court or other authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19B.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Tribunal shall consist of one person who is not connected  with the Commission or with the person by whom the sum is alleged to  be payable.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19B.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The expenses of the Tribunal shall be borne by the</p>
              <p>Commission.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Budget.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-20.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Commission shall, by such date in each year  as may be prescribed, prepare and submit to the Central Government for  approval  three separate budgets] in the prescribed form for the  next financial year, to be called the khadi budget , the village  industries budget and the general and miscellaneous budget], showing  the estimated receipts and expenditure in respect of khadi , village  industries and products of handicrafts and khadi and village  industries respectively] during that financial year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of sub- sections (3) and (4), no sum  shall be expended by or on behalf of the Commission unless the</p>
              <p>expenditure is covered by a specific provision in the budget approved  by the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Commission may within the respective limits of the  khadi budget, the village industries budget and the general and  miscellaneous budget, sanction any reappropriation from one head of  expenditure to another or from a provision made for one scheme to that  in respect of another, but subject to the proviso to sub- section (1)</p>
              <p>of section 18, in no case shall a reappropriation of fund be made from  one budget to any of the other two budgets:</p>
              <p>Provided that no reappropriation from the head" Loan" to any  other head of expenditure and vice versa in any of the budgets shall  be sanctioned by the Commission, except with the previous approval of  the Central Government.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Commission may, within such limits and subject to such  conditions as may be prescribed, incur expenditure in excess of the  limit provided in the budget approved by the Central Government under  any head of expenditure or in connection with any particular scheme,</p>
              <p>so long as the aggregate amount in the budget  approved by the</p>
              <p>Central Government is not exceeded.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Borrowing of money. Subject to such rules as may be made in  this behalf, the Commission shall have power to borrow on the security  of the khadi fund or the village industries fund or any other asset  for any purposes for which such funds may be applied.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Transfer of liabilities and obligations to the Commission.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>All liabilities incurred by, all contracts entered into with, and all  matters and things engaged to be done by, or for, the Central</p>
              <p>Government in connection with the development of khadi or village  industries at any time after the 14th day of January, 1953, and before  the commencement of this Act, shall, after such commencement, be  deemed to have been incurred by, entered into with, or engaged to be  done by, or for, the Commission.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Accounts and audit.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-23.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Commission shall maintain proper  accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual statement of  accounts, including the profit and loss account and the balance- sheet  in such form as may be prescribed by the Central Government in  consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The accounts of the Commission shall be audited by the</p>
              <p>Comptroller and Auditor- General of India at such intervals as may be  prescribed by him.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any person  appointed by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the</p>
              <p>Commission shall have the same rights and privileges and authority in  connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor- General has  in connection with the audit of Government accounts and, in  particular, shall have the right to demand the production of books,</p>
              <p>accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and to  inspect any of the offices of the Commission.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The accounts of the Commission as certified by the</p>
              <p>Comptroller and Auditor- General of India or any other person appointed  by him in this behalf together with the audit report thereon shall be  forwarded annually to the Central Government and that Government shall  cause the same to be laid before each House of Parliament.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Returns and reports.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-24.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Commission shall furnish to the</p>
              <p>Central Government, at such time and in such form and manner as may be  prescribed or as the Central Government may direct, such returns and  statements and such particulars in regard to any proposed or existing  programme for the promotion and development of khadi and village  industries, as the Central Government may, from time to time, require.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-24.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Without prejudice to the provisions of sub- section (1), the</p>
              <p>Commission shall, as soon as possible after the end of each financial  year, submit to the Central Government a report, in such form and  before such date as may be prescribed, giving a true and full account  of its activities, policy and programme during the previous financial  year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-24.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A copy of the report received under sub- section (2) shall be  laid before each House of Parliament.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-V.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-24A">
          <num>24A.</num>
          <heading>Exemption from liability to pay income- tax.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-24A.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Income- tax Act, 1961 (43 of</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1961">
          <num>1961.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1961.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>), the Commission shall not be liable to pay any income- tax on  its income, profits or gains.]</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Dissolution of the Commission.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-25.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government  may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that the</p>
              <p>Commission shall be dissolved from such date as</p>
              <p>may be specified in the notification and thereupon the Commission  shall be deemed to be dissolved accordingly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-25.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>On and from the said date--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-25.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>all properties and funds which, immediately before the  said date, were in the possession of the Commission for  the purposes of this Act shall vest in the Central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-25.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Government; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-25.2.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>all members shall vacate their office as members of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Commission.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-26.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to give effect to the  provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-26.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-26.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the  fore- going power, such rules may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-26.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the manner of filling casual vacancies among the  members of the Commission and the terms and conditions  of service of the chairman, the Chief Executive</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Officer, the Financial Adviser and other members of the</p>
              <blockList id="section-26.2.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Commission including the salary and allowances to be  paid to them and the travelling and daily allowances to  be drawn by them when they are on tour;]</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-26.2.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the procedure to be followed in removing a member  who is or becomes subject to any disqualification;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.2.list4.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the term of office and other conditions of service of,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-26.2.list6">
                <listIntroduction>the procedure to be followed in the discharge of  functions by, and the manner of filling casual  vacancies among, members of the Board;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-26.2.list6.dd">
                  <num>(dd)</num>
                  <p>the constitution of the Standing Finance Committees  under sub- section (1) of section 19A;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.2.list6.ddd">
                  <num>(ddd)</num>
                  <p>the procedure to be followed by the Tribunal in  deciding questions referred to it under sub- section (2)</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-26.2.list8">
                <listIntroduction>of section 19B;]</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-26.2.list8.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the date by which, and the form in which, the budget  shall be prepared and submitted in each year under sub-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-26.2.list10">
                <listIntroduction>section (1) of section 20;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-26.2.list10.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the procedure to be followed for placing the Commission  in possession of funds;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.2.list10.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the procedure to be followed and the conditions to be  observed in borrowing moneys or in granting loans;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.2.list10.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>the conditions subject to which, and the mode in which,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>contracts may be entered into by or on behalf of the</p>
              <blockList id="section-26.2.list13">
                <listIntroduction>Commission;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-26.2.list13.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the form and manner in which the accounts of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-26.2.list15">
                <listIntroduction>Commission shall be maintained under sub- section (1) of  section 23;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-26.2.list15.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>the form and manner in which the returns, reports or  statements shall be submitted under section 24; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.2.list15.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>any other matter which has to be, or may be, prescribed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Power to make regulations.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-27.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Commission may, with the  previous sanction of the Central Government, by notification in the</p>
              <p>Official Gazette, make regulations, not inconsistent with this Act and  the rules made thereunder, for enabling it to discharge its functions  under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-27.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such regulations may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the terms and conditions of appointment and service and  the scales of pay of officers and servants of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Commission, other than  the Chief Executive Officer]</p>
              <blockList id="section-27.2.list4">
                <listIntroduction>and the Financial Adviser to the Commission, including  payment of travelling and daily allowances in respect  of journeys undertaken by such officers and servants  for the purposes of this Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.2.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-27.2.list4.b.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>the time and place of meetings of the Commission, the  procedure to be followed in regard to transaction of  business at such meetings and the quorum necessary for  the transaction of such business at a meeting;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-27.2.list4.b.list0.bb">
                      <num>(bb)</num>
                      <p>the summoning and holding of meetings, and the  conduct of business of a Standing Finance Committee;]</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list4.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the delegation of powers and duties to  the Chief</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-27.2.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Executive Officer] or any employee of the Commission;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.2.list6.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the maintenance of minutes of meetings of the Commission  and of the Board and the transmission of copies thereof  to the Central Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list6.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the persons by whom, and the manner in which, payments,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-27.2.list8">
                <listIntroduction>deposits and investments may be made on behalf of the  commission;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.2.list8.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the custody of moneys required for the current  expenditure of the Commission and investment of moneys  not so required;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list8.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the maintenance of accounts; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list8.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>the form in which certificates of genuineness of khadi  and products of village industries may be granted by  the Commission  and the fees chargeable in respect  thereof.]</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.2A">
            <num>(2A)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The power to make regulations under this section with  respect to the terms and conditions of service and the scales of pay  and pension to be paid to the employees of the Commission shall  include the power to give retrospective effect from a date not earlier  than the commencement of this Act, to such regulations or any of them  but no retrospective effect shall be given to any such regulation so  as to prejudicially affect the interest of any person to whom such  regulation may be applicable.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official</p>
              <p>Gazette, rescind any regulation which it has sanctioned and thereupon  the regulation shall cease to have effect.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Rules and regulations to be laid before Parliament. Every  rule and every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon  as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it  is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be  comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and  if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session  or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule or regulation or both Houses agree that the  rule or regulation should not be made, the rule or regulation shall  thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that rule or regulation.]</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
