<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1997/2/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1997/2"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Maulana Azad National Urdu University Act, 1996"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1997/2/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1997/2/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1997/2/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1997/2/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Maulana Azad National Urdu University Act, 1996</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 2 OF 1997</docNumber>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-8TH">
        <num>8TH.</num>
        <heading>January, 1997.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8TH.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>An Act to establish and incorporate a University at the national level  mainly to promote and develop Urdu language and to impart vacational  and technical education in Urdu medium through conventional teaching  and distance education system and to provide for matters connected  therewith or incidental thereto.</p>
            <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- seventh Year of the Republic  of India as follows:-</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Maulana Azad National Urdu University Act, 1996.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government  may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.- In this Act, and the Statutes made hereunder, unless  the context otherwise requires,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" Academic Council" means the Academic Council of the University.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" academic staff' means such categories of staff as are designated  as academic staff by the Ordinances:</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" Board of Studies" means the Board of Studies of the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>" Chancellor"," Vice- Chancellor" and" Pro- Vice- Chancellor" means,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>respectively, the Chancellor, Vice- Chancellor and Pro- ViceChancellor  of the University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>" Court" means the Court of the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>" Department" means a Department of Studies; and includes a Centre  of Studies;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>" distance education system" means the system of imparting  education through any means of communication such as broadcasting,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>telecasting, correspondence courses, seminars, contact programmes or  the combination of ay two or more of such means;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>" employ" means any person appointed by the University and includes  teachers and other staff of the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>" Executive Council" means the Executive Council of the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>" Finance Committee" means the Finance Committee of the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>" Hall" means a unit of residence or of corporate life for the  students of the University, or of an Institution, maintained by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>" institution" means an academic institution maintained by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list8">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list8.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>" Recognised Institution" means an institution of higher learning  recognised by the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list8.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>" Regulations" means the Regulations made by any authority of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10">
              <listIntroduction>University under this Act for the time being force:</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>" School" means a school of Studies of the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10.p">
                <num>(p)</num>
                <p>" Statutes" and" Ordinances" means, respectively, the Statutes and</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list12">
              <listIntroduction>Ordinances of the University for the time being in force;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list12.q">
                <num>(q)</num>
                <p>" Teachers of the University" means Professors, Readers, Lectures  and such other persons as may be appointed for imparting instruction  or conducting research in the University or in any Institution  maintained by the University and who are designated as teachers by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list14">
              <listIntroduction>Ordinances;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list14.r">
                <num>(r)</num>
                <p>" University" means the Maulana Azad National Urdu University  established and incorporated as a University under this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Establishment of the University.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be established a</p>
            <p>University by the name of" Maulana Azad National Urdu University".</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The headquarters of the University shall be at Hyderabad.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The first Chancellor and the first Vice- Chancellor and the first  members of the Courts, the Executive Council and the Academic Council  and all persons who may hereafter become such officers or members, so  long as they continue to hold such office or membership and hereby  constituted a body corporate by the name of" Maulana Azad National</p>
            <p>Urdu University".</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The University shall have perpetual succession and a common seal  and shall sue and be sued by the said name.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Objects of University.- The objects of the University shall be to  promote and develop Urdu language; to impart education and training  in vocational and technical subjects through the medium of Urdu; to  provide wider access to people desirous of pursuing programmes of  higher education and training in Urdu medium through teaching on the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Campus as well as a distance and to provide focus on women education.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Power of the University.- The University shall have the following  powers, namely:-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>to provide for instructions and research in such branches of  learning as are relevant for furtherance of the objects of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>University.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>to grant, subject to such conditions as the University may  determine, diplomas or certificates to, and confer degrees or other  academic distinctions on the basis of examinations, evaluation or any  other method of testing, on persons, and to withdraw any such  diplomas, certificates, degrees or other academic distinctions for  goods and sufficient cause;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>to organise and to undertake extra- mural studies, training and  extension services;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>to confer honorary degrees or other distinctions in the manner  prescribed by the Statutes;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>to institute Professorships, Readerships, Lecturerships and other  teaching or academic positions, required by the University and to  appoint persons to such Professorships, Readerships, Lecturerships or  other teaching or academic positions;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.vi">
                <num>(vi)</num>
                <p>to appoint persons working in any other University or  organisation as teacher or the University for a specific period;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.vii">
                <num>(vii)</num>
                <p>to create administrative, ministerial and other posts and to  make appointments thereto;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.viii">
                <num>(viii)</num>
                <p>to co- operate or collaborate or associate with any other</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>University or authority or institution of higher learning in such  manner and for such purposes as the University may determine;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list4.ix">
                <num>(ix)</num>
                <p>to establish, with the prior approval of the Central Government,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list6">
              <listIntroduction>such centres and specialised laboratories, within or outside India, as  are, in the opinion of the University necessary for the furtherance of  its objects;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list6.x">
                <num>(x)</num>
                <p>to institute and award fellowships, scholarships, studentships,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list8">
              <listIntroduction>medals and prizes;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list8.xi">
                <num>(xi)</num>
                <p>to establish and maintain Institutions and Halls;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list8.xii">
                <num>(xii)</num>
                <p>to make provision for research and advisory services and for  that purpose to enter into such arrangements with other institutions,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list10">
              <listIntroduction>industrial or other organisations as the University may deem  necessary;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list10.xiii">
                <num>(xiii)</num>
                <p>to organise and conduct refresher courses, workshops, seminars  and other programmes for teachers, evaluators and other academic  staff;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list10.xiv">
                <num>(xiv)</num>
                <p>to make special arrangements in respect of the residence,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list12">
              <listIntroduction>discipline and teaching of women students as the University may  consider desirable;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list12.xv">
                <num>(xv)</num>
                <p>to appoint, on contract or otherwise, visiting Professors,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list14">
              <listIntroduction>Emeritus Professors, Consultants, Scholars and such other persons who  may contribute to the advancement of the objects of the University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list14.xvi">
                <num>(xvi)</num>
                <p>to confer autonomous status on a Department in accordance with  the Statutes;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list14.xvii">
                <num>(xvii)</num>
                <p>to determine standards of admission to the University which may  include examination, evaluation or any other method of testing;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list14.xviii">
                <num>(xviii)</num>
                <p>to demand and receive payment of fees and other charges;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list14.xix">
                <num>(xix)</num>
                <p>to supervise the residences of the students of the University  and to make arrangements for promoting their health and general  welfare;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list14.xx">
                <num>(xx)</num>
                <p>to lay down conditions of service of all categories of employees  including their code of conduct;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list14.xxi">
                <num>(xxi)</num>
                <p>to regulate and enforce discipline among the students and the  employees and to take such disciplinary measures in this regard as may  be deemed by the University to be necessary;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list14.xxii">
                <num>(xxii)</num>
                <p>to make arrangements for promoting the health and general  welfare of the employees;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list14.xxiii">
                <num>(xxiii)</num>
                <p>to receive benefactions, donations and gifts and to acqhire,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>hold, manage and dispose of any property, movable or immovable,</p>
            <p>including trust and endowment properties for the purposes of the</p>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list18">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list18.xxiv">
                <num>(xxiv)</num>
                <p>to borrow, with the approval of the Central Government, on the  security of the property of the University, money for the purposes of  the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list18.xxv">
                <num>(xxv)</num>
                <p>to organise suitable distance education programmes;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list18.xxvi">
                <num>(xxvi)</num>
                <p>to establish maintain or recognise Study Centres for the  delivery of the distance education system in the manner laid down by  the Ordinances;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list18.xxvii">
                <num>(xxvii)</num>
                <p>to provide for the preparation of instructional materials  including films, cassettes, tapes, video cassettes and other software  in collaboration with various Open Universities and other Institutions  dealing with the distance education system;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list18.xxviii">
                <num>(xxviii)</num>
                <p>to devise and implement suitable schemes for providing a base  for promotion and dissemination of Urdu and to bring about the  essential continuity in education with special reference to the  delivery system in distance education consistent with the objectives  of the University; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list18.xxix">
                <num>(xxix)</num>
                <p>to do all such other acts and things as may be necessary,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>incidental or conducive to the attainment of all or any of its  objects.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Jurisdiction.- The jurisdiction of the University shall extend to  the whole of India.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>University open to all classes, castes and creeds.- The University  shall be open to persons of either sex and of whatever caste, creed,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>race or class, and it shall not be lawful for the University to adopr  or impose on any person any test whatsoever of religious belief or  profession in order to entitle him to be appointed as a teacher of the</p>
            <p>University or to hold any other office therein or to be admitted as a  student in the University or to graduate thereat or to enjoy or  exercise any privilege thereof:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing in this section shall be deemed to prevent the</p>
            <p>University from making special provisions for the employment or  admission of women, physically handicapped or of persons belonging to  the weaker sections of the society and, in particular, of the</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-scheduled">
      <doc name="scheduled">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1997/2/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1997/2"/>
              <FRBRalias value="Castes and the Scheduled Tribes."/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1997/2/eng@1980-01-01/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1997/2/eng@1980-01-01"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1997/2/eng@1980-01-01/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1997/2/eng@1980-01-01"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduled">
            <section id="section-8">
              <num>8.</num>
              <heading>The Visitor.-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-8.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The President of India shall be the Visitor of  the University.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Visitor may, from time to time, appoint one or more persons to  review the work and progress of the University, including Institution  managed by it, and to submit a report thereon; and upon receipt of  that report the Visitor may, after obtaining the views of the</p>
                  <p>Executive Council thereon through the Vice- Chancellor, take such  action and issue such directions as he considers necessary in respect  of any of the matters dealt with in the report and the University  shall be bound to comply with such directions.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Visitor shall have the right to cause an inspection to be made  by such person or persons as he may direct of the University, its  buildings, laboratories and equipment and of any Institution  maintained by the University and also of the examinations, teaching  and other work conducted or done by the University and to cause an  inquiry to be made in like manner in respect of any matter connected  with the administration or finances of the University or Institutions.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Visitor shall, in every matter referred to in sub- section (3),</p>
                  <p>give notice of his intention to cause an inspection or inquiry to be  made to the University and the University shall have the right to make  such representations to the Visitor, as it may consider necessary.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>After considering the representations, if any, made by the</p>
                  <p>University, the Visitor may cause to be made such inspection or  inquiry as is referred to in sub- section (3).</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where any inspection or inquiry has been caused to be made by the</p>
                  <p>Visitor, the University shall be entitled to appoint a representative  who shall have the right to be present and be heard at such inspection  or inquiry.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Visitor may, if the inspection or inquiry is made in respect  of the University or any Institution maintained by it, address the</p>
                  <p>Vice- Chancellor with reference to the result of such inspection or  inquiry together with such views and advice with regard to the action  to be taken thereon, as the Visitor may be pleased to offer, and on  receipt of address made by the Visitor, the Vice- Chancellor shall  communicate to the Executive Council, the views of the Visitor with  such advice as the Visitor may offer upon the action to be taken  thereon.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Executive Council shall communicate, through the</p>
                  <p>Vice- Chancellor, to the Visitor such action, if any, as it proposes to  take or has been taken upon the result of such inspection or inquiry.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where the Executive Council does not, within a reasonable time,</p>
                  <p>take action to the satisfaction of the Visitor, the Visitor may, after  considering any explanation furnished or representation made by the</p>
                  <p>Executive Council, issue such directions as he may think fit and the</p>
                  <p>Executive Council shall comply with such directions.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Without prejudice to the foregoing provisions of this section,</p>
                  <p>the Visitor may, by order in writing, annul any proceeding of the</p>
                  <p>University which is not in conformity with this Act, the Statutes or  the Ordinances:</p>
                  <p>Provided that before making any such order, he shall call upon the</p>
                  <p>Registrar to show cause why such an order should not be made, and, if  any cause is shown within a reasonable time, he shall consider the  same.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-8.11">
                <num>(11)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Visitor shall have such other powers as may be prescribed by  the Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-9">
              <num>9.</num>
              <heading>Officers of the University.- The Following shall be the officers of  the University:-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-9.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Chancellor;</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Vice- Chancellor;</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Pro- Vice- Chancellor;</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Deans of Schools;</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Registrar;</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9.6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Finance Officer;</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9.7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Librarian; and</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9.8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>such other officers as may be declared by the Statutes to be  officers of the University.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-10">
              <num>10.</num>
              <heading>The Chancellor.-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-10.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Chancellor shall be appointed by the</p>
                  <p>Visitor in such manner as may be prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-10.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Chancellor shall, by virtue of his office, be the Head of the</p>
                  <p>University.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-10.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Chancellor shall, if present, preside at the convocation of  the University held for conferring degrees.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-11">
              <num>11.</num>
              <heading>The Vice- Chancellor.-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-11.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Vice- Chancellor shall be appointed  by the Visitor in such manner and on such terms and conditions of  service as may be prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-11.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Vice- Chancellor shall be the principal executive and academic  officer of the University and shall exercise general supervision and  control over the affairs of the University and give effect to the  decisions of all the authorities of the University.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-11.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Vice- Chancellor may, if he is of opinion that immediate action  is necessary on any matter, exercise any power conferred on any  authority of the University by or under this Act and shall report to  such authority the action taken by him on such matters:</p>
                  <p>Provided that if the authority concerned is of the opinion that such  action ought not to have been taken, it may refer the matter to the</p>
                  <p>Visitor whose decision thereon shall be final:</p>
                  <p>Provided further that any person in the service of the University who  is aggrieved by the action taken by the Vice- Chancellor under this  sub- section shall have the right to appeal against such action to the</p>
                  <p>Executive Councilo within three months from the date on which decision  on such action is communicated to him and thereupon the Executive</p>
                  <p>Council may confirm, modify or reverse the action taken by the</p>
                  <p>Vice- Chancellor.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-11.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Vice- Chancellor, if he is of the opinion that any decision of  any authority of the University is beyond the powers of the authority  conferred by the provisions of this Act, the Statutes or the</p>
                  <p>Ordinances or that any decision taken is not in the interest of the</p>
                  <p>University, may ask the authority concerned to review its decision  within sixty days of such decision and if the authority refuses to  review the decision either in whole or in part or no decision is taken  by it within the said period of sixty days, the matter shall be  referred to the Visitor whose decision thereon shall be final.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-11.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Vice- Chancellor shall exercise such other powers and perform  such other duties as may be prescribed by the Statutes or the</p>
                  <p>Ordinances.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-12">
              <num>12.</num>
              <heading>The Pro- Vice- Chancellor.- The Pro- Vice- Chancellor shall be  appointed in such manner and shall exercise such powers and perform  such duties as may be prescribed by the Statutes.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-13">
              <num>13.</num>
              <heading>The Deans of Schools.- Every Dean of a School shall be appointed  in such manner and shall exercise such powers and perform such duties  as may be prescribed by the Statutes.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-14">
              <num>14.</num>
              <heading>The Registrar.-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-14.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Registrar shall be appointed in such  manner as may be prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-14.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Registrar shall be appointed in such manner as may be  prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-15">
              <num>15.</num>
              <heading>The Finance Officer.- The Finance Officer shall be appointed in  such manner and shall exercise such powers and perform such duties as  may be prescribed by the Statutes.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-16">
              <num>16.</num>
              <heading>The Librarian.- The Librarian shall be appointed in such manner  and shall exercise such powers and perform such duties as may be  prescribed by the Statutes.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-17">
              <num>17.</num>
              <heading>Other officers.- The manner of appointment and powers and duties  of the other officers of the University shall be prescribed by the</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-18">
              <num>18.</num>
              <heading>Authorities of the University.- The following shall be the  authorities of the University:-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-18.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Court;</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-18.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Executive Council;</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-18.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Academic Council;</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-18.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Board of Studies;</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-18.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Finance Committee; and</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-18.6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>such other authorities as may be declared by the Statutes to be  the authorities of the University.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-19">
              <num>19.</num>
              <heading>The Court.-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-19.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The constitution of the Court and the term of  office of its members shall be prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-19.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-19.2.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Court shall have the  following powers and functions, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-19.2.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>to review, from time to time, the broad policies and programmes of  the University and to suggest measures for the improvement and  development of the University;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-19.2.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>to advise the Visitor in respect of any matter which may be  referred to it for advice; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-19.2.list1.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>to perform such other functions as may be prescribed by the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-20">
              <num>20.</num>
              <heading>The Executive Council.-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-20.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Executive Council shall be the  principal executive body of the University.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-20.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The constitution of the Executive Council, the term of office of  its members and its powers and functions shall be prescribed by the</p>
                  <p>Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-21">
              <num>21.</num>
              <heading>The Academic Council.-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-21.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Academic Council shall be the  principal academic body of the University and shall, subject to the  provisions of this Act, the Statutes and the Ordinances, co- ordinate  and exercise general supervision over the academic policies of the</p>
                  <p>University.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-22">
              <num>22.</num>
              <heading>The Board of Studies.- The constitution, powers and functions of  the Board of Studies shall be prescribed by the Statutes.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-23">
              <num>23.</num>
              <heading>The Finance Committee.- The constitution, powers and functions of  the Finance Committee shall be prescribed by the Statutes.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-24">
              <num>24.</num>
              <heading>Other authorities of the University.- The constitution, powers and  functions of other authorities, as may be declared by the Statutes to  be the authorities of the University, shall be prescribed by the</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-25">
              <num>25.</num>
              <heading>Power to make Statutes.- Subject to the provisions of this Act,</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>the Statutes may provide for all or any of the following matters,</p>
                  <blockList id="section-25.paragraph-0.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>namely:-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the constitution, powers and functions of the authorities, and  other bodies of the University, as may be constituted from time to  time;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>appointment and continuance in office of the members of the said  authorities and bodies, filling up of vacancies of members and all  other matters relating to those authorities and other bodies for which  it may be necessary or desirable to provide;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>the appointment, powers and duties of the officers of the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-25.paragraph-0.list4">
                    <listIntroduction>University and their emoluments;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list4.d">
                      <num>(d)</num>
                      <p>the appointment of teachers and other academic staff and other  employees of the University, their emoluments and other conditions of  service;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list4.e">
                      <num>(e)</num>
                      <p>the appointment of teachers, academic staff working in any other</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-25.paragraph-0.list6">
                    <listIntroduction>University or organisation for specific period for undertaking a joint  project;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list6.f">
                      <num>(f)</num>
                      <p>the conditions of service of employees including provision for  pension, insurance and provident fund, the manner of termination of  service and disciplinary action;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list6.g">
                      <num>(g)</num>
                      <p>the principles governing the seniority of service of the employees  of the University;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list6.h">
                      <num>(h)</num>
                      <p>the procedure for arbitration in cases of dispute between  employees or students and the University;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list6.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>the procedure for appeal to the Executive Council by any employee  or student against the action of any officer or authority of the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-25.paragraph-0.list8">
                    <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list8.j">
                      <num>(j)</num>
                      <p>the conferment of autonomous status on an Institution or a</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-25.paragraph-0.list10">
                    <listIntroduction>Department;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list10.k">
                      <num>(k)</num>
                      <p>the establishment and abolition of Schools, Departments, Centres,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-25.paragraph-0.list12">
                    <listIntroduction>Halls and Institutions;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list12.l">
                      <num>(l)</num>
                      <p>the conferment of honorary degrees;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list12.m">
                      <num>(m)</num>
                      <p>the withdrawal of degrees, diplomas, certificates and other  academic distinctions;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list12.n">
                      <num>(n)</num>
                      <p>the institution of fellowships, scholarships, studentships, medals  and prizes;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list12.o">
                      <num>(o)</num>
                      <p>the delegation of powers vested in the authorities or officers of  the University;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list12.p">
                      <num>(p)</num>
                      <p>the maintenance of discipline among the employees and students;</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-25.paragraph-0.list14">
                    <listIntroduction>and</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-25.paragraph-0.list14.q">
                      <num>(q)</num>
                      <p>all other matters which by this Act are to be or may be provided  for by the Statutes.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-26">
              <num>26.</num>
              <heading>Statutes how to be made.-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-26.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The first Statutes are those set out  in the Schedule.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-26.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Executive Council may, from time to time, make new or  additional Statutes or may amend or repeal the Statutes referred to in  sub- section (1):</p>
                  <p>Provided that the Executive Council shall not make, amend or repeal  any Statutes affecting the status, powers or constitution of any  authority of the University until such authority has been given an  opportunity of expressing an opinion in writing on the proposed  changes and any opinion so expressed shall be considered by the</p>
                  <p>Executive Council:</p>
                  <p>Provided further that the Executive Council shall not consider to  make, amend or repeal any statute relating to the matters provided  under clauses (j) and (k) of section 25 except with the prior approval  of the Visitor.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-26.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every new Statute or addition to the Statutes or any amendment or  repeal of a Statute shall require the assent of the Visitor who may  assent thereto or withhold assent or remit to the Executive Council  for re- consideration in the light of observations, if any, made by  him.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-26.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A new Statute or a Statute amending or repealing an existing</p>
                  <p>Statute shall have no validity unless it has been assented to by the</p>
                  <p>Visitor.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-26.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing sub- sections,</p>
                  <p>the Visitor may make new or additional Statutes or amend or repeal the</p>
                  <p>Statutes referred to in sub- section (1) during the period of three  years immediately after the commencement of this Act:</p>
                  <p>Provided that the Visitor may, on the expiry of the said period of  three years, make, within one year from the date of such expiry, such  detailed Statutes as he may consider necessary and such detailed</p>
                  <p>Statutes shall be laid before both Houses of Parliament.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-26.6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing sub- sections,</p>
                  <p>the Visitor may direct the University to make provisions in the</p>
                  <p>Statutes in respect of any matter specified by him and if the</p>
                  <p>Executive Council is unable to implement such direction within sixty  days of its receipt, the Visitor may, after considering the reaons, if  any, communicated by the Executive Council for its inability to comply  with such direction, make or amend the Statutes suitably.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-27">
              <num>27.</num>
              <heading>Powers to make Ordinance.-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-27.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Subject to the provisions of this</p>
                  <blockList id="section-27.1.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>Act and the Statutes, the Ordinances may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-27.1.list2.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the admission of students to the University and their enrolment as  such;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-27.1.list2.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>the courses of study to be laid down for all degrees, diplomas and  certificates of the University;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-27.1.list2.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>the medium of instruction and examination;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-27.1.list2.d">
                      <num>(d)</num>
                      <p>the award of degrees, diplomas, certificates and other academic  distinctions, qualifications for the same and the means to be taken  relating to the granting and obtaining of the same;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-27.1.list2.e">
                      <num>(e)</num>
                      <p>the fees to be charged for courses of study in the University and  for admission to the examinations, degrees and diplomas of the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-27.1.list4">
                    <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-27.1.list4.f">
                      <num>(f)</num>
                      <p>the conditions for awards of fellowships, scholarships,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-27.1.list6">
                    <listIntroduction>studentships, medals and prizes;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-27.1.list6.g">
                      <num>(g)</num>
                      <p>the conduct of examinations, including the term of office and  manner of appointment and the duties of examining bodies, examiners  and moderators;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-27.1.list6.h">
                      <num>(h)</num>
                      <p>the conditions of residence of the students of the University;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-27.1.list6.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>the special arrangements, if any, which may be made for the  residence, discipline and teaching of women students and prescribing  of special courses of studies for them;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-27.1.list6.j">
                      <num>(j)</num>
                      <p>the appointments and emoluments of employees other than those for  whom provision has been made in the Statutes;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-27.1.list6.k">
                      <num>(k)</num>
                      <p>the establishment of Centres of Studies, Boards of Studies,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-27.1.list8">
                    <listIntroduction>Special Centres, Specialised Laboratories and other Committees;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-27.1.list8.l">
                      <num>(l)</num>
                      <p>the manner of co- operation and collaboration with other</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-27.1.list10">
                    <listIntroduction>Universities, Institutions and other agencies including learned bodies  or associations in India or abroad;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-27.1.list10.m">
                      <num>(m)</num>
                      <p>the creation, composition and functions of any other body which is  considered necessary for improving the academic life of the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-27.1.list12">
                    <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-27.1.list12.n">
                      <num>(n)</num>
                      <p>such other terms and conditions of service of teachers and other  academic staff as are not prescribed by the Statutes;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-27.1.list12.o">
                      <num>(o)</num>
                      <p>the management of Institutions established by the University;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-27.1.list12.p">
                      <num>(p)</num>
                      <p>setting up of a machinery for redressal of grievances of  employees; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-27.1.list12.q">
                      <num>(q)</num>
                      <p>all other matters which by this Act or the Statutes may be  provided for by the Ordinances.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-27.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The first Ordinances shall be made by the Vice- Chancellor with the  previous approval of the Central Government and the Ordinances so made  may be amended, repealed or added to at any time by the Executive</p>
                  <p>Council in the manner prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-28">
              <num>28.</num>
              <heading>Regulations.- The authorities of the University may make</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Regulations, consistent with this Act, the Statutes and the Ordinances  for the conduct of their own business and that of the Committees, if  any, appointed by them and not provided for by this Act, the Statutes  or the Ordinances, in the manner prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-29">
              <num>29.</num>
              <heading>Annual report.-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-29.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The annual report of the University shall be  prepared under the direction of the Executive Council which shall  include, among other matters, the steps taken by the University  towards the fulfilment of its objects and shall be submitted to the</p>
                  <p>Visitor on or before such date as may be prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-29.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A copy of the annual report, as prepared under sub- section (1),</p>
                  <p>shall also be submitted to the Central Government, which shall, as  soon as may be, cause the same to be laid before both Houses of</p>
                  <p>Parliament.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-30">
              <num>30.</num>
              <heading>Annual accounts.-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-30.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The annual accounts and balance- sheet of the</p>
                  <p>University shall be prepared under the directions of the Executive</p>
                  <p>Council and shall, once at least every year and at intervals of not  more than fifteen months, be audited by the Comptroller and</p>
                  <p>Auditor- General of India or by such persons as he may authorise in  this behalf.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-30.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A copy of the annual accounts together with the audit report  thereon shall be submitted to the Visitor along with the observations,</p>
                  <p>if any, of the Executive Council.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-30.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Any observations made by the Visitor on the annual accounts shall  be brought to the notice of the Executive Council and the views of the</p>
                  <p>Executive Council, if any, on such observation shall be submitted to  the Visitor.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-30.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A copy of the annual accounts together with the audit report as  submitted to the Visitor shall also be submitted to the Central</p>
                  <p>Government who shall, as soon as may be, cause the same to be laid  before both Houses of Parliament.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-30.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The audited annual accounts after having been laid before both</p>
                  <p>Houses of Parliament shall be published in the Gazette of India.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-31">
              <num>31.</num>
              <heading>Conditions of service of employees.-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-31.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every employee of the</p>
                  <p>University shall be appointed under a written contract which shall be  lodged with the University and a copy of which shall be furnished to  the employee concerned.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-31.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Any dispute arising out of the contract between the University and  any employee shall, at the request of the employee, be referred to a</p>
                  <p>Tribunal of Arbitration consisting of one member appointed by the</p>
                  <p>Executive Council, one member nominated by the employee and an umpire  appointed by the Visitor.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-31.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The decision of the Tribunal shall be final and no suit shall lie  in any civil court in respect of the matters decided by the Tribunal.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-31.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every request made by the employee under sub- section (2) shall be  deemed to be a submission to arbitration upon the terms of this  section within the meaning of the Arbitration Act, 1940.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-31.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The procedure for regulating the work of the Tribunal shall be  prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-32">
              <num>32.</num>
              <heading>Procedure of appeal and arbitration in disciplinary cases against  students.-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-32.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Any student or candidate for an examination whose name  has been removed from the rolls of the University by the orders or  resolution of the Vice- Chancellor, Discipline Committee or Examination</p>
                  <p>Committee, as the case may be, and who has been debarred from  appearing at the examination of the University for more than one year,</p>
                  <p>may, within ten days of the date of receipt of such orders or copy of  such resolution by him, appeal to the Executive Council and the</p>
                  <p>Executive Council may confirm, modify or reverse the decision of the</p>
                  <p>Vice- Chancellor or the Committee, as the case may be.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-32.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Any dispute arising out of any disciplinary action taken by the</p>
                  <p>University against a student shall, at the request of such student, be  referred to a Tribunal of Arbitration and the provisions of  sub- sections (2), (3), (4) and (5) of section 31 shall, as far sa may  be, apply to a reference made under this sub- section.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-33">
              <num>33.</num>
              <heading>Right to appeal.- Every employee or student of the University of</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-33.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Institution maintained by the University shall, notwithstanding  anything contained in this Act, have a right to appeal within such  time as may be prescribed by the Statutes, to the Executive Council  against the decision of any officer or authority of the University or  of Institution, as the case may be, and thereupon, the Executive</p>
                  <p>Council may confirm, modify or reverse the decision appealed against.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-34">
              <num>34.</num>
              <heading>Provident and pension funds.-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-34.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The University shall constitute  for the benefit of its employees such provident or pension funds or  provide such insurance schemes as it may deem fit in such manner and  subject to such conditions as may be prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-34.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where such provident fund or pension fund has been so constituted,</p>
                  <p>the Central Government may declare that the provision of the Provident</p>
                  <p>Funds Act, 1925 (19 of 1925), shall apply to such fund, as if it were  a Government provident fund.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-35">
              <num>35.</num>
              <heading>Disputes as to constitution of University authorities and  bodies.- If any question arises as to whether any person has been duly  elected or appointed as, or is entitled to be, a member of any  authority or other body of the University, the matter shall be  referred to the Visitor whose decision thereon shall be final.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-36">
              <num>36.</num>
              <heading>Constitution of Committees.- Where any authority of the University  is given power by this Act or the Statutes to appoint Committees, such</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-36.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Committees shall, save as otherwise provided, consist of the members  of the authority concerned and of such other person, if any, as the  authority in each case may think fit.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-37">
              <num>37.</num>
              <heading>Filling of casual vacancies.- All casual vacancies among the  members (other than ex officio members) of any authority or other body  of the University shall be filled, as soon as may be, by the person or  body who appoints, elects or co- opts the member whose place has become  vacant and any person appointed, elected or co- opted to a casual  vacancy shall be a member of such authority or body for the residue of  the term for which the person whose place he fills would have been a  member.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-38">
              <num>38.</num>
              <heading>Proceedings of University authorities or bodies not invalidated  by vacancies.- No act or proceedings of any authority or other body of  the University shall be invalid merely by reason of the existence of a  vacancy or vacancies among its members.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-39">
              <num>39.</num>
              <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.- No suit or other legal  proceedings shall lie against any officer or other employee of the</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-39.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>University for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be  done in pursuance of any of the provisions of this Act, the Statutes  or the Ordinances.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-40">
              <num>40.</num>
              <heading>Mode of proof of University records.- A copy of any receipt,</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-40.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>application, notice, order, proceeding, resolution of any authority or</p>
                  <p>Committee of the University, or other documents in possession of the</p>
                  <p>University, or any entry in any register duly maintained by the</p>
                  <p>University, if certified by the Registrar, shall be received as prima  facie evidence of such receipt, application, notice, order,</p>
                  <p>proceeding, resolution or documents or the existence of entry in the  register and shall be admitted as evidence of the matters and  transactions therein where the original thereof would, if produced,</p>
                  <p>have been admissible in evidence, notwithstanding anything contained  in the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872) or in any other law for  the time being in force.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-41">
              <num>41.</num>
              <heading>Power to remove difficulties.-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-41.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>If any difficulty arises in  giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government  may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such  provisionss, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as  appear to it to be necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty:</p>
                  <p>Provided that no such order shall be made under this section after the  expiry of three years from the commencement of this Act.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-41.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every order made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may  be after it is made, before each House of Parliament.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-42">
              <num>42.</num>
              <heading>Transitional provisions.- Notwithstanding anything contained in  this Act and the Statutes,-</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-42.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-42.paragraph-0.list0">
                    <item id="section-42.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the first Chancellor shall be appointed by the Visitor and the  said officer shall hold office for a term of five years;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-42.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>the first Vice- Chancellor shall be appointed by the Visitor and  the said officer shall hold offive for a term of five years;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-42.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>the first Registrar and the First Finance Officer shall be  appointed by the Visitor and each of the said officers shall hold  office for a term of three years;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-42.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                      <num>(d)</num>
                      <p>the first Court and the first Executive Council shall consist of  not more than thirty members and eleven members, respectively, who  shall be nominated by the Visitor and they shall hold office for a  term of three years;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-42.paragraph-0.list0.f">
                      <num>(f)</num>
                      <p>the first Academic Council shall consist of not more than  twenty- one members, who shall be nominated by the Visitor and shall  hold office for a term of three years:</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Provided that if any vacancy occurs in the above offices or  authorities, the same shall be filled by appointment or nomination, as  the case may be, by the Visitor, and the person so appointed or  nominated shall hold office for so long as the officer or member in  whose place he is appointed or nominated would have held that office,</p>
                  <p>if such vacancy had not occurred.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-43">
              <num>43.</num>
              <heading>Statutes, Ordinances and Regulations to be published in the</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-43.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Official Gazette and to be laid before Parliament.-</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <subsection id="section-43.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every Statute,</p>
                  <p>Ordinance or Regulation made under this Act shall be published in the</p>
                  <p>Official Gazette.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-43.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every Statute, Ordinance or Regulation made under this Act shall  be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of</p>
                  <p>Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days  which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive  sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately  following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both</p>
                  <p>Houses agree in making any modification in the Statute, Ordinance or</p>
                  <p>Regulation or both Houses agree that the Statute, Ordinance or</p>
                  <p>Regulation should not be made, the Statute, Ordinance or Regulation  shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no  effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification  or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that Statute, Ordinance or Regulation.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-43.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The power to make Statutes, Ordinances or Regulations shall  include the power to give retrospective effect from a date not earlier  than the date of commencement of this Act, to the Statutes, Ordinance  or Regulations or any of them but no retrospective effect shall be  given to any Statute, Ordinance or Regulation so as to prejudically  affect the interests of any person to whom such Statute, Ordinance or</p>
                  <p>Regulation may be applicable.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
