<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-har/act/1974/30/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-har/act/1974/30"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Haryana Police (Protection Of Railways) Act, 1974"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-har/act/1974/30/eng@2017-01-22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-har/act/1974/30/eng@2017-01-22"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-22" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-har/act/1974/30/eng@2017-01-22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-har/act/1974/30/eng@2017-01-22"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-22" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Haryana Police (Protection Of Railways) Act, 1974</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[No. 30 of 1974]</p>
        <p>[September 5, 1974]</p>
        <p>An Act to provide enhanced punishments for certain derelictions of duty by members of the police forces.</p>
        <p>Be it enacted by the Legislature of the State of Haryana in the Twenty-fifth Year of the Republic of India as follows:—</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and extent.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Haryana Police (Protection of Railways) Act, 1974.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Haryana.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Enhanced punishments for derelictions of duty by police in certain circumstances.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>It shall be an offence punishable under this Act for any member of a police force whose duty for the time being is to protect from acts of violence any passenger or goods being conveyed upon any railway, as defined in the Indian Railways Act, 1890, to fail in the proper performance of that duty and notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any law or order for the time being in force regulating discipline in the police force of which he is a member but without prejudice to any other punishment to which he may be liable there under, such member of a police force shall be liable, on conviction for such offence by a competent criminal court, to be punished with rigorous imprisonment for a term which may extend to ten years or, if on the occasion of his offence any loss of human life occurs, with death or imprisonment for life or rigorous imprisonment for a period which may extend to ten years.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Repeal.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The East Punjab Police (Protection of Railways) Act, 1947 (East Punjab Act 12 of 1947), in its application to the State of Haryana, is hereby repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
