<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-pun/act/1962/11/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-pun/act/1962/11"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Punjab Good Conduct Prisoners (Temporary Release) Act, 1962"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-pun/act/1962/11/eng@2017-01-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-pun/act/1962/11/eng@2017-01-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-pun/act/1962/11/eng@2017-01-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-pun/act/1962/11/eng@2017-01-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Punjab Good Conduct Prisoners (Temporary Release) Act, 1962</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the temporary release of prisoners for good conduct on certain conditions.</p>
        <p>Be it enacted by the Legislature of the State of Punjab in the Thirteenth Year of the Republic of India as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Punjab Good Conduct Prisoners (Temporary Release) Act, 1962.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Punjab.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“District Magistrate” means the District Magistrate of the District within whose jurisdiction the prisoner after his temporary release under this Act, is likely to reside during the period of his release;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“member of prisoner’s family” means the husband, wife, son, daughter, father, mother, brother and sister of the prisoner;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“prescribed” means prescribed by the rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>“prisoner” means a person confined in prison under a sentence of imprisonment;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>“Superintendent of Jail” means the Superintendent of the Jail in which the prisoner is undergoing his sentence of imprisonment.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Temporary release of prisoners on certain grounds.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The State Government may, in consultation with the District Magistrate and subject to such conditions and in such manner as may be prescribed, release temporarily for a period specified in sub-section (2) any prisoner if the State Government is satisfied that -</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>a member of the prisoner’s family had died or is seriously ill; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the marriage of the prisoner's son or daughter is to be celebrated; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the temporary release of the prisoner is necessary for ploughing, sowing or harvesting or carrying on any other agricultural operation on his land or any other land cultivated by him and no friend of the prisoner or a member of the prisoner’s family is prepared to help him in this behalf in his absence; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>it is desirable so to do for any other sufficient cause.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The period for which a prisoner may be released shall be determined by the State Government so as not to exceed -</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>where the prisoner is to be released on the ground specified in clause (a) of sub-section (1), two weeks;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>where the prisoner is to be released on the ground specified in clause (b) or clause (d) of sub-section (1), four weeks; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>where the prisoner is to be released on the ground specified in clause (c) of sub-section (1), six weeks.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>(2-A) Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (2), where a prisoner undergoing a sentence of life imprisonment, is to be released on the ground specified in clause (d) of sub-section (1), he may be released for a period of six months or less in parts, during the five years.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The period of release under this section shall not count towards the total period of the sentence of a prisoner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may by notification authorise any officer to exercise its power under this section in respect of all or any of the grounds specified therein.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Temporary release of prisoners on furlough.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The State Government or any other officer authorised by it in this behalf may, in consultation with the District Magistrate and subject to such conditions and in such manner as may be prescribed, release temporarily, on furlough, any prisoner who has been sentenced to a term of imprisonment of not less than five years, and who-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>has, immediately before the date of his temporary release, undergone imprisonment for a period of three years, excluding remissions; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>has not during such period committed any jail offence and has earned at least three annual good conduct remissions:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that nothing herein shall apply to a prisoner who -</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list3.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>is a habitual offender as defined in clause (3) of section 2 of the Punjab Habitual Offenders (Control and Reform) Act, 1952, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list3.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>has been convicted of robbery or dacoity or such other offence as the State Government may, by notification, specify.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The period of furlough for which a prisoner is eligible under sub-section (1) shall be three weeks during the first year of his release and two weeks during each successive year thereafter.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of clause (d) of sub-section (3) of section 8 the period of release referred to in sub-section (1) shall count towards the total period of the sentence of a prisoner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Exclusion of certain days in computing period under sections 3 and 4.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of calculating the period of temporary release of a prisoner under sections 3 and 4, the days of departure from and arrival at the prison shall be excluded.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Cases where consultation with District Magistrate not necessary or where prisoners are not to be released.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in sections 3 and 4,</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>it shall not be necessary to consult the District Magistrate where the State Government is satisfied that the prisoner maintained good conduct during the period of his earlier release under any of the aforesaid sections; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>no prisoner shall be entitled to be released under this Act, if on the report of the District Magistrate, where consultation with him is necessary, the State Government or an officer authorised by it in this behalf is satisfied that his release is likely to endanger the security of the State or maintenance of public order.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Journey expenses of poor prisoners to be borne by State Government.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If, on the report of the District Magistrate, the State Government is satisfied that a prisoner’s family cannot bear the expenses of his journey from and to the prison after his temporary release under this Act, the expenses may be borne by the State Government to such extent and in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Liability of prisoner to surrender on expiry of release period and consequences of overstaying.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On the expiry of the period for which a prisoner is released under this Act, he shall surrender himself to the Superintendent of the Jail from which he was released.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If a prisoner does not surrender himself as required by sub-section (1) within a period of ten days from the date on which he should have so surrendered, he may be arrested by any police officer without a warrant and shall be remanded to undergo the unexpired portion of his sentence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If a prisoner surrenders himself to the Superintendent of the Jail from which he was released within a period of ten days of the date on which he should have so surrendered, but fails to satisfy the Superintendent of Jail that he was prevented by any sufficient cause from surrendering himself immediately on the expiry of the period for which he was released, all or any of the following penalties shall, after affording the prisoner a reasonable opportunity of being heard, be awarded to him by the Superintendent of the Jail, namely –</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>a maximum cut of five days’ remission for each day of overstay;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>stoppage of canteen concession for a maximum period of one month;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.3.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>withholding concession of either interviews or letters or both for a maximum period of three months;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.3.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the period of temporary release on furlough of the prisoner under section 4 shall not be counted towards his sentence;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.3.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>warning;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.3.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>reduction from the status and grade of “Convict Watchman” or “Convict Overseer”.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for failure to surrender.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any prisoner who is liable to be arrested under sub-section (2) of section 8, shall be punishable with imprisonment of either description which may extend to two years or with fine or with both.</p>
            <p>Explanation.- The punishment in this section is in addition to the punishment awarded to the prisoner for the offence for which he was convicted.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may by notification make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the execution by the prisoner (including the sureties) of bond for his good behaviour during the release period and for his surrender on the expiry of such period;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the amount for which and the form and manner in which such bonds shall be furnished;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the forfeiture of the amount of bonds in case of breach of any of its terms;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the conditions on which and the manner in which prisoners may be released temporarily under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the manner in which the District Magistrate shall be consulted before a prisoner is released;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the extent to which and the manner in which journey expenses of poor prisoners shall be borne by the State Government.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Repeal and saving.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Pepsu Good Conduct Prisoners (Temporary Release) Act, 1954 (Pepsu Act 11 of 1954), is hereby repealed:</p>
            <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that such repeal shall not affect –</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the previous operation of the Act so repealed or anything duly done or suffered thereunder; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any right, privilege, obligation or liability acquired or incurred under the Act so repealed; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any penalty, forfeiture or punishment incurred in respect of any offence committed against the Act so repealed; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>any investigation, legal proceeding or remedy in respect of any such right, privilege, obligation, liability, penalty, forfeiture or punishment as aforesaid:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>and any such investigation, legal proceeding or remedy may be instituted, continued or enforced, and any such penalty, forfeiture or punishment may be imposed, as if this Act had not been passed:</p>
            <p>Provided further that anything done or any action taken under the Act so repealed shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the corresponding provision of this Act and shall continue to be in force accordingly unless and until superseded by anything done or any action taken under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
