<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-asm/act/1976/20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-asm/act/1976/20"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Assam Public Premises (Eviction Of Unauthorised Occupants) Act, 1971"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-asm/act/1976/20/eng@2016-12-15/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-asm/act/1976/20/eng@2016-12-15"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-12-15" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-asm/act/1976/20/eng@2016-12-15/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-asm/act/1976/20/eng@2016-12-15"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-12-15" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Assam Public Premises (Eviction Of Unauthorised Occupants) Act, 1971</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[Act No. 20 of 1976]</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>An Act to provide an effective machinery for eviction of persons in unauthorised occupation of public</p>
      <p>premises and certain incidental matters connected therewith</p>
      <p>Whereas it is expedient to provide by law an effective machinery for eviction of persons in unauthorised occupation of public premises and certain incidental matters connected therewith;</p>
      <p>It is hereby enacted in the Twenty-Second Year of the Republic of India as follows:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act, may be called the Assam Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) Act, 1971.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Assam, to the premises held by the State Government, wherever they situate, within the territorial jurisdiction of the State of West Bengal, Tamil Nadu, Maharashtra, Meghalaya and Delhi.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf and different dates may be specified for different areas and for different purposes of the Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"Collector" means any officer who exercises the powers of a Collector under the Land Acquisition Act, 1894 (Central Act I of 1894);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"Estate Officer "means an officer appointed as such by the State Government under section 3 of this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>"Public premises" means any premises belonging to or taken on lease, hire or requisitioned by or on behalf of the State Government, the Assam State Electricity Board, the Assam State Road Transport Corporation or any Public sector undertaking owned or sponsored by the State Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>"Premises" means any land or any building or part of a building and includes,</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>the garden, grounds and out-houses, if any, appertaining to such building or part of a building, and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>any fittings affixed to such building or part of a building for the more beneficial enjoyment thereof;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>"prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>"rent" in relation to any public premises, means the consideration payable periodically for the authorised occupation of the premises, and includes,</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f.list1.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>any charge for electricity, water or any other services in connection with the occupation of the premises,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f.list1.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>any tax (by whatever name called) payable in respect of the premises; where such charge or tax is payable by the State Government;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>"State Government" means the State Government of Assam;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>"unauthorised occupation" in relation to any public premises means the occupation by any person of the public premises without authority for such occupation, and includes the continuance in occupation, by any person of the public premises, after the authority under which he was allowed to occupy the premises has expired or has been determined for any reason whatsoever.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Appointment of Estate Officers</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The State Government, may, by notification in the Official Gazette,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>appoint such persons, being Gazetted Officers of the Government, as it thinks fit to be Estate Officers, for the purposes of this Act; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>define the local limits within which, or the categories of public premises in respect of which, each Estate Officer shall exercise the powers conferred, and perform the duties imposed, on Estate Officers by or under this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Issue of notice to show cause against order of eviction</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the Estate Officer is of opinion that any person is in unauthorised occupation of any public premises and that he should be evicted, the Estate Officer shall issue in the manner hereinafter provided a notice in writing calling upon the persons concerned to show cause why an order of eviction should not be made.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The notice shall-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>specify the grounds on which the order of eviction is proposed to be made; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>require all persons concerned, that is to say, all persons who are, or may be in occupation of, or claim interest in the public premises, to show cause, if any, against the proposed order on or before such date as is specified in the notice, being a date not earlier than ten days from the date of issue thereof.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Estate Officer shall cause the notice to be served by having affixed on the outer door or some other conspicuous part of the public premises, and in such other manner as may be prescribed, whereupon the notice shall be deemed to have been duly given to all persons concerned.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the Estate Officer knows or has reason to believe that any person is in occupation of the public premises, then without prejudice to the provisions of sub-section (3), he shall cause a copy of the notice to be served on every such person by post or by delivering or tendering it to that person or in such other manner as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Eviction of unauthorised occupants</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If after considering the cause, if any, shown by any person in pursuance of a notice under section 4 and any evidence he may produce in support of the same and after giving him a reasonable opportunity of being heard, the Estate Officer is satisfied that the public premises are in unauthorised occupation, the Estate Officer, may, on a date to be fixed for the purpose make an order of eviction, for reasons to be recorded therein, directing that the public premises shall be vacated by all persons who may be in occupation thereof or any part thereof, and cause a copy of the order to be affixed on the outer door or some other conspicuous part of the public premises.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person refuses or fails to comply with the order of eviction within thirty days of the date of its publication under sub-section (1), the Estate Officer or any other officer duly authorised by the Estate Officer in this behalf may evict that person from, and take possession of the public premises and may, for that purpose, use such force as may be necessary.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Disposal of property left on public premises by unauthorised occupants</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any person has been evicted from any public premises under section 5, the Estate Officer, may, after giving fourteen days' notice to the person from whom possession of the public premises has been taken and after publishing the notice in at least one newspaper having circulation in the locality, remove or cause to be removed or dispose of by public auction any property left by such person and remaining on such premises.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any property is sold under sub-section (1), the sale proceeds shall, after deducting the expenses of the sale and the amount, if any, due to the State Government on account of arrears of</p>
            <p>rent or damages, or costs, be paid to such person or persons as may appear to the Estate Officer to be entitled to the same:</p>
            <p>Provided that where the Estate Officer is unable to decide as to the person or persons to whom the balance of the amount is payable or as to the apportionment of the same, he may refer such dispute to the civil court of competent jurisdiction and the decision of the Court thereon shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Power to recover rent or damages in respect of public premises as arrears of land revenue</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any person is in arrears of rent payable in respect of any public premises, the Estate Officer, may, by order require that person to pay the same within such time and in such manner as may be specified in the order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any person is, or has, at any time, been in unauthorised occupation of any public premises, the Estate Officer, may, having regard to such principles of assessment of damage? as may be prescribed, assess the damages on account of the use and occupation of such premises and may by order, require that person to pay the damages within such time and in such manner as may be specified in the order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No order under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) shall be made against any person until after the issue of a notice in writing to the person calling upon him to show cause within such time as may be specified in the notice why such order should not be made, and until his objections, if any, and any evidence he may produce in support of the same, have been considered by the Estate Officer.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Powers of Estate Officers</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>An Estate Officer shall, for the purpose of holding any inquiry under this Act, have the same powers as are vested in a civil court under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (Central Act 5 of 1908), when trying a suit in respect of the following matter, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person and examining him on oath;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>requiring the discovery and production of documents; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any other matter which may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Appeals</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An appeal shall lie from every order of the Estate Officer made in respect of any public premises under section 5 or section 7 to an appellate officer who shall be the Collector.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>An appeal under sub-section (1) shall be preferred-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in the case of an appeal from an order under section 5, within thirty days from the date of publication of the order under sub-section (1) of that section; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in the case of an appeal from an order under section 7, within thirty days from the date on which the order is communicated to the appellant:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that the appellate officer may entertain the appeal after the expiry of the said period of thirty days, if he is satisfied that the appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from filing the appeal in time.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an appeal is preferred from an order of the Estate Officer, the appellate officer may stay the enforcement of that order for such period and on such conditions as he deems fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every appeal under this section shall be disposed of by the appellate officer as expeditiously as possible.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The cost of any appeal under this section shall be in the discretion of the appellate officer.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Finality of orders</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Save as otherwise expressly provided in this Act, every order made by an Estate Officer or appellate officer under this Act, shall be final and shall not be called in question in any original suit, application or executive proceeding and no injunction shall be granted by any court or other authority in respect of any action taken or to be taken in pursuance of any power conferred by or under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Offences and penalties</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person who has been evicted from any public premises under this Act, again, occupies the premises without authority for such occupation, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any Magistrate convicting a person under sub-section (1) may make an order for convicting that person summarily and he shall be liable to such eviction without prejudice to any action that may be taken against him under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Power to obtain information</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If the Estate Officer has reason to believe that any person is in authorised occupation of any public premises, the Estate Officer or any other officer authorised by him in this behalf may require that or any other person to furnish information relating to the names or other particulars of the persons in occupation of the public premises and every person so required shall be bound to furnish the information in his possession.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Liability of heirs and legal representatives</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any person against whom any proceeding for the determination of arrears of rent or for the assessment of the damages is to be or has been taken dies before the proceeding is taken or during the pendency thereof, the proceeding may be taken or, as the case may be, continued against the hiers or legal representatives of that person.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any amount due to the State Government from any person whether by way of arrears of rent or damages or cost shall, after the death of the person, be payable by his heirs or legal representatives, but their liability shall be limited to the extent of the assets of the deceased in their hands.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Recovery of rent, etc., as an arrear of land revenue</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any person refuses or fails to pay the arrears of rent payable under sub-section (1) of section 7 or the damages payable under sub-section (2) of that section or the costs awarded to the State Government under sub-section (5) of section 9 or any portion of such rent, damages, or costs, within the time, if any, specified therefor in the order relating thereto, the Estate Officer may issue a certificate for the amount due to the Collector who shall proceed to recover the same as an arrear of land revenue.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the State Government or the appellate officer or the Estate Officer in respect of anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or of any rules or orders made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15A">
        <num>15A.</num>
        <heading>Bar of jurisdiction</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No Civil Court shall have jurisdiction to entertain any suit or proceeding in respect of eviction of any person who is in unauthorised occupation of any public premises or the recovery of the arrears of rent payable under sub-section (1) of section 7 or the damages payable under sub-section (2) of that section or costs awarded to the Government of Assam under sub-section (3) of section 9 or any portion of such rent, damages or costs.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Delegation of power</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government, may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that any power exercisable by it under this Act shall, subject to such conditions, if any, as may be specified in the notification, be exercisable also by an officer of the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government, may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-17.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the form of any notice required or authorised to be given under this Act and the manner in which it may be served;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the holding of inquiries under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the distribution and allocation of work to Estate Officers and the transfer of any proceeding pending before an Estate Officer to another Estate Officer;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the procedure to be followed in taking possession of public premises;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the manner in which damages for unauthorised occupation may be assessed and the principles which may be taken into account in assessing such damages;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the manner in which appeals may be preferred and the procedure to be followed in appeals; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>any other matter which has to be, or may be, prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made, before the Assam Legislative Assembly while it is in session for a total period of fourteen days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session in which it is so laid or the sessions immediately following the Assam Legislative Assembly agree in making any modification in the rule or the Assam Legislative Assembly agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect, only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of any thing previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Repeal or saving</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Assam Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) Ordinance, 1971 is hereby repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken under the Assam Public Premises (Eviction of Unauthorised Occupants) Ordinance, 1971, shall be deemed to have been done or taken under this Act, as if this Act had commenced on the eighth day of February, 1971 (the date of promulgation of the Ordinance).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
