<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1881/13/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1881/13"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Fort William Act, 1881"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1881/13/eng@1881-03-11/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1881/13/eng@1881-03-11"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1881-03-11" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1881/13/eng@1881-03-11/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1881/13/eng@1881-03-11"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Fort William Act, 1881</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 13 OF 1881AN ACT TO PROVIDE FOR THE BETTER GOVERNMENT OF FORT WILLIAM.</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 11th March, 1881.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>Preamble. WHEREAS it is expedient to give power to make rules for  the better government of Fort William in Bengal, and to provide for  the establishment of a Court within the said Fort for the trial of  persons charged with breaches of such rules; It is hereby enacted as  follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title. This Act may be called the Fort William Act,</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1881">
        <num>1881.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1881.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>;</p>
            <p>Commencement. And it shall come into force on the first day of</p>
            <p>April, 1881.</p>
            <p>But nothing herein contained shall be deemed to confer  jurisdiction over any persons (other than artificers, labourers,</p>
            <p>sutlers and followers) to whom the  Army Act] or the Indian Articles  of War, 1869, 2 (44 and 45 Vict., c. 58). (5 of 1869). is or are  applicable.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>" The Fort". The Central Government may, from time to time, by  notification, in the Official Gazette, define, for the purposes of  this Act, the limits of Fort William in Bengal; and in this Act the  expression" the Fort" means the area so defined.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Chief of the Army Staff may make rules.  The Chief of the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Army Staff] may, from time to time, with the sanction of the Central</p>
            <p>Government, make rules, to be in force within the Fort, in regard to  the matters specified in the Schedule hereto annexed and other matters  of a like nature, and may by such rules prescribe, as penalties for  the infringement thereof, fine which may extend to fifty rupees, or  imprisonment for a term which may extend to four days, or both.</p>
            <p>When a sentence of fine is passed under any such rule, the term  for which the Court directs the offender to be imprisoned in default  of payment of such fine may extend to, and shall not exceed, four  days.</p>
            <p>When any rule is made under this section, a copy thereof, in</p>
            <p>English and such other languages as the Central Government may from  time to time direct, shall be exhibited in such conspicuous places  within the Fort as the Officer Commanding the Fort may from time to  time direct.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Central Government may invest officer with power to try  breaches of rules. The Central Government may invest any commissioned  officer in the Indian Army with power to try persons charged with any  infringement of the rules made under' section 3.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The officer so invested is hereinafter called the Fort</p>
            <p>Magistrate.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Procedure to be followed. In all cases under this Act, the Fort</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Magistrate shall, except as herein otherwise provided, exercise within  the Fort the Powers, and as nearly as may be, follow the procedure,</p>
            <p>conferred on, and prescribed for, a Presidency Magistrate by the</p>
            <p>Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898]; (5 of 1898), and, subject to the  power conferred by  section 526 of that Code], every finding,</p>
            <p>sentence or order of such Magistrate. under this Act shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Power to arrest without warrant. Any police- officer, or any  other person empowered in this behalf by the Central Government by  name or as a member of a specified class, may arrest without warrant  any person who in his sight commits an offence punishable under this</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Act.</p>
            <p>Power to police- officer to release on bail. Every person so  arrested shall be taken to the police- station within the Fort, and  shall be detained there until he gives to the police- officer in charge  of such station a bond, with or without sureties, as such officer may  require, for a sum not exceeding one hundred rupees, to appear before  the Fort Magistrate at a time to be specified in such bond, or until  he can be brought before such Magistrate.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Jurisdiction of Presidency Magistrates and prosecutions under  other laws saved. Nothing in this Act, or in any rule made hereunder  shall affect the jurisdiction of the  Presidency Magistrates] or  shall prevent any person from being prosecuted under any other law for  any offence punishable under this Act, or from being liable to any  other punishment than is provided for such offence by this Act:</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Provided that no person shall be punished twice for the same  offence.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Limitation of time for prosecution under Act. No prosecution  for any offence under this Act shall be commenced after the expiration  of three months next after such offence has been committed.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Validation of penalties heretofore imposed by Garrison Quarter</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Master. Rep. by the Amending Act, 1891 (12 of 1891.)</p>
            <p>FORT WILLIAM ACT, 1881</p>
            <p>THE SCHEDULE</p>
            <p>(See section 3.)</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Throwing dirt or rubbish of any description into the drains  or roads, or anywhere but in the appointed places.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Removing night- soil without a covering or at unauthorised  hours.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Camp- followers, servants, and others not keeping the godowns  they live in clean.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Performing offices of nature in other than the appointed  places.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Bathing, or washing clothes or animals, in the cunette or  other unauthorised places.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Selling unwholesome articles of food, grain or drinks.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Adulterating food or drinks.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Making evacuations in unauthorised places.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Rash or negligent driving.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.10">
          <num>(10)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Picketing, training. or breaking in animals.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Causing obstruction by vehicles on the road.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.12">
          <num>(12)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Exposing or hawking articles for sale about the roads and  barracks or within the Fort without a Fort pass.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.13">
          <num>(13)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Beating drums or tom- toms.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.14">
          <num>(14)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Damaging lamps, posts, masonry or other Government pro-</p>
            <p>perty in any part of the Fort.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.15">
          <num>(15)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Disorderly behaviour in the public thoroughfares.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.16">
          <num>(16)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Gambling.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.17">
          <num>(17)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Spitting pan on any of the public stair cases, gateways,</p>
            <p>walls and verandahs, or defacing in any way the walls of barracks,</p>
            <p>building or gateways.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.18">
          <num>(18)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Throwing slops into the drains.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.19">
          <num>(19)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Washing cooking- pots at the water- taps and wasting water.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.20">
          <num>(20)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Cooking in unauthorised places.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.21">
          <num>(21)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Hanging clothes to dry on the guns or masonry- work.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.22">
          <num>(22)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Laying out clothes, accouterments or stable- bedding after  the authorised hours.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.23">
          <num>(23)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Destroying the trees, bushes or plants, or climbing trees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.24">
          <num>(24)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Servants smoking hookas in their masters' quarters or cook-</p>
            <p>houses, or keeping such quarters or cook- houses in an insanitary  state.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.25">
          <num>(25)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Trespassing on parade- grounds, or making foot- paths across  the grass- plots.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.26">
          <num>(26)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Being drunk and incapable.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.27">
          <num>(27)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Fighting, quarrelling and creating a disturbance, or making  unnecessary noise of any kind.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.28">
          <num>(28)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Affixing bills and papers on any walls in the Fort.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.29">
          <num>(29)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Cutting grass or interfering with the grass- contractor.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.30">
          <num>(30)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Declining to show a tin pass when called upon to do so.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.31">
          <num>(31)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Being found in the garrison without a tin pass, or being in  possession of a ticket belonging to another.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.32">
          <num>(32)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Driving vehicles without lights or with insufficiently-</p>
            <p>greased wheels.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.33">
          <num>(33)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Swinging or sitting on the chain- fences.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.34">
          <num>(34)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Interfering in any way with the guns, carriages, or piles  of shot and shell on the works, or with the packed ordnance.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.35">
          <num>(35)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Mounting the ramparts or parapets or entering the embrasures  without authority.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.36">
          <num>(36)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Smuggling liquor into the Fort.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.37">
          <num>(37)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Burning stable litter or lighting fires except in authorised  places and at authorised hours.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.38">
          <num>(38)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Carrying lights except in closed lanterns, or letting off  fire- works</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.39">
          <num>(39)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Removing property of any kind or description from the Fort  without written authority.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.40">
          <num>(40)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Allowing animals of any sort to stray into the Fort, or  to graze within the game.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.41">
          <num>(41)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Slaughtering animals or exposing carcasses or offal within  the Fort.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.42">
          <num>(42)</num>
          <content>
            <p>keeping dogs or poultry in unauthorised places.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.43">
          <num>(43)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Buying, selling or receiving any portion of a soldier' s kit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.44">
          <num>(44)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Disobedience of lawful authority in failing to attend to  authorised instructions of the police or of the several sentries  posted throughout the Fort.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.45">
          <num>(45)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Occupying buildings of any without proper allotment.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
