<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1955/42/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1955/42"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Prize Competitions Act, 1955"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1955/42/eng@1955-10-22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1955/42/eng@1955-10-22"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1955-10-22" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1955/42/eng@1955-10-22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1955/42/eng@1955-10-22"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Prize Competitions Act, 1955</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 42 OF 1955</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 22nd October, 1955.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Sixth Year of the Republic of</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the control and regulation of prize  competitions.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the control and regulation  of prize Competitions;</p>
        <p>AND WHEREAS the Legislatures of the States of Andhra, Bombay,</p>
        <p>Madras, Orissa, Uttar Pradesh, Hyderabad, Madhya Bharat, Patiala and</p>
        <p>East Punjab States Union and Saurashtra have passed resolutions in  terms of clause (1) of article 252 of the Constitution in relation to  the above- mentioned matter and matters ancillary thereto in so far as  such matters are matters enumerated in List II in the Seventh Schedule  to the Constitution;</p>
        <p>India as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be  called the Prize Competitions Act, 1955.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to  the territories which, immediately before the</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1st">
        <num>1st.</num>
        <heading>November, 1956, were comprised in] the States of Andhra, Bombay,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1st.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Madras, Orissa, Uttar Pradesh, Hyderabad, Madhya Bharat, Patiala and</p>
            <p>East Punjab States Union and Saurashtra and all Part C States.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-1st.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date  as the Central Government  may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" licensing authority" means any officer or authority  appointed by the State Government, by notification in the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Official Gazette, for the purpose of granting licences under  this Act;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" money" includes a cheque, postal- order or money-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>order;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under  this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>" prize competition" means any competition (whether  called a cross- word prize competition, a missing- word prize  competition, a picture prize competition or by any other   name) in which prizes are offered for the solution of any</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>puzzle based upon the building up, arrangement, combination  or permutation, of letters, words, or figures.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Interpretation. For the purposes of this Act,-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>references to printing shall be construed as including  references to writing and other modes of representing or re-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>producing letters, words or figures in a visible form; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>documents or other matters shall be deemed to be  distributed if they are distributed to persons or places  within or outside the territories to which this Act extends  and the word distribution' shall be construed accordingly.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition of prize competitions where the prize offered  exceeds one thousand rupees a month. No person shall promote or  conduct any prize competition or competitions in which the total value  of the prize or prizes (whether in cash or otherwise) to be offered in  any month exceeds one thousand rupees; and in every prize  competition, the number of entries shall not exceed two thousand.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Licensing of prize competitions where the prize offered does  not exceed one thousand rupees a month. Subject to the provisions of  section 4, no person shall promote or conduct any prize competition or  competitions in which the total value of the prize or prizes (whether   in cash or otherwise) to be offered in any month does not exceed one  thousand rupees unless he has obtained in this behalf a licence  granted in accordance with the provisions of this Act and the rules  made thereunder.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Licences for prize competitions.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every person desiring to  obtain a licence referred to in section 5 shall make an application in  writing to the licensing authority in such form and manner as may be  prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On the receipt of such application, the licensing authority,</p>
            <p>after making such inquiry as it considers necessary, shall, by order  in writing, either grant the licence or refuse to grant the licence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the licensing authority refuses to grant a licence it  shall record a brief statement of the reasons for such refusal and  furnish a copy thereof to the applicant.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The fees on payment of which, the period for which, the con-</p>
            <p>ditions subject to which, and the form in which, a licence may be  granted shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Promoters of prize competitions to keep accounts and submit the  same to the licensing authority. Every person who promotes or conducts  a prize competition in accordance with the provisions of this Act and  the rules made thereunder shall keep accounts relating to such  competition and submit to the licensing authority a statement of  accounts in such form and at such intervals as may be prescribed.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Power to cancel or suspend licences.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The licensing  authority may, after giving the holder of any licence under this Act a  reasonable opportunity of being heard, cancel or suspend the licence  on any one or more of the following grounds, namely:</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>that there has been a breach of any of the conditions  subject to which the licence was granted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>that the holder of the licence has contravened any of  the provisions of section 7.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whenever a licence is cancelled or suspended the licensing  authority shall record a brief statement of the reasons for such can-</p>
            <p>cellation or suspension and furnish a copy thereof to the person whose  licence has been cancelled or suspended.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for promoting or conducting any prize competition in  contravention of the provisions of sections 4 and 5. If any person  promotes or conducts any prize competition in contravention of the  provisions of section 4 or section 5, he shall be punishable with  imprisonment for a term which may extend to three months, or with  fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for failure to keep and submit accounts. If any  person liable under section 7 to keep accounts or to submit statements  of accounts fails to keep accounts or to submit statements of accounts  as required by that section or keeps accounts or submits statements of  accounts which are false and which he either knows or believes to be  false or does not believe to be true, he shall be punishable with  imprisonment for a term which may extend to one month, or with fine  which may extend to five hundred rupees, or with both, but nothing  contained in this section shall affect the provisions contained in  section B.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for other offences in connection with prize  competitions. If any person with a view to the promotion or conduct  of any prize competition except in accordance with the provisions of a  licence under this Act or in contravention of the provisions of this</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Act or in connection with any prize competition promoted- or conducted  except in accordance with such provisions-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>prints or publishes any ticket, coupon or other  document for use in the prize competition; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>sells or distributes or offers or advertises for sale  or distribution, or has in his possession for the purpose of  sale or distribution any ticket, coupon or other document for  use in the prize competition; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>prints, publishes or distributes, or has in his  possession for the purpose of publication or distribution,-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>any advertisement of the prize competition, or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>any list (whether complete or not) of prize  winners in the prize competition, or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>any such matter descriptive of, or otherwise  relating to, the prize competition as is calculated to  act as an inducement to persons to participate in that  prize competition or any other prize competition; or</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>brings, or invites any person to send, into the  territories to which this Act extends, for the purpose of  sale or distribution, any ticket, coupon or other document  for use in, or any advertisement of, the prize competition;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>sends, or attempts to send, out of the territories to  which this Act extends any money or valuable thing received  in respect of the sale or distribution of any ticket, coupon  or other document for use in the prize competition; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list3.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>uses any premises, or causes or knowingly permits any  premises to be used, for purposes connected with the pro-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list5">
              <listIntroduction>motion or conduct of the prize competition; or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list5.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>causes or procures or attempts to procure any person to  do any of the above- mentioned acts,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend  to three months, or with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees,</p>
            <p>or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Offences by Corporations.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person guilty of an  offence under this, Act is a company, every person who at the time the  offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible to, the  company, as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of that  offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished  accordingly:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render  any such person liable to any punishment provided in this Act if he  proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or that  he exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such  offence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where  an offence under this Act has been committed with the consent or  connivance of, or is attributable to gross neglect on the part of, any  director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such</p>
            <p>director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to  be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against  and punished accordingly.</p>
            <blockList id="section-12.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.2.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" company" means a body corporate and includes a firm  or other association of individuals; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.2.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" director" in relation to a firm means a partner in  the firm.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Power of licensing authority to call for and inspect accounts and  documents. The licensing authority may-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>require any person promoting or conducting a prize  competition to produce before it the accounts and other  documents kept by such person or to furnish to it such other  information relating to the prize competition as it may  require;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>inspect at all reasonable times the accounts and other  documents kept by such person.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Power of entry and search.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be lawful for any  police- officer not below the rank of Sub- inspector authorised by the</p>
            <blockList id="section-14.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>State Government in this behalf by general or special order in  writing,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to enter if necessary by force, whether by day or  night, with such assistants as he considers necessary, any  premises which he has reason to suspect, are being used for  purposes connected with the promotion or conduct of any prize  competition in contravention of the provisions of this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.1.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to search the premises and the persons whom he may find  herein;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.1.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to take into custody and produce before a Magistrate  all such persons as are concerned or against whom a reason-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>able complaint has been made or credible information has been  received or a reasonable suspicion exists of their having  been concerned with the user of such premises for purposes  connected with, or with the promotion or conduct of, any  prize competition in contravention of the provisions of this</p>
            <blockList id="section-14.1.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Act; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.1.list5.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>to seize all things found therein which are intended to  be used or reasonably suspected to have been used in  connection with such prize competition.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All searches under this section shall be made in accordance  with the provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898).</p>
            <p>Forfeiture newspapers and publications containing prize competition.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Forfeiture newspapers and publications containing prize  competition. Where any newspaper or other publication contains any  prize competition promoted or conducted in contravention of the provi-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>sions of this Act or except in accordance with the provisions of  licence under this Act or any advertisement in relation thereto, the</p>
            <p>State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare  every copy of the newspaper and every copy of the publication  containing the prize competition or the advertisement, to be forfeited  to Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Appeals. Any person aggrieved by the decision of the licensing  authority refusing to grant a licence or cancelling or suspending a  licence may, within such time as may be prescribed, prefer an appeal  to the State Government and the decision of the State Government on  such appeal shall be final.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Licensing authority and other officers to be public servants.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The licensing authority and any other officer acting under this Act  shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of section 21  of the Indian Penal Code 45 of 1860.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Jurisdiction to try offences. No Court inferior to that of a</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Presidency Magistrate or a Magistrate of the first class shall try any  offence under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken under this act. No suit,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the licensing  authority or any other officer of the Government for anything which is  in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or the rules  made thereunder.</p>
            <p>Power to make rules.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-20.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification  in the Official Gazette, and subject to the condition of previous  publication, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-20.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of  the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-20.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the form and manner of application for a licence and the  fees, if any, for such licence;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-20.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the period for which, the conditions subject to which and  the form in which, a licence may be granted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-20.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the form in which and the intervals at which statements  ofaccounts shall be submitted to the licensing authority;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-20.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the time within which an appeal against a decision of the  licensing authority may be preferred to the State Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-20.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>any other matter which is to be or may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
