<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1965/40/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1965/40"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Railways (Employment Of Members Of Thearmed Forces) Act, 1965"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1965/40/eng@1965-12-03/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1965/40/eng@1965-12-03"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1965-12-03" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1965/40/eng@1965-12-03/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1965/40/eng@1965-12-03"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Railways (Employment Of Members Of Thearmed Forces) Act, 1965</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 40 OF 1965</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 3rd December, 1965.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to make certain provisions relating to the employment of  members of the Armed Forces of the Union in the working and management  of railways.</p>
      </longTitle>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Sixteenth Year of the Republic  of India as follows:-</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and extent.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Railways (Employment of Members of the Armed Forces) Act, 1965.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Interpretation. Words and expressions used in this Act and  defined in the Indian Railways Act, 1890 (9 of 1890), shall have the  meanings respectively assigned to them in that Act.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Employment of members of Armed Forces of the Union to  assist a railway administration in connection with the service of a  railway.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>When any member of the Armed Forces of the Union is  employed to assist a railway administration in connection with the  service of a railway, then, whether such employment was before or is  after the commencement of this Act,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any provision of the Indian Railways Act, 1890 (9 of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1890">
        <num>1890.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1890.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>), or of the rules made thereunder, which confers a  power, status or immunity, or imposes a duty or liability,</p>
            <p>upon a railway servant, in connection with the working, use,</p>
            <blockList id="section-1890.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>management and maintenance of railways, shall be construed  as conferring the same power, status or immunity or imposing  the same duty or liability, as the case may be, upon such  member of the Armed Forces of the Union when so employed;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1890.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the employment of a member of the Armed Forces of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Union, in addition to or in the place of any railway servant,</p>
            <p>shall not affect any liability that would have attached to  the railway administration had such member been a railway  servant.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-1890.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in sub- section (1) shall be construed as making  applicable to the members of the Armed Forces of the Union  employed to assist a railway administration the provisions of Chapter</p>
            <p>VIA of the Indian Railways Act, 1890 (9 of 1890), or as derogating  from any provision</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Employment of members of Armed Forces of the Union to  replace railway administration in working a railway. If at any time the  whole of the working, management and maintenance of a railway or of a  specific, portion or section of a railway, is assumed by the Armed</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Forces of the Union, the Central Government may notify the fact of  such assumption in the Official Gazette and thereupon, so long as  such assumption continues, the Indian Railways Act, 1890 (9 of</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1890">
        <num>1890.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1890.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>), shall cease to be applicable to the Railway or the portion or  section of the Railway concerned.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Repeal and saving.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Railways (Employment of Members of   the Armed Forces) Ordinance, 1965 (4 of 1965) is hereby repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action  taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or  taken under this Act as if this Act had commenced on the 29th day of</p>
            <p>September, 1965.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
