<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-utp/act/1938/5/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-utp/act/1938/5"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Uttar Pradesh Prisoners’ Release On Probation Act, 1938"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-utp/act/1938/5/eng@2017-01-05/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-utp/act/1938/5/eng@2017-01-05"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-05" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-utp/act/1938/5/eng@2017-01-05/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-utp/act/1938/5/eng@2017-01-05"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-05" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Uttar Pradesh Prisoners’ Release On Probation Act, 1938</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[U.P. ACT No . VIII OF 1938]</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the release of certain presents on conditions imposed by the State Government</p>
        <p>Whereas it is expedient to provide for the conational release from prison of prisoners in certain case before the completion of the term of imprisonment to which they have been sentenced: it is hereby enacted as follows:</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Uttar Pradesh Prisoners’ Release on Probation Act, 1938.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the Uttar Pradesh.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the State Government may by notification appoint in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Power of Government to release by licence on conditions imposed by it,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in Section 401 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 where a person is confined in prison under a sentence of imprisonment, and it appears to the State Government from his antecedents and his conduct in the prison that he is likely to abstain from crime and lead a peaceable life, if he is released from prison, the State Government may by licence permit him to be released on condition that he be placed under the supervision or authority of a Government Officer or of a person professing the same religion as the prisoner, or such secular institution or such society belonging to the same religion as the prisoner as may be recognized by the State Government for the purpose, provided such other person, institution or society is willing to take charge of him.</p>
            <p>Explanation.-The expression “sentence of imprisonment” in this section shall include imprisonment in default of payment of fine and imprisonment for failure to furnish security under Chapter VIII of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Period for which licence is to be in force. –</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A licence granted under the provisions of Section 2 shall be in force until the date on which the person released would in the execution of the order of warrant authorizing his imprisonment have been discharged from prison had he not been released on licence or until the licence is revoked, whichever is earlier.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Period of release to be reckoned as imprisonment for computing period of sentence served.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The period during which a person is absent form prison under the provisions of this Act on a licence which is in force shall be reckoned as part of the period of imprisonment to which he was sentenced, for the purpose of computing the period of his sentence which might be awarded to him under any rules in force relating to such remissions</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Form of licence.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>A licence granted under the provisions of section 2 shall be in such form and shall contain such conditions as the State Government may by general or special order or by rules made in this behalf, direct.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>power to revoke licence.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may at any time for reasons to be recorded in writing revoke a licence granted under the provisions of Section 2:</p>
            <p>Provided that no licence shall be revoked on the ground of the breach of a condition of the licence without giving an opportunity to the person concerned to represent his case be fore the District Magistrate of the district in which he is residing at the time.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An order of revocation passed under the provisions of sub-section (1) shall specify the date with effect from which the licence shall cease to be in force, and shall be served, in such manner as the State Government may by rule prescribe, upon the person whose licence has been revoked.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Released absconders who escape from supervision to be punishable.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person escapes from the supervision or authority of a Government officer or secular institution or a society or person in whose charge he has been placed under the provisions of Section 2, or if any person whose licence has been revoked under the provisions of Section 6, fails, without lawful excuse, the burden of proving which shall be upon him, to return to the prison from which he was released, on or before the date specified in the order or revocation, such person shall conviction by a magistrate be liable to serve the unexpired portion of his original sentence and shall also be punishable with imprisonment for a further term which may extend to two years or with fine not exceeding rupees two hundred, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An offence punishable under sub-section (1) shall be deemed to be a cognizable offence within the meaning of clause (ƒ) of sub-section (1) of Section 4 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Power of Government to remit sentence.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may remit the whole or a part of the sentence of a person sentenced to imprisonment for an offence under any Act, on such person entering into a bond, with one or more sureties, in such amount and for such period as the State Government may direct, to be of good behavior and to observe such conditions as to residence or otherwise as the State Government may impose.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of Sections 126, 126A, 514, 514A, 514-B and 515 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 shall, so far as they may be, apply in the case of sureties offered and bonds given under this Section as if they had been offered and given under Chapter VIII of the said Code:</p>
            <p>Provided that if any person, required under Section 126-A or 514-A of the said Code to furnish fresh security, fails to furnish the same, the State Government may cancel the order passed under sub–section (1) and order that such person shall serve the whole or so much of his unexpired sentence as the State Government may direct.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person released under sub-section (1) fails to observe the conditions of his bond, the State Government may direct that he be re- arrested and sent to prison to serve the whole or such part of his unexpired sentence as it may direct, in addition to any proceedings that may be taken against him of surety or sureties in respect of such bond under the said Code .</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may make rules consistent with this Act-</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>for the form and conditions of licenses on which prisoners may be released;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>for the appointment of Government officer, the recognition of institutions and societies referred to in Section 2;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>for defining the powers and duties of Government officers, institutions or persons, under whose authority or supervisions, conditions all released prisoners may be kept;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>for defining the classes of offenders who may be conditionally released, add the periods of imprisonment after which they may be so released;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>for prescribing the manner in which an order of revocation of a licence shall be served on the person whose licence is revoked;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>generally for carrying into effect all the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
