<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1887/12/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1887/12"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Bengal, Agra And Assam Civil Courts Act, 1887"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1887/12/eng@1887-03-11/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1887/12/eng@1887-03-11"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1887-03-11" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1887/12/eng@1887-03-11/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1887/12/eng@1887-03-11"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Bengal, Agra And Assam Civil Courts Act, 1887</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 12 OF 1887  AN ACT TO CONSOLIDATE AND AMEND THE LAW RELATING TO CI</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 11th March, 1887.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>VIL COURTSIN BENGAL</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to consolidate and amend the law relating  to Civil Courts in Bengal, the North- Western Provinces and Assam; It  is hereby enacted as follows:-</p>
        <p>CHAP</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Title, extent and commencement.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called  the Bengal,  Agra] and Assam Civil Courts Act, 1887.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It extends to the territories  which were on the 11th</p>
              <p>March, 1887,] respectively administered by the Lieutenant- Governor of</p>
              <p>Bengal, the Lieutenant- Governor of the North- Western Provinces and the</p>
              <p>Chief Commissioner of Assam, except such portions of those territories  as for the time being are not subject to the ordinary civil  jurisdiction of the High Courts ; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on the first day of July, 1887.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Repeal.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-2.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All Courts constituted, appointments, nominations,</p>
              <p>rules and orders made, jurisdiction and powers conferred and lists  published under the Bengal Civil Courts Act, 1871, (6 of 1871) 2, or any  enactment thereby repealed, or purporting expressly or impliedly to  have been so constituted, made, conferred and published, shall be  deemed to have been respectively constituted, made, conferred and  published under this Act; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any enactment or document referring to the Bengal Civil</p>
              <p>Courts Act, 1871, (6 of 1871) 2, or to any enactment thereby repealed,</p>
              <p>shall be construed to refer to this Act or to the corresponding  portion thereof.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>CONSTITUTION OF CIVIL COURTS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>CONSTITUTION OF CIVIL COURTS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Classes of Courts. There shall be the following classes of</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Civil Courts under this Act, namely--</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the Court of the District Judge;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the Court of the Additional Judge;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the Court of the Subordinate Judge; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the Court of the Munsif.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Number of District Judges, subordinate Judges and Munsifs.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may alter the number of District Judges,</p>
              <p>Subordinate Judges and Munsifs now fixed.]</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Number of Munsifs. Rep. by the Decentralization Act, 1914</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>(4 of 1914), s. 2 and Sch., Part I.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Vacancies among Districts or Subordinate Judges.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Whenever the office of District Judge or Subordinate Judge is vacant  by reason of the death, resignation or removal of</p>
              <p>the Judge or other cause, or whenever  an increase in the number of</p>
              <p>District or Subordinate Judges has been made under the provisions of  section 4], the  State Government or, as the case may be, the High</p>
              <p>Court] may fill up the vacancy or appoint the Additional District</p>
              <p>Judges or Subordinate Judges .</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in this section shall be construed to prevent a</p>
              <p>State Government from appointing a District Judge or Subordinate Judge  to discharge, for such period as it thinks fit, in addition to the  functions devolving on him as such District Judge or Subordinate</p>
              <p>Judge, all or any of the functions of another District Judge or</p>
              <p>Subordinate Judge, as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Vacancies among Munsifs. Rep. by the A. O. 1937.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Additional Judges.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When the business pending before any</p>
              <p>District Judge requires the aid of Additional Judges for its speedy  disposal, the State Government may,  having consulted the High Court    appoint such Additional Judges as may be requisite.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Additional Judges so appointed shall discharge any of the  functions of a District Judge which the District Judge may assign to  them, and, in the discharge of those functions, they shall exercise  the same powers as the District Judge.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Administrative Control of Courts. Subject to the  superintendence of the High Court, the District Judge shall have  administrative control over all the Civil Courts under this Act within  the local limits of his jurisdiction.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Temporary charge of district Court.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the event of the  death, resignation or removal of the District Judge, or of his being  incapacitated by illness or otherwise for the performance of his  duties, or of his absence from the place at which his Court is held,</p>
              <p>the Additional Judge, or, if an Additional Judge is not present at  that place, the senior Subordinate Judge present thereat, shall,</p>
              <p>without relinquishing his ordinary duties, assume charge of the office  of the District Judge, and shall, continue in charge thereof until the  office is resumed by the District Judge or assumed by an officer  appointed thereto.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>While in charge of the office of the District Judge, the Addi-</p>
              <p>tional Judge or Subordinate Judge, as the case may be, may, subject  to any rules which the High Court may make in this behalf, exercise  any of the powers of the District Judge.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Transfer of proceedings on vacation of office of Subordinate</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Judge.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the event of the death, resignation or removal of a</p>
              <p>Subordinate Judge, or of his being incapacitated by illness or other-</p>
              <p>wise for the performance of his duties, or of his absence from the  place at which his Court is held, the District Judge may transfer all  or any of the proceedings pending in the Court of the Subordinate</p>
              <p>Judge either to his own Court or to any Court under his administrative  control competent to dispose of them.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Proceedings transferred under sub- section (1) shall be  disposed of as if they had been instituted in the Court to which they  are so transferred:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Provided that the District Judge may re- transfer to the Court  of the Subordinate Judge or his successor any proceedings transferred  under sub- section (1) to his own or any other Court.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purposes of proceedings which are not pending in the</p>
              <p>Court of the Subordinate Judge on the occurrence of an event referred  to in sub- section (1), and with respect to which that Court has exclu-</p>
              <p>sive jurisdiction, the District Judge may exercise all or any of the  jurisdiction of that Court.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Temporary charge of office of Munsif. Rep. by the A. O.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1937">
          <num>1937.</num>
          <heading/>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Power to fix local limits of jurisdiction of Courts.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-13.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The</p>
              <p>State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, fix and  alter the local limits of the jurisdiction of any Civil Court under  this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the same local jurisdiction is assigned to two or more</p>
              <p>Subordinate Judges or to two or more Munsifs, the District Judge may  assign to each of them such civil business cognizable by the Sub-</p>
              <p>ordinate Judge or Munsif, as the case may be, as, subject to any  general or special orders of the High Court, he thinks fit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When civil business arising in any local area is assigned by  the District Judge under sub- section (2) to one of two or more Sub-</p>
              <p>ordinate Judges, or to one of two or more Munsifs, a decree or order  passed by the Subordinate Judge or Munsif shall not be invalid by  reason only of the case in which it was made having arisen wholly or  in part in a place beyond the local area if that place is within the  local limits fixed by the State Government under sub- section (1).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A Judge of a Court of Small Causes appointed to be also a</p>
              <p>Subordinate Judge or Munsif is a Subordinate Judge or Munsif, as the  case may be, within the meaning of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The present local limits of the jurisdiction of every Civil</p>
              <p>Court under this Act shall be deemed to have been fixed under this  section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Place of sitting of Courts.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, fix and alter the place or  places at which any Civil Court under this Act is to be held.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All places at which any such Courts are now held shall be  deemed to have been fixed under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Vacations of Courts.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-15.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to such orders as may be made     by the State Government ] the High Court shall  prepare a list of days to be observed in each year as close holidays  in the Civil Courts.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The list shall be published in the Official Gazette.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A judicial act done by a Civil Court on a day specified in  the list shall not be invalid by reason only of its having been done  on that day.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Seals of Courts. Every Civil Court under this Act shall use  a seal of such form and dimensions as are prescribed by the State</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Continuance of proceeding of Courts ceasing to have  jurisdiction.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where any Civil Court under this Act has from any  cause ceased to have jurisdiction with respect to any case, any  proceeding in relation to that case which, if that Court had not  ceased to have jurisdiction, might have been had therein may be had in  the Court to which the business of the former Court has been  transferred.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in this section applies to cases for which provision  is made in section 623 or section 649 of the Code of Civil Procedure 4</p>
              <p>(14 of 1882), or in any other enactment for the time being in  force.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>ORDINARY JURISDICTION</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>ORDINARY JURISDICTION</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Extent of original jurisdiction of District or Subordinate</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Judge. Save as otherwise provided by any enactment for the time being  in force, the jurisdiction of a District Judge or Subordinate Judge  extends, subject to the provisions of section 15 of the Code of Civil</p>
              <p>Procedure 1 (14 of 1882), to all original suits for the time being cog-</p>
              <p>nizable by Civil Courts.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Extent of jurisdiction of Munsif.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-19.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Save as aforesaid,</p>
              <p>and subject to the provisions of sub- section (2), the jurisdiction of a</p>
              <p>Munsif extends to all like suits of which the value does not exceed  one thousand rupees.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, on the recommendation of the High</p>
              <p>Court, direct, by notification in the Official Gazette, with respect  to any Munsif named therein, that his jurisdiction shall extend to all  like suits of such value not exceeding two thousand rupees as may be  specified in the notification:</p>
              <p>Provided that the State Government may, by notification in the</p>
              <p>Official Gazette, delegate to the High Court its powers under this  section.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Appeals from District and Additional Judges.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-20.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Save as  otherwise provided by any enactment for the time being in force, an  appeal from a decree or order of a District Judge or Additional Judge  shall lie to the High Court.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An appeal shall not lie to the High Court from a decree or  order of an Additional Judge in any case in which, if the decree or  order had been made by the District Judge, an appeal would not lie to  that Court.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Appels from Subordinate Judges and Munsifs.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-21.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-21.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Save as  aforesaid, an appeal from a decree or order of a Subordinate Judge  shall lie-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-21.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to the District Judge where the value of the original  suit in which or in any proceeding arising out of which the  decree or order was made did not exceed five thousand rupees,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-21.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-21.1.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>to the High Court in any other case.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-21.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Save as aforesaid, an appeal from a decree or order of a</p>
              <p>Munsif shall lie to the District Judge.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-21.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where the function of receiving any appeals which lie to the</p>
              <p>District Judge under sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) has been  assigned to an Additional Judge, the appeals may be preferred to the</p>
              <p>Additional Judge.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-21.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The High Court may, with the previous sanction of the State</p>
              <p>Government, direct, by notification in the Official Gazette, that  appeals lying to the District Judge under sub- section (2) from all or  any of the decrees or orders of any Munsif shall be preferred to the</p>
              <p>Court of such Subordinate Judge as may be mentioned in the noti-</p>
              <p>fication, and the appeals shall thereupon be preferred accordingly.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>SPECIAL JURISDICTION</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>SPECIAL JURISDICTION</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Power to transfer to Subordinate Judges appeals from</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Munsifs.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-22.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A District Judge may transfer to any Subordinate Judge  under his administrative control any appeals pending before him from  the decrees or orders of Munsifs.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The District Judge may withdraw any appeal so transferred,</p>
              <p>and either hear and dispose of it himself or transfer it to a Court  under his administrative control competent to dispose of it.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Appeals transferred under this section shall be disposed of  subject to the rules applicable to like appeals when disposed of by  the district Judge.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Exercise by Subordinate Judge or Munsif of jurisdiction of</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>District Court in certain proceedings.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-23.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The High Court may, by  general or special order, authorize any Subordinate Judge or Munsif to  take cognizance of, or any District Judge to transfer to a Subordinate</p>
              <p>Judge or Munsif under his administrative control, any of the  proceedings next hereinafter mentioned or any class of those  proceedings specified in the order.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-23.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The proceedings referred to in sub- section (1) are the  following, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-23.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>proceedings under Bengal Regulation 5, 1799 (to limit  the Interference of the Zillah and City Courts of Dewanny</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Adawlut in the Execution of Wills and Administration to the</p>
              <blockList id="section-23.2.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Estates of persons dying intestate)</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-23.2.list4.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>proceedings under the Indian Succession Act, 1865 (10   of 1865) 3, and the Probate and Administration Act, 1881 (5 of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1881">
          <num>1881.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1881.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1881.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>) 3, which cannot be disposed of by District Delegates; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1881.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>references by Collectors under section 322C of the Code  of Civil Procedure. 4 (14 of 1882)</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-1881.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The District Judge may withdraw any such proceedings taken  cognizance of by, or transferred to, a Subordinate Judge or Munsif,</p>
              <p>and may either himself dispose of them or transfer them to a Court  under his administrative control competent to dispose of them.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Disposal of proceedings referred to in last foregoing  section.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-24.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Proceedings taken cognizance of by, or transferred to, a</p>
              <p>Subordinate Judge or Munsif, as the case may be, under the last  foregoing section shall be disposed of by him subject to the rules  applicable to like proceedings when disposed of by the District Judge:</p>
              <p>Provided that an appeal from an order of the Munsif in any such  proceedings shall lie to the District Judge.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-24.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An appeal from the order of the District Judge on the appeal  from the order of a munsif under this section shall lie to the High</p>
              <p>Court if a further appeal from the order of the District Judge is  allowed by the law for the time being in force.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Power to invest Subordinate Judges and Munsifs with Small</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Cause court jurisdiction. The State Government may, by notification in  the Official Gazette, confer, within such local limits as it thinks  fit, upon any Subordinate Judge or Munsif the jurisdiction of a Judge  of a Court</p>
              <p>of Small Causes under the Provincial Small Cause Courts Act, 1887</p>
              <p>(9 of 1887) for the trial of suits, cognizable by such Courts, up to  such value not exceeding five hundred 1 rupees in the case of a Subord-</p>
              <p>inate Judge or  two hundred and fifty 1 rupees] in the case of a Mun-</p>
              <p>sif as it thinks fit, and may withdraw any jurisdiction so conferred:</p>
              <p>Provided that the State Government may, by notification in the</p>
              <p>Official Gazette, delegate to the High Court its powers under this  section.]</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>Misfeasance.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <heading>.- Misfeasance. Rep. by the A. O. 1937.</heading>
        <paragraph id="chapter-V.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>CHAP</p>
            <p>Ministerial Officers.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VI">
        <num>VI</num>
        <heading>.- Ministerial Officers. Rep., ibid.</heading>
        <paragraph id="chapter-VI.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>CHAP</p>
            <p>SUPPLEMENTAL PROVISIONS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VII">
        <num>VII</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-VII.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>SUPPLEMENTAL PROVISIONS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-36">
          <num>36.</num>
          <heading>Power to confer powers of Civil Courts on officers.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-36.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The</p>
              <blockList id="section-36.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>State Government may invest with the powers of any Civil Court under  this Act, by name or in virtue of office,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-36.1.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>any officer in the Chutia Nagpur,  Sambalpur,]</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-36.1.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Jalpaiguri or Darjeeling District, or in any part of the  territories administered by the Chief Commissioner of Assam  except the district of Sylhet, or,</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-36.1.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>after consultation with the High Court, any officer  serving in any other part of the territories to which this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Act extends and belonging to a class defined in this behalf  by the State Government .</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in  sections 4, 5, 6, 8, 10 or 11] applies to any  officer so invested, but all the other provisions of this Act shall,</p>
              <p>so far as</p>
              <p>those provisions can be made applicable, apply to him as if he were a</p>
              <p>Judge of the Court with the powers of which he is invested.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where, in the territories mentioned in clause (a) of sub-</p>
              <p>section (1), the same local jurisdiction is assigned to two or more  officers invested with the powers of a Munsif, the officer invested  with the powers of a District Judge may, with the previous sanction of  the State Government, delegate his functions under sub- section (2) of  section 13 to an officer invested with the powers of a Subordinate</p>
              <p>Judge or to one of the officers invested with the powers of a Munsif.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where the place at which the Court of an officer invested  with powers under sub- section (1) is to be held has not been fixed  under section 14, the Court may be held at any place within the local  limits of its jurisdiction.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-37">
          <num>37.</num>
          <heading>Certain decisions to be according to Native law.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-37.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where  in any suit or other proceeding it is necessary for a Civil Court to  decide any question regarding succession, inheritance, marriage or  caste, or any religious usage or institution, the Muhammadan law in  cases where the parties are Muhammadans, and the Hindu law in cases  where the parties are Hindus, shall form the rule of decision except  in so far as such law has, by legislative enactment, been altered or  abolished.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-37.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In cases not provided for by sub- section (1) or by any other  law for the time being in force, the Court shall act according to  justice, equity and good conscience.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-38">
          <num>38.</num>
          <heading>Judges not to try suits in which they are interested.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-38.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The presiding officer of a Civil Court shall not try any suit or other  proceeding to which he is a party or in which he is personally  interested.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-38.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The presiding officer of an appellate Civil Court under this</p>
              <p>Act shall not try an appeal against a decree or order passed by him  self in another capacity.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-38.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When any such suit, proceeding or appeal as is referred to  in sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) comes before any such officer,</p>
              <p>the officer shall forthwith transmit the record of the case to the</p>
              <p>Court to which he is immediately subordinate, with a report of the  circumstances attending the reference.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-38.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The superior Court shall thereupon dispose of the case under  section 25 of the Code (14 of 1882) of Civil Procedure. 1</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-38.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in this section shall be deemed to affect the extra-</p>
              <p>ordinary original civil jurisdiction of the High Court.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-39">
          <num>39.</num>
          <heading>Subordination of Courts to District Court. For the purposes of  the last foregoing section the Presiding officer of a Court subject to  the administrative control of the District Judge shall be deemed to be  immediately subordinate to the Court of the District Judge, and, for  the purposes of the Code of Civil Procedure (14 of 1882), the Court of  such an officer shall be deemed to be of a grade inferior to that of  the Court of the District Judge.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-40">
          <num>40.</num>
          <heading>Application of Act to State Courts of Small Causes.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-40.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This  section and sections 15, 32, 37, 38 and 39 apply to Courts of Small</p>
              <p>Causes constituted under the Provincial Small Cause Courts Act,</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1887">
          <num>1887.</num>
          <heading>(9 of 1887).</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1887.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Save as provided by that Act, the other sections of this Act  do not apply to those Courts.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
