<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1838/19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1838/19"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Coasting- Vessels Act, 1838"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1838/19/eng@1838-08-27/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1838/19/eng@1838-08-27"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1838-08-27" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1838/19/eng@1838-08-27/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1838/19/eng@1838-08-27"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-11-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Coasting- Vessels Act, 1838]</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 19 OF 1838</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 27th August, 1838]</docDate>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Extent.-- This Act extends in the first instance  to  the territories which, immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were  comprised in the States] of Bombay, Saurashtra and Kutch, but the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette,</p>
            <p>extend it to any other State  or part of a State] which has a  sea- coast.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Rules as to coasting and other vessels belonging to any  citizen of India.--  The following rules shall be in force with  respect to vessels belonging to  any citizen of India] , and  employed on the coasts of  any State  or part of a State] to  which this Act extends] or in trading coastwise, as also with respect  to fishing- vessels and harbour- craft belonging to  any such  citizen].</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Marking or branding vessels with name of place and number.-- 11</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every such vessel employed as aforesaid, fishing- vessel and  harbour- craft shall be marked or branded with the name of the place to  which she belongs, and also with a number assigned for the same by the  officer authorised to make such registry as is hereinafter mentioned;</p>
            <p>Owner to paint name and number-- and the owner or owners of such  vessel employed as aforesaid, fishing- vessel and harbour- craft shall  cause such name and number to be painted in black paint upon a white  ground on each quarter of such vessel employed as aforesaid, fishing-</p>
            <p>vessel and harbour- craft, in English figures and letters, each figure  and letter being six inches in length.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Registry of name, number and burthen.--  The name and  number of every such vessels employed as aforesaid, fishing- vessel and  harbour- craft, and her burthen, and also the name or names of the  owner or owners thereof, shall be registered in a book to be kept for  that purpose by the person hereinafter directed to make such registry.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Registry by whom to be made. Fresh registration.-- At Bombay such  registry shall be made by the  Principal Officer, Mercantile</p>
            <p>Marine Department, and at other places  by the Collector of Sea-</p>
            <p>customs at such places respectively, or by such other person as shall  be appointed by the  Central Government] to act at such places  respectively, in the execution of this Act; and whenever any change  shall take place in the burthen of such vessel employed as aforesaid,</p>
            <p>fishing- vessel or harbour- craft, or in the name or names of the owner  or owners thereof, such registry shall be made again:</p>
            <p>Provided, however, that it shall not be lawful to give any name  to such vessel employed as aforesaid, fishing- vessel or harbour- craft,</p>
            <p>other than that by which she was first registered.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Owners to apply for registry.--  The owner or owners of  every such vessel employed as aforesaid, fishing- vessel and harbour-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>craft shall apply to the person authorised to make such registry in  respect of the same, in order to have such registry as aforesaid made,</p>
            <p>or in order to have such registry made again as aforesaid.</p>
            <p>Information of registry at subordinate port.-- And whenever such  vessel employed as aforesaid, fishing- vessel or harbour- craft is  registered at a subordinate port, information thereof, and of the  number there assigned to her, shall immediately be given by the  registering officer to the Principal Officer, Mercantile Marine</p>
            <p>Department at Bombay.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Officers to perform duty of marking and branding.--  The  duty of marking or branding and of ascertaining the burthen of such  vessels employed as aforesaid, fishing- vessels and harbour- craft, at</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Bombay, shall be performed by the  Principal Officer, Mercantile</p>
            <p>Marine Department]; and at all other places  the duty of marking  or branding and of ascertaining the burthen of such vessels employed  as aforesaid, fishing- vessels and harbour- craft shall be performed by  the Collector of Sea- customs at such places respectively, or by such  other persons as shall be appointed by the  Central Government]</p>
            <p>to act at such places respectively, in the execution of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Owner to obtain certificate of registry Replacing lost  certificate.--  The owner or owners of every such vessel employed  as aforesaid, fishing- vessel and harbour- craft shall apply for and  obtain a certificate of registry from the person authorised to make  such registry as aforesaid, and such certificate shall be in the form  specified in the Schedule appended to this Act; and in the case of any  certificate being lost or destroyed, a renewed certificate may be  obtained in the same manner and on payment of the fees hereinafter  mentioned.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Sealing certificate.--  Such certificate of registry shall  be sealed with the seal of the  Government of India], and shall  be signed by the person authorised to make such registry.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Fees for certificate.-- The owner or owners of such  vessels employed as aforesaid (fishing- vessels and harbour- craft being   excepted) on being registered as aforesaid, shall pay-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>for each certificate of registry for a vessel not exceeding 5  tons burthen, the fee of... 1 rupee;</p>
            <p>for each certificate for a vessel exceeding 5 tons burthen and  not exceeding 25 tons burthen, the fee of.... 5 rupees;</p>
            <p>for each certificate for a vessel exceeding 25 tons burthen and  not exceeding 100 tons burthen, the fee of 7 rupees;</p>
            <p>and for each certificate for a vessel of 100 tons or greater  burthen, per ton, the fee of... 2 annas.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Fees to be credited to Government.--  The person or  persons so authorised to make such registry as aforesaid shall receive  the fees payable for the same, and shall pay such fees to such officer  as  the Central Government] shall appoint; the same to be carried  to the credit of  the Central Government]:</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Provided that any such fees as immediately before the  commencement of  the Constitution] were, under this Act as then  in force to be carried to the credit of the  Provincial</p>
            <p>Government] shall be paid to such officer as the State Government may  appoint and be carried to the credit of that Government.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Production of certificate on demand.--  The owner or  owners or commander of every such Vessel employed as aforesaid,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>fishing- vessel and harbour- craft shall produce, on demand thereof by  any officer of the Customs  or by any officer of the  Navy, the  certificate so directed to be applied for and obtained in respect of  such vessel employed as aforesaid, fishing- vessel or harbour- craft, as  above mentioned.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for neglect to comply with rules.--  In case any  such vessel employed as aforesaid, fishing- vessel or harbour- craft  shall not be so marked or branded in all respects as hereinbefore  directed, or in case the name and number of any such vessel employed  as aforesaid, fishing- vessel or harbour- craft shall not be so painted,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>or shall not continue so painted on such vessel employed as aforesaid,</p>
            <p>fishing- vessel or harbour- craft, in all respects as hereinbefore  directed;</p>
            <p>or in case any such vessel employed as aforesaid, fishing- vessel  or harbour- craft shall not be furnished with such certificate as  hereinbefore specified, or in case the owner or owners or commander of  any such vessel employed as aforesaid, fishing- vessel or harbour- craft  shall not produce such certificate on demand thereof as hereinbefore  directed;</p>
            <p>the owner or owners of every such vessel employed as aforesaid  shall be subject to a fine of ten times the amount of the fees payable  in respect of the certificate of registry of such vessel, the same  being a vessel for the certificate of the registration of which any  fee is payable; and the owner or owners of any such fishing- vessel or  harbour- craft shall be subject to a fine of ten rupees;</p>
            <p>Recovery of penalties-- which fines may be recovered on conviction  before any Magistrate  Having jurisdiction,  by sale of such  vessel, fishing- vessel or harbour- craft, her furniture, ammunition,</p>
            <p>tackle and apparel;</p>
            <p>Penalty on repetition of default-- and such fines shall be payable  as often as the owner or owners or commander of any such vessel  employed as aforesaid, fishing- vessel or harbour- craft shall make such  default as aforesaid: Provided every such subsequent default be made  after the expiration of one month from the date of the last  conviction.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Power to direct compensation for trouble in seizing.--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The  Central Government] may direct compensation for trouble and  diligence in seizing such vessel employed as aforesaid, fishing- vessel  or harbour- craft, guns, furniture, tackle, ammunition and apparel, as  last mentioned, to be made, out of the proceeds of such seizure to the  person or persons who shall have seized the same, to such amount, in  such manner and in such shares or proportions, as to the said</p>
            <p>Central Government] shall seem meet.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Port- clearance. Rep. partly by the Repealing Act, 1874 (16 of 1874),</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>s. 1 and Sch., Pt. I, and partly by the Repealing Act, 1876 (12 of</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1876">
        <num>1876.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1876.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>), s. 1 and Sch., Pt. I.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
