<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/64/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/64"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Evacuee Interest (Separation) Act, 1951"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/64/eng@1951-10-31/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/64/eng@1951-10-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1951-10-31" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/64/eng@1951-10-31/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/64/eng@1951-10-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Evacuee Interest (Separation) Act, 1951</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 64 OF 1951</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 31st October, 1951.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it therefore enacted by Parliament as follows:-</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to make special provisions for the separation of the interests  of evacuees from those of other persons in property in which such  other persons are also interested and for matters connected therewith.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to make special provisions for the  separation of the interests of evacuees from those of other persons in  property in which such other persons are also interested and for  matters connected therewith;</p>
        <p>AND WHEREAS some of the aforesaid provisions may relate to  certain matters in the State List and Parliament is empowered, in  pursuance of a Resolution passed under Article 249 of the</p>
        <p>Constitution, to make such laws;</p>
        <p>CHAP</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title and extent.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the Evacuee</p>
              <p>Interest (Separation) Act, 1951.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It extends to the whole of India except  the territories  which, immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised in  the States] of Assam, West Bengal, Tripura, Manipur and Jammu and</p>
              <p>Kashmir.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" appellate officer" means an officer appointed as such  by the State Government under section 13;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>" claim" means the assertion by any person, not being an  evacuee, of any right, title or interest in any  property--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>as a co- sharer or partner of an evacuee in the  property; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>as a mortgagee of the interest of an evacuee  in the property; or</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Supplemented in:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>Am., in Panjab by Punjab Act 15 of 1960.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>Kerala in Kerala Act 15 of 1960.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>Andhra Pradesh by Andhra Pradesh Act 28 of 1960.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>U. P by U. P. Act 5 of 1961.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>Bihar by Bihar Act 20 of 1960.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>Madras by Madras 3 of 1961.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>Rajasthan by Rajasthan Act 1 of 1961.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.h.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>Mysore by Mysore Act 3 of 1961.</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.h.list0.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>as a mortgagor having mortgaged the property  or any interest therein in favour of an evacuee;</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>and includes any other interest which such person may  have jointly with an evacuee and which is notified in  this behalf by the Central Government in the Official</p>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Gazette;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" competent officer" means an officer appointed as such  by the State Government under section 4;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" composite property" means any property which, or any  property in which an interest, has been declared to be  evacuee property or has vested in the Custodian under  the Administration of Evacuee Property Act, 1950 (31 of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1956">
          <num>1956.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1956.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>), and--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>in which the interest of the evacuee consists  of an undivided share in the property held by him as a  co- sharer or partner of any other person, not being an  evacuee; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>in which the interest of the evacuee is  subject to mortgage in any form in favour of a person,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>not being an evacuee; or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list3.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>in which the interest of a person, not being  an evacuee, is subject to mortgage in any form in  favour of an evacuee; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list3.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>in which an evacuee has such other interest  jointly with any other person, not being an evacuee, as  may be notified in this behalf by the Central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Government, in the Official Gazette;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list5.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>" evacuee interest", in relation to a composite  property, means the right, title and interest of an  evacuee in that property;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list5.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>" mortgage debt" means any liability in respect of a  property due under any form of mortgage (including any   usufructuary mortgage or mortgage by conditional sale)</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list7">
                <listIntroduction>whether such liability is payable presently or in  future, or under any decree or order of a Court or  otherwise, or whether ascertained or not, which--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list7.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>in any case where it is incurred by an  evacuee, is secured by the mortgage of the interest of  the evacuee in the property in favour of a person, not  being an evacuee;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list7.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>in any case where it is incurred by a person  not being an evacuee, is secured by the mortgage of the  interest of such person in the property in favour of an  evacuee;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>but does not include any such liability of an evacuee  arising out of any transaction entered into after the</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14th">
          <num>14th.</num>
          <heading>day of August, 1947 unless such transaction has  been confirmed by the Custodian under the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14th.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Administration of Evacuee Property Act, 1950 (31 of</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1950">
          <num>1950.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1950.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>);</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list3.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list3.h.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>" principal money", in relation to a mortgage deed  executed by an evacuee, means--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list3.h.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>in the case of a mortgage deed which has not  been executed by way of renewal of a prior mortgage  deed, the sum of money advanced by way of loan at the  time of the execution of the mortgage deed;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-1950.paragraph-0.list3.h.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>in the case of a mortgage deed which has been  executed at any time before the 1st day of January,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1940">
          <num>1940.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1940.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1940.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>, by way of renewal of a prior mortgage deed, the  consideration for which the renewed mortgage deed was  executed;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1940.paragraph-0.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>in the case of a mortgage deed which has  been executed at any time after the 1st day of January,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1940">
          <num>1940.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1940.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1940.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>, by way of renewal of a prior mortgage deed  executed before that date, the sum of money which  became due on the 1st day of January, 1940, on account  of the money advanced on the prior mortgage deed and  interest thereon up to the said date;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1940.paragraph-0.list1.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>in the case of a mortgage deed which was  executed at any time after the 1st day of January,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1940">
          <num>1940.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1940.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>, by way of renewal of a prior mortgage deed which  was also executed after that date, the sum of money  advanced by way of loan at the time of the execution of  the prior mortgage deed;</p>
              <p>Explanation.-- For the purpose of calculating the  principal money in relation to any mortgage deed which  has been executed by way of renewal of a prior mortgage  deed, any sum of money advanced at the time of such  renewal in addition to the sum of money which</p>
              <blockList id="section-1940.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>was due on the prior mortgage deed shall also be taken  into account.</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1940.paragraph-0.list3.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>all words and expressions used, but not defined in this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Act and defined in the Administration of Evacuee</p>
              <p>Property Act, 1950 (31 of 1950), shall have the  meanings assigned to them in that Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Act to override other laws. Save as otherwise expressly  provided in this Act, the provisions of this Act and of the rules and  orders made thereunder shall have effect notwithstanding anything  inconsistent therewith contained in any other law for the time being  in force or in any instrument having effect by virtue of any such law.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>SEPARATION OF EVACUEE INTEREST IN COMPOSITE PROPERTY</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>SEPARATION OF EVACUEE INTEREST IN COMPOSITE PROPERTY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Power to appoint competent officers.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government  may, with the approval of the Central Government, by notification in  the Official Gazette, appoint as many competent officers as may be  necessary for the purpose of performing the functions assigned to them  by or under this Act, and a competent officer may perform his  functions in such local area or areas as may be specified in the  notification.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No person shall be qualified to be appointed as a competent  officer under this Act unless he has held a judicial office for at  least five years, or has been an advocate or a pleader for at least  seven years.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Jurisdiction of competent officers. A competent officer shall  have jurisdiction to decide any claim relating to any composite  property situate within the limits of the local area of his  jurisdiction and such cases or classes of cases as may, by general or  special order, be transferred to him under section 19 by the Central</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government or the appellate officer.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Notice to submit claims.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-6.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>For the purpose of determining or  separating the evacuee interest in a composite property, any competent  officer having jurisdiction over such property may, either on  information received in this behalf from the Custodian or on an  application from a claimant, issue, in such form and manner as may be  prescribed,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>a general notice requiring all persons who claim  interest in such property, and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>also a notice on every person who, in the opinion of  the competent officer, may have a claim in such  property, to submit claims, if any, in respect of that  property.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An application under sub- section (1) shall be in such form  and manner as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No application under this section shall be entertained if  filed after the expiry of one year from the commencement of the</p>
              <p>Evacuee Interest (Separation) Amendment Act, 1960 (27 of 1960).]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Submission of claims.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person claiming an interest in a  composite property may, within sixty days of the date of the issue of  the general notice or service of individual notice under section 6,</p>
              <p>whichever is later, submit to the competent officer a statement of his  claim in writing and signed and verified in the prescribed manner.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A statement of claim under sub- section (1) shall be drawn up,</p>
              <p>as far as may be, in the form of pleadings under the Code of Civil</p>
              <blockList id="section-7.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) and shall include the following  particulars, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.2.list3.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the nature of the interest of the claimant in the  composite property;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.2.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the estimated money value of the composite property;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.2.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>where the claim is made by a co- sharer or partner, the  extent of the share of the claimant and the money value  of such share;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.2.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-7.2.list3.d.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>where the claim is made by a mortgagee,--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-7.2.list3.d.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>the principal money and the rate of interest  chargeable under the mortgage deed;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-7.2.list3.d.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>payments made towards the mortgage debt after  the principal money was advanced or deemed to have been  advanced;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-7.2.list3.d.list0.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>the history of the mortgage debt in so far  as it is relevant to the determination of the principal  money;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-7.2.list3.d.list0.iv">
                      <num>(iv)</num>
                      <p>particulars of the property mortgaged and the  estimated value of such property;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-7.2.list3.d.list0.v">
                      <num>(v)</num>
                      <p>particulars of any property the possession of  which has been taken by the mortgagee as security for,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-7.2.list5">
                <listIntroduction>or in lieu of payment of, the mortgage debt;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.2.list5.vi">
                  <num>(vi)</num>
                  <p>the total amount claimed under the mortgage  debt in accordance with the provisions of this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.2.list5.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>where the claim is made by a mortgagor, the total  amount due under the mortgage debt and the particulars  necessary to determine the same;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.2.list5.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the order of preference in which the claimant desires  to have his interest separated from that of the evacuee  under section 10;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.2.list5.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>any other particulars which may be prescribed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The claimant shall, along with the submission of claim under  sub- section (1), file true copies of all documents in his possession  or power on which the claim is based and a list of any other documents</p>
              <p>(whether in his possession or power or not) on which he intends to  rely as evidence in support of his claim; and the claimant shall,</p>
              <p>whenever required to do so by the competent officer, produce all the  documents of which true copies have been filed and also the documents  in his possession or power which have been entered in the list.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No document which should have been but has not been filed in  accordance with the requirements of sub- section (3), shall be received  at any stage of the proceedings without the leave of the competent  officer.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Decision by competent officer.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-8.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>On receipt of a statement  of claim under section 7, the competent officer shall, subject to the  provisions of sub- sections (2) and (3), hold an inquiry into the claim  in accordance with the procedure laid down in section 17 and pass an  order determining the interest of the evacuee and the claimant in the  property in question and the order shall contain all or any of the  following particulars, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the money value of the property;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>in any case where the evacuee and the claimant are co-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-8.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>sharers or partners, their respective shares in the  property and the money value of such shares;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.1.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>in any case where the claim is made by a mortgagor, the  amount due to the evacuee;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.1.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>in any case where the claim is made by a mortgagee, the  amount due under the claim in accordance with the  provisions of section 9.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where the Custodian under the Administration of Evacuee</p>
              <p>Property Act, 1950 (31 of 1950), has determined that the property in  question or</p>
              <p>any interest therein is evacuee property, the decision of the</p>
              <p>Custodian shall be binding on the competent officer:</p>
              <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall debar  the competent officer from determining the mortgage debt in respect of  such property or any interest therein or from separating the interest  of the evacuee from that of the claimant under section 10.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If there is any dispute as to whether a liability is a  mortgage debt or not or whether any claim submitted under section 7  exists, the competent officer shall decide such dispute:</p>
              <p>Provided that a decree of a Civil Court (other than an ex- parte   decree passed after the 14th day of August, 1947) shall, subject to  the provisions of sections 9 and 10, be binding on the competent  officer in respect of any matter which has been finally decided by  such decree; and where any matter was decided by an ex- parte decree  passed by a Civil Court after the 14th day of August, 1947, the  competent officer may decide such matter afresh and on such decision  being made, the ex- parte decree shall be deemed to have no effect.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Certain reliefs in respect of mortgaged property of evacuees.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything to the contrary in any law or contract or  any decree or order of a Civil Court or other authority, where the  claim is made by a mortgagee, no mortgaged property of an evacuee  shall, subject to the provisions of sub- section (2), be liable for the  payment of interest at a rate exceeding five per cent. per annum  simple on the principal money advanced or deemed to have been  advanced.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where a mortgagee has taken possession on any terms  whatsoever of any agricultural land and is entitled to receive profits  accruing from the land and to appropriate the same, every such  mortgage shall be deemed to have taken effect as a complete  usufructuary mortgage period mentioned in the mortgage deed or twenty  years, whichever is less, from the date of the execution of the  mortgage deed; and if the aforesaid period has not expired and the  mortgage debt has not been extinguished, the competent officer shall  determine the mortgage debt due having regard to the proportion which  the unexpired portion of that period bears to the total of that  period.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Separation of the interests of evacuees from those of  claimants in composite property. Notwithstanding anything to the  contrary in any law or contract or any decree or order of a Civil</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Court or other authority, the competent officer may, subject to any  rules that may be made in this behalf, take all such measures as he  may consider necessary for the</p>
              <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>purpose of separating the interests of the evacuees from those of the  claimants in any composite property, and in particular may,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list2.a.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>in the case of any claim of a co- sharer or partner,--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list2.a.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>direct the Custodian to pay to the claimant  the amount of money assessed in respect of his share in  the composite property or deposit the same in a Civil</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Court having jurisdiction over such property and  deliver possession of the property to the Custodian and  the claimant may withdraw the amount in deposit in the</p>
              <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Civil Court; or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list5.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>transfer the property to the claimant on  payment by him of the amount of money assessed in  respect of the share of the evacuee in the property;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list7">
                <listIntroduction>or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list7.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>sell the property and distribute the sale  proceeds thereof between the Custodian and the claimant  in proportion to the share of the evacuee and of the  claimant in the property; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list7.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>partition the property according to shares of  the evacuee and the claimant and deliver possession of  the shares allotted to the evacuee and the claimant to  the Custodian and the claimant respectively;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list7.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>in the case of any claim of a mortgagor or a  mortgagee,--</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list7.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>pay to the Custodian or the claimant the  amount payable under the mortgage debt and redeem the  mortgaged property; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list7.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>sell the mortgaged property for satisfaction  of the mortgage debt and distribute the sale proceeds  thereof; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list7.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>partition the property between the mortgagor  and the mortgagee having regard to the share to which  the mortgagee would be entitled in lieu of his claim;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list7.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>adopt a combination of all or some of the aforesaid  measures:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that before taking any measure under this section, the  competent officer shall take into account the order of preference  filed by the claimant under clause (f) of sub- section (2) of section 7</p>
              <p>; and in any case where the claimant is a mortgagor and tenders the  amount due, the competent officer shall accept the same in full  satisfaction of the mortgage debt.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Vesting of evacuee interest in the Custodian free from  encumbrances and payments, etc., to be valid discharge from all  claims.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where in respect of any property, notice under section 6  is issued but no claim is filed or found to exist or where any claim  in</p>
              <p>respect of such property is found to exist and the competent officer  separates the evacuee interest therein under section 10, the whole  property, or, as the case may be, the evacuee interest in the property  thus separated shall vest in the Custodian free from all encumbrances  and liabilities and any payment, transfer or partition made or  effected under section 10, in satisfaction of any claim in respect of  the property shall be a full and valid discharge of all claims in  respect of the property.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Custodian may take possession of any such property by  evicting the claimant and other persons who may be in occupation  thereof and may, for that purpose, use or cause to be used such force  as may be necessary:</p>
              <p>Provided that the Custodian shall not disturb the possession of  any person (other than the claimant) who was in lawful possession of  the property at the commencement of this Act and has continued in such  possession.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Rights of claimants inter se and by other persons against  claimants not to be affected. Nothing in this Chapter shall prejudice  any rights in respect of the property transferred or delivered, or  payment made, to a claimant under the provisions of this Act which any  other claimant or other person may be entitled by due process of law  to enforce against the claimant to whom the property is delivered or  transferred or the payment is made.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>APPEAL, REVISION AND POWERS AND PROCEDURE OF COMPETENT OFFICERS ANDAPPELLATE</p>
              <p>OFFICERS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>APPEAL, REVISION AND POWERS AND PROCEDURE OF COMPETENT OFFICERS</p>
            <p>AND APPELLATE OFFICERS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Power to appoint appellate officers.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-13.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government  with the approval of the Central Government may, by notification in  the Official Gazette, appoint as many appellate officers as may be  necessary for the purpose of hearing appeals against the orders of the  competent officers and an appellate officer shall have jurisdiction  over such local area or areas as may be specified in the notification.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-13.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>No person shall be qualified to be appointed as an appellate  officer under this Act unless such person--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-13.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>is, or has been, or is qualified for appointment as, a</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-13.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Judge of a High Court; or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-13.2.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>is, or has been, a District Judge.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Appeals.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person aggrieved by an order of the  competent officer made under section 8 or section 10 may, within sixty  days from the date of the order, prefer an appeal to the appellate  officer in such form and manner as may be prescribed:</p>
              <p>Provided that the appellate officer may entertain the appeal  after the expiry of the said period of sixty days if he is satisfied  that the appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from filing the  appeal in time.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The appellate officer may, after hearing the appeal, confirm,</p>
              <p>vary or reverse the order appealed from and may pass such orders as he  deems fit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Power of revision of the appellate officer. The appellate  officer may at any time call for the record of any proceeding in which  the competent officer has passed an order for the purpose of  satisfying himself as to the legality or propriety of any such order  and may pass such order in relation thereto as he thinks fit:</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Provided that the appellate officer shall not pass an order under  this section prejudicially to any person without giving him a  reasonable opportunity of being heard.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Amendment of orders. Clerical or arithmetical mistakes in  orders passed by a competent officer or an appellate officer or errors  arising therein from any accidental slip or omission, may, at any  time, be corrected by the competent officer or the appellate officer  either of his own motion or on an application received in this behalf  from any of the parties.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Powers and procedure of competent officers and appellate  officers.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A competent officer or an appellate officer shall, for  the purpose of holding any inquiry or hearing any appeal under this</p>
              <p>Act, have the same powers as are vested in a Civil Court under the</p>
              <blockList id="section-17.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), when trying a suit in  respect of the following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.1.list3.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person  and examining him on oath;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.1.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>requiring the discovery and production of documents;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.1.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.1.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>any other matter which may be prescribed;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>and any proceeding before the competent officer or the appellate  officer shall be deemed to be a judicial proceeding within the meaning  of section 193 and 228 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860), and the  competent</p>
              <p>officer or the appellate officer shall be deemed to be a Civil Court  within the meaning of sections 480 and 482 of the Code of Criminal</p>
              <p>Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An appellate officer shall, subject to the provisions of this</p>
              <p>Act, have such further powers as are vested in a Court under the Code  of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), when hearing an appeal.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to any rules made in this behalf, the competent  officer and appellate officer shall follow the same procedure as a</p>
              <p>Civil Court does in regard to civil suits including recording of  evidence and the provisions of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1908">
          <num>1908.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1908.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>) shall, as far as may be, apply to such proceedings.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Finality of orders. Save as otherwise expressly provided in  this Act, every order made by any appellate officer or competent  officer shall be final and shall not be called in question in any</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Court by way of an appeal or revision or in any original suit,</p>
              <p>application or execution proceedings.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Power to transfer cases.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-19.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government or the  appellate officer may, by order in writing at any time, transfer any  case pending before a competent officer to another competent officer  for holding the inquiry and the competent officer to whom the case is  so transferred may proceed either de novo or from the stage at which  it was transferred.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government or the State Government may, by order  in writing at any time, transfer any appeal pending before an  appellate officer to another appellate officer for hearing the appeal  and the appellate officer to whom the appeal is so transferred may  proceed either de novo or from the stage at which it was transferred.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Jurisdiction of Civil Courts barred in certain matters.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-20.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Save as otherwise expressly provided in this Act, no Civil or Revenue</p>
              <p>Court shall entertain any suit or proceeding in so far as it relates  to any claim to composite property which the competent officer is  empowered by or under this Act to decide, and no injunction in respect  of any action taken or to be taken by the competent officer in respect  of the composite property shall be granted by any Civil Court or other  authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All suits and proceedings pending before a Civil or Revenue</p>
              <p>Court at the commencement of this Act shall, in so far as they relate</p>
              <p>to any claim filed before a competent officer under section 7, be  stayed during the pendency of any proceeding under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in sub- section (1) shall prevent any Civil or Revenue</p>
              <p>Court from entertaining any suit or proceeding relating to any right  in respect of any payment made, or property transferred or delivered,</p>
              <p>to a claimant under the provisions of this Act which any other  claimant or other person may be entitled by due process of law to  enforce against the claimant to whom the payment is made or the  property is delivered or transferred.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Competent officer and appellate officer to be a public  servant. Every competent officer and appellate officer shall be deemed  to be a public servant within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Penal Code (45 of 1860).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the appellate  officer or the competent officer in respect of anything which is in  good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or of  any rules or orders made thereunder.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-23.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules  to carry out the  purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-23.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-23.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the form of any notice and the manner of its service;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the form and manner in which an application may be  filed under section 6;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the form and manner in which claims may be submitted  and the particulars which a statement of claim may  contain;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which inquiries under this Act may be  held and the procedure to be followed by competent  officers in such proceedings;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the form and manner in which appeals may be preferred  against the order of competent officers and the  procedure to be followed by appellate officers;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.2.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the powers vested in a Civil Court which may be  exercised by the competent officers and appellate  officers while</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-23.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>holding an inquiry or hearing an appeal, as the case  may be, under this Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-23.2.list3.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the manner of separating the interests of the evacuees  from those of claimants in any composite property;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.2.list3.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>any other matter which has to be, or may be, prescribed  under this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
