<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-nag/act/1965/05/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-nag/act/1965/05"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Nagaland Police Enhanced Disciplinary Powers Act, 1965"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-nag/act/1965/05/eng@2017-01-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-nag/act/1965/05/eng@2017-01-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-nag/act/1965/05/eng@2017-01-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-nag/act/1965/05/eng@2017-01-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Nagaland Police Enhanced Disciplinary Powers Act, 1965</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[26th April, 1965]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[Act 5 of 1965]</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for regulation and maintenance of discipline in Nagaland Police Forces and the Nagaland Armed Police Battalion.</p>
        <p>Preamble.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the regulation and maintenance of discipline in the Nagaland Police Forces and the Naga¬land Armed Police Battalion;</p>
        <p>It is hereby enacted in the Sixteenth Year of the Republic of India as. follows :—</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act nay be called the Nagaland Police Enhanced Disciplinary Powers Act; 1963.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to whole of Nagaland and applies to all members of the Nagaland Police Forces and the Nagaland Armed Police Battalion wherever they may be serving.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force at once.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>General superintendence and control of the Nagaland Armed Police Battalion.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The General superintendence and control of the Nagaland Armed Police Battalion shall be exercised by such person or authority as the State Government may appoint in this behalf, designated the "Commandant of Nagaland Armed Police Battalion" and in exercise of such superintendence and Control the, person or authority so appointed shall be governed by Police Act, 1861 (V of 1861).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Power of Punishment.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in section 7 (b) of Police Act, 1861 (Act V of 1861), any Police Officer below the rank of Sub Inspector of Police or any member of the Nagaland Armed Police Battalion below the rank of Sub-Inspector of Police who shall discharge his duty in a careless or negligent manner or who by any act of his own shall render himself unfit for the discharge thereof, may be awarded with the following punishment by the different authorities subject to the maximum period noted against each:-</p>
            <table id="section-3.1.table1">
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p/>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>Authority</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>Punishment</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>Maximum Period</p>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p>(a)</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p/>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p/>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p>(i)</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>The Superintendent of Police in regard to the District Police Force.</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>Confinement in the quarter-guard</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>28 days</p>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p>(ii)</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>The Principal of the Police Training College in regard to the personnel under training in the College.</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>“</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p>(iii)</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>The Commandant of the Nagaland Armed. Police Battalion, in regard to the person­nel of the Nagaland Armed Police Battalion and trainees of “other units” under his com­mand for the time being, and;</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>“</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p>(iv)</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>Any other officer of the rank of Superintendent of Police in respect of Police personnel under his command.</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>“</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p>(b)</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p/>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p/>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p>(i)</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>Deputy Superintendent of Police in regard to District Police force, and</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>Confinement, in the quarter-guard room or lines, punishment drill, extra guard, fatigue or other duty.</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>7 days</p>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p>(ii)</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>Deputy Commandant of the Nagaland Armed Police Battalion in regard-to the. personnel of the Nagaland Armed Police Battalion.</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>“</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p>(c)</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p/>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p/>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p/>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                  <p/>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>Inspector or Sub-Inspec­tor of Police in charge of a circle or thanas or in charge of independent detachments of the Naga­land Police Battalion in regard to the District Police Force employed in the Circle or thana or personnel of Nagaland Armed Police Battalion under his corn wand.</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p>Confinement in the quarter-guard room or lines, punish­ment drill, extraguard, fatigue or other duty.</p>
                </td>
                <td>
                  <p/>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </table>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In addition to the above, the Commandant of the Nagaland Armed Police Battalion shall have powers to award all other punishment admissible under section: 7 of the Police Act (Act V of 1861).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Effect.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>This Act is in addition and not derogatory to Police Act 1861 (Act V of 1861)</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
