<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1992/1/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1992/1"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Government Of National Capital Territory Of Delhi Act, 1991"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1992/1/eng@1992-01-02/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1992/1/eng@1992-01-02"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1992-01-02" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1992/1/eng@1992-01-02/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1992/1/eng@1992-01-02"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Government Of National Capital Territory Of Delhi Act, 1991</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>NO. 1 OF 1992</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 2nd January, 1992.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- second Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to supplement the provisions of the Constitution relating to  the Legislative Assembly and a Council of Ministers for the National</p>
        <p>Capital Territory of Delhi and for matters connected therewith or  incidental thereto.</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:--</p>
        <p>PART</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <part id="part-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="part-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the</p>
              <p>Government of National Capital Territory of Delhi Act, 1991.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on such date 1 as the Central</p>
              <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint:</p>
              <p>Provided that different dates may be appointed for different  provisions of this Act and any reference in any such provision to the  commencement of this Act shall be construed as a reference to the  coming into force of that provision.</p>
              <p>The Provisions of section 56 of this Act, shall come into force  on 29. 11. 1993 vide Notification No. S. O. 910 (E), dated 29. 11. 1993.</p>
              <p>The provisions of sections 46, 47 and 48 of this Act, shall come  into force on 25. 11. 1993 vide Notification No. S. O. 894 (E), dated</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>11. 1993.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of sections 4 to 37 (both inclusive), 41 to 45</p>
              <p>(both inclusive), 49 to 52 (both inclusive), 54 and 55 of this Act,</p>
              <p>shall come into force on 2. 10. 1993; vide Notification No. S. O. 735 (E)</p>
              <p>dated 30. 9. 1993.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" article" means an article of the Constitution;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" assembly constituency" means a constituency provided  under this Act for the purpose of elections to the Legislative</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Assembly;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" Capital" means the National Capital Territory of Delhi;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" Election Commission" means the Election Commission  referred to in article 324;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>" Legislative Assembly" means the Legislative Assembly of  the National Capital Territory of Delhi;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>" Scheduled Castes", in relation to the Capital, means  such castes, races or tribes or parts of or groups within such  castes, races or tribes as are deemed under article 341 to be</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-scheduled">
      <doc name="scheduled">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1992/1/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1992/1"/>
              <FRBRalias value="Castes in relation to the Capital."/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1992/1/eng@1992-01-02/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1992/1/eng@1992-01-02"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1992/1/eng@1992-01-02/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1992/1/eng@1992-01-02"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduled">
            <heading>PART</heading>
            <paragraph id="scheduled.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <part id="part-II">
              <num>II</num>
              <paragraph id="part-II.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>LEGISLALTIVE ASSEMBLY</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-3">
                <num>3.</num>
                <heading>Legislative Assembly and its composition.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-3.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The total number  of seats in the Legislative Assembly to be filled by persons chosen by  direct election from territorial constituencies shall be seventy.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-3.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>For the purpose of elections to the Legislative Assembly, the</p>
                    <p>Capital shall be divided into single- member assembly constituencies in  accordance with the provisions of Part III in such manner that the  population of each of the constituencies shall, so far as practicable,</p>
                    <p>be the same throughout the Capital.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-3.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Seats shall be reserved for the Scheduled Castes in the</p>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly, and the number of seats so reserved shall bear,</p>
                    <p>as nearly as may be, the same proportion to the total number of seats  in the Assembly as the population of the Scheduled Castes in the</p>
                    <p>Capital bears to the total population of the Capital and the  provisions of article 334 shall apply to such reservation.</p>
                    <p>Explanation.-- In this section, the expression" Population" means  the Population as ascertained in the last preceding census of which  the relevant figures have been published:</p>
                    <p>Provided that where such figures have not been published, then  for the purposes of elections for the constitution of the first</p>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly under this Act, the provisional figures of the  population of the Capital as published in relation to the 1991 census  shall be deemed to be the population of the Capital.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-4">
                <num>4.</num>
                <heading>Qualifications for membership of Legislative Assembly. A</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>person shall not be qualified to be chosen to fill a seat in the</p>
                    <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>Legislative Assembly unless he--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>is a citizen of India and makes and subscribes before  some person authorised in that behalf by the Election Commission  an oath or affirmation according to the form set out for the  purpose in the Schedule;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>is not less than twenty- five years of age; and</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>possesses such other qualifications as may be prescribed  in that behalf by or under any law made by Parliament.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-5">
                <num>5.</num>
                <heading>Duration of Legislative Assembly. The Legislative Assembly,</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>unless sooner dissolved, shall continue for five years from the date  appointed for its first meeting and no longer, and the expiration of  the said period of five years shall operate as a dissolution of the</p>
                    <p>Assembly:</p>
                    <p>Provided that the said period may, while a Proclamation of</p>
                    <p>Emergency issued under clause (1) of article 352 is in operation, be  extended by the President by order for a period not exceeding one year  at a time and not extending in any case beyond a period of six months  after the Proclamation has ceased to operate.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-6">
                <num>6.</num>
                <heading>Sessions of Legislative Assembly, prorogation and dissolution.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-6.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Lieutenant Governor shall, from time to time, summon the</p>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly to meet at such time and place as he thinks fit,</p>
                    <p>but six months shall not intervene between its last sitting in one  session and the date appointed for its first sitting in the next  session.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-6.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-6.2.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>The Lieutenant Governor may, from time to time,--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-6.2.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>prorogue the Assembly;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-6.2.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>dissolve the Assembly.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-7">
                <num>7.</num>
                <heading>Speaker and Deputy Speaker of Legislative Assembly.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-7.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The</p>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly shall, as soon as may be, choose two members of  the Assembly to be respectively Speaker and Deputy Speaker thereof  and, so often as the office of Speaker or Deputy Speaker becomes  vacant, the Assembly shall choose another member to be Speaker or</p>
                    <p>Deputy Speaker, as the case may be.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-7.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>A member holding office as Speaker or Deputy Speaker of the</p>
                    <blockList id="section-7.2.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>Legislative Assembly--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-7.2.list2.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>shall vacate his office if he ceases to be a member of  the Assembly;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-7.2.list2.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>may, at any time by writing under his hand addressed, if  such member is the Speaker, to the Deputy Speaker, and if such  member is the Deputy Speaker, to the Speaker, resign his office;</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-7.2.list4">
                      <listIntroduction>and</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-7.2.list4.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>may be removed from his office by a resolution of the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Assembly passed by a majority of all the then members of the</p>
                    <p>Assembly:</p>
                    <p>Provided that no resolution for the purpose of clause (c) shall  be moved unless at least fourteen days' notice has been given of the  intention to move the resolution:</p>
                    <p>Provided further that whenever the Assembly is dissolved, the</p>
                    <p>Speaker shall not vacate his office until immediately before the first  meeting of the Assembly after the dissolution.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-7.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>While the office of Speaker is vacant, the duties of the  office shall be performed by the Deputy Speaker or. if the office of</p>
                    <p>Deputy Speaker is also vacant. by such member of the Assembly as may  be determined by the rules of procedure of the Assembly.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-7.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>During the absence of the Speaker from any sitting of the</p>
                    <p>Assembly, the Deputy Speaker, or, if he is also absent, such person as</p>
                    <p>may be determined by the rules of procedure of the Assembly, or, if no  such person is present, such other person as may be determined by the</p>
                    <p>Assembly, shall act as Speaker.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-7.5">
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>There shall be paid to the Speaker and the Deputy Speaker of  the Legislative Assembly such salaries and allowances as may be  respectively fixed by the Legislative Assembly by law and, until  provision in that behalf is so made, such salaries and allowances as  the Lieutenant Governor may, with the approval of the President, by  order determine.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-8">
                <num>8.</num>
                <heading>Speaker or Deputy Speaker not to preside while a resolution  for his removal from office is under consideration.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-8.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>At any sitting  of the Legislative Assembly, while any resolution for the removal of  the Speaker from his office is under consideration, the Speaker, or  while any resolution for the removal of the Deputy Speaker from his  office is under consideration, the Deputy Speaker, shall not, though  he is present, preside and the provisions of sub- section (4) of  section 7 shall apply in relation to every such sitting as they apply  in relation to a sitting from which the Speaker or, as the case may  be, the Deputy Speaker is absent.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-8.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Speaker shall have the right to speak in, and otherwise  to take part in the proceedings of, the Legislative Assembly while any  resolution for his removal from office is under consideration in the  assembly and shall, notwithstanding anything in section 13, be  entitled to vote only in the first instance on such resolution or on  any other matter during such proceedings but not in the case of an  equality of votes.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-9">
                <num>9.</num>
                <heading>Right of Lieutenant Governor to address and send messages to</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-9.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Lieutenant Governor may address the</p>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly and for that purpose require the attendance of  members.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-9.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Lieutenant Governor may send messages to the Assembly  whether with respect to a Bill then pending in the Assembly or  otherwise, and when a message is so sent, the Assembly shall with all  convenient despatch consider any matter required by the message to be  taken into consideration.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-10">
                <num>10.</num>
                <heading>Special address by the Lieutenant Governor.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-10.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>At the  commencement of the first session after each general election to the</p>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly and at the commencement of the first session of  each year, the Lieutenant Governor shall address the Legislative</p>
                    <p>Assembly and inform it of the causes of its summons.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-10.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Provision shall be made by rules to be made by the Assembly  regulating its procedure for the allotment of time for discussion of  the matters referred to in such address.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-11">
                <num>11.</num>
                <heading>Rights of Ministers as respects Legislative Assembly. Every</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Minister shall have the right to speak in, and otherwise to take part  in the proceedings of, the Legislative Assembly and to speak in, and  otherwise to take part in the proceedings of, any committee of the</p>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly of which he may be named a member, but shall not  by virtue of this section be entitled to vote.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-12">
                <num>12.</num>
                <heading>Oath or affirmation by members. Every member of the</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly shall, before taking his seat, make and subscribe  before the Lieutenant Governor, or some person appointed in that  behalf by him, an oath or affirmation according to the form set out  for the purpose in the Schedule.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-13">
                <num>13.</num>
                <heading>Voting in Assembly, power of Assembly to act notwithstanding  vacancies and quorum.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-13.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Save as otherwise provided in this Act, all  questions at any sitting of the Legislative Assembly shall be  determined by a majority of votes of the members present and voting  other than the Speaker or person acting as such.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-13.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Speaker or person acting as such shall not vote in the  first instance. but shall have and exercise a casting vote in the case  of an equality of votes.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-13.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Legislative Assembly shall have power to act  notwithstanding any vacancy in the membership thereof, and any  proceedings in the Legislative Assembly shall be valid notwithstanding  that it is discovered subsequently that some person who was not  entitled so to do, sat or voted or otherwise took part in the  proceedings.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-13.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The quorum to constitute a meeting of the Legislative</p>
                    <p>Assembly shall be one- third of the total number of members of the</p>
                    <p>Assembly.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-13.5">
                  <num>(5)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>If at any time during a meeting of the Legislative Assembly  there is no quorum, it shall be the duty of the Speaker, or person  acting as such, either to adjourn the Assembly or to suspend the  meeting until there is a quorum.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-14">
                <num>14.</num>
                <heading>Vacation of seats.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-14.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>No person shall be a member both of</p>
                    <p>Parliament and of the Legislative Assembly and if a person is chosen a  member both of Parliament and of such Assembly, then, at the  expiration of such period as is specified in or under the</p>
                    <p>Representation of the People Act, 1951 (43 of 1951). and the rules  made by the President under clause (2) of article 101 and clause (2)</p>
                    <p>of article 190. that person' s seat in Parliament shall become vacant,</p>
                    <p>unless he has previously resigned his seat in the Legislative</p>
                    <p>Assembly.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-14.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-14.2.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>If a member of the Legislative Assembly--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-14.2.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>becomes subject to any disqualification mentioned in  section 15 or section 16 for membership of the Assembly, or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-14.2.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>resigns his seat by writing under his hand addressed to  the Speaker and his resignation is accepted by the Speaker,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>his seat shall thereupon become vacant:</p>
                    <p>Provided that in the case of any resignation referred to in  clause (b), if from the information received or otherwise and after  making such inquiry as he thinks fit, the Speaker is satisfied that  such resignation is not voluntary or genuine, he shall not accept such  resignation.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-14.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>If for a period of sixty days a member of the Legislative</p>
                    <p>Assembly is without permission of the Assembly absent from all  meetings thereof, the Assembly may declare his seat vacant:</p>
                    <p>Provided that in computing the said period of sixty days, no  account shall be taken of any period during which the Assembly is  prorogued or is adjourned for more than four consecutive days.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-15">
                <num>15.</num>
                <heading>Disqualifications for membership.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-15.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>A person shall be  disqualified for being chosen as, and for being, a member of the</p>
                    <blockList id="section-15.1.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>Legislative Assembly--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-15.1.list2.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>if he holds any office of profit under the Government of</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>India or the Government of any State or the Government of any</p>
                    <p>Union territory other than an office declared by law made by</p>
                    <p>Parliament or by the Legislature of any State or by the</p>
                    <blockList id="section-15.1.list7">
                      <listIntroduction>Legislative Assembly of the Capital or of any other Union  territory not to disqualify its holder; or</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-15.1.list7.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>if he is for the time being disqualified for being  chosen as, and for being, a member of either House of Parliament  under the provisions of sub- clause (b), sub- clause (c) or sub-</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>clause (d) of clause (1) of article 102 or of any law made in  pursuance of that article.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-15.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>For the purposes of this section, a person shall not be  deemed to hold an office of profit under the Government of India or  the Government of any State or the Government of any Union territory  by reason only that he is a Minister either for the Union or for such</p>
                    <p>State or Union territory.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-15.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>If any question arises as to whether a member of the</p>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly has become disqualified for being such a member  under the provisions of sub- section (1), the question shall be  referred for the decision of the President and his decision shall be  final.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-15.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Before giving any decision on any such question, the</p>
                    <p>President shall obtain the opinion of the Election Commission and  shall act according to such opinion.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-16">
                <num>16.</num>
                <heading>Disqualification on ground of defection. The provisions of  the Tenth Schedule to the Constitution shall, subject to the necessary  modifications (including modifications for construing references  therein to the Legislative Assembly of a State, article 188, article</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-194">
                <num>194.</num>
                <heading>and article 212 as references, respectively, to the Legislative</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-194.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-194.paragraph-0.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>Assembly, section 12, section 18 and section 37 of this Act), apply to  and in relation to the members of the Legislative Assembly as they  apply to and in relation to the members of the Legislative Assembly of  a State, and accordingly:--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-194.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>the said Tenth Schedule as so modified shall be deemed  to form part of this Act; and</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-194.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>a person shall be disqualified for being a member of the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly if he is so disqualified under the said</p>
                    <p>Tenth Schedule as so modified.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-17">
                <num>17.</num>
                <heading>Penalty for sitting and voting before making oath or  affirmation or when not qualified or when disqualified. If a person  sits or votes as a member of the Legislative Assembly before he has  complied with the requirements of section 12 or when he knows that he  is not qualified or that he is disqualified for membership thereof, he  shall be liable in respect of each day on which he so sits or votes to  a penalty of five hundred rupees to be recovered as a debt due to the</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Union.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-18">
                <num>18.</num>
                <heading>Powers, privileges, etc., of members.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-18.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Subject to the  provisions of this Act and to the rules and standing orders regulating  the procedure of the Legislative Assembly, there shall be freedom of  speech in the Legislative Assembly.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-18.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>No member of the Legislative Assembly shall be liable to any  proceedings in any court in respect of anything said or any vote given  by him in the Assembly or any committee thereof and no person shall be  so liable in respect of the publication by or under the authority of  such Assembly of any report, paper, votes or proceedings.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-18.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>In other respects, the powers, privileges and immunities of  the Legislative Assembly and of the members and the committees thereof  shall be such as are for the time being enjoyed by the House of the</p>
                    <p>People and its members and committees.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-18.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The provisions of sub- sections (1), (2) and (3) shall apply  in relation to persons who by virtue of this Act have the right to  speak in, and otherwise to take part in the proceedings of, the</p>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly or any committee thereof as they apply in  relation to members of that Assembly.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-19">
                <num>19.</num>
                <heading>Salaries and allowances of members. Members of the</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly shall be entitled to receive such salaries and  allowances as may from time to time be determined by the Legislative</p>
                    <p>Assembly by law and until provision in that behalf is so made, such  salaries and allowances as the Lieutenant Governor may, with the  approval of the President, by order determine.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-20">
                <num>20.</num>
                <heading>Exemption of property of the Union from taxation. The  property of the Union shall, save in so far as Parliament may by law  otherwise provide, be exempted from all taxes imposed by or under any  law made by the Legislative Assembly or by or under any other law in  force in the Capital:</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Provided that nothing in this section shall, until Parliament by  law otherwise provides, prevent any authority within the Capital from  levying any tax on any property of the Union to which such property  was immediately before the commencement of the Constitution liable or  treated as liable, so long as that tax continues to be levied in the</p>
                    <p>Capital.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-21">
                <num>21.</num>
                <heading>Restrictions on laws passed by Legislative Assembly with  respect to certain matters.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-21.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The provisions of article 286, article</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-287">
                <num>287.</num>
                <heading>and article 288 shall apply in relation to any law passed by the</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-287.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly with respect to any of the matters referred to in  those articles as they apply in relation to any law passed by the</p>
                    <p>Legislature of a State with respect to those matters.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-287.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The provisions of article 304 shall, with the necessary  modifications, apply in relation to any law passed by the Legislative</p>
                    <p>Assembly with respect to any of the matters referred to in that  article as they apply in relation to any law passed by the Legislature  of a State with respect to those matters.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-22">
                <num>22.</num>
                <heading>Special provisions as to financial bills.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-22.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>A Bill or  amendment shall not be introduced into, or moved in, the Legislative</p>
                    <blockList id="section-22.1.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>Assembly except on the recommendation of the Lieutenant Governor, if  such Bill or amendment makes provision for any of the following  matters, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-22.1.list2.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>the imposition, abolition, remission, alteration or  regulation of any tax;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-22.1.list2.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>the amendment of the law with respect to any financial  obligations undertaken or to be undertaken by the Government of  the Capital;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-22.1.list2.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>the appropriation of moneys out of the Consolidated fund  of the Capital;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-22.1.list2.d">
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <p>the declaring of any expenditure to be expenditure  charged on the Consolidated Fund of the Capital or the increasing  of the amount of any such expenditure;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-22.1.list2.e">
                        <num>(e)</num>
                        <p>the receipt of money on account of the Consolidated Fund  of the Capital or the custody or issue of such money:</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Provided that no recommendation shall be required under this  sub- section for the moving of an amendment making provision for the  reduction or abolition of any tax.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-22.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>A Bill or amendment shall not be deemed to make provision for  any of the matters aforesaid by reason only that it provides for the  imposition of fines or other pecuniary penalties, or for the demand or  payment of fees for licences or fees for services rendered, or by  reason that it provides for the imposition, abolition, remission,</p>
                    <p>alteration or regulation of any tax by any local authority or body for  local purposes.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-22.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>A Bill which, if enacted and brought into operation, would  involve expenditure from the Consolidated Fund of the Capital shall  not be passed by the Legislative Assembly unless the Lieutenant</p>
                    <p>Governor has recommended to that Assembly the consideration of the</p>
                    <p>Bill.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-23">
                <num>23.</num>
                <heading>Procedure as to lapsing of Bills.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-23.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>A Bill pending in the</p>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly shall not lapse by reason of the prorogation of  the Assembly.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-23.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>A Bill which is pending in the Legislative Assembly shall  lapse on a dissolution of the Assembly.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-24">
                <num>24.</num>
                <heading>Assent to Bills. When a Bill has been passed by the</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly, it shall be presented to the Lieutenant Governor  and the Lieutenant Governor shall declare either that he assents to  the Bill or that he withholds assent therefrom or that he reserves the</p>
                    <p>Bill for the consideration of the President:</p>
                    <p>Provided that the Lieutenant Governor may, as soon as possible  after the presentation of the Bill to him for assent, return the Bill  if it is not a Money Bill together with a message requesting that the</p>
                    <p>Assembly will reconsider the Bill or any specified provisions thereof,</p>
                    <p>and, in particular, will consider the desirability of introducing any  such amendments as he may recommend in his message and, when a Bill is  so returned, the Assembly will reconsider the Bill accordingly, and if  the Bill is passed again with or without amendment and presented to  the Lieutenant Governor for assent, the Lieutenant Governor shall  declare either that he assents to the Bill or that he reserves the</p>
                    <p>Bill for the consideration of the President:</p>
                    <blockList id="section-24.paragraph-0.list7">
                      <listIntroduction>Provided further that the Lieutenant Governor shall not assent  to, but shall reserve for the consideration of the President, any Bill  which,--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list7.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>in the opinion of the Lieutenant Governor would, if it  became law, so derogate from the powers of the High Court as to  endanger the position which that Court is, by the Constitution,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-24.paragraph-0.list9">
                      <listIntroduction>designed to fill; or</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list9.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>the President may, by order, direct to be reserved for  his consideration; or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list9.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>relates to matters referred to in sub- section (5) of  section 7 or section 19 or section 34 or sub- section (3) of  section 43.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section and section 25, a</p>
                    <p>Bill shall be deemed to be a Money Bill if it contains only provisions  dealing with all or any of the matters specified in sub- section (1) of  section 22 or any matter incidental to any of those matters and, in  either case, there is endorsed thereon the certificate of the Speaker  of the Legislative Assembly signed by him that it is a Money Bill.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-25">
                <num>25.</num>
                <heading>Bills reserved for consideration. When a Bill is reserved by  the Lieutenant Governor for the consideration of the President, the</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>President shall declare either that he assents to the Bill or that he  withholds assent therefrom:</p>
                    <p>Provided that where the Bill is not a Money Bill, the President  may direct the Lieutenant Governor to return the Bill to the</p>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly together with such a message as is mentioned in  the first proviso to section 24 and, when a Bill is so returned, the</p>
                    <p>Assembly shall reconsider it accordingly within a period of six months  from the date of receipt of such message and, if it is again passed by  the Assembly with or without amendment, it shall be presented again to  the President for his consideration.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-26">
                <num>26.</num>
                <heading>Requirements as to sanction, etc. No Act of the Legislative</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Assembly, and no provision in any such Act, shall be invalid by reason  only that some previous sanction or recommendation required by this</p>
                    <p>Act was not given, if assent to that Act was given by the Lieutenant</p>
                    <p>Governor, or, on being reserved by the Lieutenant Governor for the  consideration of the President, by the President.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-27">
                <num>27.</num>
                <heading>Annual financial statement.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-27.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Lieutenant Governor shall  in respect of every financial year cause to be laid before the</p>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly, with the previous sanction of the President, a  statement of the estimated receipts and expenditure of the Capital for  that year, in this Part referred to as the" annual financial  statement".</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-27.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-27.2.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>The estimates of expenditure embodied in the annual financial  statement shall show separately--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-27.2.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>the sums required to meet expenditure described by this</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Act as expenditure charged upon the Consolidated Fund of the</p>
                    <blockList id="section-27.2.list4">
                      <listIntroduction>Capital; and</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-27.2.list4.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>the sums required to meet other expenditure proposed to  be made from the Consolidated Fund of the Capital, and shall  distinguish expenditure on revenue account from other  expenditure.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-27.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-27.3.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time  being in force, the following expenditure shall be expenditure charged  on the Consolidated Fund of the Capital:--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-27.3.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>the emoluments and allowances of the Lieutenant Governor  and other expenditure relating to his office as determined by the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-27.3.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>President by general or special order;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-27.3.list3.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>the charges payable in respect of loans advanced to the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Capital from the Consolidated Fund of India including interest,</p>
                    <blockList id="section-27.3.list6">
                      <listIntroduction>sinking fund charges and redemption charges, and other  expenditure connected therewith;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-27.3.list6.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>the salaries and allowances of the Speaker and the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-27.3.list8">
                      <listIntroduction>Deputy Speaker of the Legislative Assembly;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-27.3.list8.d">
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <p>expenditure in respect of the salaries and allowances of</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-27.3.list10">
                      <listIntroduction>Judges of the High Court of Delhi;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-27.3.list10.e">
                        <num>(e)</num>
                        <p>any sums required to satisfy any judgment, decree or  award of any court of arbitral tribunal;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-27.3.list10.f">
                        <num>(f)</num>
                        <p>any other expenditure declared by the Constitution or by  law made by Parliament or by the Legislative Assembly to be so  charged.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-28">
                <num>28.</num>
                <heading>Procedure in Legislative Assembly with respect to estimates.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-28.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>So much of the estimates as relates to expenditure charged upon  the Consolidated Fund of the Capital shall not be submitted to the  vote of the Legislative Assembly, but nothing in this sub- section  shall be construed as preventing the discussion in the Legislative</p>
                    <p>Assembly of any of those estimates.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-28.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>So much of the said estimates as relates to other expenditure  shall be submitted in the form of demands for grants to the</p>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly, and the Legislative Assembly shall have power to  assent, or to refuse to assent, to any demand, or to assent to any  demand subject to a reduction of the amount specified therein.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-28.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>No demand for a grant shall be made except on the  recommendation of the Lieutenant Governor.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-29">
                <num>29.</num>
                <heading>Appropriation Bills.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-29.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>As soon as may be after the grants  under section 28 have been made by the Legislative Assembly, there  shall be introduced a Bill to provide for the appropriation out of the</p>
                    <blockList id="section-29.1.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>Consolidated Fund of the Capital of all moneys required to meet--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-29.1.list2.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>the grants so made by the Assembly, and</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-29.1.list2.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>the expenditure charged on the Consolidated Fund of the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Capital but not exceeding in any case the amount shown in the  statement previously laid before the Assembly.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-29.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>No amendment shall be proposed to any such Bill in the</p>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly which will have the effect of varying the amount  or altering the destination of any grant so made or of varying the  amount of any expenditure charged on the Consolidated Fund of the</p>
                    <p>Capital and the decision of the person presiding as to whether an  amendment is inadmissible under this sub- section shall be final.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-29.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Subject to the other provisions of this Act, no money shall  be withdrawn from the Consolidated Fund of the Capital except under  appropriation made by law passed in accordance with provisions of this  section.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-30">
                <num>30.</num>
                <heading>Supplementary, additional or excess grants.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-30.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The</p>
                    <blockList id="section-30.1.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>Lieutenant Governor shall,--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-30.1.list2.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>if the amount authorised by any law made in accordance  with the provisions of section 29 to be expended for a particular  service for the current financial year is found to be  insufficient for the purposes of that year or when a need has  arisen during the current financial year for supplementary or  additional expenditure upon some new service not contemplated in  the annual financial statement for that year, or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-30.1.list2.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>if any money has been spent on any service during a  financial year in excess of the amount granted for that service  and for that year,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>cause to be laid before the Legislative Assembly, with the previous  sanction of the President, another statement showing the estimated  amount of that expenditure or cause to be presented to the Legislative</p>
                    <p>Assembly with such previous sanction a demand for such excess, as the  case may be.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-30.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The provisions of sections 27, 28 and 29 shall have effect in  relation to any such statement and expenditure or demand and also to  any law to be made authorising the appropriation of moneys out of the</p>
                    <p>Consolidated Fund of the Capital to meet such expenditure or the grant  in respect of such demand as they have effect in relation to the  annual financial statement and the expenditure mentioned therein or to  a demand for a grant and the law to be made for the authorisation of  appropriation of moneys out of the Consolidated Fund of the Capital to  meet such expenditure or grant.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-31">
                <num>31.</num>
                <heading>Votes on account.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-31.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Notwithstanding anything in the  foregoing provisions of this Part, the Legislative Assembly shall have  power to make any grant in advance in respect of the estimated  expenditure for a part of any financial year pending the completion of  the procedure prescribed in section 28 for the voting of such grant  and the passing of the law in accordance with the provisions of  section 29 in relation to that expenditure and the Legislative</p>
                    <p>Assembly shall have power to authorise by law the withdrawal of moneys  from the Consolidated Fund of the Capital for the purposes for which  the said grant is made.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-31.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The provisions of sections 28 and 29 shall have effect in  relation to the making of any grant under sub- section (1) or to any  law to be</p>
                    <p>made under that sub- section as they have effect in relation to the  making of a grant with regard to any expenditure mentioned in the  annual financial statement and the law to be made for the  authorisation of appropriation of moneys, out of the Consolidated Fund  of the Capital to meet such expenditure.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-32">
                <num>32.</num>
                <heading>Authorisation of expenditure pending its sanction by</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-32.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly. Notwithstanding anything in the foregoing  provisions of this Part, the Lieutenant Governor may authorise such  expenditure from the Consolidated Fund of the Capital as he deems  necessary for a period of not more than six months beginning with the  date of the constitution of the Consolidated Fund of the Capital,</p>
                    <p>pending the sanction of such expenditure by the Legislative Assembly.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-33">
                <num>33.</num>
                <heading>Rules of procedure.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-33.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Legislative Assembly may make  rules for regulating, subject to the provisions of this Act, its  procedure and the conduct of its business:</p>
                    <blockList id="section-33.1.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>Provided that the Lieutenant Governor shall, after consultation  with the Speaker of the Legislative Assembly and with the approval of  the President, make rules--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-33.1.list2.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>for securing the timely completion of financial  business;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-33.1.list2.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>for regulating the procedure of, and the conduct of  business in, the Legislative Assembly in relation to any  financial matter or to any Bill for the appropriation of moneys  out of the Consolidated Fund of the Capital;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-33.1.list2.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>for prohibiting the discussion of, or the asking of  questions on, any matter which affects the discharge of the  functions of the Lieutenant Governor in so far as he is required  by or under this Act or any law to act in his discretion.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-33.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Until rules are made under sub- section (1), the rules of  procedure and standing orders with respect to the Legislative Assembly  of the State of Uttar Pradesh in force immediately before the  commencement of this Act shall have effect in relation to the</p>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly subject to such modifications and adaptations as  may be made therein by the Lieutenant Governor.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-34">
                <num>34.</num>
                <heading>Official language or languages of the Capital and language  or languages to be used, in Legislative Assembly.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-34.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Legislative</p>
                    <p>Assembly may by law adopt any one or more of the languages in use in  the Capital or Hindi as the official language or languages to be used  for all or any of the official purposes of the Capital:</p>
                    <blockList id="section-34.1.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>Provided that the President may by order direct--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-34.1.list3.i">
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <p>that the official language of the Union shall be adopted  for such of the official purposes of the Capital as may be  specified in the order;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-34.1.list3.ii">
                        <num>(ii)</num>
                        <p>that any other language shall also be adopted  throughout the Capital or such part thereof for such of the  official purposes of the Capital as may be specified in the  order, if the President is satisfied that a substantial  proportion of the population of the Capital desires the use of  that other language for all or any of such purposes.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-34.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The business in the Legislative Assembly shall be transacted  in the official language or languages of the Capital or in Hindi or in</p>
                    <p>English:</p>
                    <p>Provided that the Speaker of the Legislative Assembly or person  acting as such, as the case may be, may permit any member who cannot  adequately express himself in any of the languages aforesaid to  address the Assembly in his mother- tongue.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-35">
                <num>35.</num>
                <heading>Language to be used for Bills, Acts, etc. Notwithstanding  anything contained in section 34, until parliament by law otherwise  provides, the authoritative texts--</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-35.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-35.paragraph-0.list0">
                      <item id="section-35.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>of all Bills to be introduced or amendments thereto to  be moved in the Legislative Assembly;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-35.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>of all Acts passed by the Legislative Assembly; and</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-35.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>of all orders, rules, regulations and bye- laws issued  under any law made by the Legislative Assembly,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>shall be in the English language:</p>
                    <p>Provided that where the Legislative Assembly has prescribed any  language other than the English language for use in Bills introduced  in, or Acts passed by, the Legislative Assembly or in any order, rule,</p>
                    <p>regulation or bye- law issued under any law made by the Legislative</p>
                    <p>Assembly, a translation of the same in the English language published  under the authority, of the Lieutenant Governor in the Official Gazette  shall be deemed to be the authoritative text thereof in the English  language.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-36">
                <num>36.</num>
                <heading>Restriction on discussion in the Legislative Assembly. No  discussion shall take place in the Legislative Assembly with respect  to the conduct of any Judge of the Supreme Court or of a High Court in  the discharge of his duties.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-37">
                <num>37.</num>
                <heading>Courts not to inquire into proceedings of Legislative</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-37.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Assembly.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-37.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The validity of any proceedings in the Legislative</p>
                    <p>Assembly shall not be called in question on the ground of any alleged  irregularity of procedure.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-37.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>No officer or member of the Legislative Assembly in whom  powers are vested by or under this Act for regulating procedure or the  conduct of business, or for maintaining order in the Legislative</p>
                    <p>Assembly shall be subject to the jurisdiction of any court in respect  of the exercise by him of those powers.</p>
                    <p>PART</p>
                    <p>DELIMITATION OF CONSTITUENCIES</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
            </part>
            <part id="part-III">
              <num>III</num>
              <paragraph id="part-III.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>DELIMITATION OF CONSTITUENCIES</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-38">
                <num>38.</num>
                <heading>Election Commission to delimit constituencies.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-38.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The</p>
                    <blockList id="section-38.1.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>Election Commission shall, in the manner herein provided, distribute  the seats assigned to the Legislative Assembly under section 3 to  single- member territorial constituencies and delimit them having  regard to the following provisions, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-38.1.list2.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>all constituencies shall, as far as practicable, be  delimited in such manner that the ratio between the population of  each of such constituencies and the total population of the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-38.1.list4">
                      <listIntroduction>Capital is the same; and</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-38.1.list4.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>constituencies in which seats are reserved for the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
            </part>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-scheduled">
      <doc name="scheduled">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1992/1/scheduled"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1992/1"/>
              <FRBRalias value="Castes shall, as far as practicable, be located in  areas where the proportion of their population to the total  population is comparatively large."/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1992/1/eng@1992-01-02/scheduled"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1992/1/eng@1992-01-02"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1992/1/eng@1992-01-02/scheduled"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1992/1/eng@1992-01-02"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduled">
            <subsection id="scheduled.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <blockList id="scheduled.2.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>The Election Commission shall--</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="scheduled.2.list1.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>publish its proposals for the delimitation of  constituencies in the Official Gazette and also in such other  manner as the Commission may consider fit, together with a notice  inviting objections and suggestions in relation to the proposals  and specifying a date on or after which the proposals will be  further considered by it;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="scheduled.2.list1.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>consider all objections and suggestions which may have  been received by it before the date so specified;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="scheduled.2.list1.c">
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <p>after considering all objections and suggestions which  may have been received by it before the date so specified,</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <p>determine by one or more orders the delimitation of  constituencies and cause such order or orders to be published in  the Official Gazette; and upon such publication, the order or  orders shall have the full force of law and shall not be called  in question in any court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <section id="section-39">
              <num>39.</num>
              <heading>Power of Election Commission to maintain delimitation orders  up- to date. The Election Commission may, from time to time, by  notification in the Official Gazette,--</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-39.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-39.paragraph-0.list0">
                    <item id="section-39.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>correct any printing mistakes in any order made under  section 38 or any error arising therein from inadvertent slip or  omission; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-39.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>where the boundaries or name of any territorial division  mentioned in any such order are or is altered, make such  amendments as appear to it to be necessary or expedient for  bringing such order up- to- date.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-40">
              <num>40.</num>
              <heading>Elections to the Legislative Assembly.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-40.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>For the purpose of  constituting the Legislative Assembly, a general election will be held  as soon as may be, after the delimitation of all the assembly  constituencies under section 38.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-40.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>For the purposes of sub- section (1), the Lieutenant Governor  shall, by one or more notifications published in the Official Gazette,</p>
                  <p>call upon all the said assembly constituencies to elect members in  accordance with the provisions of the Representation of the People</p>
                  <p>Act, 1951 (43 of 1951), and of the rules and orders made or issued  thereunder as applicable under sub- section (3).</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-40.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Representation of the People Act, 1950 (43 of 1950), the</p>
                  <p>Representation of the People Act, 1951 (43 of 1951), the rules and  orders made or issued under the said Acts and all other laws for the  time being in force relating to elections shall apply with necessary  modifications (including modifications for construing references  therein to a State, State Government and Governor as including  references to the Capital, Government of the Capital and Lieutenant</p>
                  <p>Governor, respectively) to, and in relation to, the general election  referred to in sub- section (1).</p>
                  <p>PART</p>
                  <p>CERTAIN PROVISIONS RELATING TO LIEUTENANT GOVERNOR AND MINISTERS</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <part id="part-IV">
              <num>IV</num>
              <paragraph id="part-IV.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>CERTAIN PROVISIONS RELATING TO LIEUTENANT GOVERNOR AND MINISTERS</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-41">
                <num>41.</num>
                <heading>Matters in which Lieutenant Governor to act in his  discretion.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-41.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-41.1.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>The Lieutenant Governor shall act in his discretion in  a matter--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-41.1.list1.i">
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <p>which falls outside the purview of the powers conferred  on the Legislative Assembly but in respect of which powers or  functions are entrusted or delegated to him by the President; or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-41.1.list1.ii">
                        <num>(ii)</num>
                        <p>in which he is required by or under any law to act in  his discretion or to exercise any judicial or quasi- judicial  functions.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-41.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>If any question arises as to whether any matter is or is not  a matter as respects which the Lieutenant Governor is by or under any  law required to act in his discretion, the decision of the Lieutenant</p>
                    <p>Governor thereon shall be final.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-41.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>If any question arises as to whether any matter is or is not  a matter as respects which the Lieutenant Governor is required by any  law to exercise any judicial or quasi- judicial functions, the decision  of the Lieutenant Governor thereon shall be final.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-42">
                <num>42.</num>
                <heading>Advice by Ministers. The question whether any, and if so  what, advice was tendered by Ministers to the Lieutenant Governor  shall not be inquired into in any court.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-43">
                <num>43.</num>
                <heading>Other provisions as to Ministers.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-43.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Before a Minister  enters upon his office, the Lieutenant Governor shall administer to  him the oaths of office and of secrecy according to the forms set out  for the purpose in the Schedule.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-43.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>A Minister who, for any period of six consecutive months, is  not a member of the Legislative Assembly shall, at the expiration of  that period, cease to be a Minister.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-43.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The salaries and allowances of Ministers shall be such as the</p>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly may from time to time by law determine, and until  the Legislative Assembly so determines, shall be determined by the</p>
                    <p>Lieutenant Governor with the approval of the President.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-44">
                <num>44.</num>
                <heading>Conduct of business.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-44.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-44.1.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>The President shall make rules--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-44.1.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>for the allocation of business to the Ministers in so  far as it is business with respect to which the Lieutenant</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-44.1.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>Governor is required to act on the aid and advice of his Council  of Ministers; and</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-44.1.list3.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>for the more convenient transaction of business with the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Ministers, including the procedure to be adopted in the case of a  difference of opinion between the Lieutenant Governor and the</p>
                    <p>Council of Ministers or a Minister.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-44.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Save as otherwise provided in this Act, all executive action  of the Lieutenant Governor whether taken on the advice of his</p>
                    <p>Ministers or otherwise shall be expressed to be taken in the name of  the Lieutenant Governor.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-44.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Orders and other instruments made and executed in the name of  the Lieutenant Governor shall be authenticated in such manner as may  be specified in rules to be made by the Lieutenant Governor and the  validity of an order or instrument which is so authenticated shall not  be called in question on the ground that it is not an order or  instrument made or executed by the Lieutenant Governor.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-45">
                <num>45.</num>
                <heading>Duties of Chief Minister as respects the furnishing of  information to the Lieutenant Governor, etc. It shall be the duty of  the Chief Minister--</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-45.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-45.paragraph-0.list0">
                      <item id="section-45.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>to communicate to the Lieutenant Governor all decisions  of the Council of Ministers relating to the administration of the  affairs of the Capital and proposals for legislation;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-45.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>to furnish such information relating to the  administration of the affairs of the Capital and proposals for  legislation as Lieutenant Governor may call for; and</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-45.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>if the Lieutenant Governor so requires, to submit for  the consideration of the Council of Ministers any matter on which  a decision has been taken by a Minister but which has not been  considered by the Council.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>PART</p>
                    <p>MISCELLANEOUS AND TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
            </part>
            <part id="part-V">
              <num>V</num>
              <paragraph id="part-V.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>MISCELLANEOUS AND TRANSITIONAL PROVISIONS</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-46">
                <num>46.</num>
                <heading>Consolidated Fund of the Capital.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-46.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>As from such date as  the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette,</p>
                    <p>appoint in this behalf, all revenues received in the Capital by the</p>
                    <p>Government of India or the Lieutenant Governor in relation to any  matter with respect to which the Legislative Assembly has power to  make laws, and all grants made and all loans advanced to the Capital  from the Consolidated Fund of India and all moneys received by the</p>
                    <p>Capital in repayment of loans shall form one Consolidated Fund to be  entitled" the Consolidated Fund of the National Capital Territory of</p>
                    <p>Delhi" (referred to in this Act as the Consolidated Fund of the</p>
                    <p>Capital).</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-46.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>No moneys out of the Consolidated Fund of the Capital shall  be appropriated except in accordance with and for the purposes and in  the manner provided in this Act.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-46.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The custody of the Consolidated Fund of the Capital, the  payment of moneys into such Fund, the withdrawal of moneys therefrom  and all other matters connected with or ancillary to those matters  shall be regulated by rules made by the Lieutenant Governor with the  approval of the President.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-47">
                <num>47.</num>
                <heading>Contingency Fund of the Capital.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-47.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>There shall be  established a Contingency Fund in the nature of an imprest to be  entitled" the Contingency Fund of the National Capital Territory of</p>
                    <p>Delhi" into which shall be paid from and out of the Consolidated Fund  of the Capital such sums as may, from time to time, be determined by  law made by the Legislative Assembly; and the said Fund shall be held  by the Lieutenant Governor to enable advances to be made by him out of  such Fund.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-47.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>No advances shall be made out of the Contingency Fund  referred to in sub- section (1) except for the purposes of meeting  unforeseen expenditure pending authorisation of such expenditure by  the Legislative Assembly under appropriations made by law.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-47.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Lieutenant Governor may make rules regulating all matters  connected with or ancillary to the custody of, the payment of moneys  into, and the withdrawal of moneys from, the aforesaid Contingency</p>
                    <p>Fund.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-48">
                <num>48.</num>
                <heading>Audit reports. The reports of the Comptroller and Auditor-</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-48.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>General of India relating to the accounts of the Capital for any  period subsequent to the date referred to in sub- section</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-48.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>of  section 46 shall be submitted to the Lieutenant Governor who shall  cause them to be laid before the Legislative Assembly.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-49">
                <num>49.</num>
                <heading>Relation of Lieutenant Governor and his Ministers to</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-49.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>President. Notwithstanding anything in this Act, the Lieutenant</p>
                    <p>Governor and his Council of Ministers shall be under the general  control of, and comply with such particular directions, if any, as may  from time to time be given by, the President.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-50">
                <num>50.</num>
                <heading>Period of order made under article 239AB and approval thereof  by Parliament.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-50.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every order made by the President under article</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-239AB">
                <num>239AB.</num>
                <heading>shall expire at the end of one year from the date of issue of  the order and the provisions of clauses (2) and (3) of article 356  shall, so far as may be, apply to such order as they apply to a</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-239AB.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Proclamation issued under clause (1) of article 356.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-239AB.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), the</p>
                    <p>President may extend the duration of the aforesaid order for a further  period not exceeding two years from the date of expiry of the order  under sub- section (1) subject to the condition that every extension of  the said order for any period beyond the expiration of one year shall  be approved by resolutions of both Houses of Parliament.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-51">
                <num>51.</num>
                <heading>Authorisation of expenditure by President. Where the</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-51.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly is dissolved or its functioning as such Assembly  remains suspended, on account of an order made by the President under  article 239AB, it shall be competent for the President to authorise  when the House of the People is not in session expenditure from the</p>
                    <p>Consolidated Fund of the Capital pending the sanction of such  expenditure by Parliament.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-52">
                <num>52.</num>
                <heading>Contracts and suits. For the removal of doubts it is hereby  declared that--</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-52.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-52.paragraph-0.list0">
                      <item id="section-52.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>all contracts in connection with the administration of  the Capital are contracts made in the exercise of the executive  power of the Union; and</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-52.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>all suits and proceedings in connection with the  administration of the Capital shall be instituted by or against  the Government of India.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-53">
                <num>53.</num>
                <heading>Power of president to remove difficulties.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-53.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>If any  difficulty arises in relation to the transition from the provisions of  any law repealed by this Act or in giving effect to the provisions of  this Act and in particular in relation to the constitution of the</p>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly, the President may by order do anything not  inconsistent with the provisions of the Constitution or of this Act  which appear to him to be necessary or expedient for the purpose of  removing the difficulty:</p>
                    <p>Provided that no order under this sub- section shall be made after  the expiry of three years from the date of constitution of the first</p>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-53.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every order made under sub- section (1) shall be laid before  each House of Parliament.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-54">
                <num>54.</num>
                <heading>Laying of rules before Legislative Assembly. Every rule made  by the Lieutenant Governor under this Act shall be laid, as soon as it  is made, before the Legislative Assembly.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-55">
                <num>55.</num>
                <heading>Ammendment of section 27A of Act 43 of 1950. In section 27A</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-55.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>of the Representation of People Act, 1950, for sub- section (3), the  following sub- section shall be substituted, namely:--</p>
                    <p>" (3) The electoral college for the Union territory of Delhi  shall consist of the elected members of the Legislative Assembly  constituted for that territory under the Government of National</p>
                    <p>Capital Territory of Delhi Act, 1991."</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-56">
                <num>56.</num>
                <heading>Repeal of Act 19 of 1966. The Delhi Administration Act, 1966  is hereby repealed.</heading>
              </section>
            </part>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
