<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1898/9/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1898/9"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Live- Stock Importation Act, 1898"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1898/9/eng@1898-08-12/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1898/9/eng@1898-08-12"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1898-08-12" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1898/9/eng@1898-08-12/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1898/9/eng@1898-08-12"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Live- Stock Importation Act, 1898</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 9 OF 1898</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 12th August, 1898.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to make better provision for the regulation of the importation  of live- stock.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to make better provision for the regula-</p>
        <p>tion of the importation of live- stock which is liable to be affected  by infectious or contagious disorders; It is hereby enacted as  follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and local extent.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called  the Live- stock Importation Act, 1898.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India ;] ,</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant  in the subject or context,-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the expression" infectious or contagious disorders"</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>includes tick- pest, anthrax, glanders, farcy, scabies and any  other disease or disorder which may be specified by the</p>
            <p>Central Government by notification in the Official Gazette;</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" live- stock" includes horses, kine, camels, sheep and  any other animal which may be specified by the Central</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6">
              <listIntroduction>Government by notification in the Official Gazette;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" import" means the bringing or taking, by sea, land  or air, into  India].]</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Power to regulate importation of live- stock.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The</p>
            <p>Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette,</p>
            <p>regulate, restrict or prohibit, in such manner and to such extent as  it may think fit,  the import], into  India] or any</p>
            <p>specified place therein, of any live- stock which may be liable to be  affected by infectious or contagious disorders, and of any fodder,</p>
            <p>dung, stable- litter, clothing, harness or fittings appertaining to  livestock or that may have been in contact therewith.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A notification under sub- section (1) shall operate as if it  had been issued under section 19 of the Sea Customs Act, 1878, (8 of</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1871">
        <num>1871.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1871.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>) and the officers of customs at every port shall have the same  power in respect of any live- stock or thing, with regard to the  importation of which such a notification has been issued, and the  vessel containing the same, as they have for the time being in respect  of any article the importation of which is regulated, restricted or  prohibited by the law relating to sea customs and the vessel  containing the same; and the enactments for the time being in force  relating to sea customs or any such article or vessel shall apply  accordingly.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Power for State Government to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State</p>
            <p>Government may  make rules for the detention, inspection,</p>
            <p>disinfection or destruction of imported live- stock, and of fodder,</p>
            <p>dung, stable- litter, clothing, harness or fittings appertaining to  imported live- stock or that may have been in contact therewith, and  for regulating the powers and duties of the officers whom it may  appoint in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In making any rule under this section the State Government  may direct that a breach thereof shall be punishable with fine which  may extend to one thousand rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Protection to persons acting under Act. No suit,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any person  for anything in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
