<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1883/19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1883/19"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Land Improvement Loans Act, 1883"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1883/19/eng@1883-10-12/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1883/19/eng@1883-10-12"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1883-10-12" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1883/19/eng@1883-10-12/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1883/19/eng@1883-10-12"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Land Improvement Loans Act, 1883</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 19 OF 1883</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 12th October, 1883.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to consolidate and amend the law relating to loans of money by  the Government for agricultural improvements.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Land Improvement</p>
            <p>Loans Act, 1883.</p>
            <p>Local extent, Commencement.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India except  the territories  which, immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised in</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <part id="part-B">
        <num>B</num>
        <heading>States], but shall not come into force in any part of  the  territories to which this Act extends] until such date as the State</heading>
        <paragraph id="part-B.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Government  may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint  in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Acts 26 of 1871 and 21 of 1876 repealed.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-2.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Land</p>
              <p>Improvement Act, 1871, and Act XXI of 1876 (An Act to amend the Land</p>
              <p>Improvement Act, 1871), shall, except as regards the recovery of  advances made before this Act comes into force and costs incurred by  the Government in respect of such advances, be repealed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When in any Act, Regulation or Notification passed or issued  before this Act comes into force, reference is made to either of those</p>
              <p>Acts, the reference shall, so far as may be practicable, be read as  applying to this Act or the corresponding part of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>" Collector" defined. In this Act," Collector"  means the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Collector of land- revenue of a district, or the Deputy Commissioner,</p>
              <p>or any officer empowered by the State Government by name or by virtue  of his office to discharge the functions of a Collector under this</p>
              <p>Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Purposes for which loans may be granted under this Act.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to such rules as may be made under section 10, loans may be  granted under this Act, by such officer as may, from time to time, be  empowered in this behalf by the State Government, for the purpose of  making any improvement, to any person having a right to make that  improvement, or, with the consent of that person, to any other person.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-4.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>" Improvement" means any work which adds to the letting value  of land, and includes the following, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the construction of wells, tanks and other works for the  storage, supply or distribution of water for the  purposes of agriculture, or for the use of men and  cattle employed in agriculture;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the preparation of land for irrigation;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the drainage, reclamation from rivers or other waters,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-4.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>or protection from floods or from erosion or other  damage by water, or land used for agricultural purposes  or wasteland which is culturable;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.2.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the reclamation, clearance, enclosure or permanent  improvement of land for agricultural purposes;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.2.list3.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the renewal or reconstruction of any of the foregoing  works, or alterations therein or additions thereto; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.2.list3.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>such other works as the State Government  may, from  time to time, by notification in the Official Gazette,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>declare to be improvements for the purposes of this</p>
              <p>Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Mode of dealing with applications for loans.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When an  application for a loan is made under this Act, the officer to whom the  application is made may, if it is, in his opinion, expedient that  public notice be given of the application, publish a notice, in such  manner as the State Government may, from</p>
              <p>time to time, direct, calling upon all persons objecting to the loan  to appear before him at a time and place fixed therein and submit  their objections.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The officer shall consider every objection submitted under  sub- section (1), and make an order in writing either admitting or  overruling it:</p>
              <p>Provided that, when the question raised by an objection is, in  the opinion of the officer, one of such a nature that it cannot be  satisfactorily decided except by a Civil Court, he shall postpone his  proceedings on the application until the question has been so decided.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Period for repayment of loans.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every loan granted under  this Act shall be made repayable by instalments (in the form of an   annuity or otherwise), within such period from the date of the actual  advance of the loan, or, when the</p>
              <p>loan is advanced in instalments,  from the date of the advance of  the last instalment actually paid] as may, from time to time, be fixed  by the rules made under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The period fixed as aforesaid shall not ordinarily exceed  thirty- five years.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government , in making  the rules fixing  the period, shall, in considering whether the period should extend to  thirty- five years, or whether it should extend beyond thirty- five  years, have regard to the durability of the work for the purpose of  which the loan is granted, and to the expediency of the cost of the  work being paid by the generation of persons who will immediately  benefit by the work.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Recovery of loans.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-7.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Subject to such rules as may be made  under section 10, all loans granted under this Act, all interest (if   any) chargeable thereon, and costs (if any) incurred in making the  same, shall, when they become due, be recoverable by the Collector in  all or any of the following modes, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>from the borrower-- as if they were arrears of land-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-7.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>revenue due by him;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.1.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>from his surety (if any)-- as if they were arrears of  land- revenue due by him;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.1.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>out of the land for the benefit of which the loan has  been granted-- as if they were arrears of land- revenue  due in respect of that land;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.1.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>out of the property comprised in the collateral security</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>(if any)-- according to the procedure for the  realization of land- revenue by the sale of immovable  property other than the land on which that revenue is  due:</p>
              <blockList id="section-7.1.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that no proceeding in respect of any land under clause</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.1.list6.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>shall affect any interest in that land which existed before the  date of the order granting the loan, other than the interest of the  borrower, and of mortgagees of, or persons having charges on, that  interest, and, where the loan is granted under section 4 with the  consent of another person, the interest of that person, and of  mortgagees of, or persons having charges on, that interest.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When any sum due on account of any such loan, interest or  costs is paid to the Collector by a surety or an owner of property  comprised in any collateral security, or is recovered under sub-</p>
              <p>section (1) by the Collector from a surety or out of any such  property, the</p>
              <p>Collector shall, on the application of the surety or the owner of that  property (as the case may be), recover that sum on his behalf from the  borrower, or out of the land for the benefit of which the loan has  been granted, in manner provided by sub- section (1).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall be in the discretion of a Collector acting under  this section to determine the order in which he will resort to the  various modes of recovery permitted by it.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Order granting loan conclusive on certain points. A written  order under the hand of an officer empowered to make loans under this</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Act granting a loan to, or with the consent of, a person mentioned  therein, for the purpose of carrying out a work described therein, for  the benefit of land specified therein, shall, for the purposes of this</p>
              <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Act, be conclusive evidence--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>that the work described is an improvement within the  meaning of this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>that the person mentioned had at the date of the order a  right to make such an improvement; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>that the improvement is one benefiting the land  specified.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Liability of joint borrowers as among themselves. When a loan  is made under this Act to the members of a village- community or to any  other persons on such terms that all of them are jointly and severally  bound to the Government for the payment of the whole amount payable in  respect thereof, and a statement showing the portion of that amount  which as among themselves each is bound to contribute is entered upon  the order granting the loan and is signed by each of them and by the  officer making the order, that statement shall be conclusive evidence  of the portion of that amount which as among themselves each of those  persons is bound to contribute.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules. The State Government  may, from  time to time, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules  consistent with this Act to provide for the following matters,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the manner of making applications for loans;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the officers by whom loans may be granted;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the manner of conducting inquiries relative to  applications for loans, and the powers to be exercised  by officers conducting those inquiries;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the nature of the security to be taken for the due  application and repayment of the money, the rate of  interest at which, and the conditions under which,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>loans may be granted, and the manner and time of  granting loans;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list3.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the inspection of works for which loans have been  granted;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list3.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the instalments by which, and the mode in which, loans,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>the interest to be charged on them and the costs  incurred in the making thereof, shall be paid;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list5.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the manner of keeping and auditing the accounts of the  expenditure of loans and of the payments made in  respect of the same; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list5.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>all other matters pertaining to the working of the Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Exemption of improvements from assessment to land- revenue.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>When land is improved with the aid of a loan granted under this Act,</p>
              <p>the increase in value derived from the improvement shall not be taken  into account in revising the assessment of land- revenue on the land:</p>
              <p>Provided as follows--</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>where the improvement consists of the reclamation of  waste- land, or of the irrigation of land assessed at  unirrigated rates, the increase may be so taken into  account after the expiration of such period as may be  fixed by rules to be framed by the State Government</p>
              <p>;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>nothing in this section shall entitle any person to call  in question any assessment of land- revenue otherwise  than as it might have been called in question if this</p>
              <p>Act had not been passed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Certain powers of State Government to be exercisable by</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Board of Revenue or Financial Commissioner. The powers conferred on a</p>
              <p>State Government by sections 4 (1), 5 (1) and 10 may, in a State for  which there is a Board of Revenue or a Financial Commissioner, be  exercised in the like manner and subject to the like conditions by  such Board or Financial Commissioner, as the case may be: Provided  that rules made by a Board of Revenue or Financial Commissioner shall  be subject to the control of the State Government.]</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
