<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1950/40/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1950/40"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Army And Air Force (Disposal Of Private Property) Act, 1950"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1950/40/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1950/40/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1950/40/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1950/40/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Army And Air Force (Disposal Of Private Property) Act, 1950</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called The Army and Air Force (Disposal of Private Property) Act, 1950.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India, and applies to citizens of India and persons subject to the Army Act, 1950, or the Air Force Act, 1950, wherever they may be.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government may by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“Committee” means the Committee of Adjustment constituted under section 4;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“Prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>“Regimental and other debts in camp or quarters” includes—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.3.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>in relation to any person subject to the Army Act, 1950, moneys due as military debts, namely, sums due in respect of or of any advance in respect of—</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>quarters;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>mess, band and other regimental accounts;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.3.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>military clothing, appointments and equipments, not exceeding a sum equal to three months’ pay of the deceased and having become due within eighteen months before the date of his death; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.3.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>in relation to any person subject to the Air Force Act, 1950, moneys due as air force debts, namely, sums due in respect of or of any advance in respect of—</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>quarters;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>mess, band and other service accounts;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.3.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>air force clothing, appointments and equipments, not exceeding a sum equal to three months’ pay of the deceased and having become due within eighteen months before the date of his death;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“representation” includes probate, letters of administration, with or without the will annexed and a succession certificate, constituting a person executor or administrator of the estate of a deceased person or authorising him to receive or realise the assets of a deceased person;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>“representative” means any person who has taken out representation, but does not include an Administrator-General;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>all words and expressions used herein and defined in the Army Act, 1950, or the Air Force Act, 1950, and not in this Act defined shall be deemed to have the meaning respectively attributed to them by those Acts.</p>
            <p>.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Property of deceased persons and deserters other than officers.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>On the death or desertion of any person, not being an officer, subject to the Army Act, 1950, or the Air Force Act, 1950, as the case may be, the commanding officer of the corps, department, detachment or unit to which the deceased or deserter belonged, shall as soon as may be and subject to any rules that may be made in this behalf—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>secure all the movable property belonging to the deceased or deserter that is in camp or quarters, and cause an inventory thereof to be made,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>draw the pay and allowances due to such person,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>make due provision for the payment of regimental and other debts in camp or quarters, if any, of such persons.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In the case of a deceased person, the commanding officer,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>if in any case not otherwise provided for by rules made under this Act it appears to him to be necessary to make provision for the payment of regimental and other debts in camp or quarters, the funeral expenses of the deceased and the expenses, if any, incurred by the commanding officer in respect of the estate of the deceased, shall, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in any other case, may,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>collect all moneys left by the deceased in any banking company (including any post office savings bank, co-operative bank or society or any other institution receiving deposits in money however named) and for that purpose may require the agent, manager or other proper officer of such banking company, society or other institution to pay the moneys to the commanding officer forthwith, notwithstanding anything in the rules of the banking company, society or other institution, and such agent, manager or other officer shall be bound to comply with the requisition.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any money has been paid by a banking company, society or other institution in compliance with a requisition made under sub-section (2), no person shall have any claim against the banking company, society or other institution in respect of such money.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the representative of a deceased has given security to the satisfaction of the commanding officer for the payment of the regimental and other debts in camp or quarters, if any, and of the funeral expenses of the deceased in cases where no provision for the payment of such expenses has been made otherwise and of the expenses, if any, incurred by the commanding officer in respect of the estate and deceased, the commanding officer shall deliver over the property received by him under sub-sections (1) and (2) to that representative, whereupon his responsibility for the administration of the estate of the deceased shall cease.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.5.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In the case of a deceased whose estate has not been dealt with under sub-section (4), or under section 10, and in the case of a deserter, the commanding officer,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.5.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>if in any case it is necessary in his opinion so to do for the purpose of securing the payment of the regimental and other debts in camp or quarters of the deceased or deserter, the funeral expenses of the deceased, if any, and the expenses, if any, incurred by the commanding officer in respect of the estate of the deceased or deserter, shall, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.5.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>In any other case, may,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>cause the moveable property of the deceased or deserter, as the case may be, to be sold or converted into money.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The commanding officer shall, out of the moneys received, collected or realised under sub-sections (1), (2) and (5), pay the regimental and other debts in camp or quarters, if any, of the deceased or deserter, as the case may be, the expenses, if any, incurred by the commanding officer in respect of the estate of the deceased or deserter, and in the case of a deceased his funeral expenses in cases where no provision for the payment of such expenses has been made otherwise.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.7.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The surplus, if any, after payment of the debts and expenses specified in sub-section (6), shall,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.7.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in the case of a deceased, be paid to his representative, if any, or in the event of no claim to such surplus being established within twelve months after the death, to the prescribed person; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.7.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in the case of a deserter, be forthwith paid to the prescribed person, and shall, on the expiry of three years from the date of desertion, be forfeited to the Central Government, unless the deserter shall have surrendered or been apprehended in the meantime:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that the prescribed person may, if the deserter has not surrendered or been apprehended in the meantime, pay the whole or any part of the surplus received by him under clause (b), to the wife or children or any other dependent of the deserter at any time during the said period of three years.</p>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <p>In this section and in section 4, the word “officer” with reference to persons subject to the Air Force Act, 1950, includes a warrant officer who has died or deserted.</p>
            <p>.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Property of officers who die or desert.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The provisions of section 3 shall also apply to the disposal of the property of any officer subject to the Army Act, 1950, or the Air Force Act, 1950, who dies or deserts, but with the following modifications, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the functions of the commanding officer under section 3 shall be performed by a Committee of Adjustment constituted in this behalf in the prescribed manner;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>the surplus, if any, after payment of the debts and expenses specified in sub-section (6) of section 3, shall in the case of a deceased officer, be paid to the prescribed person.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Decision of questions as to regimental and other debts in camp or quarters.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If in any case a doubt or difference arises as to what are the regimental and other debts in camp or quarters of a deceased or deserter or as to the amount payable in respect thereof, the decision of the prescribed person shall be final and shall be binding on all persons for all purposes.</p>
            <p>.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Representative powers of commanding officer or Committee.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of the exercise of his or its duties under section 3 or section 4, the commanding officer or the Committee, as the case may be, shall, to the exclusion of all other persons and authorities whosoever or whatsoever, have the same rights and powers as if he or it had taken out representation to the estate of the deceased, and any receipt given by the commanding officer or the Committee, as the case may be, shall have effect accordingly.</p>
            <p>.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to hand over estate of deceased to the Administrator-General.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Administrators-General Act, 1963 (45 of 1863), an Administrator-General shall not interpose in any manner in relation to any property of a deceased which has been dealt with under the provisions of section 3 or section 4, except insofar as he is expressly required or permitted to do so by or under the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, at any time and in such circumstances as it thinks fit, direct that the estate of a deceased shall be handed over by the commanding officer or the Committee, as the case may be, to the Administrator-General of a State for administration, and thereupon the commanding officer or the Committee, as the case may be, shall make over the estate to such Administrator-General.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where under this section any estate is handed over to the Administrator-General, the Administrator-General shall administer such estate in accordance with the provisions of</p>
            <p>the Administrators-General Act, 1963 (45 of 1963), or if that Act is not in force in any State of the corresponding law in force in that State:</p>
            <p>Provided that the regimental and other debts in camp or quarters of the deceased, if any, shall be paid by the Administrator-General in priority to any other debts due by the deceased.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Administrator-General shall pay the surplus, if any, remaining in his hands after discharging all debts and charges, to the heirs of the deceased, and, if no heir is traceable, shall make over the surplus in the prescribed manner to the prescribed person.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Administrator-General shall not charge in respect of his duties under this section any fee exceeding three per cent. of the gross amount coming to or remaining in his hands after payment of the regimental and other debts in camp or quarters.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Disposal of surplus by prescribed persons.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>On receipt of the surplus referred to in sub-section (7) of section 3 or clause (ii) of section 4 or sub-section (4) of section 7, the prescribed person shall,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>if he knows of a representative of the deceased, pay the surplus to that representative;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>if he does not know of any such representative and the surplus has not been disposed of under section 10, publish every year a notice in the prescribed form and manner for six consecutive years and if no claim to the surplus is made by a representative of the deceased within six months even after the publication of the last of such notices, the prescribed person shall deposit the surplus together with any income or accumulation of income accrued therefrom, to the credit of the Central Government:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that such deposit shall not bar the claim of any person to such surplus or any part thereof, if he is otherwise entitled to it.</p>
            <p>.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Disposal of effects, not money.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where any part of the estate of a deceased person consists of effects, securities or other property not converted into money the provisions of sub-section (7) of section 3, clause (ii) of section 4 and section 8, with respect to the payment of the surplus, shall, save as may be prescribed, extend to the delivery, transmission or transfer of such effects, securities or property, and the prescribed person shall have the same power of converting the same into money as a representative of the deceased.</p>
            <p>.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Disposal of certain property without production of probate, etc.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Property deliverable and money payable to the representative of a deceased under section 3 or section 4 or section 8 may, if the total amount or value thereof does not exceed two lakhs rupees and if the prescribed person thinks fit, be delivered or paid to any person appearing to him to be entitled to receive it or to administer the estate of the deceased without requiring such person to produce any probate, letters of administration, succession certificate or other such conclusive evidence of title.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Discharge of commanding officer, Committee, prescribed person and the Central Government.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any payment or application of money or application, delivery, sale or other disposition of any property made, or purported to be made, by the commanding officer, the Committee or the prescribed person in good faith in pursuance of section 3, section 4, section 8, section 9 or section 10 shall be valid and shall be a full discharge to the commanding officer, the Committee or the prescribed person, as the case may be, and to the Central Government from all further liability in respect of that money or property, but nothing herein contained shall affect the right of any executor or administrator or other representative, or of any creditor of the deceased against any person to whom such payment or delivery has been made.</p>
            <p>.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Property in the hands of commanding officer, Committee or prescribed person not to be assets where commanding officer, Committee or prescribed person is stationed.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any property coming into the hands of the commanding officer or the Committee or the prescribed person under section 3, section 4 or sub-section (4) of section 7 shall not, by reason thereof, be deemed to be assets or effects at the place in which that commanding officer or the Committee or the prescribed person is stationed, and it shall not be necessary by reason thereof that representation be taken out in respect of that property for that place.</p>
            <p>.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Saving of rights of representative.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>After the commanding officer, or the Committee has paid to the prescribed person the surplus of the property of any deceased under sub-section (7) of section 3 or clause (ii) of section 4, any representative of the deceased or any Administrator-General, shall, as regards any property of the deceased not collected by the commanding officer or the Committee, as the case may be, and not forming part of the aforesaid surplus, have the same rights and duties as if sections 3 and 4 that not been enacted.</p>
            <p>.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Application of sections 3 to 13 to persons of unsound mind or to persons reported missing on active service.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of section 3 to 13 shall, so far as they can be made applicable, also apply in the case of a person subject to the Army Act, 1950, or the Air Force Act, 1950, as the case may be, who, notwithstanding anything contained in the Mental Health Act, 1987 (14 of 1987), is ascertained in the prescribed manner to be of unsound mind, or who, while on active service, is officially reported missing, as if he had died on the day on which his unsoundness of mind is so ascertained or, as the case may be, on the day on which he is officially reported missing:</p>
            <p>Provided that in the case of a person so reported missing, no action shall be taken under sub-sections (2) to (6) of section 3 or section 4 or section 7 until such time as he is officially presumed to be dead.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Appointment of Standing Committee of Adjustment in certain cases.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>When an officer dies or deserts or is ascertained in the prescribed manner to be of unsound mind or while on active service is officially reported missing, the references in the foregoing provisions of this Act to the committee shall be construed as references to the Standing Committee of Adjustment, if any, constituted in this behalf in the prescribed manner and such Standing Committee shall alone be entitled to perform all the functions of the Committee under this Act.</p>
            <p>.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-16.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for the purpose of carrying into effect the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-16.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>prescribe the manner in which any property belonging to a deceased or deserter may be secured or collected and his regimental and other debts in camp or quarters paid;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>provide for the payment of the funeral expenses of any deceased;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>provide for the constitution of the Committee of Adjustment or any Standing Committee of Adjustment under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>specify the person who shall be regarded as the prescribed person for the purposes of this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>prescribe the circumstances in which the estate of any deceased shall be handed over to the Administrator-General;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>prescribe the form and manner in which a notice under section 8 shall be published;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>prescribe the procedure by which any person may be ascertained to be of unsound mind.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Repeals.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>(Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1957 (36 of 1957), sec. 2 and Sch. I (w.e.f. 17-9-1957).</p>
            <p>.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
