<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-arp/act/1997/6/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-arp/act/1997/6"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Arunachal Pradesh Prevention Of Defacement Of Property Act, 1997"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-arp/act/1997/6/eng@2017-01-16/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-arp/act/1997/6/eng@2017-01-16"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-16" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-arp/act/1997/6/eng@2017-01-16/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-arp/act/1997/6/eng@2017-01-16"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-13" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Arunachal Pradesh Prevention Of Defacement Of Property Act, 1997</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[Act No. 06 of 1997]</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>An Act to provide for the prevention of defacement of property and for matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.</p>
      <p>BE it enacted by the Legislative Assembly of Arunachal Pradesh in the Forty-eighth Year of the Republic of India as follows:-</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Arunachal Pradesh Prevention of Defacement of Property Act, 1997.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Arunachal Pradesh.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires:</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"Deputy Commissioner" means the Deputy Commissioner of a district and includes any officer appointed by the Government to exercise and perform all or any of the powers and functions of a Deputy Commissioner under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>'defacement' includes impairing or interfering with the appearance or beauty, damaging, disfiguring, spoiling or injuring in any way whatsoever and the word "deface" shall be construed accordingly;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>"Government" means the Government of Arunachal Pradesh;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>"notification" means a notification published in the Official Gazette;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>"Official Gazette" means the Official Gazette of Arunachal Pradesh;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>"property" means any property--Government or private including any building, hut, monument, statue, water pipe lines, public roads, structure, wall including compound wall, trees, fence, post, pole or any other erection except those specified or identified places as may be allowed by the Deputy Commissioner or by such officer authorised by him in this behalf from time to time;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>"public place" means any place (including a road, street or way whether a thorough fare or not and a landing place) to which the public are granted access or have a right to resort or over which they have a right to pass;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>"public view" means anything which is visible to public while they are in or passing along with any public place;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>"writing" includes decoration, lettering, ornamentation etc., produced by stencil or in any other manner.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for defacement of property</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever defaces any property in public view by defecating or spitting or urinating or pasting pamphlets, posters or writing or marking with ink, chalk, paint or any other material or method except for the purpose of indicating the name and address of the owner or occupier of such property, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any offence committed under sub-section (1) is for the benefit of some other person or a company or other body corporate or an association of persons (whether incorporated or not), then such other person and every President, Chairman, Director, partner, Manager, Secretary, agent or any other officer or person concerned with the management thereof as the case may be, shall, unless he proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or consent, be deemed to be guilty of such offence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for attempt to commit offences</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Whoever attempts to commit any offence punishable under this Act or to cause such offence to be committed and in such attempt does any act towards the commission of the offence shall be punishable with the punishment provided for the offence under section 3.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for abetment</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any person who, by the supply of or solicitation for money, provides premises, supply material's or in any manner whatsoever, procures, counsels, aids, abets in the commission of offence or is accessory to such commission of offence under this Act shall be punishable with the punishments provided for the offence under section 3.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Offence to be cognizable</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>An offence punishable under this Act shall be cognizable.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Erasure of writings etc. powers of Deputy Commissioner</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Without prejudice to the provisions of section 3, it shall be competent for the Deputy Commissioner to take such steps as may be necessary for erasing any writing, freeing any defacement or removing any mark, hoarding or cut outs from any property.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against the Government, any local authority or person for anything which is in good faith or in public interest done or intended to be done under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Act to over ride other laws</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any other law for the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
