<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1997/17/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1997/17"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Lalit Kala Akadami (Taking Over Management) Act, 1997"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1997/17/eng@1997-03-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1997/17/eng@1997-03-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1997-03-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1997/17/eng@1997-03-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1997/17/eng@1997-03-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Lalit Kala Akadami (Taking Over Management) Act, 1997</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 17 OF 1997</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 25th March, 1997]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- eighth year of Republic of</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the taking over of the management of the Lalit</p>
        <p>Kala Akadami for a limited period in the public interest and for  matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS the Lalit Kala Akadami was set up as a apex cultural body in  the field of visual arts by the Government of India by the Parliament  any Resolution passed on the 5th day of August, 1954 to encourage and  promote visual arts such as painting, graphics, sculptures, etc.;</p>
        <p>AND WHEREAS the Lalit Kala Akadami was registered as a society under  the Societies Registration Act, 1860 on the 11th day of March, 1957;</p>
        <p>AND WHEREAS the Akadami has full functional autonomy in the field of  its activity, even though the Government of India is the sole- funding  agency for the organisation;</p>
        <p>AND WHEREAS pursuant to the complaints received with regard to the  misuse of funds by the Lalit Kala Akadami from several quarters  including from the Hon' ble Members of Parliament, a Committee was set  up by the Government of India by resolution dated the 24th day of</p>
        <p>March, 1988 under the Chairmanship of Shri P. N. Haksar to go into the  functioning of National Akadamies including the Lalit Kala Akadami and  the said Committee, after a detailed scrutiny of the affairs in the  management of the said Akadami, recommended the restructuring of their</p>
        <p>General Council Executive Board and the electoral roll, of the artists  constituency;</p>
        <p>AND WHEREAS, in view of the serious difficulties which have arisen  with regard to the management of the Lalit Kala Akadami, it is  necessary to take over, for a limited period, the management thereof  and it is felt that any delay in taking over the management of the</p>
        <p>Lalit Kala Akadami would be highly detrimental to the interests and  objective of Akadami;</p>
        <p>India as follows:-</p>
        <p>CHAP</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <heading>Preliminary</heading>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the Lalit Kala Akadami (Taking Over of</p>
              <p>Management) Act, 1997.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 24th day of</p>
              <p>January, 1997.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" Administrator" means a person appointed as the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Administrator under section 4;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" Societies Registration Act" means the Societies Registration Act,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1860">
          <num>1860.</num>
          <heading>(21 of 1860), as in force in the National Capital Territory of</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-1860.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1860.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Delhi;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1860.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" society" means the Lalit Kala Akadami being a society  registered under the Societies Registration Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1860.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>words and expressions used herein and not defined, but  defined in the Societies Registration Act shall have the meanings  respectively assigned to them in that Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>TAKING OVER OF THE MANAGEMENT OF THE LALIT KALA AKADAMI</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <heading>Taking over of the management of the lalit kala akadami</heading>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Management of the society.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On and from the commencement of this Act, and for a period of  three years thereafter, the management of the society shall vest in  the Central Government:</p>
              <p>Provided that if the Central Government is of opinion that in order to  secure the proper management of the society, it is expedient that such  management should continue to vest in the Central Government after the  expiry of the said period of three years, it may, from time to time,</p>
              <p>issue directions for the continuance of such management for such  period, not exceeding one year at a time, as it may think fit; so,</p>
              <p>however, that the total period for which such management shall  continue to vest in the Central Government shall not, in any case,</p>
              <p>exceed five years.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The management of the society shall be deemed to include  management of all assets, rights, lease- holds, powers, authorities and  privileges and all property, movable and immovable, including lands,</p>
              <p>buildings, works of art, workshops, projects, stores, instruments,</p>
              <p>library, machinery automobile and other vehicles, cash balances,</p>
              <p>reserve funds, investments and book debts and all other rights and  interests arising out of such property as were immediately before the  commencement of this Act in the ownership, possession, power or  control of the society, and all such books of account, registers,</p>
              <p>maps, plans and all other documents of whatever nature relating  thereto.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any contracts, whether express or implied, or other arrangement,</p>
              <p>in so far as it relates to the management of the society and affairs  of the society and in force immediately before the commencement of  this Act shall be deemed to have terminated on such commencement.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All persons in charge of the management of the society, including  persons holding offices as Chairman, Vice- Chairman, Secretary or</p>
              <p>Honorary Secretary, as the case may be, and members of the General</p>
              <p>Council, Executive Board, Finance Committee and all other committees  of the society immediately before the commencement of this Act shall  be deemed to have vacated their offices as such on such commencement.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Administrator of society.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government shall, as from the commencement of  this Act, appoint a person as the Administrator of the society for the  purpose of taking over the administration thereof and the</p>
              <p>Administrator shall carry on the management of the Society for and on  behalf of the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the supervision control and directions of the</p>
              <p>Administrator, the functions of the finance Committee of the Society,</p>
              <p>before the commencement of this Act, shall be exercised by an officer  of the Central Government, to be appointed by that Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may issue such directions (including  directions as to initiating, defending or continuing any legal   proceedings before any court, tribunal or other authority) to the</p>
              <p>Administrator as to his powers and duties as that Government may deem  desirable and the Administrator may apply to the Central Government at  any time for instructions as to the manner in which he shall conduct  the management of the society or in relation to any matter arising in  the course of such management.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the other provisions of this Act and the rules made  thereunder and to the control of the Central Government, the</p>
              <p>Administrator shall be entitled, notwithstanding anything contained in  the Societies Registration Act or any other law for the time being in  force, to exercise, in relation to the management of the society, the  powers of the General Council, or, as the case may be, the Executive</p>
              <p>Board, including the powers to dispose of any property or assets of  such society, whether such powers are derived under any law for the  time being in force or form the memorandum and rules and regulations  of the society or from any other source.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every person having possession, custody or control of any  property forming part of the society shall deliver forthwith such  property to the Administrator.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person who, on the commencement of this Act, has in his  possession or under his control any books, papers, works of art or  other documents relating to management of the society, including the  minutes books containing the resolutions of the persons in charge of  the management of the society before the commencement of this Act, the  current cheque books relating to the management of the society, any  letters, memoranda, notes or other communications between him and the  society shall, notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for  the time being in force, liable to account for the books, papers,</p>
              <p>works of art and other documents (including such minutes books, cheque   books, letters, memoranda, notes or other communications) to the</p>
              <p>Administrator.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person in charge of the administrator of the society  immediately before the commencement of this Act shall, within ten days  from that day or within such further periods as the Central Government  may allow in this behalf, furnish to the Administrator a complete  inventory of all the properties and assets (including particulars of   book debts and investments and belongings) forming part of the society  immediately before the commencement of this Act, and of all the  liabilities and obligations of the society, in relation to its  administration, subsisting immediately before such commencement, and  also of all agreements entered into by the society in relation to its  administration and in force immediately before such commencement.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Administrator shall receive from the funds of the society  such remuneration as the Central Government may fix.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>No right to compensation for premature termination of a contract.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time being in  force, no person in respect of whom any contract of management or  other arrangement is terminated by reason of the provisions contained  in sub- section (3) of section 3 or who ceases to hold any office by  reason of the provisions contained in sub- section (4) of that section,</p>
              <p>shall be entitled to claim any compensation for the premature  termination of the contract of administration or other arrangement or  for the loss of his office.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Relinquishment of administration of the society.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1) of that  section 3, if, at any tim e before the expiry of the period referred  to in of purposes have Government been fulfilled or that for any other  reason it is not necessary that the management of the society should  remain vested in that Government, it may, by order published in the</p>
              <p>Official Gazette, relinquish the management of the society with effect  from such date as may be specified in the order.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On and from the date specified under sub- section (1), the  administration of the society shall vest in the General Council of the  society and such management shall be carried on in accordance with the  provisions of the Societies Registration Act so, however, that the  steps, if any, in relation to the management of the society may be  taken after the publication of the order under sub- section (1).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Application of Act 21 of 1860.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Societies Registration</p>
              <p>Act or in the memorandum and rules and regulations of the society, but  subject to the provisions of sub- section (2) of section 6, so long as  the management of the society remains vested in the Central</p>
              <blockList id="section-7.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Government.-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.1.list3.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>it shall not be lawful for the members of the society or any other  person to nominate or appoint any person to be a member of the General</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-7.1.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Council of the society;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.1.list5.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>no resolution passed at any meeting of the members of the society  or at any meeting of the General Council of the society, on or after  the commencement of this Act, shall be given effect to unless approved  by the Central Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.1.list5.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>no proceeding for the dissolution of the society or for the merger  with any other society or for the appointment of a Receiver in respect  of its administration shall lie in any court except with the consent  of the Central Government.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions contained in sub- section (1) and subject  to such other exception, restrictions and limitations, if any, as may  be prescribed, the Societies Registration Act shall continue to apply  to the society in the same manner as it applied there to before the  commencement of this Act.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <heading>Miscellaneous</heading>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Penalties.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Any person who,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>having in his possession or custody or under his control any  property forming part of the society, wrongfully withholds such  property from the Administrator or any person authorised under this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Act, or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>wrongfully obtains possession of any such property, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>wilfully retains, or fails to deliver, any property forming part  of the society or removes or destroys it, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>wilfully withholds or fails to account for any books, papers,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>works of art or other documents which may be in his possession or  custody or under his control to the Administrator or any person  authorised under this Act, or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list5.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>fails, without any reasonable cause, to furnish information or  particulars as provided in sub- section (6) of section 4,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which mayextend to two  years, or with fine which may extend to ten thousand rupees, or with  both.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Offences by companies.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where an offence under this Act has been committed by a company,</p>
              <p>every person who at the time the offence was committed was in charged  of, and was responsible to, the company for te conduct of the business  of the company as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of  the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished  accordingly:</p>
              <p>Provided that nothing contained in this section shall render any such  person liable to any punishment if he proves that the offence was  committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised all due  diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where any  offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is  proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or  connivance of, or is attributable to, any neglect on the part of any  director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such  director, manager, secretary or other officer shall be deemed to be  guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and  punished accordingly.</p>
              <blockList id="section-9.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-9.2.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" company" means any body corporate and include a firm or other  association of individuals; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.2.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partnet in the firm.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Exclusion of period of operation of Act.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Inc computing the period of limitation prescribed by any law for the  time being in force for any suit or application against any person by  the society in respect of any matter arising out of any transaction in  relation to its management, the time during which this Act is in force  shall be excluded.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Act to have overriding effect.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of this Act or any notification, order or rule made  thereunder shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent  therewith contained in any law other than this Act or in any  instrument having effect by virtue of any law other than this Act or  in any decree or order of any court.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-12.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall against the</p>
              <p>Administrator or any officer of the Central Government or any other  person for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done  under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No Suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central</p>
              <p>Government or the Administrator or any officer of the Central</p>
              <p>Government or any other person for any damage caused or likely to be  caused by anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done  under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Contracts in bad faith may be cancelled or varied.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-13.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the Central Government is satisfied, after such inquiry as it  may think fit, that any contract or agreement entered into at any time  within one year immediately proceeding the commencement of this Act,</p>
              <p>between the society and any other person, in so far as such contract  or agreement relates to the management of the society, has been  entered into in bad faith, or is detrimental to the interests of the  society, it may make an order cancelling or varying (either  unconditionally or subject to such conditions as it may think fit to   impose) such contract or agreement and thereafter the contract or  agreement shall have effect accordingly:</p>
              <p>Provided that no contract or agreement shall be cancelled or varied  except after giving to the parties to the contract or agreement a  reasonable opportunity of being heard.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person aggrieved by an order under sub- section (1) may make an  application to the High Court at Delhi for the variation or reversal  of such order and thereupon such court may confirm, modify or reverse  such order.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Power to terminate contract of employment.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>If the Administrator is of opinion that any contract of employment  entered into by the society in relation to its management, at any time  before the commencement of this Act, is unduly onerous, he may, by  giving to the employee one month' s notice in writing or the salary or  wages for one month in lieu thereof, terminate such contract of  employment.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-15.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official</p>
              <p>Gazette, make rules for carrying out the provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act shall be  laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of</p>
              <p>Parliament while it is session for a total period of thirty days which  may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions,</p>
              <p>and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the  sessions or the successive sessions aforesaid, both House agree in  making any modification in the rule or bothHouses agree that the rule  should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such  modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however,</p>
              <p>that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to  the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Repeal and saving.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-16.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Lalit Kala Akadami (Taking Over of Management) Ordinance, 1997  is hereby repealed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding the repeal of the Lalit Kala Akadami (Taking Over   of Management) Ordinance, 1997, anything done or any action taken  under the said Ordinance, shall be deemed to have been done or taken  under the corresponding provisions of this Act.</p>
              <p>K. L. MOHANPURIA,</p>
              <p>Secy, to the Govt. of India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
