<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1855/12/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1855/12"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Legal Representatives' Suits Act, 1855"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1855/12/eng@1855-03-27/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1855/12/eng@1855-03-27"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1855-03-27" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1855/12/eng@1855-03-27/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1855/12/eng@1855-03-27"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-11-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Legal Representatives' Suits Act, 1855]</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 12 OF 1855</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 27th March, 1855]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to enable Executors, Administrators or Representatives to sue  and be sued for certain wrongs.</p>
        <p>Preamble.-- WHEREAS it is expedient to enable executors,</p>
        <p>administrators or representatives in certain cases to sue and be sued  in respect of certain wrongs which, according to the present law, do  not survive to or against such executors, administrators or  representatives;</p>
        <p>It is enacted as follows:--</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Executors may sue and be sued in certain cases for wrongs  committed in lifetime of deceased.-- An action may be maintained by the  executors, administrators or representatives of any person deceased,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>for any wrong committed in the time of such person, which has  occasioned pecuniary loss to his estate, for which wrong an action  might have been maintained by such person, so as such wrong shall have  been committed within one year before his death ; and the  damages, when recovered, shall be part of the personal estate of such  person;</p>
            <p>and further, an action may be maintained against the executors or  administrators or heirs or representatives of any person deceased for  any wrong committed by him in his lifetime for which he would have  been subject to an action, so as such wrong shall have been committed  within one year before such person' s death ; and the d amages to  be recovered in such action shall, if recovered against an executor or  administrator bound to administer according to the English law, be  payable in like order of administration as the simple contract debts  of such person.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Death of either party not to abate suit. Proviso.-- No action  commenced under the provisions of this Act shall abate by reason of  the death of either party, but the same may be continued by or against  the executors, administrators or representatives of the party  deceased: Provided that, in any case in which any such action shall be  continued against the executors, administrators or representatives of  a deceased party, such executors, administrators or representatives  may set up a want of assets as a defence to the action, either wholly  or in part, in the same manner as if the action had been originally  commenced against them.</heading>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
