<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/30/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/30"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The President' S Emoluments And Pension Act, 1951"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/30/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/30/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/30/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/30/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The President' S Emoluments And Pension Act, 1951</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 30 OF 1951 AN ACT TO PROVIDE FOR THE EMOLUMENTS OF THE PRESIDENT</docNumber>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>AND FORPENSION TO</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-13th">
        <num>13th.</num>
        <heading>May, 1951.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title. This Act may be called the President' s Emoluments  and Pension Act, 1951.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1A">
        <num>1A.</num>
        <heading>Emoluments of the President. There shall be paid to the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>President by way of emoluments twenty thousand rupees per mensem.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>] Pension to retiring Presidents. There shall be paid  to every person who ceases to hold office as President, either by the  expiration of his term of office or by resignation of his office, a  pension of  one lakh twenty thousand rupees per annum for the remainder  of his life.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to any rules that may be made in this behalf,</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>every such person shall, for the remainder of his life, be entitled-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.2.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to the use of a furnished residence (including its   maintenance), without payment of rent, a telephone and a  motor- car, free of charge or to such car allowance as may be  specified in the rules-,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.2.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to secretarial staff consisting of a Private Secretary,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.2.list4">
              <listIntroduction>a Personal Assistant and a Peon, and office expenses the  total expenditure on which shall not exceed twelve thousand  rupees per annum;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.2.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to medical attendance and treatment free of charge.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.2.list4.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>to travel anywhere in India, accompanied by one person,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>by  highest class by air, rail or steamer.</p>
            <p>Explanation.-- For the purposes of this sub- section</p>
            <p>" residence" shall have the meaning assigned to it in the</p>
            <p>Salaries and allowances of Ministers Act, 1952</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2A">
          <num>(2A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to any rules that may be made in this behalf, the  spouse of every such person shall, for the remainder of life, be  entitled to medical attendance and treatment, free of charge.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any such person is re- elected to the office of</p>
            <p>President, such person or the spouse of such person shall not be  entitled to any benefit under this section for the period during which  such person again holds that office.]]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Free medical attendance and treatment to spouse of President  dying in office. Subject to any rules that may be made in this  behalf, the spouse of a person who dies while holding the office of</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>President shall, for the remainder of life, be entitled to medical  attendance and treatment, free of charge.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Sums to be charged on the Consolidated Fund of India. Any    sum] payable under this Act shall be charged on the Consolidated</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Fund of India.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the</p>
            <p>Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this</p>
            <p>Act.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made by the Central Government under this</p>
            <p>Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each</p>
            <p>House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of  thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more  successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session  immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or  both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall  thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</p>
            <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously clone under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
