<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1855/28/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1855/28"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Usury Laws Repeal Act, 1855"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1855/28/eng@1855-09-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1855/28/eng@1855-09-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1855-09-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1855/28/eng@1855-09-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1855/28/eng@1855-09-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Usury Laws Repeal Act, 1855</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 28 OF 1855</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 19th September, 1855.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act for the repeal of the Usury Laws.</p>
        <p>Preamble.-- WHEREAS it is expedient to repeal the laws now in  force relating to usury; It is enacted as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Repeal of enactments. Rep. by the Repealing Act, 1870 (14 of</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1870">
        <num>1870.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1870.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Rate of interest to be decreed by Courts.-- In any suit in  which interest is recoverable the amount shall be adjudged or decreed  by the Court at the rate (if any) agreed upon by the parties; and if  no rate shall have been agreed upon, at such rate as the Court shall  deem reasonable.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Rate of interest upon a judgment or decree.-- Whenever a Court  shall direct that a judgment or decree shall bear interest, or shall  award interest upon a judgment or decree, it may order the interest to  be calculated at the rate allowed in the judgment or decree upon the  principal sum adjudged, or at such other rate as the Court shall think  fit.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Contracts for usufruct of property in lieu of interest.-- A</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>mortgage or other contract for the loan of money, by which it is  agreed that the use or usufruct of any property shall be allowed in  lieu of interest, shall be binding upon the parties.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Amount of interest to be deposited in certain cases of  conditional sales under Benga Regulaions. Proviso.-- Whenever, under  the Regulations of the Bengal Code, a deposit may be made of the   principal sum and interest due upon any mortgage or conditional sale  of land hereafter to be entered into, the amount of interest to be  deposited shall be at the rate stipulated in the contract, or, if no  rate has been stipulated and interest be payable under the terms of  the contract, at the rate of twelve Percentum per annum:</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Provided that, in the latter case, the amount deposited shall be  subject to the decision of the Court as to the rate at which interest  shall be calculated.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Rate of interest on future adjustments of acconts.-- In any  case in which an adjustment of accounts may become necessary between  the lender and the borrower of money upon any mortgage, conditional  sale of landed property, or other contract whatsoever, which may be  entered into after the passing of this Act, interest shall be  calculated at the rate stipulated therein; or, if no rate of interest  shall have been stipulated and interest be payable under the terms of  the contract, at such rate as the Court shall deem reasonable.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Saving of prior transactions. Rep. by the Repealing Act,</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1870">
        <num>1870.</num>
        <heading>(14 of 1870).</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Commencement of Act. Rep., ibid.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Schedule of Repealed Enactments. Rep., ibid.</heading>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
