<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1879/14/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1879/14"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Hackney- Carriage Act, 1879"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1879/14/eng@1879-09-05/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1879/14/eng@1879-09-05"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1879-09-05" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1879/14/eng@1879-09-05/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1879/14/eng@1879-09-05"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Hackney- Carriage Act, 1879</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 14 OF 1879</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 5th September, 1879.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act for the regulation and control of hackney- carriages  in  certain Municipalities and Cantonments.</p>
        <p>Preamble.- WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the  regulation  and control of hackney- carriages in certain municipalities  and  cantonments; It is hereby enacted as follows</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title.- This Act may be called the Hackaey- carriage</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Act, 1879</p>
            <p>Saving.- Nothing herein contained shall affect any power conferred  by any law relating to municipalities, or any rule made in exercise of  any such power.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Interpretation- clause.- In this Act-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>" hackney- carriage" means any wheeled vehicle drawn by animals and  used for the conveyance of passengers which is kept or offered or  plies for hire; and</p>
            <p>" committee" means a municipal committee, or a body of municipal  commissioners, constituted under the provisions of any enactment for  the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Application of Act to municipalities.-  The State Government  concerned may, by notification in the Official Gazette, apply this Act  to any municipalities in Uttar Pradesh,  Punjab as it existed  immediately before the 1st November, 1956], the Central Provinces,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Assam, Ajmer or Coorg.]</p>
            <p>Power of committees to make rules.- When this Act has been so  applied to any municipality, the committee of such municipality may,</p>
            <p>from time to time, make rules for the regulation and control of  hackney- carriages within the limits of such municipality, in the  manner in which, under the law for the time being in force, it makes  rules or bye- laws for the regulation and control of other matters  within such limits.</p>
            <p>Confirmation and publication of rules.- Every rule made under this  section shall, when confirmed by the  Commissioner] and published for  such time and in such, manner as the Commissioner may, from time to  time, prescribe, have the force of law:</p>
            <p>Power of Commissioner to rescind rules. Provided that the 5</p>
            <p>Commissioner may at anytime, rescind any such rule.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules for cantonments. Rep. by the A. O. 1937.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Power to extent operation of rules beyond limits of  municipality or cantonment.- The authority making any rules under this</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Act may' with the sanction of the Commissioner extend their  operation to any railway station, or specified part of a road, not  more than six miles from the local limits of the municipality   concerned.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>What rules under section 3 may provide for.-- The rules to be  made under section 3  may, among other matters,-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>direct that no hackney- carriage, or no hackney-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>carriage of a particular description, shall be let to  hire, or taken to ply, or offered for hire, except under  a license granted in that behalf;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>direct that no person shall act as driver of a  hackney- carriage except under a license granted in that  behalf;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>provide for the issue of the licenses referred to  in clauses (a) and (b), prescribe the conditions (if   any) on which such licenses shall be granted, and fix  the fees (if any) to be paid therefore;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>regulate the description of animals, harness and  other things to be used with licensed carriages, and the  condition in which such carriages, and the animals,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>harness and other things used therewith, shall be kept,</p>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list5">
              <listIntroduction>and the lights (if any) to be carried after sun set and  before sunrise;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list5.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>provide for the inspection of the premises on which  any such carriages, animals, harness and other, things  are kept;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list5.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>fix the time for which such licenses shall continue  in force, and the events (if any) upon which within such  time they shall be subject to revocation or suspension;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list5.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>provide for the numbering of such carriages;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list5.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>determine the times at which, and the  circumstances under which, any person keeping a hackney-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list7">
              <listIntroduction>carriage shall be bound to let or refuse to let such  carriage to any person requiring the same;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list7.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>appoint places as stands for hackney- carriages, and prohibit  such carriages waiting for hire except at such places;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list7.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>limit the rates or fares, as well for time as distance,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>which may be demanded for the hire of any hackney-</p>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list10">
              <listIntroduction>carriage; and prescribe the minimum speed at which such  carriages when hired by time shall be driven;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list10.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>limit the number of persons, and the weight of  property, which may be conveyed by any such carriage;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list10.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>require the owner or person in charge of any such  carriage to keep a printed list of fares, in English and  such other language as may be prescribed, affixed  inside such carriage in such place as may be determined  by the rules, and prohibit the destruction or defacement  of such list;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list10.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>require drivers to wear a numbered badge or ticket,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>and to produce their licenses when required by a</p>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list13">
              <listIntroduction>Magistrate or other person authorized by the rules in  this, behalf, and prohibit the transfer or lending of  such licenses and badges; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list13.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>provide for the deposit of property found in such  carriages, and the payment of a fee by the owner of such  property on the delivery thereof to him.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for breach of rules.- Any person breaking any rule made  under this Act shall be punished with fine which may extend to fifty  rupees.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Disposal of fees and payment of expenses.- The amount of any  fees received and the amount of any expenses incurred in giving effect  to this Act shall  be credited and debited respectively to the  municipal fund .</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Power of Magistrate to decide disputes regarding fares.- If any  dispute arises between the hirer of any hackney- carriage and the owner  or driver of such carriage as to the amount of the fare payable by  such hirer under any rule made under this Act, such dispute shall,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>upon application made in that behalf by either of the disputing  parties, be hear and determined by any Magistrate or Bench of</p>
            <p>Magistrates within the local limits of whose jurisdiction such dispute  has arisen; and such Magistrate or Bench may, besides determining the  amount so in dispute, direct that either party shall pay to the other  such sum as compensation for loss of time as such Magistrate or Bench  thinks fit.</p>
            <p>Any sum determined to be due or directed to be paid under this  section shall be recoverable as if it were a fine. 4</p>
            <p>The decision of any Magistrate or Bench in any case under this  section shall be final.</p>
            <p>When any such case is heard by a Bench, any difference of opinion  arising between the members of such Bench shall be settled in the same  manner as differences of opinion arising between such members in the  trial of criminal cases.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>In case of dispute, hirer may require driver to take him to</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Court.- If, at the time any dispute mentioned in section 9 arises, any</p>
            <p>Magistrate or Bench of Magistrates having jurisdiction in respect of  such dispute is sitting within the local limits to which the rules  apply, the hirer of the carriage may require the driver thereof to  take him in the same to the Court of such Magistrate or Bench for the  purpose of making an application under that section.</p>
            <p>Any driver neglecting or refusing to comply with such requisition  shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one  month, or with fine not exceeding fifty rupees, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
