<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1921/18/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1921/18"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Maintenance Orders Enforcement Act, 1921"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1921/18/eng@1921-10-05/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1921/18/eng@1921-10-05"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1921-10-05" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1921/18/eng@1921-10-05/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1921/18/eng@1921-10-05"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Maintenance Orders Enforcement Act, 1921</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 5th October, 1921.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 5th October, 1921.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>ACT NO. 18 OF</p>
        <p>An Act to facilitate the enforcement in  India] of Maintenance</p>
        <p>Orders made   in  reciprocating territories]],  and vice  versa.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to facilitate the enforcement in</p>
        <p>India] of Maintenance Orders made   in  reciprocating  territories]],  and vice versa; It is hereby enacted as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and extent.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Maintenance Orders Enforcement Act, 1921.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India  except the State of</p>
            <p>Jammu and kashmir].]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant  in the subject or context,-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>" Court of summary jurisdiction" means the Court of a Chief</p>
            <p>Presidency Magistrate or of a District Magistrate;</p>
            <p>" dependants" means such persons as a person against whom a  maintenance order is made is liable to maintain according to the law  in force in  the reciprocating territory] in which the maintenance  order is made;</p>
            <p>India" means the territory of India excluding the State of</p>
            <p>Jammu and Kashmir;]</p>
            <p>" maintenance order" means a decree or order, other than an order  of affiliation, made by a Court in the exercise of civil or criminal  jurisdiction for the periodical payment of sums of money towards</p>
            <p>the maintenance of the wife or other dependants of the person against  whom the order is made;</p>
            <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
            <p>" proper authority" means the authority appointed by, or under the  law of, a reciprocating territory to receive and transmit documents to  which this Act applies; and</p>
            <p>reciprocating territory" means any country or territory  outside India in respect of which this Act for the time being applies  by virtue of a declaration under section 3.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Declaration of reciprocal arrangements. If the Central</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Government is satisfied that legal provision exists in any country or  territory outside India for the enforcement within that country or  territory of maintenance orders made by Courts in India, the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare that  this Act applies in respect of that country or territory and thereupon  it shall apply accordingly.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Registration in India of maintenance orders made in the  reciprocating territories.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a maintenance order has, whether  before or after the passing of this Act, been made against any person  by any Court in any reciprocating territory, and a certified copy of  the order has been transmitted by the proper authority of that  territory to the Central Government, the Central Government shall send  a copy of the order to the prescribed officer of a Court in  India]</p>
            <p>for registration, and, on receipt thereof, the order shall be  registered in the prescribed manner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Court in which an order is to be so registered as  aforesaid shall, if the Court by which the order was made was, in the  opinion of the Central Government, a Court of superior jurisdiction,</p>
            <p>be a High Court, and, if the Court was not, in its opinion, a Court of  superior jurisdiction, be a Court of summary jurisdiction.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Transmission of maintenance orders made in India. Where a</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Court in  India] has, whether before or after the commencement of  this Act, made a maintenance order against any person, and it is  proved to that Court that the person against whom the order was made  is resident in a reciprocating territory, the Court shall send to the</p>
            <p>Central Government, for transmission to the proper authority of that  territory, a certified copy of the order.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Power of summary Courts to make provisional maintenance orders  against persons resident in reciprocating territories.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where  application is made to a Court of summary jurisdiction in  India]</p>
            <p>for a maintenance order against any person, and it is proved that  person is resident in a reciprocating territory, the Court may, in the  absence of that person, if after hearing the evidence it is satisfied  of the justice of the application, make any such order as it might  have made if that person had wilfully neglected to attend the Court;</p>
            <p>but in such case the order shall be provisional only and shall have no  effect unless and until confirmed by a competent Court in such  territory.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The evidence of every witness who is examined on any such  application shall be reduced to writing, and such deposition shall be  read over to, and signed by, him.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where such an order is made, the Court shall send to the</p>
            <p>Central Government, for transmission to the proper authority of the  reciprocating territory in which the person against whom the order is  made is alleged to reside, the depositions so taken and a certified  copy of the order together with a statement of the grounds on which  the making of the order might have been opposed if the person against  whom the order is made had been duly served with a summons and had  appeared at the hearing and such information as the Court possesses  for facilitating the identification of that person and ascertaining  his whereabouts.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any such provisional order has come before a Court in a  reciprocating territory for confirmation, and the order has by that</p>
            <p>Court been remitted to the Court of summary jurisdiction which made  the order for the purpose of taking further evidence, that Court  shall, after giving the prescribed notice, proceed to take the  evidence in like manner and subject to the like conditions as the  evidence in support of the original application.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If it appears to the Court hearing such evidence that the  order ought not to have been made, the Court may rescind the order,</p>
            <p>but in any other case the depositions shall be sent to the Central</p>
            <p>Government and dealt with in like manner as the original depositions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The confirmation of an order made under this section shall  not affect any power of a Court of summary jurisdiction to vary or  rescind that order:</p>
            <p>Provided that, on the making of a varying or rescinding order,</p>
            <p>the Court shall send a certified copy thereof to the Central</p>
            <p>Government for transmission to the proper authority of the  reciprocating territory in which the original order was confirmed, or  to which it was sent for confirmation and that, in the case of an  order varying the</p>
            <p>original order, the order shall not have any effect unless and until  confirmed in like manner as the original order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Power of Court of summary jurisdiction to confirm maintenance  order made out of India.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a maintenance order has been made  by a Court in a reciprocating territory and the order is provisional  only, and has no effect unless and until confirmed by a Court of  summary jurisdiction in  India], and a certified copy of the order,</p>
            <p>together with the depositions of the witnesses and a statement of the  grounds on which the order might have been opposed, has been  transmitted to the Central Government, and it appears to the Central</p>
            <p>Government that the person against whom the order has been made is  resident in  India], the Central Government may send the said  documents to the prescribed officer of a Court of summary  jurisdiction, with a requisition that a summons be issued calling upon  the person to show cause why that order should not be confirmed, and,</p>
            <p>upon recipt of such documents and requisition, the Court shall issue  such a summons and cause it to be served upon such person.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A summons issued under sub- section (1) shall for all purposes  be deemed to be a summons issued by the Court in the exercise of its  original criminal jurisdiction.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>At the hearing it shall be open to the person to whom the  summons was issued to raise any defence which he might have raised in  the original proceedings had he been a party thereto, but no other  defence, and the certificate from the Court which made the provisional  order stating the grounds on which the making of the order might have  been opposed if the person against whom the order was made had been a  party to the proceedings shall be conclusive evidence that those  grounds are grounds on which objection may be taken.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If at the hearing the person served with the summons does not  appear or, on appearing, fails to satisfy the Court that the order  ought not to be confirmed, the Court may, notwithstanding any  pecuniary limit imposed on its power by any law for the time being in  force in  India], confirm the order either without modification or  with such modifications as to the Court after hearing the evidence may  seem just:</p>
            <p>Provided that no sum shall be awarded as maintenance under this  section, or shall be recoverable as such, at a rate exceeding that  proposed in the provisional order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the person to whom the summons was issued appears at the  hearing and satisfies the Court that for the purpose of any defence</p>
            <p>it is necessary to remit the case to the Court which made the  provisional order for the taking of any further evidence, the Court  may for that purpose send a certified copy of the record to the</p>
            <p>Central Government for transmission to that Court through the proper  authority of the reciprocating territory, and may adjourn the  proceedings.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a provisional order has been confirmed under this  section, it may be varied or rescinded in like manner as if it had  originally been made by the confirming Court, and where on an  application for rescission or variation the Court is satisfied that it  is necessary to remit the case to the Court which made the provisional  order for the purpose of taking any further evidence, the Court may  for that purpose send a certified copy of the record to the Central</p>
            <p>Government for transmission to that Court through the proper authority  of the reciprocating territory, and may adjourn the proceedings.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Enforcement of maintenance orders.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the  provisions of this Act, where an order has been registered under this</p>
            <p>Act in a High Court, the order shall, from the date of such  registration, be of the same force and effect, and all proceedings may  be taken thereon as if it had been an order originally obtained in the</p>
            <p>High Court in the exercise of its civil jurisdiction, or in such Civil</p>
            <p>Court subordinate to that High Court as may be named by the High Court  in this behalf, and that Court shall have power to enforce the order  accordingly.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A Court of summary jurisdiction in which an order has been  registered under this Act or by which an order has been confirmed  under this Act, and the officers of such Court, shall have such powers  and perform such duties, for the purpose of enforcing the order, as  may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Payment of charges for transmission of sums awarded as  maintenance and other costs and charges. A Court in registering or  confirming an order for maintenance in accordance with the provisions  of this Act shall direct that the charges for the transmission to the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Court, from which the order has been received or in which the  provisional order has been made, as the case may be, of the sum  awarded as maintenance shall be borne by the person against whom the  order has been so made or confirmed, and shall be recovered from him  in addition to the sum awarded as maintenance and in addition to, and  in the same manner as, such other costs and charges as may be awarded  or levied by the Court.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Proof of documents signed by officers of Court. For the  purposes of this Act, any document purporting to be signed by a judge  or officer of a Court outside  India] shall, until the contrary is  proved, be deemed to have been so signed without</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>proof of the signature of judicial or official character of the person  appearing to have signed it, and the officer of a Court by whom a  document is signed shall, until the contrary is provided, be deemed to  have been the proper officer of the Court to sign the document.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Depositions to be evidence. Depositions taken in a Court in  any reciprocating territory may, for the purposes of this Act, be  received in evidence in proceedings before Courts of summary  jurisdiction under this Act.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Rule- making power.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government  may,</p>
            <p>by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules] for the purpose  of carrying into effect the purposes of this Act, and in particular  may make rules for the levy of the costs or charges for anything done  under this Act and for all matters which are directed or permitted to  be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act  shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House  of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty  days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more  successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session  immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or  both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall  thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</p>
            <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that rule.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
