<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1960/32/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1960/32"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The International Development Association (Status, Immunities Andprivileges) Act, 1960"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1960/32/eng@1960-09-09/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1960/32/eng@1960-09-09"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1960-09-09" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1960/32/eng@1960-09-09/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1960/32/eng@1960-09-09"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The International Development Association (Status, Immunities Andprivileges) Act, 1960</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 32 OF 1960</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 9th September, 1960.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to implement the international agreement for the establishment  and operation of the International Development Association in so far  as it relates to the status, immunities and privileges of that</p>
        <p>Association, and for matters connected therewith.</p>
      </longTitle>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Eleventh Year of the Republic  of India as follows:--</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be  called the International Development Association (Status, Immunities   and Privileges) Act, 1960.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date  as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" Agreement" means the Agreement for the establishment  and operation of the international body known as the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>International Development Association;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" Association" means the International Development</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Association established under the Agreement.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Conferment of status and certain immunities and privileges on  the Association and conferment of certain immunities and privileges on  its officers and employees.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything to the  contrary contained in any other law, the provisions of Article VIII of  the Agreement set out in the Schedule shall have the force of law in</p>
            <p>India:</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that nothing in section 9 thereof shall be construed  as--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>entitling the Association to import into India goods  free of any duty of customs without any restriction on  their subsequent sale therein; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>conferring on the Association any exemption from duties  or taxes which form part of the price of goods sold; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>conferring on the Association any exemption from duties  or taxes which are in fact no more than charges for  services rendered.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, from time to time, by  notification in the Official Gazette, amend the Schedule in conformity  with any amendments, duly made and adopted, of the provisions of the</p>
            <p>Agreement set out therein.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.- The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the  purposes of this Act.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Notifications under section 3 and rules under section 4 to be  placed before Parliament.- Every notification issued under sub- section</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of section 3 and every rule made under section 4 shall be laid as  soon as may be after it is issued or made before each House of</p>
            <p>Parliament while it is in session for a period of thirty days which  may be comprised in one session or  in two or more successive  sessions, and if, before the expiry of the sessions, immediately  following the session or the successive sesions aforesaid] both Houses  agree for making any modification in the notification, or as the case  may be, in the rule, or both Houses agree that the notification or  rule should not be issued or made, the notification or rule shall  thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</p>
            <p>as the case may be, so however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that notification or rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
