<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/29/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/29"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Visva- Bharati Act, 1951"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/29/eng@1951-05-09/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/29/eng@1951-05-09"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1951-05-09" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/29/eng@1951-05-09/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/29/eng@1951-05-09"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Visva- Bharati Act, 1951</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 29 OF 1951</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 9th May, 1951.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament as follows:--</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to declare the institution known as" Visva- Bharati" to be an  institution of national importance and to provide for its functioning  as a unitary teaching and residential university.</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Visva- Bharati Act, 1951.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date  as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Declaration of Visva- Bharati as an institution of national  importance. Whereas the late Rabindranath Tagore (Thakur) founded an  institution known as Visva- Bharati at Santiniketan in the district of</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Birbhum in West Bengal the objects of which are such as to make the  institution one of national importance, it is hereby declared that the  institution known as" Visva- Bharati" aforesaid is an institution of  national importance  and is as such hereby constituted as a</p>
            <p>University].</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>In this Act, and in all Statutes made hereunder, unless the  context otherwise requires,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" academic staff" means such categories of staff as are  designated as academic staff by the statutes;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" Acharya (Chancellor)" and" Upacharya (Vice-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Chancellor)" mean, respectively, the Acharya (Chancellor) and the</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Upacharya (Vice- Chancellor) of the University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" adhyapaka" includes a Professor, Reader, Lecturer and  any other person engaged in imparting instruction in relation to  any learning process and designated as an adhyapaka by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Ordinances;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list5.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>" Alumni Association" means the Association of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list7">
              <listIntroduction>Alumni of the University, constituted under the provisions of  this Act and the Statutes;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list7.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>" approved institution" means an institution (not being   an institution maintained by the University) of higher learning  or studies approved by the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list7.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>" Bhavana" means an academic institution maintained by  the University and named as such;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list7.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>" campus" means a unit established or constituted by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list9">
              <listIntroduction>University for imparting instruction or supervising research, for  both;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list9.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>" Chatravasa" means a unit of residence, or of corporate  life, for the students of the University provided, maintained or  recognised by the University;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list9.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>" Department" means a Department of Studies and includes  a centre of studies established by, or under, the Statutes;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list9.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>" employee of the University" means any person appointed  by the University or any Institution, and includes an employee of  a Bhavana;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list9.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>" Institute Board" means a Board constituted by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list11">
              <listIntroduction>University for the management of an Institute;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list11.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>" Institution" means an institution maintained by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list13">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list13.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>" Karma- Samiti (Executive Council)" means the Karma-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list15">
              <listIntroduction>Samiti (Executive Council) of the University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list15.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>" Patha- Samiti (Board of Studies)" means a Board  constituted by the University for the regulation of studies;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list15.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by the Statutes,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list17">
              <listIntroduction>Ordinances or Regulations;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list17.p">
                <num>(p)</num>
                <p>" Samsad (Court)" means the Samsad (Court) of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list19">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list19.q">
                <num>(q)</num>
                <p>" Siksha- Samiti (Academic Council)" means the Siksha-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list21">
              <listIntroduction>Samiti (Academic Council) of the University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list21.r">
                <num>(r)</num>
                <p>" Statutes"," Ordinances" and" Regulations" mean,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>respectively, such Statutes, Ordinances and Regulations of the</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list24">
              <listIntroduction>University as are for the time being in force;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list24.s">
                <num>(s)</num>
                <p>" University" means the institution known as Visva-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Bharati and incorporated as a University under this Act.]</p>
            <p>THE UNIVERSITY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Incorporation. The first Acharya (Chancellor) and Upacharya</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>(Vice- Chancellor) of the University who shall be the persons appointed  in this behalf by the Central Government by notification in the</p>
            <p>Official Gazette, and the first members of the Samsad (Court) and all  persons, who may hereafter become or be appointed as such officers or  members, so long as they continue to hold such office or membership;</p>
            <p>are hereby constituted a body corporate  as a unitary, teaching and  residential University] by the name of Visva- Bharati, and shall have  perpetual succession and a common seal, and shall sue and be sued by  that name.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Effect of incorporation of the University in certain cases. On  and from the commencement of this Act,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>all references in any enactment to the Society of the  name of Visva- Bharati registered on the 16th May, 1922,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>under the Societies Registration Act, 1860 (21 of</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1860">
        <num>1860.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1860.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>), shall be construed as references to the</p>
            <blockList id="section-1860.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1860.paragraph-0.list2.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>all property, assets, rights and liabilities of  the said Society shall be the property, assets, rights  and liabilities of the University and any will, deed or  other document, whether made or executed before or  after the commencement of this Act, which contains or  purports to contain any bequest, gift, trust, payment  of money or transfer or assignment of any right or  property, movable or immovable, in favour of the said</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Society shall be construed</p>
            <blockList id="section-1860.paragraph-0.list5">
              <listIntroduction>as if the University was therein named instead of the  said Society;]</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1860.paragraph-0.list5.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>subject to the provisions of this Act, every  person employed immediately before the commencement of  this Act in the said Society shall hold employment in  the University by the same tenure and upon the same  terms and conditions and with the same rights and  privileges as to pension and gratuity as he would have  held under the said Society, if this Act had not been  passed:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that if the University decides to alter the terms and  conditions of service of any such employee, a fresh contract shall be  executed for the purpose, and if the employee is not agreeable to  serve under the new terms and conditions, his services may be  terminated in accordance with his original contract of employment or,</p>
            <p>if no provision is made therein in this behalf, on payment to him by  way of compensation of an amount equal to his salary for six months.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5A">
        <num>5A.</num>
        <heading>The objects of the University.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The objects of the</p>
            <p>University shall be to disseminate and advance knowledge and  understanding by providing instructional, extension and research  facilities and by the example and influence of its corporate life, and  the University shall, in organising its activities, have due regard to  the following objects for which the Visva- Bharati at Santiniketan was  founded by Rabindranath Tagore, as expressed in his own words,</p>
            <blockList id="section-5A.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5A.1.list3.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>to study the mind of Man in its realisation of  different aspects of truth from diverse points of view;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5A.1.list3.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>to bring into more intimate relations with one another,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>through patient study and research, the different cultures of the</p>
            <blockList id="section-5A.1.list6">
              <listIntroduction>East on the basis of their underlying unity;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5A.1.list6.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>to approach the West from the standpoint of such a  unity of the life and thought of Asia;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5A.1.list6.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>to seek to realise in a common fellowship of study the  meeting of the East and the West, and thus ultimately to  strengthen the fundamental conditions of world peace through the  establishment of free communication of ideas between the two  hemispheres; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5A.1.list6.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>with such ideals in view to provide at Santiniketan  aforesaid a Centre of Culture where research into and study of  the religion, literature, history, science and art of Hindu,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Buddhist, Jain, Islamic, Sikh, Christian and other civilisations  may be pursued along with the culture of the West, with that  simplicity in externals which is necessary for true spiritual  realisation in amity, good fellowship and co- operation between  the thinkers and scholars of both Eastern and Western countries,</p>
            <p>free from all antagonisms of race, nationality, creed or caste  and in the name of the One Supreme Being who is Shantam, Shivam,</p>
            <p>Advaitam.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The objects of the University shall also include harmonising  the cultures of India, the East and the West by, among other things,</p>
            <p>the admission of students and appointment of adhyapakas from various  regions of India and various countries of the world, and by providing  incentives therefor.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5B">
        <num>5B.</num>
        <heading>Principles to be followed in organising activities of the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5B.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>University. The University shall, in organising its activities and the  implementation of its academic programmes, have due regard to the  pattern of education envisaged by Rabindranath Tagore in his  writings."]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Powers of the University. The University shall have the  following powers, namely:--</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to provide facilities for studies, instruction, socially  useful productive work and community service and research in such  branches of learning as may be deemed desirable and found practicable  by the University and for the promotion of understanding of cultures  between the East and the West and for the advancement of learning and  dissemination of knowledge generally;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to undertake educational experiments and evolve contents,</p>
            <p>systems and methods of education for the furtherance of the objects of  the University;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to make provision for research and advisory services; and for  that purpose, to enter into such arrangements with other institutions  or bodies as the University may deem necessary;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to co- operate, collaborate or associate with any other</p>
            <p>University, authority or institution of learning in such manner and  for such purposes as the University may determine;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to approve any institution of higher learning or studies for  such purposes as the University may determine, and to withdraw such  approval;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to establish and maintain such Bhavanas, Schools of Studies  and Research, Chatravasas, Gymnasia and such other institutions as are  deemed necessary, from time to time, for the development of a healthy  corporate life in the University and to abolish any such Bhavana,</p>
            <p>School, Chatravasa, Gymnasium or other institution;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to establish, at any place in India, campuses, special  centres, specialised laboratories or other units for research and  instruction as are, in the opinion of the University, necessary for  the furtherance of its objects;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to organise the application of class room, library and  laboratory learning to problems of the villages as part of the  curriculum;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to undertake the promotion of adult education, rural re-</p>
            <p>construction, co- operative organisations, social welfare, development  of cottage industries and all other nation- building activities and  works for the benefit of the public;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.10">
          <num>(10)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to establish such examination centres and to recognise such  certificates as may be necessary to give effect to the provisions of  section 7A;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to grant, subject to such conditions as the University may  determine, diplomas or certificates to, and confer degrees or other  academic distinctions (on the basis of examinations, evaluation or   other modes of testing) on, persons;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.12">
          <num>(12)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to confer honorary degrees or other distinctions in the  manner prescribed by the Statutes;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.13">
          <num>(13)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to determine the standards for admission and the methods of  admission to courses of the University, which methods shall include  examinations, evaluation and other modes of testing;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.14">
          <num>(14)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to supervise the residences of students of the University  and to make arrangements for promoting their health and general  welfare;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.15">
          <num>(15)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to make such special arrangements in respect of women  students as the University may consider desirable;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.16">
          <num>(16)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to regulate the conduct of students of the University, and  to take such disciplinary measures in this regard as may be deemed  necessary;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.17">
          <num>(17)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to create such teaching and other academic posts as may be  required by the University and to appoint persons to such posts;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.18">
          <num>(18)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to appoint Visiting Professors, Emeritus Professors,</p>
            <p>Fellows, Scholars, Resident Artists, Resident Writers or such other  persons who may contribute to the achievement of the objects of the</p>
            <p>University;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.19">
          <num>(19)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to appoint or recognise persons as Professors, Readers or</p>
            <p>Lecturers or otherwise as adhyapakas of the University;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.20">
          <num>(20)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.20.list1">
              <listIntroduction>to approve persons working in-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.20.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any institution co- operating, collaborating or  associating with the University; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.20.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any approved institution,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>for imparting instruction or supervising research, or both, and to  withdraw such approval;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.21">
          <num>(21)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to undertake publication of literary, scientific,</p>
            <p>educational and scholarly works and books on art, aesthetics and other  subjects aimed at better understanding of the different cultures of  the world and furthering thereby the objectives of the University;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.22">
          <num>(22)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to appoint persons working in any other University,</p>
            <p>institution or organisation as adhyapakas of the University for a  specified period;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.23">
          <num>(23)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to create administrative, ministerial and other posts in the</p>
            <p>University and to make appointments thereto;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.24">
          <num>(24)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to provide for the terms and conditions of service of  employees, whether employed by the University or any institution;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.25">
          <num>(25)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to regulate the conduct and duties of the employees of the</p>
            <p>University;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.26">
          <num>(26)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to regulate and enforce discipline among the employees of  the University and to take such disciplinary measures in this regard  as may be deemed necessary;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.27">
          <num>(27)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to make arrangements for promoting the health and general  welfare of the employees of the University;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.28">
          <num>(28)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to demand and receive payment of fees and other charges;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.29">
          <num>(29)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to institute and award fellowships, scholarships,</p>
            <p>studentships, medals and prizes;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.30">
          <num>(30)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to receive benefactions, donations and gifts, and to  acquire, hold, manage and dispose of any property, movable or  immovable, including trust and endowment properties, for the purposes  of the University;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.31">
          <num>(31)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to borrow, with the approval of the Central Government,</p>
            <p>whether on the security of the property of the University or  otherwise, money for the purposes of the University;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.32">
          <num>(32)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to establish campuses within the territorial limits of the</p>
            <p>University specified in the Second Schedule;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.33">
          <num>(33)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to admit students of any other University or College whether  in India or outside to any examination of the University subject to  such conditions as the University may lay down for the purpose;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.34">
          <num>(34)</num>
          <content>
            <p>to do all such acts and things as may be necessary or  incidental to the exercise of all or any of the powers of the</p>
            <p>University or as are necessary or conducive to the attainment of all  or any of the objects of the University."]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Territorial jurisdiction of the University. Save as otherwise  provided in this Act, the powers of the University conferred by or  under this Act shall be restricted to the area specified in the Second</heading>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-schedule">
      <doc name="schedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/29/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/29"/>
              <FRBRalias value="Schedule"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/29/eng@1951-05-09/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/29/eng@1951-05-09"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1951/29/eng@1951-05-09/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1951/29/eng@1951-05-09"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="schedule">
            <section id="section-7A">
              <num>7A.</num>
              <heading>Maintenance of examination centres outside territorial  limits. Notwithstanding anything contained in section 7, the</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-7A.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>University may establish and maintain, at any place in India  examination centres for home study courses conducted by its Loka</p>
                  <p>Shiksha Samsad (People' s Education Council) and recognise, for such  purposes as may be provided in the Ordinances, the certificates  awarded by the said Loka Shiksha Samsad (People' s Education Council)</p>
                  <p>on the results of examinations conducted by it.]</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-8">
              <num>8.</num>
              <heading>University to be open to all races, creeds and classes. The</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>University shall be open to all persons irrespective of sex,</p>
                  <p>nationality, race, creed, caste or class, and no test or condition  shall be imposed as to religious belief or profession in admitting or  appointing members, students,  adhyapakas] workers, or in any other  connection whatsoever, except in respect of any particular benefaction  accepted by the University of which such test is made a condition by  the instrument creating such benefaction:</p>
                  <p>Provided that no benefaction shall hereafter be accepted which in  the opinion of the authorities of the University involves conditions  or obligations opposed to the spirit and object of this section:</p>
                  <p>Provided further that nothing in this section shall be deemed to  prevent religious instruction being given in any manner approved of by  the authorities concerned to those who have given their consent  thereto by  adhyapakas] duly and properly authorised for that  purpose.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-9">
              <num>9.</num>
              <heading>Teaching at the University. All teaching in the University  shall be conducted by and in the name of the University in accordance  with the Statutes and Ordinances made in this behalf.</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>THE PARIDARSAKA (VISITOR)</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-10">
              <num>10.</num>
              <heading>The Paridarsaka (Visitor).</heading>
              <subsection id="section-10.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The President of India  shall be the Paridarsaka (Visitor) of the University.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-10.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Subject to the provisions of sub- sections (3) and (4), the</p>
                  <p>Paridarsaka (Visitor) shall have the right to cause an inspection to  be made, by such person or persons as he may specify, of the</p>
                  <p>University, its buildings, laboratories and equipment, and of any</p>
                  <p>Bhavana or other Institution, and also of the examinations, teaching  and other work conducted or done by the University, Bhavana or other</p>
                  <p>Institution; and to cause an inquiry to be made in like manner in  respect of any matter connected with the administration or finances of  the University.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-10.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Paridarsaka (Visitor) shall give notice to the University  of his intention to cause an inspection or inquiry to be made and the</p>
                  <p>University shall, on receipt of such notice, have the right to make,</p>
                  <p>within thirty days or such other period as the Paridarsaka (Visitor)</p>
                  <p>may determine, from the date of receipt of the notice, such  representations to the Paridarsaka (Visitor) as it may consider  necessary.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-10.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>After considering the representations, if any, made by the</p>
                  <p>University, the Paridarsaka (Visitor) may cause to be made such  inspection or inquiry as is referred to in sub- section (2).</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-10.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where any inspection or inquiry has been caused to be made by  the Paridarsaka (Visitor), the University shall be entitled to appoint  a representative who shall have the right to be present and to be  heard at such inspection or inquiry.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-10.6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Paridarsaka (Visitor) may address the Upacharya (Vice-</p>
                  <blockList id="section-10.6.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>Chancellor) with reference to the results of such inspection or  inquiry together with such views and advice with regard to the action  to be taken thereon as the Paridarsaka (Visitor) may be pleased to  offer, and on receipt of the address made by the Paridarsaka</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-10.6.list2.Visitor">
                      <num>(Visitor)</num>
                      <p>, the Upacharya (Vice- Chancellor) shall communicate forthwith  to the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) the results of the inspection  or inquiry and the views of the Paridarsaka (Visitor) and the advice  tendered by him upon the action to be taken thereon.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-10.7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) shall communicate  through the Upacharya (Vice- Chancellor) to the Paridarsaka (Visitor)</p>
                  <p>such action, if any, as it proposes to take or has been taken by it  upon the results of such inspection or inquiry.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-10.8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-10.8.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>Where the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) does not, within a  reasonable time, take action to the satisfaction of the Paridarsaka</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-10.8.list1.Visitor">
                      <num>(Visitor)</num>
                      <p>, the Paridarsaka (Visitor) may, after considering any  explanation furnished or representation made by the Karma- Samiti</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>(Executive Council), issue such directions as he may think fit and</p>
                  <p>Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) shall be bound to comply with such  directions.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-10.9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Without prejudice to the foregoing provisions of this  section, the Paridarsaka (Visitor may, be order in writing, annual any  proceeding of the University which is not in conformity with this Act,</p>
                  <p>the Statutes or the Ordinances:)</p>
                  <p>Provided that before making any such order he shall call upon the</p>
                  <p>University to show cause why such an order should not be made and, if  any cause is shown within a reasonable time, he shall consider the  same.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-10.10">
                <num>(10)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Paridarsaka (Visitor) shall have such other powers as  may be specified in the Statutes."]</p>
                  <p>THE PRADHANA (RECTOR)</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-11">
              <num>11.</num>
              <heading>The Pradhana (Rector.) The Government of West Bengal shall be  the Pradhana (Rector) of the University.</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>OFFICERS OF THE UNIVERSITY</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-12">
              <num>12.</num>
              <heading>Officers of the University. The following shall be the  officers of the University, namely:--</heading>
              <subsection id="section-12.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Acharya (Chancellor);</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-12.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Upacharya (Vice- Chancellor);</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-12.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Director of Studies, Educational Innovations and</p>
                  <p>Rural Reconstruction;</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-12.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Director of Culture and Cultural Relations;</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-12.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Director of Physical Education, Sports, National</p>
                  <p>Service and Student Welfare;</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-12.6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Karma- Sachiva (Registrar);</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-12.7">
                <num>(7)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Vitta- Adhikari (Finance Officer);</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-12.8">
                <num>(8)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Adhyakshas of Bhavanas; and</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-12.9">
                <num>(9)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>such other officers as may be declared by the Statutes  to be officers of the University.]</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-12.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Acharya (Chancellor) shall, by virtue of his office,</p>
                  <p>be the Head of the University.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-12.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Acharya (Chancellor) shall be appointed by the</p>
                  <p>Paridarsaka (Visitor) from out of a panel of persons prepared and  recommended by the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) under sub- section</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-12.2A">
                <num>(2A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-12.2A">
                <num>(2A)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) shall prepare and  recommend a panel of not less than three persons each of whom shall be  a person of eminence in the academic or public life of the country,</p>
                  <p>and is in the opinion of the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) a fit  and proper person to be appointed as the Acharya (Chancellor) of the</p>
                  <p>University:</p>
                  <p>Provided that if the Paridarsaka (Visitor) does not approve of  any of the persons specified in the panel prepared and recommended by  the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council), he may call upon the Karma-</p>
                  <p>Samiti (Executive Council) to prepare a fresh panel of persons.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-12.2B">
                <num>(2B)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Acharya (Chancellor) shall hold office for a term of  three years and shall be eligible for re- appointment:</p>
                  <p>Provided that the Acharya (Chancellor) shall, notwithstanding the  expiry of the term of his office, continue to hold such office until  his successor is appointed and has entered upon his office."]</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-12.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Acharya (Chancellor), shall, if present, preside at the</p>
                  <p>Convocation of the University and at meetings of the Samsad (Court)</p>
                  <p>and the Karma Samiti (Executive Council)].</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-1">
              <num>1.</num>
              <heading>Subs. by Act 31 of 1984, s. 7 (w. e. f. 8. 8. 1984).</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-2">
              <num>2.</num>
              <heading>Subs. by s. 8, ibid. (w. e. f. 8. 8. 1984).</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-3">
              <num>3.</num>
              <heading>Ins. by Act 60 of 1961, s. 8.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-3.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every proposal for the conferment of an honorary degree shall  be subject to the confirmation of the Acharya (Chancellor).</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-3.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Acharya (Chancellor) shall have such other powers as may  be conferred on him by this Act or the Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-14">
              <num>14.</num>
              <heading>The Upacharya (Vice- Chancellor).</heading>
              <subsection id="section-14.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Upacharya (Vice-</p>
                  <p>Chancellor) shall be appointed by the Paridarsaka (Visitor) in such  manner, for such term and on such emoluments and other conditions of  service as may be prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-14.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Upacharya (Vice- Chancellor) shall be the principal  executive and academic officer of the University, and shall exercise  general supervision and control over the academic affairs of the</p>
                  <p>University and all Bhavanas and other Institutions and give effect to  the decisions of all the authorities of the University.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-14.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Upacharya (Vice- Chancellor) may, if he is of opinion that  immediate action is necessary on any matter, exercise any power  conferred on any authority of the University by or under this Act and  shall report to such authority the action taken by him on such matter:</p>
                  <p>Provided that if the authority concerned is of opinion that such  action ought not to have been taken, it may refer the matter to the</p>
                  <p>Paridarsaka (Visitor) whose decision thereon shall be final:</p>
                  <p>Provided further that an employee of the University, who is  aggrieved by the action taken by the Upacharya (Vice- Chancellor) under  this sub- section, shall have the right to appeal against such action  to the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) within ninety days from the  date on which such action is communicated to him and thereupon the</p>
                  <p>Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) may confirm, modify or reverse the  action taken by the Upacharya (Vice- Chancellor).</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-14.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Upacharya (Vice- Chancellor) shall exercise such other  powers and perform such other functions as may be prescribed by the</p>
                  <p>Statutes and the Ordinances."]</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-16">
              <num>16.</num>
              <heading/>
              <subsection id="section-16.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Karma- Sachiva (Registrar) shall be appointed in  such manner, and on such emoluments and other conditions of service,</p>
                  <p>as may be prescribed by the statutes and the Ordinances.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-16.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Karma- Sachiva (Registrar) shall have the power to enter  into agreements, sign documents and authenticate records on behalf of  the University and shall exercise such other powers and perform such  other functions as may be prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-17">
              <num>17.</num>
              <heading>Other officers.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-17.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>All officers of the University, other  than the Acharya (Chancellor), the Upacharya (Vice- Chancellor) and the</p>
                  <p>Karma- Sachiva (Registrar), shall be appointed in such manner, for such  term and on such emoluments and other conditions of service as may be  prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-17.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The powers and functions of the officers appointed under sub-</p>
                  <p>section (1) shall be such as may be prescribed by the Statutes."]</p>
                  <p>AUTHORITIES OF THE UNIVERSITY</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-18">
              <num>18.</num>
              <heading>Authorities of the University. The following shall be  authorities of the University:-</heading>
              <subsection id="section-18.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Samsad (Court),</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-18.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Karma Samiti (Executive Council),</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-18.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>the Shiksha Samiti (Academic Council),</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-18.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Artha- Samiti (Finance Committee);</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-18.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Institute Board; and]</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-18.6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>such other authorities as may be declared by the</p>
                  <p>Statutes to be authorities of the University.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-19">
              <num>19.</num>
              <heading>The Samsad (Court).</heading>
              <subsection id="section-19.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-19.1.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>The constitution of the Samsad</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-19.1.list1.Court">
                      <num>(Court)</num>
                      <p>and the term or office of its members shall be such as may be  prescribed by the Statutes.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-19.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-19.2.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>Subject to the other provisions of this Act, the Samsad</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-19.2.list1.Court">
                      <num>(Court)</num>
                      <p>shall have the following powers and functions, namely:-</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-19.2.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>to review, from time to time, the broad policies and  programmes of the University, including the maintenance of  standards and adherence to the objectives of the University and  to suggest measures for the development and improvement of the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-19.2.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>University which shall be considered by the appropriate  authorities of the University;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-19.2.list3.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>to consider and pass resolutions on the annual report  and annual accounts of the University and the report of its  auditors on such accounts;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-19.2.list3.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>to advice the Paridarsaka (Visitor) in respect of any  matter which may be referred to it for advice; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-19.2.list3.d">
                      <num>(d)</num>
                      <p>to exercise such other powers and perform such other  functions as may be prescribed by the Statutes."]</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-22">
              <num>22.</num>
              <heading>The Karma- Samiti (Executive Council).</heading>
              <subsection id="section-22.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Karma-</p>
                  <p>Samiti (Executive Council) shall be the principal executive body of  the University.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-22.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The constitution of the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) and  the term of office of its members shall be such as may be prescribed  by the Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-22.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-22.3.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>The Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) shall exercise the  following powers and perform the following functions, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-22.3.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>to manage and administer the revenue and property of  the University and to conduct all administrative affairs of the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>University not otherwise provided for in this act or the</p>
                  <blockList id="section-22.3.list4">
                    <listIntroduction>Statutes;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-22.3.list4.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>to create teaching and academic posts and to define the  duties and conditions of service of Professor, Readers, Lecturers  and other adhyapakas and academic staff employed by the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>University:</p>
                  <p>Provided that before determining the number, qualifications  and emoluments of adhyapakas and other academic staff, the Karma-</p>
                  <blockList id="section-22.3.list8">
                    <listIntroduction>Samiti (Executive Council) shall consider the recommendations of  the Siksha- Samiti (Academic Council);</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-22.3.list8.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>to appoint such Professors, readers, Lecturers and  other adhyapakas and academic staff as may be necessary on the  recommendation of the Selection Committees constituted for the  purpose and to fill up temporary vacancies therein;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-22.3.list8.d">
                      <num>(d)</num>
                      <p>to provide for the appointment of Visiting Professors,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Emeritus Professors, Fellows, Scholars, Resident Artists and</p>
                  <blockList id="section-22.3.list11">
                    <listIntroduction>Resident Writers and to determine the terms and conditions of  such appointment;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-22.3.list11.e">
                      <num>(e)</num>
                      <p>to manage and regulate the finances, accounts,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-22.3.list13">
                    <listIntroduction>investments, property, business and all other administrative  affairs of the University, and for that purpose, to appoint such  agents as it may think fit;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-22.3.list13.f">
                      <num>(f)</num>
                      <p>to invest any money belonging to the University,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-22.3.list15">
                    <listIntroduction>including any unapplied income, in such stocks, funds, shares or  securities as it thinks fit, or in the purchase of immovable  property in India;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-22.3.list15.g">
                      <num>(g)</num>
                      <p>to exercise such other powers and perform such other  functions as may be conferred or specified by this Act or the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Statutes."]</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-24">
              <num>24.</num>
              <heading>The Shiksha Samiti (Academic Council). The Shiksha Samiti</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>(Academic Council) shall be" the principal academic body  of the</p>
                  <p>University, and shall, subject to the provisions of this Act, the</p>
                  <p>Statutes and the Ordinances, have the control and general regulation,</p>
                  <p>and be responsible for the maintenance of standards of  learning,</p>
                  <p>education, instruction, evaluation and examination"] within the</p>
                  <p>University, and shall exercise such other powers and perform such  other duties as may be conferred or imposed upon it by the Statutes  and shall have the right to advise the Karma Samiti (Executive</p>
                  <p>Council) on all academic matters.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <subsection id="section-24.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The constitution of the Shiksha Samiti (Academic Council) and  the terms of office of its members shall be prescribed by the</p>
                  <p>Statutes.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-25">
              <num>25.</num>
              <heading>Other authorities of the University. The constitution,</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>powers and functions of the Artha- Samiti (Finance Committee), the</p>
                  <p>Institute Board and of such other authorities as may be declared by  the Statutes to be authorities of the University shall be such as may  be prescribed by the Statutes."]</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-26">
              <num>26.</num>
              <heading>Alumni Association. The University shall have an Alumni</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Association open to past students and past workers of the University,</p>
                  <p>including members of the Asramika Sangha of the former Visva- Bharati</p>
                  <p>Society, on such conditions as may be laid down in the Statutes.</p>
                  <p>STATUTES, ORDINANCES AND REGULATIONS</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-27">
              <num>27.</num>
              <heading>Statutes. Subject to the provisions of this Act, the</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-27.paragraph-0.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>Statutes may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the manner of appointment, of the Upacharya (Vice-</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-27.paragraph-0.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>Chancellor), the term of his appointments, emoluments and other  conditions of his service;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>the powers that may be exercised and the functions that  may be performed by the Upacharya (Vice- Chancellor);</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <blockList id="section-27.paragraph-0.list3.c.list0">
                        <listIntroduction>the manner of appointment of the Karma- Sachiva</listIntroduction>
                        <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list3.c.list0.Registrar">
                          <num>(Registrar)</num>
                          <p>, the emoluments and other conditions of his service  and the powers that may be exercised and the functions that may  be performed by him;</p>
                        </item>
                      </blockList>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                      <num>(d)</num>
                      <p>the manner of appointment of all other officers, the  terms of their appointment, emoluments and other conditions of  their service and the powers and functions of such officers;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list3.e">
                      <num>(e)</num>
                      <p>the constitution of the Samsad (Court), the term of  office of its members and its powers and functions;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list3.f">
                      <num>(f)</num>
                      <p>the constitution of the Karma- Samiti (Executive</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-27.paragraph-0.list5">
                    <listIntroduction>Council), the term of office of its members and its powers and  functions;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list5.g">
                      <num>(g)</num>
                      <p>the constitution of other authorities or bodies of the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-27.paragraph-0.list7">
                    <listIntroduction>University, the term of office of their members and their powers  and functions;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list7.h">
                      <num>(h)</num>
                      <p>the election and continuance in office of the members  the said authorities and bodies, the filling up of vacancies of  members and all other matters relating to those authorities and  other bodies for which it may be necessary or desirable to  provide;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list7.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>the appointment of adhyapakas and other academic staff  and other employees of the University and their emoluments and  other conditions of service;</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-27.paragraph-0.list9">
                    <listIntroduction>Provided that where any person who had held any post and is  in receipt of a pension or other form of retirement benefits is  appointed as an adhyapaka of the University or to any other  academic post, the salary of such person together with the  pension and other benefits shall not exceed the salary payable to  him in accordance with the Statutes;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list9.j">
                      <num>(j)</num>
                      <p>the appointment of adhyapakas and other academic staff  working in any other University, institution or organisation for  a specified period for undertaking a joint project;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list9.k">
                      <num>(k)</num>
                      <p>the appointment of Visiting Professors, Emeritus</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Professors, Fellows, Scholars, Resident Artists and Resident</p>
                  <blockList id="section-27.paragraph-0.list12">
                    <listIntroduction>Writers, and terms and conditions of such appointment;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list12.l">
                      <num>(l)</num>
                      <p>the constitution of a pension or provident fund or the  establishment of an insurance scheme for the benefit of the  employees of the University;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list12.m">
                      <num>(m)</num>
                      <p>the principles governing seniority of service of the  employees of the University;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list12.n">
                      <num>(n)</num>
                      <p>the procedure in relation to any appeal or application  for review by any employee or student of the University, against  the action of any officer or authority of the University,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-27.paragraph-0.list14">
                    <listIntroduction>including the time within which such appeal or application for  review may be preferred or made;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list14.o">
                      <num>(o)</num>
                      <p>the procedure for the settlement of disputes between  employees of the University, or students of the University, and  the University;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list14.p">
                      <num>(p)</num>
                      <p>the conferment of honorary degrees;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list14.q">
                      <num>(q)</num>
                      <p>the institution of fellowships, scholarships,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-27.paragraph-0.list16">
                    <listIntroduction>studentships, medals and prizes;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list16.r">
                      <num>(r)</num>
                      <p>the maintenance of discipline among the employees and  students of the University;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list16.s">
                      <num>(s)</num>
                      <p>the establishment and abolition of Bhavanas,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-27.paragraph-0.list18">
                    <listIntroduction>Departments, Chatravasas and other institutions and their  management, supervision and inspection;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list18.t">
                      <num>(t)</num>
                      <p>the regulation of the conduct and duties of the  employees of the University and the conduct of the students of  the University;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list18.u">
                      <num>(u)</num>
                      <p>the establishment of campuses, special centres,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-27.paragraph-0.list20">
                    <listIntroduction>specialised laboratories or other units for research and  instruction;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list20.v">
                      <num>(v)</num>
                      <p>the administration and regulation of the funds received  in trust or otherwise by the University;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list20.w">
                      <num>(w)</num>
                      <p>the delegation of powers vested in the officers or  authorities of the University;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list20.x">
                      <num>(x)</num>
                      <p>the constitution and activities of the Alumni</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-27.paragraph-0.list22">
                    <listIntroduction>Association;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list22.y">
                      <num>(y)</num>
                      <p>the categories of misconduct for which any action may  be taken under this Act, or the Statutes or the Ordinances; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list22.z">
                      <num>(z)</num>
                      <p>all other matters which, by this Act, are to be, or may  be, provided for by the Statutes."]</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-28">
              <num>28.</num>
              <heading>Statutes, how made.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-28.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>On the commencement of the Visva-</p>
                  <p>Bharati (Amendment) Act, 1984 (31 of 1984), the Statutes in force  immediately before such commencement, as amended by that Act,</p>
                  <p>shall be the Statutes of the University."]</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-28.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Statutes may be amended, repealed or added to by</p>
                  <p>Statutes made by the Karma Samiti (Executive Council).</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-28.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Karma Samiti (Executive Council) shall not propose the  draft of any Statute affecting the status, powers or constitution of  any authority of the University until such authority has been given an  opportunity of expressing the opinion upon the proposal and any  opinion so expressed shall be in writing and shall be submitted to the</p>
                  <p>Paridarsaka (Visitor).</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-28.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every new Statute or addition to a Statute or any amendment  or repeal of a Statute shall be submitted to the Paridarsaka (Visitor)</p>
                  <p>who may assent to it or withhold his assent therefrom or remit it to  the Karma Samiti (Executive Council) for further consideration.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-28.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A Statute passed by the Karma Samiti (Executive Council)</p>
                  <p>shall have no validity until it has been assented to by the</p>
                  <p>Paridarsaka (Visitor).]</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-29">
              <num>29.</num>
              <heading>Matters to be provided for in the Ordinances. Subject to  the provisions of this Act and the Statutes, the Ordinances may  provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:-</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-29.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-29.paragraph-0.list0">
                    <item id="section-29.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the admission of students to the University and their  enrolment as such;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-29.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>the pattern of learning process, courses of study to be  laid down for all degrees, diplomas and certificates of the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-29.paragraph-0.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-29.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>the degrees, diplomas, certificates and other academic  distinctions to be awarded by the University, the qualifications  for the same and the means to be adopted relating to the granting  and obtaining of the same;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-29.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                      <num>(d)</num>
                      <p>the purposes for which certificates awarded by the Lok</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-29.paragraph-0.list4">
                    <listIntroduction>Siksha- Samsad (People' s Education Council) of the University may  be recognised by the University;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-29.paragraph-0.list4.e">
                      <num>(e)</num>
                      <p>the fees to be charged for courses of study in the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>University and for admission to the examinations, and processes  of evaluation, degrees, diplomas and certificates of the</p>
                  <blockList id="section-29.paragraph-0.list7">
                    <listIntroduction>University;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-29.paragraph-0.list7.f">
                      <num>(f)</num>
                      <p>the conditions of the award of fellowships,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-29.paragraph-0.list9">
                    <listIntroduction>scholarships, studentships, medals and prizes;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-29.paragraph-0.list9.g">
                      <num>(g)</num>
                      <p>the conduct of tests, evaluations and examinations,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-29.paragraph-0.list11">
                    <listIntroduction>including the terms of office and manner of appointment and  duties of examining bodies, examiners, moderators and persons  entrusted with the responsibility of evaluation;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-29.paragraph-0.list11.h">
                      <num>(h)</num>
                      <p>the conditions of residence of the students of the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-29.paragraph-0.list13">
                    <listIntroduction>University and the special arrangements, if any, for the  residence of women students;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-29.paragraph-0.list13.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>the special arrangements, if any, which may be made for  the discipline and teaching of women students, and prescribing  for them special courses of study;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-29.paragraph-0.list13.j">
                      <num>(j)</num>
                      <p>the terms and conditions of service of the employees of  the University other than those prescribed by the Statutes</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>(including the emoluments of the non- teaching staff):</p>
                  <p>Provided that where any person who had held any post and is  in receipt of a pension or other form of retirement benefits is  appointed to a non- teaching post of the University, the salary  such person together with the pension and other benefits shall  not exceed the salary payable to him in accordance with the</p>
                  <blockList id="section-29.paragraph-0.list17">
                    <listIntroduction>Ordinances;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-29.paragraph-0.list17.k">
                      <num>(k)</num>
                      <p>the terms and conditions of approval of institutions of  higher learning and its withdrawal;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-29.paragraph-0.list17.l">
                      <num>(l)</num>
                      <p>the manner of co- operation or collaboration or  association with other Universities, authorities or institutions  of learning;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-29.paragraph-0.list17.m">
                      <num>(m)</num>
                      <p>the terms and conditions on which persons working in an  approved institution, or in any institution co- operating,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-29.paragraph-0.list19">
                    <listIntroduction>collaborating or associating with the University, may be approved  as adhyapakas and for withdrawing such approval;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-29.paragraph-0.list19.n">
                      <num>(n)</num>
                      <p>the educational experimentation and the creation,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-29.paragraph-0.list21">
                    <listIntroduction>composition and functioning of any other body which is considered  necessary for improving the academic life of the University; and</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-29.paragraph-0.list21.o">
                      <num>(o)</num>
                      <p>all other matters which, by this Act or the Statutes,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>are to be, or may be, provided for by the Ordinances.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-30">
              <num>30.</num>
              <heading>Power to make Ordinances.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-30.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Ordinances in force  immediately before the commencement of the Visva- Bharati (Amendment)</p>
                  <p>Act, 1984 (31 of 1984), may be amended, repealed or added to, at any  time by the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council);</p>
                  <blockList id="section-30.1.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>Provided that no Ordinance shall be made in respect of matters  enumerated in section 29, other than those enumerated in clauses (e),</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-30.1.list3.h">
                      <num>(h)</num>
                      <p>, (j), (m) and (o) thereof, unless a draft of such Ordinance has  been proposed by the Siksha- Samiti (Academic Council).</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-30.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) shall not have power to  amend any draft proposed by the Siksha- Samiti (Academic Council) under  the provisions of sub- section (1), but may reject the proposal or  return the draft to the Siksha- Samiti (Academic Council) for  reconsideration either in whole or in part, together with any  amendments which the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) may suggest.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-30.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) has rejected or  returned the draft of an Ordinance proposed by the Siksha- Samiti</p>
                  <p>(Academic Council), the Siksha- Samiti (Academic Council) may consider  the question afresh and in case the original draft is reaffirmed by a  majority of not less than one- half of the total membership of the</p>
                  <p>Siksha- Samiti (Academic Council) and by a majority of not less than  two- thirds of the members of the Siksha- Samiti (Academic Council)</p>
                  <p>present and voting, the draft may be sent back to the Karma- Samiti</p>
                  <p>(Executive Council), which shall either adopt it or refer it to the</p>
                  <p>Paridarsaka (Visitor) whose decision thereon shall be final.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-30.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every Ordinance made by the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council)</p>
                  <p>shall come into effect immediately.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-30.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every Ordinance made by the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council)</p>
                  <p>shall be submitted to the Paridarsaka (Visitor) within four weeks of  the date of the meeting of the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council), and  the Paridarsaka (Visitor) shall have the power to direct the</p>
                  <p>University, within six weeks from the date of the receipt of the</p>
                  <p>Ordinance, to suspend the operation of any Ordinance and he shall, as  soon as possible, inform the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) about  his objection to the proposed Ordinance.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-30.6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Paridarsaka (Visitor) may, after receiving the comments  of the University, either withdraw the order directing the suspension  of the Ordinance or disallow the Ordinance and his decision thereon  shall be final."]</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-31">
              <num>31.</num>
              <heading>Regulations.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-31.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The authorities of the University may make</p>
                  <p>Regulations consistent with this Act, the Statutes and the Ordinances-</p>
                  <blockList id="section-31.1.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-31.1.list3.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>laying down the procedure to be observed at their  meetings and the number of members required to form a  quorum;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-31.1.list3.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>providing for all matters which by this Act, the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Statutes or the Ordinances are to be prescribed by the</p>
                  <blockList id="section-31.1.list6">
                    <listIntroduction>Regulations; and</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-31.1.list6.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>providing for all other matters solely concerning the  authorities or committees appointed by them and not  provided for by this Act, the Statutes and the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Ordinances.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-31.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every authority of the University shall make Regulations  providing for the giving of notice to the members of such authority of  the dates of meetings and of the business to be considered at meetings  and for the keeping of a record of the proceedings of meetings.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-31.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Karma Samiti (Executive Council) may direct the  amendment, in such manner as it may specify, of any Regulation made  under this section or the amendment of any Regulation made under sub-</p>
                  <p>section (1).</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-32">
              <num>32.</num>
              <heading>Residence. Every student of the University  other than a  student of its Loka Shiksha Samsad (People' s Education Council)] shall  reside in a Chatravasa  or under such conditions as may be  prescribed by the Statutes and the Ordinances.</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-32.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>ADMISSION AND EXAMINATIONS</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-33">
              <num>33.</num>
              <heading>Admission. Admission of students to the University shall be  made in such manner as may be prescribed by the Ordinances.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-34">
              <num>34.</num>
              <heading>Examinations. Subject to the provisions of the Statutes, all  arrangements for the conduct of  tests, evaluations and  examinations] shall be made by the Karma Samiti (Executive Council) in  such manner as may be prescribed by the Ordinances.</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-34.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>ANNUAL REPORTS AND ACCOUNTS</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-35">
              <num>35.</num>
              <heading>Annual report.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-35.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The annual report of the University  shall be prepared under the directions of the Karma- Samiti (Executive</p>
                  <p>Council) which shall include, among other matters, the steps taken by  the University to promote socially relevant research in physical and  social sciences, weaker sections' need oriented extension activities  and integration of the community life of the University with that of  the wider world.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-35.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The annual report so prepared shall be submitted to the</p>
                  <p>Samsad (Court) on or before such date as may be prescribed by the</p>
                  <p>Statutes and shall be considered by the Samsad (Court) in its annual  meeting.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-35.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-35.3.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>The Samsad (Court) may communicate its comments on the annual  report to the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) and the Paridarsaka</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-35.3.list1.Visitor">
                      <num>(Visitor)</num>
                      <p>.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-35.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A copy of the annual report, as prepared under sub- section</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-35.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>shall also be submitted to the Central Government which shall, as  soon as may be, cause the same to be laid before both the Houses of</p>
                  <p>Parliament.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-36">
              <num>36.</num>
              <heading>Annual Accounts.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-36.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The annual accounts and balance- sheet of  the University shall be prepared under the direction of the</p>
                  <p>Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) and shall once at least every year  and at intervals of not more than fifteen months, be audited by the</p>
                  <p>Comptroller and Auditor- General of India or by such person or persons  as he may authorise in this behalf.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-36.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A copy of the accounts together with the audit report shall  be submitted to the Samsad (Court) and the Paridarsaka (Visitor) along  with the observations of the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council).</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-36.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Any observations made by the Paridarsaka (Visitor) on the  annual accounts shall be brought to the notice of the Samsad (Court)</p>
                  <p>and the observations of the Samsad (Court), if any, shall, after being  considered by the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council), be submitted to  the Paridarsaka (Visitor).</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-36.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>A copy of the accounts together with the audit report, as  submitted to the Paridarsaka (Visitor), shall also be submitted to the</p>
                  <p>Central Government, which shall, as soon as may be, cause the same to  be laid before both the Houses of Parliament.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-36.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The audited annual accounts, after having been laid before  both the Houses of Parliament, shall be published in the Gazette of</p>
                  <p>India."]</p>
                  <p>SUPPLEMENTARY PROVISIONS</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-37">
              <num>37.</num>
              <heading>Adhyapakas of the University to be appointed under a  written contract.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-37.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>No adhyapaka of the University shall be  appointed to a permanent post, except under a written contract and  such contract shall not be inconsistent with the provisions of this</p>
                  <p>Act, the Statutes and the Ordinances.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-37.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The contract referred to in sub- section (1) shall be lodged  with the University and a copy thereof shall be furnished to the  adhyapaka concerned.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-37.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>In the case of an adhyapaka appointed by the University  before the commencement of the Visva- Bharati (Amendment) Act, 1984</p>
                  <blockList id="section-37.3.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>(31 of 1984), the contract in force immediately before such  commencement, in relation to his emoluments, shall, to the extent of  any inconsistency with the provisions of this Act or the Statutes or  the Ordinances, be deemed to have been modified by the said provisions  and where there is no such contract and the adhyapaka is a salaries  adhyapaka appointed to a permanent post, a written contract shall be  executed by, and between, such adhyapaka and the University within a  period of six months from the commencement of the Visva- Bharati</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-37.3.list2.Amendment">
                      <num>(Amendment)</num>
                      <p>Act, 1984.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-38">
              <num>38.</num>
              <heading>Tribunal of Arbitration.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-38.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Any dispute arising out of a  contract of employment referred to in section 37, including a dispute  relating to the noncompliance of the provisions of this Act, the</p>
                  <p>Statutes or the Ordinances, shall, at the request of the adhyapaka, be  referred to a Tribunal of Arbitration which shall consist of one  member nominated by the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council), one member  nominated by the adhyapaka concerned and one member (who shall act as   umpire) nominated by the Paridarsaka (Visitor).</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-38.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every request made under sub- section (1) shall be deemed to  be a submission to arbitration upon the terms of this section within  the meaning of the Arbitration Act, 1940 (10 of 1940), and all the  provisions of that Act, with the exception of section 2 thereof,</p>
                  <p>shall apply accordingly.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-38.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>If, for any reason, a vacancy occurs in the office of a  member of the Tribunal of Arbitration, the appropriate body or person  concerned shall nominate another person in accordance with the  provisions of sub- section (1) to fill the vacancy and the proceedings  may be continued before the Tribunal from the stage at which the  vacancy is filled.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-38.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The decision of the Tribunal of Arbitration shall be final  and binding on the parties.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-38.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-38.5.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>The Tribunal of Arbitration shall have the power--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-38.5.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>to regulate its own procedure;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-38.5.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>to order reinstatement of the adhyapaka concerned; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-38.5.list1.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>to award salary to the adhyapaka concerned, after  deducting therefrom such income, not being income from property,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>as such adhyapaka might have derived during the period of his  suspension or during the period intervening between the date on  which he was removed or dismissed from service or, as the case  may be, his service was terminated, and the date on which he is  reinstated:</p>
                  <p>Provided that the income which could have been derived by the  adhyapaka concerned shall not be taken into account if, at the time  when the income was derived, he could have derived such income had he  not been suspended or removed or dismissed from service or if his  service had not been terminated.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-38.6">
                <num>(6)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>No suit or other proceedings shall lie in any court in  respect of any matter which is required by sub- section (1) to be  referred to the Tribunal of Arbitration.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-38A">
              <num>38A.</num>
              <heading>Power to suspend adhyapaka or other member of academic  staff.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-38A.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Upacharya (Vice- Chancellor) may, by order in writing,</p>
                  <blockList id="section-38A.1.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>place and adhyapaka or other member of the academic staff under  suspension--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-38A.1.list2.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>where a disciplinary proceeding against such adhyapaka  or other member is contemplated or is pending; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-38A.1.list2.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>where a case against him in respect of any criminal  offence is under investigation or trial.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-38A.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where any order of suspension is made under sub- section (1),</p>
                  <p>the circumstances in which such order has been made shall be reported  forthwith to the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council).</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-38A.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) may, within fifteen days  from the date of receipt of the report referred to in sub- section (2),</p>
                  <p>revoke the order of suspension if it is of opinion that the  circumstances of the case do not warrant the suspension.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-38A.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Any person aggrieved by an order of suspension, which has not  been revoked under sub- section (3), may prefer an appeal to the Karma-</p>
                  <p>Samiti (Executive Council) within thirty days from the date on which  such order is communicated to him and the Karma- Samiti (Executive</p>
                  <p>Council) may confirm modify or reverse the order appealed against.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-38B">
              <num>38B.</num>
              <heading>Authorities by whom order for removal or dismissal or  adhyapaka, etc., may be made and the procedure therefor.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-38B.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>No  adhyapaka, or other member of the academic staff, appointed by the</p>
                  <p>University shall be dismissed or removed from service or punished in  any other manner by any authority other than the Karma- Samiti</p>
                  <p>(Executive Council).</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-38B.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>No adhyapaka, or other member of the academic staff,</p>
                  <p>appointed by the University shall be dismissed or removed from service  or punished in any other manner except after an inquiry in which he  has been informed of the charges against him and given a reasonable  opportunity of being heard in respect of those charges:</p>
                  <p>Provided that where it is proposed after such inquiry, to impose  upon the adhyapaka or other member of the academic staff any  punishment, such punishment may be imposed on the basis of the  evidence adduced during such inquiry and it shall not be necessary to  give such adhyapaka or other member of the academic staff any  opportunity of making representation on the punishment proposed.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-38B.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) shall be entitled to  dismiss or remove from service, without holding any such inquiry as is  referred to in sub- section (2), an adhyapaka, or other member of the  academic staff, of the University, where the Karma- Samiti (Executive</p>
                  <blockList id="section-38B.3.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>Council), for reasons to be recorded in writing, is satisfied that  such adhyapaka or other member of the academic staff-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-38B.3.list2.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>is of unsound mind or is a deaf- mute or suffers from  contagious leprosy; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-38B.3.list2.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>is an undischarged insolvent; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-38B.3.list2.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>has been convicted, by a court of law, of an offence  involving moral turpitude.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-38B.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The dismissal or removal from service of, or any other  punishment imposed on, an adhyapaka, or other member of the academic  staff, appointed by the University shall take effect from the date on  which the order of dismissal or removal from service is made or other  punishment is imposed:</p>
                  <p>Provided that, where the adhyapaka or other member of the  academic staff is under suspension at the time when the order for his  dismissal or removal from service is made or other punishment is  imposed, such order may, if the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) so  directs, take effect from the date on which he was placed under  suspension.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-38B.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-38B.5.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding the terms of contract between the University  and an adhyapaka, or other member of the academic staff, appointed by  the University, such adhyapaka or other member of the academic staff  may resign his office--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-38B.5.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>where he is permanent, by giving three months' notice  in writing to the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) or by paying  to the University three months' salary in lieu of such notice; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-38B.5.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>where he is not permanent, one month' s notice in  writing to the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) or by paying to  the University one month' s salary in lieu of such notice:</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Provided that if the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) so permits,</p>
                  <p>the period of three months' notice or of one month' s notice, as the  case may be, may be reduced or waived:</p>
                  <p>Provided further that such resignation shall take effect from the  date on which it is accepted by the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council).</p>
                  <p>Explanation.--" Suspension" shall not be deemed to be a punishment  within the meaning of this section."]</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-39">
              <num>39.</num>
              <heading>Pension and provident funds.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-39.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The University shall  constitute, for the benefit of its officers including the Upacharya</p>
                  <p>(Vice- Chancellor), teachers', and other servants, in such manner  and subject to such conditions as may be prescribed by the Statutes,</p>
                  <p>such pension, insurance and provident funds as it may deem fit.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-39.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where any such pension, insurance or provident fund has been  so constituted, the Central Government may declare that the provisions  of the Provident Funds Act, 1925 (19 of 1925), shall apply to such  fund as if it were a Government Provident Fund.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-40">
              <num>40.</num>
              <heading>Filling of casual vacancies.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-40.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Subject to any provision in  this Act and in the Statutes, the Karma Samiti (Executive Council)</p>
                  <p>shall appoint, with the approval of the Paridarsaka (Visitor), a  person to fill a casual vacancy</p>
                  <p>in the office of the Upacharya (Vice- Chancellor), and the person so  appointed shall hold office  until his successor enters upon his  office].</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-40.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>All casual vacancies among the members (other than ex officio   members) of any authority or other body of the University shall be  filled, as soon as conveniently may be, by the person or body who  appointed, elected or co- opted the member whose place has become  vacant, and the Person appointed, clected or co- opted to a casual  vacancy shall be member of such authority or body for the residue of  the term for which the person whose place he fills would have been a  member.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-41">
              <num>41.</num>
              <heading>Removal from membership of the University. The Karma</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-41.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Samiti (Executive Council) may, on the recommendation of not less than  two- thirds of its members remove any person from the membership of any  authority or board of the University if such a person is guilty of a  serious offence involving moral turpitude, or if he has been guilty of  scandalous conduct and for the same reasons may withdraw any degree or  diploma conferred on, or granted to, any person by the University:</p>
                  <p>Provided that no action shall be taken under this section against  any person except after giving him a reasonable opportunity of being  heard with regard to the proposed action.]</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-42">
              <num>42.</num>
              <heading>Disputes as to constitution of any University authority or  body. If any question arises whether any person has been duly elected  or appointed as, or is entitled to be, a member of any authority or  other body of the University, the matter shall be referred to the</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-42.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Paridarsaka (Visitor), whose decision thereon shall be final.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-43">
              <num>43.</num>
              <heading>Constitution of committees. Where any authority of the</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-43.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>University is given power by this Act or by the Statutes to appoint  committees, such committee shall, unless there is some special  provision to the contrary, consist of members of the authority  concerned and of such other persons (if any) as the authority in each  case may think fit.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-44">
              <num>44.</num>
              <heading>Proceedings of the University authorities not invalidated by  vacancies. No act or proceeding of any authority or other body of the</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-44.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>University shall be invalidated merely by reason of the existence of a  vacancy or vacancies among its members.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-44A">
              <num>44A.</num>
              <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit or  other legal proceeding shall lie against any officer or employee of  the University for anything which is in good faith done, or intended  to be done, in pursuance of the provisions of this Act, the Statutes  or the Ordinances.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-44B">
              <num>44B.</num>
              <heading>Mode of proof of University record. A copy of any receipt,</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-44B.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>application, notice, order, proceeding or resolution of any authority  or committee of the University, or other documents in the possession  of the University, or any entry in any register duly maintained by the</p>
                  <p>University, if certified by the Karma- Sachiva (Registrar), shall,</p>
                  <p>notwithstanding anything contained in the Indian Evidence Act, 1872</p>
                  <p>(1 of 1872), or in any other law for the time being in force, be  admitted as evidence of the matters and transactions specified therein  where the original thereof would, if produced, have been admissible in  evidence."]</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-45">
              <num>45.</num>
              <heading>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises with  respect to the establishment of the University or any authority of the</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-45.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>University or in connection with the first meeting of any authority of  the University, the Paridarsaka (Visitor) in consultation with the</p>
                  <p>Upacharya (Vice- Chancellor) may, by order, make any appointment or do  anything which appears to him necessary or expedient for the proper  establishment of the University or any authority thereof or for the  first meeting of any authority of the University.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
