<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1902/57/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1902/57"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Delhi Motor Vehicles Taxation Act, 1962"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1902/57/eng@1902-12-15/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1902/57/eng@1902-12-15"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1902-12-15" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1902/57/eng@1902-12-15/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1902/57/eng@1902-12-15"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Delhi Motor Vehicles Taxation Act, 1962</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 57 OF 1962</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 15th December, 1902]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirteenth year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to impose a tax on motor vehicles in the Union territory  of Delhi and for other matters connected therewith.</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be  called the Delhi Motor Vehicles Taxation Act, 1962.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the Union territory of Delhi.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Administrator 2  may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" Administrator" means the Administrator of Delhi  appointed by the president under article 239 of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Constitution:]</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" Delhi" means the Union territory of Delhi;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>" quarter" means.. a period of three months commencing  on the first day of April, the first day of July, the first  day of October or the first day of January in each year;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>registered owner" means the person in whose name a motor  vehicle is registered under the Motor Vehicles Act, 1939; (4   of 1939)</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>" tax" means the tax levied under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>" taxation authority" means any person or authority  appointed by the  Administrator] by notification in the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6">
              <listIntroduction>Official Gazette to exercise' the powers and perform' the  duties conferred or imposed upon a taxation authority by or  under. this Act;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>" token of means a ticket to be displayed on A motor  vehicle as an indication that the tax has been duly paid or  that no tax is payable;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>" Year" means the financial year;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>all words and expressions used, but not, defined in  this Act, and defined in the Motor Vehicles Act, 1939, (4 of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1939">
        <num>1939.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1939.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>) shall have the, 4 of meanings respectively assigned to  them in that Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Lavy of tax.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the other provisions of this</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Act, on and from the commencement of the Delhi Motor Vehicles Taxation</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list2.Amendment">
                <num>(Amendment)</num>
                <p>Act, 1989, there shall be levied and collected on</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>all motor vehicles described in column (1) of Part A of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-scheduleI">
      <doc name="scheduleI">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1902/57/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1902/57"/>
              <FRBRalias value="and used or kept for use in Delhi, a tax at the  rate specified in the corresponding entry in column (2) of  the said Part;"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1902/57/eng@1902-12-15/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1902/57/eng@1902-12-15"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1902/57/eng@1902-12-15/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1902/57/eng@1902-12-15"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduleI">
            <paragraph id="scheduleI.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <blockList id="scheduleI.paragraph-0.list0">
                  <item id="scheduleI.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>all motor vehicles described in column (1) of Part B of</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-scheduleI">
      <doc name="scheduleI">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1902/57/scheduleI"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1902/57"/>
              <FRBRalias value="and used or kept for use in Delhi"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1902/57/eng@1902-12-15/scheduleI"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1902/57/eng@1902-12-15"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1902/57/eng@1902-12-15/scheduleI"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1902/57/eng@1902-12-15"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduleI">
            <paragraph id="scheduleI.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <blockList id="scheduleI.paragraph-0.list0">
                  <item id="scheduleI.paragraph-0.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>on their first registration in Delhi, a one time tax at  the amount specified in the corresponding entry in column (2)</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <blockList id="scheduleI.paragraph-0.list2">
                  <listIntroduction>of the said Part;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="scheduleI.paragraph-0.list2.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>the same having been earlier registered in Delhi or in  any other State, then having regard to the month of their  first registration in Delhi or, as the case may be, in that  other State, a one time tax at the amount specified in the  respective columns (3) to (14) of Part C of Schedule I:</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <p>Provided that where such motor vehicles are more than ten years  old from the date of their first registration, the owners thereof  shall present the registration certificates of such motor vehicles to  the taxation authority for an endorsement therein to the effect that  the motor vehicles are more than ten years old and their use or  keeping for use in Delhi do not attract any tax.]</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <section id="section-2">
              <num>2.</num>
              <heading/>
              <subsection id="section-2.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The Administrator may, by notification in the official</p>
                  <p>Gazette, increase from time to time, the rate specified in Schedule I</p>
                  <p>in relation to any motor vehicles:</p>
                  <p>Provided that the rate as so increased shall in no case exceed  the rate as so specified by more than twenty- five per cent thereof:]</p>
                  <p>Provided further that any such increase shall not apply in  respect of a motor vehicle specified in part B of Schedule I on which  one time tax has been levied and collected."]</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-4">
              <num>4.</num>
              <heading>Declaration and payment of tax.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-4.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every registered owner  or person having possession or, control of a motor vehicle used or  kept for use in Delhi shall fill up, and sign a declaration in the  prescribed form stating the prescribed particulars and shall deliver  the same to the taxation authority within the prescribed time.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-4.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The tax to which a registered owner or person having pos-</p>
                  <blockList id="section-4.2.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>session or control of a motor vehicle appears by such declaration to  be liable under section 3 shall be paid by him,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-4.2.list2.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <blockList id="section-4.2.list2.a.list0">
                        <listIntroduction>where such vehicle is described in Part A of Schedule I,-</listIntroduction>
                        <item id="section-4.2.list2.a.list0.i">
                          <num>(i)</num>
                          <p>for a year at the rate specified in the corresponding  entry in column (2) thereof (hereinafter referred to as the   annual rate); or</p>
                        </item>
                        <item id="section-4.2.list2.a.list0.ii">
                          <num>(ii)</num>
                          <p>for one or more quarters, at one- fourth of the annual  rate fox each quarter; or</p>
                        </item>
                        <item id="section-4.2.list2.a.list0.iii">
                          <num>(iii)</num>
                          <p>for any period less than a quarter expiring on the last  day of the quarter, at one- twelfth of the annual rate for  each complete month or part thereof included in such period;</p>
                        </item>
                      </blockList>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-4.2.list4">
                    <listIntroduction>or</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-4.2.list4.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>where such vehicle is described in Part B of Schedule I,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>a one time tax at the amount specified in the corresponding  entry in column (2) in the said Part or, as the case may be,</p>
                  <p>the amount specified in the respective columns in Part C.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-4.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The tax shall be paid within such time and in such manner  as may be prescribed.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-4.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>In calculating the tax due for any period less than one year,</p>
                  <p>fraction of a rupee shall be counted as a rupee.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-5">
              <num>5.</num>
              <heading>Issue of token.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-5.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>When a person pays the amount of tax  leviable under section 3 in respect of any motor vehicle or proves to  the satisfaction of the taxation authority that no such tax is payable</p>
                  <blockList id="section-5.1.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>In respect of such vehicle, the taxation authority shall,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-5.1.list2.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>issue to such person a token in the prescribed form  specifying therein the period for which such tax has been  paid or that no such, tax is payable, and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-5.1.list2.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>specify in the certificate of registration granted, in  respect of the vehicle under the Motor Vehicles Act, 1939, (4   of 1939), or in the case of vehicles not registered under  that Act, in a certificate in such form As may be prescribed,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>that the tax has been, paid for the period specified under  clause (a) or that no tax is payable. in respect of that  vehicle, as the case may be;</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-5.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>No motor vehicle liable to tax under this Act shall be used  or kept for use in DEW unless the registered owner or the person  having possession or control of ouch vehicle has obtained a valid  token in respect of that vehicle, and that token is displayed on the  vehicle in the prescribed manner.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-6">
              <num>6.</num>
              <heading>Additional declaration.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-6.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>When a motor vehicle used or kept  for use in Delhi is altered or is proposed to be used in such manner  as to render the registered owner or the person who has possession or  control such vehicle liable to the payment of additional tax under  section 7, such owner or person shall fill up, sign and deliver in the  manner provided in sub- section (2), an additional declaration and  shall along with such additional declaration (accompanied by the   certificate of registration in respect of such motor vehicle), pay to  the taxation authority an additional tax payable under that section  which he appears by such additional declaration to be liable to in  respect of such vehicle.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-6.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The additional declaration shall be in the prescribed form  containing the prescribed particulars and shall be delivered to the  taxation authority after being duly filled up and signed within the  prescribed time. The additional declaration shall indicate clearly  also the nature of alteration made in the motor vehicle or, as the  case may be, the altered use to which the vehicle is proposed to put.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-6.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>On receipt of the additional tax under sub- section (1), the  taxation authority shall issue to the registered owner or the personal  who has possession or control of the vehicle, a fresh taken in place I</p>
                  <p>of the original token and shall cause an entry of such payment to be  made in the certificate of registration.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-7">
              <num>7.</num>
              <heading>Liability for additional tax. When any motor vehicle in respect  of which a tax for any period is payable or has been paid, is altered  during such period, or proposed to be used during such period in such  manner, as, to, cause the vehicle to become a vehicle in respect of  which a higher rate of tax is payable, the registered owner or the  person who hap possession or control of the vehicle, shall in addition  to the tax. if any, due from him for that period, be liable to pay for  the unexpired portion of such period since the vehicle is altered or</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>proposed to be used, an additional tax of a sum equal to the  difference between the amount of tax payable for such unexpired  portion at the higher rate and the rate at which the tax was payable  or paid before the alteration or use of the vehicle for that portion;</p>
                  <p>and until such additional tax has been paid, the taxation authority  shall not grant a fresh token in respect of the vehicle so altered or  proposed to be so used.</p>
                  <p>Explanation.- In calculating the unexpired portion under this  section any broken period in a month shall be considered as a full  month.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-8">
              <num>8.</num>
              <heading>Production of certificate of insurance. Every registered owner  or person having possession or control of a motor vehicle shall, at  the time of making payment of the tax, produce before the taxation  authority a valid certificate of insurance in respect of the vehicle  complying with the requirements of Chapter VIII of the Motor Vehicles</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Act, 1939. (4 of 1939).</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-9">
              <num>9.</num>
              <heading>Liability to pay arrears of tax of person succeeding to the  ownership, possession or control of motor vehicles.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-9.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>If the tax  leviable in respect of any motor vehicle remains unpaid by any person  liable for payment thereof and such person before having paid the tax  has transferred the ownership of such vehicle or has ceased to be in  possession or control of such vehicle, the person to whom the  ownership of the vehicle has been transferred or the person who has  possession or control of such vehicle shall be liable to pay the said  tax to the taxation authority.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Nothing contained in this section shall be deemed to affect  the liability to pay the said tax of the person who has transferred  the ownership or has ceased to be in possession or control of such  vehicle.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-10">
              <num>10.</num>
              <heading>Refund of tax.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-10.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-10.1.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>When any person who has paid the tax in  respect of a motor vehicle produces before the taxation authority a  certificate signed by the registering authority stating that the tax  token and the certificate of registration issued in respect of such  vehicle have been surrendered on the date specified by the registering  authority in his certificate, such person shall, on an application  made in that behalf to the taxation authority and subject to such  conditions is may be prescribed, be entitled to a refund,--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-10.1.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>in a case where payment of tax has been made in accord-</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-10.1.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>ance with clause (a) of subsection (2) of section 4, for each  complete month of the period for which such tax has been paid  and which is unexpired on the date on which the tax token and  the certificate of registration were surrendered, of an  amount equal to one- twelfth of the annual tax payable in  respect of such vehicle; and</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-10.1.list3.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>in a case where payment of tax has been made in accord-</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>ance with clause (b) of sub- section (2) of section 4, at the  rates specified in Schedule IA.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-10.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-10.2.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>When any person has paid the tax in respect of a motor  vehicle and the vehicle is removed outside Delhi before the expiry of  the period for which the tax has been paid and taxed in another State  or the registration of such vehicle is cancelled before the expiry of  the period for which the tax has been paid, such person shall, on an  application made in that behalf to the taxation authority and subject  to such conditions as may be prescribed, be entitled to a refund,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-10.2.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>in a case where payment of tax has been made in ac-</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-10.2.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>cordance with clause (a) of sub- section (2) of section 4, for  each complete month of the period for which such tax has been  paid, and during which the vehicle was removed from Delhi or  such vehicle' s registration is cancelled, of an amount equal  to one- twelfth of the annual tax payable in respect of such  vehicle; and</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-10.2.list3.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>in a case where payment of tax has been made in ac-</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>cordance with clause (b) of Sub- section (2) of section 4, at  the rates specified in Schedule IB.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-10.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where the rates of tax leviable under Part B of Schedule I</p>
                  <p>are increased by notification in the Official Gazette under. sub-</p>
                  <p>section (2) of section 3, the Administrator may, from time to time, by  the same notification or by a separate notification in the official</p>
                  <p>Gazette, correspondingly increase the rates of refund payable under  this section and the refund of tax payable, in respect of the vehicles  registered on or after the date of such notification shall be at such  increase rates."]</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-11">
              <num>11.</num>
              <heading>Penalty payable when tax not paid. When any registered owner  or any person who has possession or control of any motor vehicle used  or kept for use in Delhi is in default in making a payment of the tax  the taxation authority may direct that, in addition to the amount of  arrears, a sum not exceeding the annual tax payable in respect of such  vehicle shall be recovered from him by way of penalty:</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Provided that before giving any such direction the registered  owner or such person shall be given a reasonable opportunity of being  heard.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-12">
              <num>12.</num>
              <heading>Arrears of tax and penalty recoverable as arrears of land  revenue.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-12.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Any tax due and not paid as provided for by or under this</p>
                  <p>Act and any sum directed to be recovered by way of penalty under  section 11 shall be recoverable in the same manner as an arrear of  land revenue.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-12.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The motor vehicle in respect of which the tax is due or in  respect of which any sum has been directed to be recovered as penalty  under section 11, or its accessories may be distrained and sold in  pursuance of this section whether or not such vehicle or accessories  is or are in the possession or control of the person liable to pay the  tax or penalty.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-13">
              <num>13.</num>
              <heading>Exemptions.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-13.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where the registered owner or the person  having possession or control of a motor vehicle is an agriculturist  and that motor vehicle has been designed for agricultural operations  and is used solely for such operations in relation to his own'. and  then, that vehicle shall be exempt from the payment of the tax.</p>
                  <p>Explanation.- For the purposes of this sub- section the expression</p>
                  <blockList id="section-13.1.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>" agricultural operations" includes,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-13.1.list3.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>tilling, sowing, harvesting, crushing of any agricultural  produce or any other similar operation carried out for the  purpose of agriculture;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-13.1.list3.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>transport of manure, seeds, insecticides and other like  articles required for work in the land from the market to the  land; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-13.1.list3.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>transport of any agricultural produce from the land to  the place of storage or from the place of storage to the  market.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-13.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>When the registered owner or the person having possession or  control of a motor vehicle has given previous intimation in writing to  the taxation authority that the motor vehicle would not be used in any  public place for a particular period, being not less than one month,</p>
                  <p>and deposits the certificate of registration of such motor vehicle  with the taxation authority and obtains an acknowledgment therefor  from that authority, he shall be exempt from the payment of the tax  for that period.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-13.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where the  Administrator] is of opinion that it is neces-</p>
                  <p>sary or expedient in the public interest so to do, he may, by notifi-</p>
                  <p>cation in the Official Gazette, and subject to such conditions as he  may specify in the notification, exempt either totally or partially  any class of motor vehicles other than those falling under sub- section</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-13.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>or any motor vehicles belonging to any class of persons from the  payment of the tax.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-14">
              <num>14.</num>
              <heading>Reduction of tax in cases of certain motor vehicles. Where  the registered owner of a motor vehicle used or kept for use in Delhi  is a co- operative society registered under any law relating to co-</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>operative societies for the time being in force, the tax payable in  respect of that motor vehicle shall be one half of the rates specified  in Schedule I, if the taxation authority is satisfied, after such  enquiry as it deems fit, that,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>the co- operative society is solely engaged in the  business of transport of goods or passengers or both from one  place to another in motor vehicles;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>at least seventy- five per cent. of the members of the  cooperative society are its employees;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list1.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>at least fifty per cent of the members of the co- opera-</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-14.paragraph-0.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>tive society are not related to each other; and</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-14.paragraph-0.list3.iv">
                      <num>(iv)</num>
                      <p>the motor vehicle is used or kept for use exclusively  for the purpose of the co- operative society.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Explanation.- For the purposes of this section a member shall be  deemed to be related to any other member if that member is the hus-</p>
                  <p>band, wife, brother or sister or any lineal ascendant or descendant of  that other member.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-15">
              <num>15.</num>
              <heading>Effect of payment of tax in other States with respect to motor  vehicles brought into Delhi. Where in respect of a motor vehicle the  tax payable under law relating to taxation on motor vehicles in force  in any State h been paid in that State for any period and that motor  vehicle is brought into Delhi for use during that period, then,-</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-15.paragraph-0.list0">
                    <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>no tax under this Act shall be payable in respect of  that motor vehicle; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>the token issued in that State in respect of that motor  vehicle shall be deemed to be a token issued under this Act,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>for such period or for a period of ninety days from the date on which  the motor vehicle is brought into Delhi, whichever is shorter:</p>
                  <p>Provided that the registered owner or the person having posses-</p>
                  <p>Sion or control of the motor vehicle complies with the provisions of  sub- section (1) of section 4.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-16">
              <num>16.</num>
              <heading>Appeal.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-16.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Any person who is aggrieved by any order or  direction of the taxation authority may file an appeal before such  person or authority, in such manner, within such time and on payment  of such fees, as may be prescribed.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-16.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The appeal shall be heard and decided in such manner as may  be prescribed.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-16.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every decision on such appeal shall be final and shall not  be called in question in any court of law.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-17">
              <num>17.</num>
              <heading>Powers of police officers and other officers. Any police  officer in uniform, not below the rank of Sub- InSpector or any other  officer prescribed in this behalf may-</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-17.paragraph-0.list0">
                    <item id="section-17.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>enter at any time between sunrise and sunset any premi-</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-17.paragraph-0.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>ses where he has reason to believe that a motor vehicle is  kept, or,</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-17.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>require the driver of any motor vehicle in any public  place to stop such vehicle and cause it to remain stationary  so long as may reasonably be necessary,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>for the purpose of satisfying himself that the amount of the tax in  respect of such vehicle, has been paid.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-18">
              <num>18.</num>
              <heading>Penalty for incomplete and untrue declaration, etc. Whoever-</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-18.paragraph-0.list0">
                    <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>delivers in respect of a motor vehicle a declaration or  additional declaration wherein the particulars required by or  under this Act to be therein set forth are not fully and  truly stated, or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>obstructs any officer in the exercise of the powers  conferred by clause (a) of section 17 or fails to stop the  motor vehicle</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>when required to do so by such officer under clause (b) of that  section,</p>
                  <blockList id="section-18.paragraph-0.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>shall on conviction be punishable-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list3.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>with fine which may extend to a sum equal to the annual  tax payable in respect of such vehicle; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list3.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>in the event of such person having been previously  convicted of an offence under this section, with fine which  may extend to a sum equal to twice the annual tax payable in  respect of such vehicle.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-19">
              <num>19.</num>
              <heading>Other penalties. Whoever contravenes any of the provisions of  this Act or the rules made thereunder other than those punishable  under section 18 shall on conviction be punishable with fine which may  extend to one hundred rupees and in the event of such person having  been previously convicted of an offence under this section, with fine  which may extend to two hundred rupees.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-20">
              <num>20.</num>
              <heading>Utilization of the proceeds of tax. The proceeds of the tax  collected under this Act (Which shall form part of the Consolidated</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Fund of India) reduced by the cost of collection as determined by the</p>
                  <blockList id="section-20.paragraph-0.list2">
                    <listIntroduction>Central Government shall, if Parliament by appropriation made by law  in this behalf so provides, be paid to,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list2.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>the Municipal Corporation of Delhi established under  section 3 of the Delhi Municipal Corporation Act, 1957; (66   of 1957).</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list2.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>the New Delhi Municipal Committee established under  section 11 of the Punjab Municipal Act, 1911, (Punjab Act 3 of</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-1911">
              <num>1911.</num>
              <heading/>
              <paragraph id="section-1911.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-1911.paragraph-0.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>) as extended to Delhi; and</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-1911.paragraph-0.list1.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>the Cantonment Board, Delhi, constituted under the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Cantonments Act, 1924, (2 of 1924).</p>
                  <p>for the performance of their respective functions under the said Acts  and the payment shall be made in such proportion as may be prescribed</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-21">
              <num>21.</num>
              <heading>Trial of offences. No court inferior to that of a magistrate  of the second class shall try an offence punishable under this Act.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-22">
              <num>22.</num>
              <heading>Protection for bona fide acts. No prosecution, suit or other  proceedings shall lie against the taxation authority or any other  authority for anything in good faith done or intended to be done under  this Act.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-23">
              <num>23.</num>
              <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-23.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>The  Administrator] may, subject to  the condition of previous publication, make rules for carrying out the  purposes of this Act.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-23.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-23.2.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing provision, the  Administrator] may or any of the following  matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-23.2.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the time within which, and the manner in which, the tax  shall be paid;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-23.2.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>the form of declaration and additional declaration,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-23.2.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>particulars to be stated therein and the time within which  the declaration or additional declaration shall be delivered  under section 4 or section 6, as the case may be;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-23.2.list3.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>the form of the tax token and the manner in which the  tax token shall be displayed in the motor vehicle under sec-</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-23.2.list5">
                    <listIntroduction>tion 5;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-23.2.list5.d">
                      <num>(d)</num>
                      <p>the conditions subject to which refund of tax may be  allowed under section 10;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-23.2.list5.e">
                      <num>(e)</num>
                      <p>the authority before which, the manner in which, the  time within which and the fee on payment of which, an appeal  may be filed and the manner in which such appeal shall be  heard and decided under section 16;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-23.2.list5.f">
                      <num>(f)</num>
                      <p>the issue of duplicate tokens and of certified copies  of the records of the taxation authority and the fees  chargeable therefor;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-23.2.list5.g">
                      <num>(g)</num>
                      <p>any other matter which is to be, or may be,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>prescribed.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-23.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every rule made under this section and every notification  issued under sub- section (2) of section 3,  and sub- section (3) of  section 10] shall be laid, as soon as may be, after it is made or  issued, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session for a  total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or  in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the  session immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or  notification, or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made or  the notification should not be issued, the rule or notification shall  thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</p>
                  <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that rule or notification"].</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-24">
              <num>24.</num>
              <heading>Repeal.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-24.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>On and from the commencement of this Act, the Acts  specified in Schedule II shall stand repealed.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-24.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-24.2.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>The repeal of the said Acts by sub- section (1) shall not  affect,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-24.2.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>the previous operation of the said Acts or anything  duly done or suffered thereunder; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-24.2.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>any right, privilege, obligation or right conferred,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>accrued or incurred under any of the said Acts; or</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-131">
              <num>131.</num>
              <heading>M of Law- 52</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-131.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-131.paragraph-0.list0">
                    <item id="section-131.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>any penalty, forfeiture or punishment incurred in respect  of any offence committed against any of the said Acts;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-131.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                      <num>(d)</num>
                      <p>any investigation,. legal proceeding or remedy in res-</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>pect of any- such right, privilege, obligation, liability,</p>
                  <p>penalty forfeiture or punishment as aforesaid;</p>
                  <p>and any, such investigation, legal proceeding or remedy: may be  instituted, continued or enforced and any such penalty, forfeiture or  punishment may be imposed as if the said Acts had not been repealed.</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <subsection id="section-131.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Subject to the provisions contained in sub- section (2) and  notwithstanding the repeal of the Punjab Motor Vehicles Taxation Act</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-1924">
              <num>1924.</num>
              <heading/>
              <paragraph id="section-1924.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-1924.paragraph-0.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>, (Punjab Act 4 of 1924.) as extended to Delhi,-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-1924.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>every declaration delivered under that Act in respect  of any motor vehicle shall be deemed to be a declaration  delivered under this Act; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-1924.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>every token issued under that Act and valid immediately  before the commencement of this Act, shall continue to be  valid after such commencement for the unexpired portion of  the, period for which it has been issued.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-25">
              <num>25.</num>
              <heading>Amendment of section 184, Act 66 of 1957. In the Delhi</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Municipal Corporation Act, 1957, for section 184, he following section  shall be substituted, namely--</p>
                  <p>" 184. Central Government to pay proceeds of entertainment and  betting taxes to Corporation. The proceeds of the  entertainment and betting, taxes collected in Delhi under the  provisions of the U. P. Entertainment and Betting Tax Act,</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <section id="section-1937">
              <num>1937.</num>
              <heading/>
              <paragraph id="section-1937.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>, (U. P. Act 8 of 1937.) as extended to Delhi (which shall   form part of the Consolidated Fund of India) reduced by the  cost of collection as determined by the Central Government  shall if parliament by appropriation made by law in this  behalf so provides, be paid to the Corporation for the  performance of its functions under this Act."</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
