<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1980/54/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1980/54"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Hotel- Receipts Tax Act, 1980"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1980/54/eng@1980-12-09/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1980/54/eng@1980-12-09"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-12-09" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1980/54/eng@1980-12-09/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1980/54/eng@1980-12-09"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Hotel- Receipts Tax Act, 1980</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 54 OF 1980</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 9th December, 1980.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty- first Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to impose a special tax on gross receipts of certain hotels.</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:--</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and extent.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Hotel-</p>
            <p>Receipts Tax Act, 1980.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>" assessee" means a person by whom hotel- receipts tax or any  other sum of money is payable under this Act and includes--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>every person in respect of whom any proceeding under  this Act has been taken for the assessment of his chargeable  receipts or of the amount of refund due to him or of the  chargeable receipts of any other person in respect of which he is  assessable or of the amount of refund due to such other person;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>every person who is deemed to be an assessee in default  under any provision of this Act;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" assessment" includes reassessment;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" assessment year" means the period of twelve months  commencing on the 1st day of April every year;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" Board" means the Central Board of Direct Taxes constituted  under the Central Boards of Revenue Act, 1963 (54 of 1963);</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" chargeable receipts" means the total amount of all charges  referred to in section 6, computed in the manner laid down in section</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>;</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-7.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" hotel" includes a building or part of a building where  residential accommodation is, by way of business, provided for a  monetary consideration;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" hotel- receipts tax" or" tax" means the tax chargeable under  the provisions of this Act;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" Income- tax Act" means the Income- tax Act, 1961 (43 of</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1961">
        <num>1961.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1961.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>);</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-1961.9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1961.10">
          <num>(10)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-1961.10.list1">
              <listIntroduction>" room charges" means the charges for a unit of residential  accommodation in a hotel and includes the charges for--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1961.10.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>furniture, air- conditioner, refrigerator, radio, music,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-1961.10.list3">
              <listIntroduction>telephone, television, and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1961.10.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>such other services as are normally included by a hotel  in room rent,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>but does not include charges for food, drink and any services other  than those referred to in sub- clauses (a) and (b);</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1961.11">
          <num>(11)</num>
          <content>
            <p>all other words and expression used herein but not defined  and defined in the Income- tax Act shall have the meanings respectively  assigned to them in that Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Application of the Act.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of sub-</p>
            <p>section (2) and sub- section (3), this Act shall apply in relation to  every hotel wherein the room charges for residential accommodation  provided to any person at any time during the previous year are  seventy- five rupees or more per day per individual.</p>
            <p>Explanation.-- Where the room charges are payable otherwise than  on daily basis or per individual, then the room charges shall be  computed as for a day and per individual based on the period of  occupation of the residential accommodation for which the charges are  payable and the number of individuals ordinarily permitted to occupy  such accommodation according to the rules and custom of the hotel.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a composite charge is payable in respect of residential  accommodation and food, the room charges included therein shall be  determined in the prescribed manner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.3.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>a composite charge is payable in respect of residential  accommodation, food, drink and other services, or any of them,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>and the case is not covered by the provisions of sub- section (2),</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.3.list4">
              <listIntroduction>or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.3.list4.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>it appears to the Income- tax Officer that the charges  for residential accommodation, food, drink or other services are  so arranged that the room charges are understated and the other  charges are overstated,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>the Income- tax Officer shall, for the purposes of sub- section (1),</p>
            <p>determine the room charges on such reasonable basis as he may deem  fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Tax authorities.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Director of Inspection,</p>
            <p>Commissioner of Income- Tax, Commissioner of Income- tax (Appeals),</p>
            <p>Inspecting Assistant Commissioner of Income- tax, Officer and Inspector  of Income- tax shall have the like powers and perform the like  functions under this Act as he has and performs under the Income- tax</p>
            <p>Act, and for the exercise of his powers and the performance of his  functions, his jurisdiction under this Act shall be the same as he has  under the Income- tax Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All officers and persons employed in the execution of this</p>
            <p>Act shall observe and follow the orders, instructions and directions  of the Board:</p>
            <blockList id="section-4.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that no such orders, instructions or directions shall be  issued--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.2.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>so as to require any tax authority to make a particular  assessment or to dispose of a particular case in a particular  manner; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.2.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>so as to interfere with the discretion of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Commissioner (Appeals) in the exercise of his appellate  functions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Income- tax Officer employed in the execution of this</p>
            <p>Act shall observe and follow the orders, instructions and directions  issued for his guidance by the Director of Inspection or by the</p>
            <p>Commissioner or by the Inspecting Assistant Commissioner within whose  jurisdiction he performs his functions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Charge of tax.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act,</p>
            <p>there shall be charged on every person carrying on the business of a  hotel in relation to which this Act applies, for every assessment year  commencing on or after the 1st day of April, 1981, a tax in respect of  his chargeable receipts of the previous year at the rate of fifteen  per cent. of such receipts:</p>
            <p>Provided that where such chargeable receipts include any charges  received in foreign exchange, then, the tax payable by the assessee  shall be reduced by an amount equal to five per cent. of the charges</p>
            <p>(exclusive of the amounts payable by way of sales tax, entertainment   tax, tax on luxuries or tax under this Act) so received in foreign  exchange.</p>
            <blockList id="section-5.1.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation.-- For the purposes of this sub- section,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.1.list5.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>charges received in Indian currency obtained by  conversion of foreign exchange into Indian currency shall, in  such cases and in such circumstances as may be prescribed, be  deemed to have been received in foreign exchange; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list5.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" foreign exchange" and" Indian currency" shall have the  meanings respectively assigned to them in clauses (h) and (k) of  section 2 of the Foreign Exchange Regulation Act, 1973 (46 of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1973">
        <num>1973.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1973.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-1973.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-1973.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where, under an arrangement made between a person carrying on  the business of a hotel to which this Act applies and any other person  having close connection with him, any food, drink or other services is  or are provided on the premises of such hotel by the second- mentioned  person and the Income- tax Officer is of opinion that such arrangement  has been made with a view to avoiding or reducing the liability under  this Act by the first- mentioned person, then,</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1973.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the second- mentioned person shall also be deemed to be a  person carrying on the business of a hotel to which this Act  applies; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1973.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>hotel- receipts tax shall be charged on the second-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>mentioned person in respect of charges for food, drink or other  services so provided by him as if such charges were the  chargeable receipts of the</p>
            <blockList id="section-1973.2.list4">
              <listIntroduction>business of a hotel deemed to be carried on by him under clause</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1973.2.list4.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>, and all the provisions of this Act shall apply accordingly.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-1973.2.list6">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation.-- For the purposes of this sub- section,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1973.2.list6.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>a close connection shall be deemed to exist between a  person carrying on the business of a hotel and another person if,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>in relation to the person carrying on the business of a hotel,</p>
            <p>such other person is a person referred to in clause (b) of sub-</p>
            <blockList id="section-1973.2.list10">
              <listIntroduction>section (2) of section 40A of the Income- tax Act;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1973.2.list10.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>any food, drink or other service shall be deemed to  have been provided on the premises of a hotel if the same is or  are provided in the hotel or any place appurtenant thereto and  where the hotel is situate in a part of building, in any other  part of the building.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Scope of chargeable receipts.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of  this Act, the chargeable receipts of any previous year of an assessee  shall be the total amount of all charges, by whatever name called,</p>
            <p>received by, or accruing or arising to, the assessee in connection  with the provision of residential accommodation, food, drink and other  services or any of them (including such charges from persons not  provided with such accommodation  but excluding such charges from  persons within] the purview of the Vienna Convention on Diplomatic</p>
            <p>Relations, 1961 or the Vienna Convention on Consular Relations, 1963  in the course of carrying on the business of a hotel to which this</p>
            <p>Act applies and shall also include every amount collected by the  assessee by way of tax under this Act, sales tax, entertainment tax  and tax on luxuries.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that where  any such charges have been included in the chargeable receipts of any  previous year as charges accruing or arising to the assessee during  that previous year, such charges shall not be included in the  chargeable receipts of any subsequent previous year in which they are  received by the assessee.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Computation of chargeable receipts.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Subject to the  provisions of sub- section (2), the following deductions shall be  allowed in computing the chargeable receipts of any previous year--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the amount of charges accruing or arising in an earlier  previous year which is established to have become a bad debt  during the previous year:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-7.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that such charges have been taken into account in  computing the chargeable receipts of the assessee of any earlier  previous year and the amount has been written off as  irrecoverable in the accounts of the assessee for the previous  year during which it is established to have become a bad debt;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.1.list3.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>any amount payable by way of sales tax, entertainment  tax or tax on luxuries in respect of any charges included in the  chargeable receipts of the previous year;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.1.list3.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>the amount of tax chargeable under this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Explanation.-- For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared  that in computing the chargeable receipts of a previous year, no  deduction, other than the deductions specified in this sub- section,</p>
            <p>shall be allowed from the total amount of charges received by, or  accruing or arising to, the assessee.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In computing the chargeable receipts of a previous year, the  amount of charges which is received by or which accrues or arises to  the assessee before the expiry of one month from the end of the month  in which this Act comes into force  or after the 27th day of</p>
            <p>February, 1982] shall not be taken into account.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Ins. by Act 14 of 1982, s. 41 (retrospectively).</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Ins. by s. 42, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 4- 1982).</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Return of chargeable receipts.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every person, who, during  the previous year, carried on the business of a hotel in relation to  which this Act applies or is assessable in respect of the chargeable  receipts of any other person under this Act, shall furnish a return of  his chargeable receipts or the chargeable receipts of such other  person of the previous year in the prescribed form and verified in the  prescribed manner and setting forth such other particulars as may be  prescribed, before the expiry of four months from the end of the  previous year in respect of the business of the hotel or where there  is more than one previous year in respect of such business, from the  end of the previous year which expired last before the commencement of  the assessment year, or before the 30th day of June of the assessment  year, whichever is later:</p>
            <p>Provided that, on an application made in this behalf, the Income-</p>
            <p>tax Officer may, in his discretion, extend the date for furnishing the  return.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the case of any person who, in the Income- tax Officer' s  opinion is assessable under this Act, whether in respect of his own  chargeable receipts or in respect of the chargeable receipts of any  other person, the Income- tax Officer may, before the end of the  relevant assessment year, issue a notice to him and serve the same  upon him, requiring him to furnish within thirty days from the date of  service of the notice a return of his chargeable receipts or the  chargeable receipts of such other person of the previous year in the  prescribed form and verified in the prescribed manner and setting  forth such other particulars as may be prescribed:</p>
            <p>Provided that on an application made in this behalf, the Income-</p>
            <p>tax Officer may, in his discretion, extend the date for furnishing the  return.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any assessee who has not furnished a return within the time  allowed under sub- section (1) or sub- section (2), or having furnished  a return under sub- section (1) or sub- section (2), discovers any  omission or wrong statement therein, may furnish a return or a revised  return, as the case may be, at any time before the assessment is made.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Self- assessment.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any hotel- receipts tax is payable  on the basis of any return required to be furnished under section 8 or  section 13 after taking into account the amount of hotel- receipts tax,</p>
            <p>if any, already paid under any provision of this Act, the assessee  shall be liable to pay such tax before furnishing the return and the  return shall be accompanied by proof of payment of such tax.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>After an assessment under section 10 or section 11 has been  made, any amount paid under sub- section (1) shall be deemed to have  been paid towards such assessment.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any assessee fails to pay the hotel- receipts tax or any  part thereof in accordance with the provisions of sub- section (1), the</p>
            <p>Income- tax Officer may direct that a sum equal to two per cent. of  such tax or part thereof, as the case may be, shall be recovered from  him by way of penalty for every month during which the default  continues:</p>
            <p>Provided that before levying any such penalty, the assessee shall  be given a reasonable opportunity of being heard.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Assessment.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of making an assessment under  this Act, the Income- tax Officer may serve on any person who has  furnished a return</p>
            <p>under section 8 or upon whom a notice has been served under sub-</p>
            <p>section (2) of section 8 (whether a return has been furnished or not)</p>
            <p>a notice requiring him on a date therein to be specified, to produce  or cause to be produced such accounts or documents or other evidence  as the Income- tax Officer may require for the purposes of this Act and  may, from time to time, serve further notices requiring the production  of such further accounts or documents or other evidence as he may  require.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Income- tax Officer, after considering such accounts,</p>
            <p>documents or other evidence, if any, as he has obtained under sub-</p>
            <p>section (1) and after taking into account any relevant material which  he has gathered, shall, by an order in writing, assess the chargeable  receipts and the amount of the hotel- receipts tax payable on the basis  of such assessment.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Best judgment assessment. If--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any person fails to make the return required by any  notice given under sub- section (2) of section 8 and has not made  a return or a revised return under sub- section (3) of that  section, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any person having made a return, fails to comply with  all the terms of a notice issued under sub- section (1) of section</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>, or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the Income- tax Officer is not satisfied about the  correctness or the completeness of the accounts of the assessee,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>the Income- tax Officer, after taking into account all relevant  material which he has gathered, shall make the assessment of the  chargeable receipts to the best of his judgment and determine the sum  payable by the assessee or refundable to the assessee on the basis of  such assessment.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Re- opening of assessment at the instance of the assessee.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-12.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where an assessee assessed under section 11 makes an application to  the Income- tax Officer, within one month from the date of service of a  notice of demand issued in consequence of the assessment, for the  cancellation of the assessment on the ground--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>that he was prevented by sufficient cause from making  the return required under sub- section (2) of section 8, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.1.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>that he did not receive the notice issued under sub-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-12.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>section (1) of section 10, or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.1.list3.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>that he had not a reasonable opportunity to comply, or  was prevented by sufficient cause from complying, with the terms  of the notice referred to in clause (ii),</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>the Income- tax Officer shall, if satisfied about the existence of such  ground, cancel the assessment and proceed to make a fresh assessment  in accordance with the provisions of section 10 or section 11.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every application made under sub- section (1) shall be  disposed of within ninety days from the date of receipt thereof by the</p>
            <p>Income- tax Officer:</p>
            <p>Provided that in computing the period of ninety days aforesaid,</p>
            <p>any delay in disposing of the application which is attributable to the  assessee shall be excluded.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Receipt' s escaping assessment. If--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the Income- tax Officer has reason to believe that by  reason of the omission or failure on the part of the assessee to  make a return under section 8 for any assessment year or to  disclose fully and truly all material facts necessary for his  assessment for any assessment year, chargeable receipts for that  year have escaped assessment or have been under- assessed or have  been made the subject of excessive relief under this Act, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>notwithstanding that there has been no omission or  failure as mentioned in clause (a) on the part of the assessee,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>the Income- tax Officer has, in consequence of information in his  possession, reason to believe that chargeable receipts assessable  for any assessment year have escaped assessment or have been  under- assessed or have been the subject of excessive relief under  this Act,</p>
            <p>he may, in cases falling under clause (a), at any time, and in cases  falling under clause (b), at any time within four years of the end of  that assessment year, serve on the assessee a notice containing all or  any of the requirements which may be included in a notice under  section 8 and may proceed to assess or reassess the amount chargeable  to hotel- receipts tax, and the provisions of this Act shall, so far as  may be, apply, as if the notice were a notice issued under that  section.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Advance payment of hotel receipts tax.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Hotel- receipts tax  shall be payable in advance during the financial year in respect of  the chargeable receipts of the period which would be the previous year  for the immediately following assessment year in accordance with the  provisions of this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Hotel- receipts tax shall be payable in advance in two  instalments on the following dates during the financial year, namely:-</p>
            <blockList id="section-14.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.2.list2.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the 15th day of September in respect of the chargeable  receipts attributable to the first half of the previous year; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.2.list2.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>the 15th day of March in respect of the chargeable  receipts attributable to the second half of the previous year:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that the hotel- receipts tax payable in advance during  the financial year commencing on the 1st day of April, 1980 shall be  payable in one sum on the 15th day of March, 1981.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every assessee shall, in each financial year, on or before  such of the dates on which an instalment of hotel- receipts tax is  payable in advance, send to the Income- tax Officer, an estimate of the  chargeable receipts attributable to the relevant part of the previous  year and the hotel- receipts tax payable in advance on such chargeable  receipts and shall pay such amount of hotel- receipts tax as accords  with his estimate on or before the relevant date specified in sub-</p>
            <p>section (2):</p>
            <p>Provided that in respect of the hotel- receipts tax payable in  advance during the financial year commencing on the 1st day of April,</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1980">
        <num>1980.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1980.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>, the assessee shall send to the Income- tax Officer an estimate of  the chargeable receipts attributable to the period which would be the  previous year for the assessment year commencing on the 1st day of</p>
            <p>April, 1981 and the hotel- receipts tax payable in advance on such  chargeable receipts and shall pay such amount of hotel- receipts tax as  accords with his estimate on or before the 15th day of March, 1981.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-1980.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every estimate under this section shall be sent in the  prescribed form and verified in the prescribed manner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1980.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any assessee does not pay on or before the specified date  any instalment of hotel- receipts tax payable in advance, he shall be  deemed to be an assessee in default in respect of such instalment.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for failure to furnish returns, comply with notices,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>concealment of receipts, etc.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If, in the course of any proceedings  under this Act, the Income- tax Officer or the Commissioner (Appeals)</p>
            <blockList id="section-15.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>is satisfied that any person--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>has, without reasonable cause, failed to furnish the  return of chargeable receipts which he was required to furnish  under sub- section (1) of section 8 or by notice given under sub-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-15.1.list4">
              <listIntroduction>section (2) of section 8 or section 13 or has, without reasonable  cause, failed to furnish it within the time allowed and the  manner required by sub- section (1) of section 8 or by such  notice, as the case may be, or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.1.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>has, without reasonable cause, failed to comply with the  notice under sub- section (1) of section 10, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.1.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>has concealed the particulars of his chargeable receipts  or furnished inaccurate particulars of such receipts,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-15.1.list6">
              <listIntroduction>he may direct that such person shall pay by way of penalty,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.1.list6.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>in the cases referred to in clause (a), in addition to  the hotel- receipts tax payable by him, a sum equal to two per  cent. of the assessed tax for every month during which the  default continued, but not exceeding in the aggregate fifty per  cent. of the assessed tax.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Explanation.-- In this clause," assessed tax" means  hotel- receipts tax chargeable under the provisions of this Act,</p>
            <blockList id="section-15.1.list9">
              <listIntroduction>as reduced by the sum, if any, paid in advance under section 14;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15.1.list9.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>in the cases referred to in clause (b), in addition to  the hotel- receipts tax payable by him, a sum which shall not be  less than ten per cent. but which shall not exceed fifty per  cent. of the amount of the hotel- receipts tax which would have  been avoided if the return made by him had been accepted as  correct;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15.1.list9.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>in the cases referred to in clause (c), in addition to  the hotel receipts tax payable by him, a sum which shall not be  less than, but which shall not exceed twice, the amount of hotel-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>receipts tax which would have been avoided if the return made by  him had been accepted as correct:</p>
            <p>Provided that in a case falling under clause (c), the Income- tax</p>
            <p>Officer shall not impose any penalty without the previous approval of  the Inspecting Assistant Commissioner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On making an order imposing a penalty under this section, the</p>
            <p>Commissioner (Appeals) shall forthwith send a copy of the same to the</p>
            <p>Income- tax Officer.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Penality for false estimate of, or failure to pay, hotel-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>receipts tax payable in advance. If, in the course of any proceedings  in connection with the assessment under section 10 or section 11, the</p>
            <blockList id="section-16.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Income- tax Officer is satisfied that any assessee--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>has furnished under section 14, an estimate of the  hotel- receipts tax payable in advance by him which he knew or had  reason to believe to be untrue, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>has, without reasonable cause, failed to furnish an  estimate of the hotel- receipts tax payable in advance by him in  accordance with the provisions of section 14,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>he may direct that the assessee shall, in addition to the hotel-</p>
            <blockList id="section-16.paragraph-0.list5">
              <listIntroduction>receipts tax payable by him, pay by way of penalty a sum--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list5.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>which, in the case referred to in clause (a), shall not  be less than ten per cent. but shall not exceed one and a half  times the amount by which the hotel- receipts tax paid in advance  during the financial year immediately preceding the assessment  year, falls short of eighty- five per cent. of the hotel- receipts  tax chargeable under the provisions of this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list5.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>which, in the case referred to in clause (b), shall not  be less than ten per cent. but shall not exceed one and a half  times of eighty- five per cent. of the hotel- receipts tax  chargeable under the provisions of this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Opportunity of being heard. No order imposing penalty under  section 15 or section 16 shall be made unless the assessee has been  heard, or has been given a reasonable opportunity of being heard.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Appeals to the Commissioner (Appeals).</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person  objecting to the amount of hotel- receipts tax for which he is assessed  by the Income- tax Officer, or denying his liablility to be assessed  under this Act, or objecting to an order under section 12 refusing to  re- open an assessment made under section 11 or objecting to any  penalty or fine imposed by the Income- tax Officer, or to the amount  allowed by the Income- tax Officer by way of any relief under any  provision of this Act, or to any refusal by the Income- tax Officer to  grant relief, or to an order of rectification having the effect of  enhancing the assessment or reducing the refund, or to an order  refusing to allow the claim made by the assessee for a rectification  under section 20, may appeal to the Commissioner (Appeals).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every appeal shall be in the prescribed form and shall be  verified in the prescribed manner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-18.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>An appeal shall be presented within thirty days of the  following date, that is to say,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>where the appeal relates to assessment or penalty or  fine, the date of service of the notice of demand relating to the  assessment or penalty or fine, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in any other case, the date on which the intimation of  the order sought to be appealed against is served:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that the Commissioner (Appeals) may admit an appeal  after the expiration of the said period if he is satisfied that the  appellant had sufficient cause for not presenting it within that  period.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commissioner (Appeals) shall hear and determine the  appeal and, subject to the provisions of this Act, pass such orders as  he thinks fit and such orders may include an order enhancing the  assessment or penalty:</p>
            <p>Provided that an order enhancing the assessment or penalty shall  not be made unless the person affected thereby has been given a  reasonable opportunity of showing cause against such enhancement.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The procedure to be adopted in the hearing and determination  of the appeals shall, with any necessary modification, be in  accordance with the procedure applicable in relation to income- tax.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Appeals to Appellate Tribunal.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-19.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any assessee aggrieved by  an order passed by a Commissioner under section 22, or an order passed  by a Commissioner (Appeals) under any provision of this Act, may  appeal to the Appellate Tribunal against such order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commissioner may, if he objects to any order passed by  the Commissioner (Appeals) under any provision of this Act, direct the</p>
            <p>Income- tax Officer to appeal to the Appellate Tribunal against the  order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every appeal under sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) shall  be filed within sixty days of the date on which the order sought to be  appealed against is communicated to the assessee or to the</p>
            <p>Commissioner, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Income- tax Officer or the assessee, as the case may be,</p>
            <p>on receipt or a notice that an appeal against the order of the</p>
            <p>Commissioner (Appeals) has been preferred under sub- section (1) or  sub- section (2) by the other party may, notwithstanding that he may  not have appealed against such order or any part thereof, within  thirty days of the receipt of the notice, file a memorandum of cross-</p>
            <p>objections, verified in the prescribed manner, against any part of the  order of the Commissioner (Appeals), and such memorandum shall be  disposed of by the Appellate Tribunal as if it were an appeal  presented within the time specified in sub- section (3).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Appellate Tribunal may admit an appeal or permit the  filing of a memorandum of cross- objections after the expiry of the  relevant period referred to in sub- section (3) or sub- section (4), if  it is satisfied that there was sufficient cause for not presenting it  within that period.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An appeal to the Appellate Tribunal shall be in the  prescribed form and shall be verified in the prescribed manner and  shall, except in the case of an appeal referred to in sub- section (2)</p>
            <p>or a memorandum of cross- objections referred to in sub- section (4), be  accompanied by a fee of  two hundred rupees].</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act, in hearing and making  an order on any appeal under this section, the Appellate Tribunal  shall exercise the same powers and follow the same procedure as it  exercises and follows in hearing and making an order on any appeal  under the Income- tax Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Rectification of mistakes.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-20.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>With a view to rectifying any  mistake apparent from the record, the Income- tax Officer, the</p>
            <blockList id="section-20.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Commissioner (Appeals), the Commissioner and the Appellate Tribunal  may, of his or its own motion or on an application by the assessee in  this behalf, or where the authority concerned is the Commissioner</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-20.1.list2.Appeals">
                <num>(Appeals)</num>
                <p>, by the Income- tax Officer also, amend any order passed by  him or it in any proceeding under this Act within four years of the  date on which such order was passed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An amendment which has the effect of enhancing the assessment  or reducing a refund or otherwise increasing the liability of the  assessee shall not be made under this section unless the authority  concerned has</p>
            <p>given notice to the assessee of its intention so to do and has allowed  the assessee a reasonable opportunity of being heard.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an amendment is made under this section, the order  shall be passed in writing by the authority concerned.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the other provisions of this Act, where any such  amendment has the effect of reducing the assessment, the Income- tax</p>
            <p>Officer shall make any refund which may be due to such assessee.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any such amendment has the effect of enhancing the  assessment or reducing the refund already made, the Income- tax Officer  shall serve on the assessee a notice of demand in the prescribed form  specifying the sum payable.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Hotel- receipts tax deductible in computing total income under</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Income- tax Act. Notwithstanding anything contained in the Income- tax</p>
            <p>Act, in computing the income chargeable to income- tax under the head</p>
            <p>" Profits and gains of business or profession" in the case of an  assessee carrying on the business of a hotel to which this Act  applies, the hotel- receipts tax payable by the assessee for any  assessment year shall be deductible from the profits and gains of the  business of the hotel assessable for that assessment year.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Revision of order prejudicial to revenue.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-22.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The</p>
            <p>Commissioner may call for and examine the record of any proceeding  under this Act and if he considers that any order passed therein by  the Income- tax Officer is erroneous in so far as it is prejudicial to  the interests of the revenue, he may, after giving the assessee an  opportunity of being heard and after making or causing to be made such  enquiry as he deems necessary, pass such order thereon as the  circumstances of the case justify, including an order enhancing or  modifying the assessment, or cancelling the assessment and directing a  fresh assessment.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-22.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-22.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>No order shall be made under sub- section (1)--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-22.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to revise an order of reassessment made under section</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>, or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>after the expiry of two years from the date of the order  sought to be revised.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-13.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (2), an  order in revision under this section may be passed at any time in the  case of an order which has been passed in consequence of, or to give  effect to, any finding or direction contained in an order of the</p>
            <p>Appellate Tribunal, the High Court or the Supreme Court.</p>
            <p>Explanation.-- In computing the period of limitation for the  purposes of sub- section (2), any period during which any proceeding  under this section is stayed by an order or injunction of any court  shall be excluded.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Revision of orders by Commissioner.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-23.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commissioner may,</p>
            <p>either of his own motion or on an application by the assessee for  revision, call for the record of any proceeding under this Act which  has been taken by an Income- tax Officer subordinate to him and may  make such enquiry or cause such enquiry to be made and, subject to the  provisions of this Act, may pass such</p>
            <p>order thereon, not being an order prejudicial to the assessee, as he  thinks fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commissioner shall not of his own motion revise any order  under this section if the order has been made more than one year  previously.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the case of an application for revision under this section  by the assessee, the application shall be made within one year from  the date on which the order in question was communicated to him or the  date on which he otherwise came to know of it, whichever is earlier:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Commissioner may, if he is satisfied that the  assessee was prevented by sufficient cause from making the application  within that period, admit an application made after the expiry of that  period.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-23.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Commissioner shall not revise any order under this  section in the following cases:--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-23.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>where an appeal against the order lies to the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-23.4.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Commissioner (Appeals) but has not been made and the time within  which such appeal may be made has not expired, or the assessee  has not waived his right of appeal; or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-23.4.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>where the order has been made the subject of an appeal  to the Commissioner (Appeals).</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every application by an assessee for revision under this  section shall be accompanied by a fee of twenty- five rupees.</p>
            <p>Explanation.-- An order by the Commissioner declining to interfere  shall, for the purposes of this section, be deemed not to be an order  prejudicial to the assessee.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Application of provisions of Income- tax Act. The provisions  of the following sections and Schedules of the Income- tax Act and the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Income- tax (Certificate Proceedings) Rules, 1962, as in force from  time to time, shall apply with necessary modifications as if the said  provisions and the rules referred to hotel- receipts tax instead of to  income- tax:--</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-24.43B">
          <num>(43B)</num>
          <content>
            <p>and (44), 41 (4), 118, 125, 125A, 128 to 136 (both   inclusive), 138, 140, 144A, 156, 159 to 163 (both inclusive),</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-166">
        <num>166.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-166.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>, 167, 170, 171, 173 to 179 (both inclusive), 187, 188, 189,</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-219">
        <num>219.</num>
        <heading>to 227 (both inclusive), 228A, 229, 231, 232, 237 to 242</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-219.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>(both inclusive), 244, 245, 254 to 262 (both inclusive), 265,</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-266">
        <num>266.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-266.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>, 268, 269, 278B, 278C, 278D, 281, 281B, 282, 283, 284, 287,</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-288">
        <num>288.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-288.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>, 288A, 288B, 289 to 293 (both inclusive), the Second Schedule  and the Third Schedule:</p>
            <p>Provided that references in the said provisions and the rules to  the" assessee" shall be construed as references to an assessee as  defined in this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Income- tax papers to be available for the purposes of this</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-25.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Income- tax Act, all  information contained in any statement or return made or furnished  under the provisions of that Act or obtained or collected for the  purposes of that Act may be used for the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All information contained in any statement or return made on  furnished under the provisions of this Act or obtained or collected  for the purposes of this Act may be used for the purposes of the</p>
            <p>Income- tax Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Wilful attempt to evade tax, etc.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-26.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-26.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If a person wilfully  attempts in any manner whatsoever to evade any tax, penalty or  interest chargeable or imposable under this Act, he shall, without  prejudice to any penalty that may be imposable on him under any other  provision of this Act, be punishable,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-26.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>in a case where the amount sought to be evaded exceeds  one hundred thousand rupees, with rigorous imprisonment for a  term which shall not be less than six months but which may extend  to seven years and with fine;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-26.1.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>in any other case, with rigorous imprisonment for a  term which shall not be less than three months but which may  extend to three years and with fine.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-26.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If a person wilfully attempts in any manner whatsoever to  evade the payment of any tax, penalty or interest under this Act, he  shall, without prejudice to any penalty that may be imposable on him  under any other provision of this Act, be punishable with rigorous  imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than three months but  which may extend to three years and shall, in the discretion of the  court, also be liable to fine.</p>
            <p>Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section, a wilful attempt  to evade any tax, penalty or interest chargeable or imposable under  this Act or the payment thereof shall include a case where any person-</p>
            <blockList id="section-26.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-26.2.list3.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>has in his possession or control any books of account or  other documents (being books of account or other documents   relevant to any proceeding under this Act) containing a false  entry or statement; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-26.2.list3.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>makes or causes to be made any false entry or statement  in such books of account or other documents; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-26.2.list3.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>wilfully omits or causes to be omitted any relevant  entry or statement in such books of account or other documents;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-26.2.list5">
              <listIntroduction>or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-26.2.list5.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>causes any other circumstance to exist which will have  the effect of enabling such person to evade any tax, penalty or  interest chargeable or imposable under this Act or the payment  thereof.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Failure to furnish returns of chargeable receipts. If a  person wilfully fails to furnish in due time the return of chargeable  receipts which he is required to furnish under sub- section</heading>
        <subsection id="section-27.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-27.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>of  section 8 or by notice given under sub- section (2) of section 8 or  section 13, he shall be punishable,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-27.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>in a case where the amount of tax, which would have been  evaded if the failure had not been discovered, exceeds one  hundred thousand rupees, with rigorous imprisonment for a term  which shall not be less than six months but which may extend to  seven years and with fine;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-27.1.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>in any other case, with imprisonment for a term which  shall not be less than three months but which may extend to three  years and with fine:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-27.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that a person shall not be proceeded against under this  section for failure to furnish in due time the return of chargeable  receipts under sub- section (1) of section 8, if--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-27.1.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the return is furnished by him before the expiry of the  assessment year; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-27.1.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the tax payable by him on the chargeable receipts  determined on assessment as reduced by the tax paid in advance  under section 14, if any, does not exceed three thousand rupees.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28">
        <num>28.</num>
        <heading>Failure to produce accounts and documents. If a person  wilfully fails to produce, or cause to be produced, on or before the  date specified in any notice served on him under sub- section</heading>
        <subsection id="section-28.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of  section 10, such accounts and documents as are referred to in the  notice, he shall be punishable with rigorous imprisonment for a term  which may extend to one year, or with fine equal to a sum calculated  at a rate which shall not be less than four rupees or more than ten  rupees for every day during which the default continues, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29">
        <num>29.</num>
        <heading>False statement in verification, etc. If a person makes a  statement in any verification under this Act or under any rule made  thereunder, or delivers an account or statement which is false, and  which he either knows or believes to be false, or does not believe to  be true, he shall be punishable,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-29.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-29.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-29.paragraph-0.list0.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>in a case where the amount of tax, which would have been  evaded if the statement or account had been accepted as true,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-29.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>exceeds one hundred thousand rupees, with rigorous imprisonment  for a term which shall not be less than six months but which may  extend to seven years and with fine;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-29.paragraph-0.list2.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>in any other case, with rigorous imprisonment for a  term which shall not be less than three months but which may  extend to three years and with fine.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-30">
        <num>30.</num>
        <heading>Abetment of false return, etc. If a person abets or induces  in any manner another person to make and deliver an account or a  statement or declaration relating to any chargeable receipts which is  false and which he either knows to be false or does not believe to be  true or to commit an offence under sub- section</heading>
        <subsection id="section-30.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-30.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>of section 26, he  shall be punishable,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-30.1.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>in a case where the amount of tax, penalty or interest  which would have been evaded, if the declaration, account or  statement had been accepted as true, or which is wilfully  attempted to be evaded, exceeds one hundred thousand rupees, with  rigorous imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than six  months but which may extend to seven years and with fine;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-30.1.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>in any other case, with rigorous imprisonment for a  term which shall not be less than three months but which may  extend to three years and with fine.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-31">
        <num>31.</num>
        <heading>Punishment for second and subsequent offences. If any person  convicted of an offence under sub- section</heading>
        <subsection id="section-31.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of section 26 or section</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>or section 29 or section 30 is again convicted for an offence under  any of the aforesaid provisions, he shall be punishable for the second  and for every subsequent offence with rigorous imprisonment for a term  which shall not be less than six months but which may extend to seven  years and with fine.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-32">
        <num>32.</num>
        <heading>Certain offences to be non- cognizable. Notwithstanding  anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1974">
        <num>1974.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1974.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>), an offence punishable under section 26 or section 27 or section</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29">
        <num>29.</num>
        <heading>or section 30 shall be deemed to be non- cognizable within the  meaning of that Code.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-33">
        <num>33.</num>
        <heading>Institution of proceedings and composition of offences.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-33.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A</p>
            <p>person shall not be proceeded against for any offence under section 26  or section 27 or section 28 or section 29 or section 30 for any  offence under the Indian Penal Code relating to any matter connected  with or arising out of this Act, (45 of 1860) except at the instance  of the Commissioner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-33.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Commissioner may, either before or after the institution  of proceedings, compound any offence punishable under section 26 or  section 27 or section 28 or section 29 or section 30.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-34">
        <num>34.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-34.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board may, subject to the  control of the Central Government, by notification in the Official</p>
            <p>Gazette, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-34.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-34.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-34.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the manner in which the room charges may be determined  under sub- section (2) of section 3 in cases where composite  charges are payable in respect of residential accommodation and  food;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-34.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the cases and the circumstances in which payments made  in Indian currency by conversion of foreign exchange into Indian  currency shall be deemed to have been made in foreign exchange  for the purposes of sub- section (1) of section 5;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-34.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the form in which returns under section 8 may be  furnished, the manner in which they may be verified and the other  particulars which a form may contain;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-34.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the form in which an estimate under section 14 may be  sent and the manner in which it may be verified;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-34.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the form in which appeals under section 18 or section 19  may be filed and the manner in which they may be verified;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-34.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the form in which a memorandum of cross- objections under  sub- section (4) of section 19 may be verified;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-34.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the procedure to be followed on applications for  rectification of mistakes under section 20;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-34.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the form in which a notice of demand may be served on  the assessee under sub- section (5) of section 20;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-34.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>any other matter which by this Act is to be or may be  prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-34.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The power to make rules conferred by this section shall on  the first occasion of the exercise thereof include the power to give  retrospective effect to the rules or any of them from a date not  earlier than the date of commencement of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-34.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government shall cause every rule made under this  section to be laid, as soon as may be, after it is made before each</p>
            <p>House of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of  thirty</p>
            <p>days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more  successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session  immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or  both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall  thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</p>
            <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-35">
        <num>35.</num>
        <heading>Power to exempt. Where the Central Government is of the  opinion that it is necessary or expedient so to do either in the  public interest or having regard to the peculiar circumstances of the  case, it may, by notification in the Official Gazette and subject to  such conditions, if any, as may be specified in the notification,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-35.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>exempt any hotel or any class of hotels from the levy of hotel-</p>
            <p>receipts tax.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-36">
        <num>36.</num>
        <heading>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in  giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government  may, by order, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-36.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>remove the difficulty:</p>
            <p>Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a  period of two years from the commencement of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
