<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1961/46/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1961/46"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Voluntary Surrender Of Salaries (Exemption From Taxation) Act 1961"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1961/46/eng@1961-12-06/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1961/46/eng@1961-12-06"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1961-12-06" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1961/46/eng@1961-12-06/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1961/46/eng@1961-12-06"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Voluntary Surrender Of Salaries (Exemption From Taxation) Act 1961</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 46 OF 1961</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 6th December, 1961.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for exempting from taxes on income a portion of the  salary or allowances payable to any person who has in the public  interest volunteered to forego it.</p>
        <p>Be it enacted by Parliament in the Twelfth year of the Republic  of India as follows:--</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title. This Act may be called the Voluntary Surrender of</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Salaries (Exemption from Taxation) Act, 1961.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Exemption from taxes on income in respect of salaries  surrendered in favour of Government. Notwithstanding anything  contained in the Indian Income- tax Act, 1922, (11 of 1922.) or in any  other law for the time being in force relating to taxation on income,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>no income- tax or super- tax shall be payable by any person--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>where his salary is paid out of the Consolidated Fund of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>India or of the Consolidated Fund of a State, in respect of  that part of the salary due to him for any period after the</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-31st">
        <num>31st.</num>
        <heading>day of March, 1961 which he has, by a declaration in  writing, volunteered to forego in the public interest;</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-31st.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-31st.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-31st.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in any other case, in respect of that part of the salary  which is due to him for any period after the 31st day of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>March, 1961 which has been, in the public interest  surrendered in favour of, and paid to, the Central Government  in accordance with the rules made in this behalf by that</p>
            <p>Government;</p>
            <p>and such part of the salary shall not be included in his total income  for the purposes of any law relating to taxation on income.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Provisions of section 2 apply to allowances. The provision of  section 2 shall apply in relation to any allowances due to any such  person as is referred to therein for any period after the 31st day of</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>March, 1961 as they apply in relation to his salary.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the  purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as  may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is in  session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in  one session or  in two or more successive sessions, and if, before  the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the  successive sessions aforesaid] both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not  be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified  from or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however that any such  modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity  of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Repeal. The Voluntary Surrender of Salaries (Exemption   from Taxation) Act, 1950, (61 of 1950) is hereby repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding such repeal any declaration made under the  said Act shall be deemed to be a declaration made for the purposes of  this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
