<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1856/9/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1856/9"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Indian Bills Of Lading Act, 1856"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1856/9/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1856/9/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1856/9/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1856/9/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Indian Bills Of Lading Act, 1856</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 9 OF 1856</docNumber>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-11th">
        <num>11th.</num>
        <heading>April, 1856</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11th.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>An Act to amend the Law relating to Bills of Lading.</p>
            <p>Preamble.-- Whereas by the custom of merchants a bill of lading of  goods being transferable by endorsement, the property in the goods may  thereby pass to the endorsee, but nevertheless all rights in respect  of the contract contained in the bill of lading continue in the  original shipper or owner, and it is expedient that such rights should  pass with the property; and whereas it frequently happens that the  goods in respect of which bills of lading purport to be signed have  has been laden on board, and it is proper that such bills of lading in  the hands of a bona fide holder for value should not be questioned by  the master or other person signing the same, on the ground of the  goods not having been laden as aforesaid: It is enacted is follows:-</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Rights under bills of lading to vest in consignee of  endorsee.-- Every consignee of goods named in a bill of lading, and  every endorsee of a bill of lading to whom the property in the goods  therein mentioned shall pass, upon or by reason of such consignment or  endorsement shall have transferred to and vested in him all rights of  suit, and be subject to the same liabilities in respect of such goods  as if the contract contained in the bill of lading had been made with  himself.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Not to affect right of stoppage in transitu of claims for  freight.-- Nothing herein contained shall prejudice or affect any right  of stoppage in transitu,  or any right to claim freight against  the original shipper or owner, or any liability of the consignee or  endorsee by reason or in consequence of his being such consignee or  endorsee, or of his receipt of the goods by reason or in consequence  of such consignment or endorsement.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Bill of lading in hands of consignee, ect., conclusive  evidence of the shipment as against master, etc.-- Every bill of lading  in the hands of a consignee or endorsee for valuable consideration,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>representing goods to have been shipped on board a vessel, shall be  conclusive evidence of such shipment as against the master or other  person signing the same, notwithstanding that such goods or some part  thereof may not have been so shipped, unless such holder of the bill  of lading shall have had actual notice at the time of receiving the  same that the goods had not in fact been laden on board:</p>
            <p>Provided that the master or other person so signing may exonerate  himself in respect of such misrepresentation, by showing that it was  caused without any default on his part, and wholly by the fraud of the  shipper, or of the holder, or some person under whom the holder  claims.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
