<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1958/42/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1958/42"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The International Finance Corporation (Status, Immunities Andprivileges) Act, 1958"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1958/42/eng@1958-10-17/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1958/42/eng@1958-10-17"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1958-10-17" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1958/42/eng@1958-10-17/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1958/42/eng@1958-10-17"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The International Finance Corporation (Status, Immunities Andprivileges) Act, 1958</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 42 OF 1958</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 17th October, 1958.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Ninth Year of the Republic of</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to implement the international agreement for the establishment  and operation of the International Finance Corporation in so far as it  relates to the status, immunities and privileges of that Corporation,</p>
        <p>and for matters connected therewith.</p>
        <p>India as follows:--</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and extent.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>International Finance Corporation (Status, Immunities and Privileges)</p>
            <p>Act, 1958.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" Agreement" means the Agreement for the establishment  and operation of the international body known as the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>International Finance Corporation;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" Corporation" means the International Finance</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Corporation established under the Agreement.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Conferment of status and certain immunities and privileges on  the Corporation and conferment of certain immunities and privileges on  its officers and employees.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything to the  contrary contained in any other law, the provisions of the Agreement  set out in the Schedule shall have the force of law in India:</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that nothing in Section 9 of Article VI of the Agreement  shall be construed as--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>entitling the Corporation to import into India goods  free of any duty of customs without any restriction on  their subsequent sale therein; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>conferring on the Corporation any exemption from duties  or taxes which form part of the price of goods sold; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>conferring on the Corporation any exemption from duties  or taxes which are in fact no more than charges for  services rendered.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, from time to time, by notification  in the Official Gazette, amend the Schedule in conformity with</p>
            <p>any amendments duly made and adopted, of the provisions of the</p>
            <p>Agreement set out therein:</p>
            <p>Provided that any notification issued under this sub- section  shall be laid for not less than thirty days before each House of</p>
            <p>Parliament as soon as may be after it is issued and shall be subject  to such modifications as Parliament may make during the session in  which it is so laid or the session immediately following.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the  purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as  may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament while it is  in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised  in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before  the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the  successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not  be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified  form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any  such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the  validity of anything previously done under that rule.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
