<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1948/41/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1948/41"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Diplomatic And Consular Officers (Oaths And Fees) Act, 1948"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1948/41/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1948/41/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1948/41/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1948/41/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Diplomatic And Consular Officers (Oaths And Fees) Act, 1948</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>ACT NO. 41 OF</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the administration of oaths by diplomatic and  consular officers and to prescribe the fees leviable in respect of  certain of their official duties.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-3rd">
        <num>3rd.</num>
        <heading>September, 1948.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3rd.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the administration of  oaths by diplomatic and consular officers and for the levy of fees in  respect of certain official duties performed by them;</p>
            <p>It is hereby enacted as follows:-</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title.- This Act may be called the Diplomatic and</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Consular Officers (Oaths and Fees) Act, 1948.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.- In this Act,-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" consular officer" includes consul- general, consul,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>vice- consul, consular agent, pro- consul and any other  person authorized to perform the duties of consul-</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>general, consul, vice- consul or consular agent;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" diplomatic officer" means any ambassador, envoy,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5">
              <listIntroduction>minister, charge d' affaires, or secretary of embassy or  legation; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Powers as to oaths and notarial acts abroad.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every  diplomatic or consular officer may, in any foreign country or place  where he is exercising his functions, administer any oath and take any  affidavit and also do any notarial act which any notary public may do  within  a State]; and every oath, affidavit and notarial act  administered, sworn or done by or before any such person shall be as  effectual as if duly administered, sworn or done by or before any  lawful authority in  a State].</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any document purporting to have affixed, impressed or  subscribed thereon or thereto the seal and signature of any person  authorized by this Act to administer an oath in testimony of any oath.</p>
            <p>affidavit or act, being administered, taken or done by or before him,</p>
            <p>shall be admitted in evidence without proof of the seal or signature  being the seal or signature of that person, or of the official  character of that person.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Punishment for offences under this Act.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever swears  falsely in any oath or affidavit taken or made in accordance with the  provisions of this Act shall be punished with imprisonment for a term  which may extend to three years and shall also be liable to fine.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever forges or fraudulently alters the seal or signature  of any person authorized by or under this Act to administer an oath or  tenders in evidence, or otherwise uses, any affidavit having any seal  or signature so forged or counterfeited or fraudulently altered  knowing the same to be forged, counterfeited or fraudulently altered,</p>
            <p>shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to  three years and shall also be liable to fine.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Trial of offences.- Any offence under this Act may be inquired  into, dealt with, tried and punished in  any  State]] in which the  person charged with the offence was apprehended or is in custody, in  the same manner and to the same extent as if the offence had been  committed within the State where he was apprehended or is in custody.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Power to prescribe fees.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, from  time to time, prescribe the fees to be levied in respect of any matter  or thing done by a diplomatic or consular officer in the execution of  his office.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All such fees shall be levied, accounted for and applied and  may be remitted in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A diplomatic or consular officer shall not, save as may be  provided by any rules made in this behalf, ask for or take any fee or  reward for or on account of any act or thing, or service done,</p>
            <p>performed or rendered by him in the execution of his office.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Publication and issue of tables of fees.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Tables of the  fees which may, for the time being, be levied under the rules shall be  published in such manner and copies thereof shall be issued  gratuitously to such persons as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every consular officer, and every diplomatic officer in any  foreign country or place where there is no consular officer, shall  keep exhibited in a conspicuous place in his office a copy of the  table of fees to be levied under this Act and shall permit the same to  be inspected by any person interested therein.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may , by  notification in the official Gazette,] make rules  to carry out the  purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may prescribe-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the scale of fees leviable under this Act and the manner  in which such fees shall be levied and collected;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the remuneration, if any, payable to a diplomatic or  consular officer in the execution of any of the duties  vested in him by this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the registers to be kept and the returns to be made in  pursuance of this Act; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the manner in which copies of tables of fees may be  published and distributed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as  may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament while it is  in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in  one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the  expiry of the session immediately following the session or the  successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not  be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified  form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any  such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the  validity of anything previously done under that rule.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
