<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1923/5/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1923/5"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Boilers Act, 1923"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1923/5/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1923/5/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1923/5/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1923/5/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Boilers Act, 1923</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the *** Boilers Act, 1923.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>"accident" means an explosion of boiler, or boiler component, which is calculated to weaken the strength or an uncontrolled release of water or steam therefrom, liable to cause death or injury to any person or damage to any property;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.aa">
                    <num>(aa)</num>
                    <p>"Board" means the Central Boilers Board constituted under section 27A;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>"boiler" means a pressure vessel in which steam is generated for use external to itself by application of heat which is wholly or partly under pressure when steam is shut off but does not include a pressure vessel,-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list1.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>with capacity less than 25 litres (such capacity being measured from the feed check valve to the main steam stop valve);</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list1.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>with less than one kilogram per centimetre square design gauge pressure and working gauge pressure; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list1.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list1.iii.list0">
                      <listIntroduction>in which water is heated below one hundred degrees centigrade;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list1.iii.list0.ba">
                        <num>(ba)</num>
                        <p>"boiler component" means steam piping, feed piping, economiser, superheater, any mounting or other fitting and any other external or internal part of a boiler which is subject to pressure exceeding one kilogram per centimetre square gauge;</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list2">
                  <listIntroduction>"Chief Inspector", "Deputy Chief Inspector", and "Inspec­tor" mean, respectively, a person appointed to be a Chief Inspec­tor, a Deputy Chief Inspector and an Inspector under this Act;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list2.ca">
                    <num>(ca)</num>
                    <p>"Competent Authority" means an institution recognised in such manner as may be prescribed by regulations for issue of certificate to the welders for welding of boiler and boiler components;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list2.cb">
                    <num>(cb)</num>
                    <p>"Competent Person" means a person recognised in such manner as may be prescribed by regulations for inspection and certification of boilers and boiler components during manufacture, erection and use;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list2.cc">
                    <num>(cc)</num>
                    <p>"economiser" means any part of a feed-pipe that is wholly or partially exposed to the action of flue gases for the purpose of recovery of waste heat;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list2.ccc">
                    <num>(ccc)</num>
                    <p>"feed-pipe" means any pipe or connected fitting wholly or partly under pressure through which feed water passes directly to a boiler and which does not form an integral part thereof;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list2.ccd">
                    <num>(ccd)</num>
                    <p>"Inspecting Authority" means an institution recognised in such manner as may be prescribed by regulations for the inspection and certification of boilers and boiler components during manufacture. All Chief Inspectors of Boilers shall be ipso facto Inspecting Authorities;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list2.cce">
                    <num>(cce)</num>
                    <p>"manufacture" means manufacture, construction and fabrication of boiler or boiler component, or both;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c.list2.ccf">
                    <num>(ccf)</num>
                    <p>"manufacture" means a person engaged in the manufacture;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>"owner" includes any person possessing or using a boiler as agent of the owner thereof and any person using a boiler which he has hired or obtained on loan from the owner thereof;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>"prescribed" means prescribed by regulations or rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f.list3">
                  <listIntroduction>"Steam-pipe" means any pipe through which steam passes if-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f.list3.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>the pressure at which steam passes through such pipe exceeds 3.5 kilogram per square centimetres above atmospheric pressure; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f.list3.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>such pipe exceeds 254 millimetres in internal diameter and the pressure of steam exceeds 1 kilogram per square centimetres above the atmospheric pressure, and includes in either case any connected fitting of a steam-pipe;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g.list4">
                  <listIntroduction>"Structural alteration, addition or renewal" means,-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g.list4.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>any change in the design of a boiler or boiler component;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g.list4.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>replacement of any part of boiler or boiler component by a part which does not conform to the same specification; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g.list4.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>any addition to any part of a boiler or boiler component;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>"superheater" means any equipment which is partly or wholly exposed to flue gases for the purpose of raising the temperature of steam beyond the saturation temperature at that pressure and includes a re-heater;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>"Technical Adviser" means the Technical Adviser appointed under sub-section (1) of section 4A.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>"(f) "steam-pipe" means any pipe through which steam passes from a boiler to a prime-mover or other user or both, if-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the pressure at which steam passes through such pipe exceeds 3.5 kilograms per square centimetre above atmospheric pressure; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>such pipe exceeds 254 millimetres in internal diameter;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>and includes in either case any connected fitting of a steam-pipe;".</p>
            <p>"(g) "Structural alteration, addition or renewal" shall not be deemed to include any renewal or replacement of a petty nature when the part or fitting used for replacement is not inferior in strength, efficiency or otherwise to the replaced part or fit­ting.".</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2A">
        <num>2A.</num>
        <heading>Application of Act to feed pipes. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every reference in this Act except where the word "steam-pipe" is used in clause (f) of section 2 to a steam-pipe or steam-pipes shall be deemed to include also a reference to a feed-pipe or feed-pipes, respectively.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2B">
        <num>2B.</num>
        <heading>Application of Act to economisers.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2B.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Every reference in this Act to a boiler or boilers except in clause (ccc) of section 2, [*** [*** shall be deemed to include also a reference to an economiser or economisers, respectively.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Limitation of application. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Nothing in this Act shall apply to-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>locomotive boilers belonging to or under the control of the railways;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>any boiler or boiler component,-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>in any vessel propelled wholly or in part by the agency of steam;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>belonging to, or under the control of, the Army, Navy or Air Force; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>appertaining to a sterilizer disinfector used in hospitals or nursing homes, if the boiler does not exceed one hundred litres in capacity.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>“3. Limitation of application.—</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Nothing in this Act shall apply in the case of any boiler or steam-pipe—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in any steam-pipe as defined in section 3 of the Indian Steam-ships Act, 1884 (7 of 1884), or in any steam-vessel as defined in section 2 of the Inland Steam-vessels Act, 1917 (1 of 1917); or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>belonging to, or under the control of, the Army, Navy or Air Force; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>appertaining to a sterilizer or disinfector of a type such as is commonly used in hospitals, if the boiler does not exceed ninety-one litres in capacity.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare that the provisions of this Act shall not apply in the case of boilers or steam-pipes, or any specified class of boilers or steam-pipes, belonging to or under the control of any railway administered by the Central Government or by any State Government or by any railway company as defined in clause (5) of section 3 of the Indian Railways Act, 1890 (9 of 1890).”.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Power to limit extent.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, exclude any specified area from the operation of all or any specified provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4A">
        <num>4A.</num>
        <heading>Technical Adviser. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government shall appoint a Technical Adviser from amongst the persons having such qualifications and experience as may be prescribed by rules.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The terms and conditions of service of the Technical Adviser shall be such as may be prescribed by the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Technical Adviser shall, in addition to exercising the powers and discharging the functions assigned to him under this Act or rules or regulations made thereunder, exercise such other powers and discharge such functions as the Central Government and the Board may delegate to him.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4B">
        <num>4B.</num>
        <heading>Welders certificate.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4B.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person who proposes to undertake any welding work connected with or related to a boiler, or a boiler component or both shall apply to a Competent Authority for issue of a Welders certificate.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4B.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On receipt of an application under sub-section (1), the Competent Authority shall follow such procedure for examination and grant of Welders certificate as may be prescribed by regulations.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4B.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Competent Authority may, if satisfied that the person applying for Welders certificate under sub-section (2) has compiled with the conditions precedent for issue of the Welders certificate, issue such certificate, to such person subject to the payment of such fee and such other conditions as may be prescribed by regulations: Provided that the Competent Authority shall not refuse Welders certificate to any person unless such person is given an opportunity of being heard.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4C">
        <num>4C.</num>
        <heading>Conditions precedent for manufacture of boiler and boiler component. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4C.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4C.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>No person shall manufacture or cause to be manufactured any boiler or boiler component, or both unless-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4C.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>he has provided in the premises or precincts wherein such boiler or boiler component, or both are manufactured, such facilities for design and construction as may be prescribed by regulations;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4C.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the design and drawings of the boiler and boiler component have been approved by the Inspecting Authority under clause (a) of sub-section (2) of section 4F;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4C.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the materials, mounting and fittings used in the construction of such boiler or boiler component, or both conform to the specifications prescribed by regulations; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4C.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the persons engaged for welding boiler or boiler component hold Welders certificate issued by a Competent Authority.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4D">
        <num>4D.</num>
        <heading>Inspection during manufacture. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4D.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every manufacturer, before commencing manufacture of a boiler or boiler component, shall engage an Inspecting Authority for carrying out inspection at such stages of manufacture as may be prescribed by regulations.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4D.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4D.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Inspecting Authority engaged under sub-section (1) shall follow such procedure for inspection and certification of boiler or boiler component as may be prescribed by regulations and after inspection, if it is-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4D.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>satisfied that the boiler or the boiler component conforms to the standards prescribed by regulations, it shall issue a certificate of inspection and stamp the boiler, or boiler component, or both; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4D.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>of the opinion that the boiler, or boiler component, or both does not conform to the standards prescribed by regulations, it may for reasons to be recorded in writing refuse to issue such certificate:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that no certificate shall be refused unless the Inspecting Authority had directed the manufacturer of the boiler or boiler component, or both in writing to carry out such modifications or rectifications as it deems necessary and the Inspecting Authority is of the opinion that inspite of such direction the manufacturer of the boiler or boiler component, or both did not carry out the direction.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4D.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Inspecting Authority may, for the purposes of inspection under this section, charge such fee as may be prescribed by regulations.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4E">
        <num>4E.</num>
        <heading>Inspection during erection. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4E.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The owner who proposes to register a boiler under section 7, shall engage on Inspecting Authority for carrying out inspection at the stage of erection of the boiler.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4E.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4E.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>the Inspecting Authority shall follow such procedure for inspection and certification of a boiler or boiler component, or both as may be prescribed by regulations and after inspection if it is-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4E.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>satisfied that the erection of the boiler is in accordance with the regulations, it shall issue a certificate of inspection in such form as may be prescribed by regulations; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4E.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>of the opinion that the boiler has not been erected in accordance with the regulations, it may for reasons to be recorded in writing, refuse to grant the certificate and shall communicate such refusal to the manufacturer of the boiler or boiler component forthwith:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that no such certificate shall be refused unless the Inspecting Authority had directed the owner in writing to carry out such modifications or rectifications as it deems necessary and the Inspecting Authority is of the opinion that in spite of such direction the owner did not carry out the direction.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4E.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the Inspecting Authority may, for the purposes of inspection under this section, charge such fee as may be prescribed by regulations.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4F">
        <num>4F.</num>
        <heading>Conditions precedent for repairing boiler and boiler component. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4F.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4F.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>No person shall repair or cause to be repaired any boiler or boiler component or both, unless-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4F.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>he has provided in the premises or precincts, where in such boiler or boiler component or both are being used, such facilities for repairs as may be prescribed by regulations;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4F.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the design and drawings of the boiler or boiler component, as the case may be, and the materials, mountings and fittings used in the repair of such boiler or boiler component conform to the regulations;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4F.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>persons engaged in welding, holds a Welders certificate issued by a Competent Authority;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4F.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>every user who does not have the in-house facilities for repair of boiler or boiler component shall engaged a Boiler Repairer possessing a Boiler Repairer certificate for repair of a boiler or boiler component or both, as the case may be;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4F.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>every user shall engage a Competent Person for approval of repairs to be carried out in-house or by the repairers.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Chief Inspector, Deputy Chief Inspectors and Inspectors. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may appoint such persons as it thinks fit to be Inspectors for the State for the purposes of this Act, and may define the local limits within which each Inspector shall exer­cise the powers and perform the duties conferred and imposed on Inspectors by or under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may appoint such persons as it thinks fit to be Deputy Chief Inspectors for the State and may define the local limits within which each Deputy Chief Inspector shall exercise his powers and perform his duties under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Deputy Chief Inspector may exercise the powers and perform the duties conferred and imposed on Inspectors by or under this Act and, in addition thereto, may exercise such powers or perform such duties conferred or imposed on the Chief Inspec­tor by or under this Act, as the State Government may assign to him.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government shall appoint a person to be Chief Inspector for the State who may, in addition to the powers and duties conferred and imposed on the Chief Inspector by or under this Act, exercise any power or perform any duty so conferred or imposed on Deputy Chief Inspectors or Inspectors.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.4A">
          <num>(4A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No person shall be appointed as the Chief Inspector, Deputy Chief Inspector or Inspector unless he possess such qualifications and experience as may be prescribed by the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Deputy Chief Inspectors and Inspectors shall exercise the powers and perform the duties conferred and imposed on them by or under this Act under the general superintendence and control of the Chief In­spector.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chief Inspector, Deputy Chief Inspectors and Inspectors may offer such advice as they think fit to owners regarding the proper maintenance and safe working of boilers.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chief Inspector and all Deputy Chief Inspectors and Inspectors shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>"Public servant". -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The words "public servant" denote a person falling under any of the descriptions hereinafter following, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1.Second">
                <num>(Second)</num>
                <p>- Every Commissioned Officer in the Military, Naval or Air Forces of India ;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-21.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Third .-Every Judge including any person empowered by law to discharge. whether by himself or as a member of any body of persons, any adjudicatory function;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list3.Fourth">
                <num>(Fourth)</num>
                <p>- Every officer of a Court of Justice (including a liqui­dator, receiver or commissioner) whose duty it is, as such officer, to investigate or report on any matter of law or fact, or to make authenticate, or keep any document, or to take charge or dispose of any property, or to execute any judicial process, or to administer any oath, or to interpret, or to preserve order in the Court, and every person specially authorized by a Court of Justice to perform any of such duties;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-21.paragraph-0.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Fifth .-Every juryman, assessor, or member of a panchayat assist­ing a Court of Justice or public servant;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list5.Sixth">
                <num>(Sixth)</num>
                <p>- Every arbitrator or other person to whom any cause or matter has been referred for decision or report by any Court of Justice, or by any other competent public authority;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list5.Seventh">
                <num>(Seventh)</num>
                <p>- Every person who holds any office by virtue of which he is empowered to place or keep any person in confinement;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list5.Eighth">
                <num>(Eighth)</num>
                <p>- Every officer of the Government whose duty it is as such officer, to prevent offences, to give information of offenc­es, to bring offenders to justice, or to protect the public health, safety or convenience;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list5.Ninth">
                <num>(Ninth)</num>
                <p>- Every officer whose duty it is, as such officer, to take, receive, keep or extend any property on behalf of the Govern­ment, or to make any survey, assessment or contract on behalf of the Government, or to execute any revenue-process, or to inves­tigate, or to report, on any matter affecting the pecuniary inter­ests of the Government, or to make, authenticate or keep any document relating to the pecuniary interests of the Government, or to prevent the infraction of any law for the protection of the pecuniary interests of the Government.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list5.Tenth">
                <num>(Tenth)</num>
                <p>-Every officer whose duty it is, as such officer, to take, receive, keep or expand any property, to make any survey or as­sessment or to levy any rate or tax for any secular common pur­pose of any village, town or district or to make, authenticate or keep any document for the ascertaining of the rights of the people of any village, town or district;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-21.paragraph-0.list7">
              <listIntroduction>Eleventh .-Every person who holds any office in virtue of which he is empowered to prepare, publish, maintain or revise an elec­toral roll or to conduct an election or part of an election;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list7.Twelfth">
                <num>(Twelfth)</num>
                <p>-Every person-</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list7.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in the service or pay of the Government or remunerated by fees or commission for the performance of any public duty by the Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list7.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in the service or pay of a local authority, a corporation established by or under a Central, Provincial or State Act or a Government company as defined in section 617 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956).</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition of use of unregistered or uncertificated boiler. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Save as otherwise expressly provided in this Act, no owner of a boiler shall use the boiler or permit it to be used-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>unless it has been registered in accordance with the provi­sions of this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in the case of any boiler which has been transferred from one State to another, until the transfer has been reported in the prescribed manner;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>unless a certificate or provisional order authorising the use of the boiler is for the time being in force under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>at a pressure higher than the maximum pressure recorded in such certificate or provisional order;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>where the Central Government has made rules requiring that boilers shall be in charge of persons holding certificates of proficiency or competency, unless the boiler is in charge of a person holding the certificate required by such rules:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that any boiler registered, or any boiler certified or licensed, under any Act hereby repealed shall be deemed to have been registered or certified, as the case may be, under this Act.</p>
            <p>***</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Registration. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The owner of any boiler which is not regis­tered under the provisions of this Act may apply to the Inspector along with such other documents as may be prescribed by regulations to have the boiler registered. Every such application shall be accompanied by prescribed fee.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On receipt of an application under sub-section (1) the In­spector shall fix a date, within thirty days or such shorter period as may be prescribed from the date of the receipt, for the examination of the boiler and shall give the owner thereof not less than ten days' notice of the date so fixed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On the said date the Inspector shall inspect the boiler with a view to satisfying himself that the boiler has not suffered any damage during its transit from the place or manufacture to the site of erection and forward a report of the inspection along with the documents to the Chief Inspector within seven days.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Chief Inspector, on receipt of the report, may-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>register the boiler and assign a register number thereto either forthwith or after satisfying himself that any structural alteration, addition or renewal which he may deem necessary has been made in or to the boiler or any steam-pipe attached thereto, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.4.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>refuse to register the boiler:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that where the Chief Inspector refuses to register a boiler, he shall forthwith communicate his refusal to the owner of the boiler together with the reasons therefor.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chief Inspector shall, on registering the boiler, order the issue to the owner of a certificate in the prescribed form authorising the use of the boiler for a period not exceeding twelve months at a pressure not exceeding such maximum pressure as he thinks fit and as is in accordance with the regulations made under this Act:</p>
            <p>Provided that a certificate issued under this sub-section in respect of an economiser or of an unfired boiler which forms an integral part of a processing plant in which steam is generated solely by the use of oil, asphalt or bitumen as a heating medium may authorise its use for a period not exceeding twenty-four months.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Inspector shall forthwith convey to the owner of the boiler the orders of the Chief Inspector and shall in accordance therewith issue to the owner any certificate of which the issue has been ordered, and, where the boiler has been registered, the owner shall within the prescribed period cause the register number to be permanently marked thereon in the prescribed manner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Renewal of certificate. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A certificate authorising the use of a boiler shall cease to be in force-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>on the expiry of the period for which it was granted; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>when any accident occurs to the boiler; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>when the boiler is moved, the boiler not being a vertical boiler the heating surface of which is less than  [20 square metres], or a portable or vehicular boiler; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>save as provided in section 12, when any structural alteration, addition or renewal is made in or to the boiler;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>if the Chief Inspector in any particular case so directs, when any structural alteration, addition or renewal is made in or to any steam-pipe attached to the boiler; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>on the communication to the owner of the boiler of an order of the Chief Inspector or Inspector prohibiting its use on the ground that it or any boiler component attached thereto is in a dan­gerous condition.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an order is made under clause (f) of sub-section (1), the grounds on which the order is made shall be communicated to the owner with the order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When a certificate ceases to be in force, the owner of the boiler may apply to the Competent Person for renewal thereof for such period as may be prescribed by regulations.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On receipt of an application under sub-section (3), the Competent Person shall, within fifteen days from the date of such receipt, inspect the boiler in such manner as may be prescribed by regulations.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.5.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If the Competent Person is-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.5.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>satisfied that the boiler and the boiler components attached thereto are in good condition he shall issue a certificate for such period as may be prescribed by regulations.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.5.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>of the opinion that the boiler or boiler component, or both does not conform to the standards prescribed by regulations, it may, for reasons to be recorded in writing, refuse to issue such certificate:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that no certificate shall be refused unless the Inspecting Authority had directed the owner of the boiler or the boiler component, or both in writing to carry out such modifications or rectifications as it deems necessary and the Competent Person is of the opinion that inspite of such direction the owner of the boiler or boiler component, or both did not carry out the direction:</p>
            <p>Provided further that the Competent Person shall, within forty-eight hours of making the examination, inform the owner of the boiler or boiler component any defect in his opinion and the reasons therefor and shall forthwith report the case to the Chief Inspector.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Competent Person may for the purpose of inspection under this section charge such fee as may be prescribed by regulations.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in this section shall be deemed to prevent an owner of a boiler from applying for a renewed certificate therefor at any time during the currency of a certificate.</p>
            <p>"(d) when any structural alteration, addition or renewal is made in or to the boiler; or".</p>
            <p>"(3) When a certificate ceases to be in force, the owner of the boiler may apply to the Inspector for a renewal thereof for such period not exceeding twelve months as he may specify in the application:</p>
            <p>Provided that where the certificate relates to an economiser or of an unfired boiler which forms an integral part of a proces­sing plant in which steam is generated solely by the use of oil, asphalt or bitumen as a heating medium, the application for its renewal may be for a period not exceeding twenty-four months.".</p>
            <p>"(4) An application under sub-section (3) shall be accompanied by the prescribed fee and, on receipt thereof, the Inspector shall fix a date, within thirty days or such shorter period as may be prescribed from the date of the receipt, for the examination of the boiler and shall give the owner thereof not less than ten days' notice of the date so fixed:</p>
            <p>Provided that, where the certificate has ceased to be in force owing to the making of any structural alteration, addition or renewal, the Chief Inspector may dispense with the payment of any fee:</p>
            <p>Provided further that in the case of an economiser or of an unfired boiler which forms an integral part of a processing plant in which steam is generated solely by the use of oil, asphalt or bitumen as a heating medium, the date fixed for its examination shall be within sixty days from the date of receipt of the appli­cation and the owner shall be given not less than thirty days' notice of the date so fixed.".</p>
            <p>"(5) On the said date the Inspector shall examine the boiler in the prescribed manner, and if he is satisfied that the boiler and the steam-pipe or steam-pipes attached thereto are in good condi­tion shall issue a renewed certificate authorising the use of the boiler for such period not exceeding twelve months and at a pressure not exceeding such maximum pressure as he thinks fit and as is in accordance with the regulations made under this Act:</p>
            <p>Provided that renewed certificate issued under this sub-section in respect of an economiser or of an unfired boiler which forms an integral part of a processing plant in which steam is generat­ed solely by the use of oil, asphalt or bitumen as heating medi­um may authorise its use for a period not exceeding twenty-four months:</p>
            <blockList id="section-8.7.list10">
              <listIntroduction>Provided further that if the Inspector-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.7.list10.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-8.7.list10.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>proposes to issue any certificate-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-8.7.list10.a.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>having validity for a less period than the period entered in the application, or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-8.7.list10.a.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>increasing or reducing the maximum pressure at which the boiler may be used, or</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.7.list10.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>proposes to order any structural alteration, addition or renewal to be made in or to the boiler or any steam-pipe attached thereto, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.7.list10.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>is of opinion that the boiler is not fit for use, the Inspec­tor shall, within forty-eight hours of making the examination, inform the owner of the boiler in writing of his opinion and the reasons therefor, and shall forthwith report the case for orders to the Chief Inspector.".</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>"(6) The Chief Inspector, on receipt of a report under sub-section (5), may, subject to the provisions of this Act and of the regu­lations made hereunder, order the renewal of the certificate in such terms and on such conditions, if any, as he thinks fit, or may refuse to renew it:</p>
            <p>Provided that where the Chief Inspector refuses to renew a cer­tificate, he shall forthwith communicate his refusal to the owner of the boiler, together with the reasons therefor."</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Provisional orders. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where the Inspector reports the case of any boiler to the Chief Inspector under sub-section (3) of sec­tion 7 ***, he may, if the boiler is not a boiler the use of which has been prohibited under clause (f) of sub-section</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>of section 8, grant to the owner thereof a provisional order in writing permitting the boiler to be used at a pressure not exceeding such maximum pressure as he thinks fit and as is in accordance with the regulations made under this Act pending the receipt of the orders of the Chief Inspector. Such provisional order shall cease to be in force-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>on the expiry of six months from the date on which it is granted, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>on receipt of the orders of the Chief Inspector, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>in any of the cases referred to in clauses (b), (c), (d), (e) and (f) of sub-section (1) of section 8,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>and on so ceasing to be in force shall be surrendered to the Inspector.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Use of boiler pending grant of certificate. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwith­standing anything hereinbefore contained, when the period of a certificate relating to a boiler has expired, the owner shall, provided that he has applied before the expiry of that period for a renewal of the certificate, be entitled to use the boiler at the maximum pressure entered in the former certificate pending the issue of orders on the application.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in sub-section (1) shall be deemed to authorise the use of a boiler in any of the cases referred to in clauses (b), (c), (d), (e) and (f) of sub-section (1) of section 8 occurring after the expiry of the period of the certificate.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Revocation of certificate or provisional order.-The Chief Inspector may at any time withdraw or revoke any certificate or provisional order on the report of an Inspector or otherwise-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>if there is reason to believe that the certificate or provi­sional order has been fraudulently obtained or has been granted erroneously or without sufficient examination; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>if the boiler in respect of which it has been granted has sustained injury or has ceased to be in good condition; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>where the State Government has made rules requiring that boilers shall be in charge of persons holding certificates of proficiency or competency, if the boiler is in charge of a person not holding the certificate required by such rules; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>where no such rules have been made, if the boiler is in charge of a person who is not, having regard to the condition of the boiler in the opinion of the Chief Inspector competent to have charge thereof:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that where the Chief Inspector withdraws or revokes a certificate or provisional order on the ground specified in clause (d), he shall communicate to the owner of the boiler his reasons in writing for the withdrawal or revocation and the order shall not take effect until the expiry of thirty days from the receipt of such communication.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Alterations and renewals to boilers. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No structural alteration, addition or renewal shall be made in or to any boiler registered under this Act unless such alteration, addition or renewal has been sanctioned in writing by the Chief Inspector:</p>
            <p>Provided that no such sanction is required where the structural alteration, addition or renewal is made under the supervision of a Competent Person.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Alteration or renewal of boiler component. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Before the owner of any boiler registered under this Act makes any structural alteration, addition or renewal in or to any boiler component attached to the boiler, he shall transmit to the Chief Inspector a report in writing of his intention and send therewith such particu­lars of proposed alteration, addition or renewal as may be prescribed by regulations.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>any structural alteration, addition or renewal referred to in sub-section (1) shall be made by a person possessing a Boiler Repairer certificate under the supervision of the Competent Person.</p>
            <p>“13. Alterations and renewals to steam-pipes.—</p>
            <p>Before the owner of any boiler registered under this Act makes any structural alteration, addition or renewal in or to any steam-pipe attached to the boiler, he shall transmit to the Chief Inspector a report in writing of his intention and shall send therewith such particulars of the purposed alteration, addition or renewal as may be prescribed.”.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Duty of owner at examination. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>On any date fixed under this Act for the examination of a boiler, the owner thereof shall be bound-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to afford to the Competent Person all reasonable facilities for the examination and all such information as may reasonably be re­quired of him;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to have the boiler properly prepared and ready for examina­tion in the manner prescribed by regulations; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>in the case of an application for the registration of a boiler, to provide such drawings, specifications, certificates and other particulars as may be prescribed by regulations.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the owner fails, without reasonable cause to comply with the provisions of sub-section (1), the Competent Person shall refuse to make the examination and shall report the case to the Chief Inspector who shall, unless sufficient cause to the contrary is shown, require the owner to file a fresh application under sec­tion 7 or section 8, as the case may be, and may forbid him to use the boiler notwithstanding anything contained in section 10.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Production of certificates, etc.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The owner of any boiler who holds a certificate or provisional order relating thereto shall, at all reasonable times during the period for which the certificate or order is in force be bound to produce the same when called upon to do so by a District Magistrate, Commissioner of Police or Magistrate of the first class having jurisdiction in the area in which the boiler is for the time being or by the Chief Inspector or by an Inspector or by any Inspector appointed under the Factories Act, 1948 (63 of 1948), or by any person specially authorised in writing by a District Magistrate or Commissioner of Police.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Transfer of certificates, etc.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any person becomes the owner of a boiler during the period for which a certificate or provisional order relating thereto is in force, the preceding owner shall be bound to make over to him the certificate or provisional order.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Powers of entry.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>An Inspector may, for the purpose of inspecting or examining a boiler or any steam-pipe attached thereto or of seeing that any provision of this Act or of any regulation or rule made hereunder has been or is being observed, at all reasonable times enter any place or building within the limits of the area for which he has been appointed in which he has reason to believe that a boiler is in use.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Report of accidents. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any accident occurs to a boiler or boiler component, the owner or person in charge thereof shall within twenty-four hours of the accident, report the same in writing to the Inspector. Every such report shall contain a true description of the nature of the accident and of the injury, if any, caused thereby to the boiler or to the boiler component or to any person, and shall be in sufficient detail to enable the Inspector to judge of the gravity of the accident.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every person shall be bound to answer truly to the best of his knowledge and ability every question put to him in writing by the Inspector as to the cause, nature or extent of the accident.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Without prejudice to the provisions of sub-section (1), where any death has resulted due to any accident, an inquiry may be conducted by such person and in such manner as may be prescribed by the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Appeals to Chief Inspector. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-19.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-19.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any person considering himself aggrieved by,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-19.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>an order made or purporting to be made by an Inspector in the exercise of any power conferred by or under this Act, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-19.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>a refusal of an Inspector to make any order or to issue any certificate which he is required or enabled by or under this Act to make or issue,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>may, within thirty days from the date on which such order or refusal is communicated to him, appeal against the order or refusal to the Chief Inspector.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every appeal under sub-section (1) shall be made in such manner as may be prescribed by the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The procedure for disposing of an appeal shall be such as may be prescribed by the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Appeals to appellate authority.-Any person considering himself aggrieved by an original or appellate order of the Chief Inspector-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-20.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>refusing to register a boiler or to grant or renew a certifi­cate in respect of a boiler; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>refusing to grant a certificate having validity for the full period applied for; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>refusing to grant a certificate authorising the use of a boiler at the maximum pressure desired; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>withdrawing or revoking a certificate or provisional order; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list0.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>reducing the amount of pressure specified in any certificate or the period for which such certificate has been granted; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list0.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>ordering any structural alteration, addition or renewal to be made in or to a boiler or steam-pipe, or refusing sanction to the making of any structural alteration, addition or renewal in or to a boiler,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>may, within thirty days of the communication to him of such order, lodge with the Chief Inspector an appeal to an appellate authority to be constituted by the State Government under this Act</p>
            <p>.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20A">
        <num>20A.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to revise order of appellate authority. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-20A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person considering himself aggrieved by an order of the appellate authority refusing under section 20 to interfere with an order not to register a boiler or not to grant or renew a certificate in respect thereof on the ground that the boiler does not conform to the regulations made under this Act may, within two months of the communication to him of such order, make an application to the Central Government for a revision of that order on the ground that such boilers are in use in other countries.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon the receipt of such an application, the Central Govern­ment may, after calling for relevant records and other informa­tion from the appellate authority and considering the observa­tions, if any, of that authority on the application and after obtaining such technical advice as the Central Government may consider necessary, pass such order in relation to the applica­tion, as the Central Government thinks fit; and, where the revi­sion is allowed, the order shall specify the terms and conditions on which any variations from the regulations made under this Act are to be dealt with during the examination of the boiler.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Finality of orders.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>An order of the Central Government under sections 20 and 20A, or of the Chief Inspector, or of a Deputy Chief Inspector, or of an Inspector, shall be final and shall not be called in question in any court.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Minor penalties. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-22.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any owner of a boiler who refuses or with­out reasonable excuse neglects-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-22.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>to surrender a provisional order as required by section 9, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-22.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>to produce a certificate or provisional order when duly called upon to do so under section 15, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-22.paragraph-0.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>to make over to the new owner of a boiler a certificate or provisional order as required by section 16,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall be punished with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees.</p>
            <p>State Amendment</p>
            <p>Gujarat.  -</p>
            <p>In section 22, for the words "one hundred rupees", substitute the words "two hundred rupees".</p>
            <p>Vide Gujarat Act 19 of 1990, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 8-11-1990 ).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Penalties for illegal use of boiler. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any owner of a boiler who, in any case in which a certificate or provisional order is required for the use of the boiler under this Act, uses the boiler either without any such certificate or order being in force or at a higher pressure than that allowed thereby, shall be punishable with fine which may extend to one lakh rupees, and, in the case of a continuing offence, with an additional fine which may extend to one thousand rupees for each day after the first day in regard to which he is convicted of having persisted in the offence.</p>
            <p>State Amendment</p>
            <p>Gujarat.  -</p>
            <p>In section 23,-</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-23.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>for the words "five hundred rupees", substitute the words "one thousand rupees".</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-23.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>for the words "one hundred rupees", substitute the words "five hundred rupees".</p>
            <p>Vide Gujarat Act 19 of 1990, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 8-11-1990 ).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Other penalties. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-24.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any person who-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>uses or permits to be used a boiler of which he is the owner and which has been transferred from one State to another without such transfer having been reported as required by section 6, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>being the owner of a boiler fails to cause the register number allotted to the boiler under this Act to be marked on the boiler as required by sub-section (6) of section 7, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>makes any structural alteration, addition or renewal in or to a boiler without first obtaining the sanction of the Chief In­spector when so required by section 12, or to a steam-pipe with­out first informing the Chief Inspector, when so required by section 13, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>fails to report an accident to a boiler or steam-pipe when so required by section 18, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>tempers with a safety valve of a boiler so as to render it inoperative at the maximum pressure at which the use of the boiler is authorised under this Act, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>allows another person to go inside a boiler without effec­tively disconnecting the same in the prescribed manner from any steam or hot water connection with any other boiler or from fuel mains,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall be punishable with imprisonment which may extend to two years or with fine which may extend to one lakh rupees, or with both.</p>
            <p>State Amendment</p>
            <p>Gujarat.  -</p>
            <p>In section 24, for the words "five hundred rupees", substitute the words "one thousand rupees".</p>
            <p>Vide Gujarat Act 19 of 1990, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 8-11-1990 ).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for tampering with register mark. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-25.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever re­moves, alters, defaces, renders invisible or otherwise tampers with the register number marked on a boiler in accordance with the provisions of this Act or any Act repealed hereby, shall be punishable with fine which may extend to one lakh rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever fraudulently marks upon a boiler a register number which has not been allotted to it under this Act or any Act repealed hereby, shall be punishable with imprisonment which may extend to two years, or with fine which may extend to one lakh rupees, or with both.</p>
            <p>State Amendment</p>
            <p>Gujarat.  -</p>
            <p>In section 25, in sub-section (1), for the words "five hundred rupees", substitute the words "one thousand rupees".</p>
            <p>Vide Gujarat Act 19 of 1990, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 8-11-1990 ).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Limitation and previous sanction for prosecutions. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No prosecution for an offence made punishable by or under this Act shall be instituted except within twenty-four months from the date of the commission of the offence, and no such prosecution shall be instituted without the previous sanction of the Chief Inspector.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Trial of offences.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No offence made punishable by or under this Act shall be tried by a Court inferior to that of a Presidency Magistrate or a Magistrate of the first class.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27A">
        <num>27A.</num>
        <heading>Central Boilers Board. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-27A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A Board to be called the Central Boilers Board shall be constituted to exercise the powers conferred by section 28.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-27A.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Board shall consist of the following members, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-27A.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the Secretary to the Government of India incharge of the Department of the Central Government having administrative control of the Board who shall be the Chairperson ex officio;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-27A.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>a senior technical officer conversant with the inspection and examination of boilers, to be nominated by the Government of each State (other than a Union territory);</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-27A.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <blockList id="section-27A.2.list1.c.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>equal number of other persons as in sub-section (b) above to represent-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-27A.2.list1.c.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>Central Government,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-27A.2.list1.c.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>the Bureau of Indian Standards,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-27A.2.list1.c.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>boiler and boiler component manufactures,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-27A.2.list1.c.list0.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>National laboratories,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-27A.2.list1.c.list0.v">
                    <num>(v)</num>
                    <p>engineering consultancy agencies,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-27A.2.list1.c.list0.vi">
                    <num>(vi)</num>
                    <p>users of boilers, and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-27A.2.list1.c.list0.vii">
                    <num>(vii)</num>
                    <p>such other interests which in the opinion of the Central Government ought to be represented on the Board,</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-27A.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>to be nominated by the Central Government;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-27A.2.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>Technical Adviser, Member-Secretary ex officio.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The term of office of the members nominated under clauses (b) and (c) of sub-section (2) shall be such as may be prescribed by the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27A.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall have full power to regulate by means of bye-laws or otherwise its own procedure and the conduct of all business to be transacted by it, the constitution of committees and sub-committees of members and the delegation to them of any of the powers and duties of the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27A.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-27A.5.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The powers of the Board may be exercised notwithstanding any vacancy in the Board.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-27A.5.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>such number of members, including the Chairman, not exceeding fifteen, as the Central Government may nominate in the prescribed manner to represent that Government, the Union territories, the railways, the coal industry, the Indian Standards Institution, the boiler manufacturing industry, the users of boilers and, any other interests which, in the opinion of the Central Government, ought to be represented on the Board;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-27A.5.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>a senior technical officer conversant with the inspection and examination of boilers, to be nominated by the Government of each State (other than a Union territory).”.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>“(3) Any vacancy occurring in the Board shall be filled as soon as may be by a nomination made by the authority by whom the member vacating office was nominated.”.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28">
        <num>28.</num>
        <heading>Power to make regulations. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-28.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-28.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Board may, by notification in the Gazette of India , make regulations con­sistent with this Act for all or any of the following purposes, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-28.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-28.1.list1.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>for laying down the standard conditions in respect of materi­al, design, construction, erection, operation and maintenance which shall be required for the pur­poses of enabling the registration and certification of boilers, boiler components, boiler mountings and fittings under this Act;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-28.1.list1.a.list0.aa">
                    <num>(aa)</num>
                    <p>for prescribing the circumstances in which, the extent to which, and the conditions subject to which variation from the standard conditions laid down under clause (a) may be permitted;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>for prescribing the method of determining the maximum pres­sure at which a boiler may be used;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>for regulating the registration of boilers, prescribing the fees payable therefor and for the inspection and examination of boilers or parts thereof, the drawings, specifications certifi­cates and particulars to be produced by the owner, the method of preparing a boiler for examination, the form of the Inspector's report thereon, the method of marking the register number, and the period within which such number is to be marked on the boil­er;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>for regulating the inspection and examination of boilers and boiler components, boiler mountings and fittings, and prescribing forms of certificates therefor;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <blockList id="section-28.1.list1.e.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>for ensuring the safety of persons working inside a boiler; and</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-28.1.list1.e.list1.ea">
                    <num>(ea)</num>
                    <p>for prescribing the qualifications and experience subject to which the Inspecting Authorities, Competent Authorities and Competent Persons shall be recognised under this Act;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-28.1.list1.e.list1.eb">
                    <num>(eb)</num>
                    <p>the conditions subject to which and the manner in which manufacturer of boiler components or material may be recognised;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-28.1.list1.e.list1.ec">
                    <num>(ec)</num>
                    <p>facilities for design and construction which are required to be provided in the premises in which the manufacturing of any boiler or boiler component is carried out;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-28.1.list1.e.list1.ed">
                    <num>(ed)</num>
                    <p>fee for the purposes of inspection or grant of recognition or any certificate under this Act;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-28.1.list1.e.list1.ef">
                    <num>(ef)</num>
                    <p>procedure for examination and grant of Welders certificate;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-28.1.list1.e.list1.eg">
                    <num>(eg)</num>
                    <p>powers and functions which the Board may delegate to the Technical Adviser;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-28.1.list1.e.list1.eh">
                    <num>(eh)</num>
                    <p>documents to be enclosed alongwith the application for registration of boilers or renewal of a certificate authorising the use of boilers;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-28.1.list1.e.list1.ei">
                    <num>(ei)</num>
                    <p>the manner of inspection of boilers;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-28.1.list1.e.list1.ej">
                    <num>(ej)</num>
                    <p>the period for which a certificate authorising the use of a boiler may be renewed;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-28.1.list1.e.list1.ek">
                    <num>(ek)</num>
                    <p>the conditions subject to which and the form in which Competent Person shall renew a certificate authorising the use of boilers;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-28.1.list1.e.list1.el">
                    <num>(el)</num>
                    <p>the manner and the form in which a Repairer's certificate shall be issued;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-28.1.list1.e.list1.em">
                    <num>(em)</num>
                    <p>the manner in which the boiler shall be prepared for examination;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-28.1.list1.e.list1.en">
                    <num>(en)</num>
                    <p>drawings specification, documents and other particulars which owner of a boiler is required to make available to the Competent Person;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-28.1.list1.e.list1.eo">
                    <num>(eo)</num>
                    <p>the manner in which a person may be authorised to conduct energy audit and the manner in which such audit shall be conduct;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-28.1.list1.e.list1.ep">
                    <num>(ep)</num>
                    <p>the manner in which disputes between the States with respect to registration of boilers shall be resolved;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28.1.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>for providing for any other matter which is not, in the opinion of the Board, a matter of merely local or State impor­tance.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-28.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid both Houses agree in making any modification in the regulation or both Houses agree that the regulation should not be made, the regulation shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modifi­cation or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that regulation.</p>
            <p>"(a) for laying down the standard conditions in respect of materi­al design and construction which shall be required for the pur­pose of enabling registration and certification of a boiler under this Act;".</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28A">
        <num>28A.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to make rules. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-28A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-28A.1A">
          <num>(1A)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-28A.1A.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-28A.1A.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>In procedure to be followed in making applications under section 20A and the fees payable in respect of such application;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28A.1A.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the qualifications and experience of persons to be appointed as Chief Inspectors, Deputy Chief Inspectors and Inspectors;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28A.1A.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the manner in which appeals may be preferred to the Board, the fees payable in respect of appeals and the procedure to be followed of disposing such appeals;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28A.1A.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the term of office of the members and the manner in which they shall be nominated under clauses (b) and (c) of sub-section (2) of section 27A;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28A.1A.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the qualifications and experience of the Technical Adviser;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28A.1A.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>for requiring boilers to be under the charge of persons holding certificate of proficiency or competency and for prescribing the conditions on which such certificate may be granted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28A.1A.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the manner in which and the person who shall conduct inquiry into the accident.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-28A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under sub-section (1) shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or [ in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.]</p>
            <blockList id="section-28A.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>"(1) The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to provide for-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-28A.2.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the procedure to be followed in making applications under section 20A and the fees payable in respect of such applications; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28A.2.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any matter relating to the nomination of members under clause (a) of sub-section (2) of section 27A.".</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29">
        <num>29.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-29.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-29.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules consistent with this Act and the regulations made thereunder for all or any of the following purposes, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-29.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the powers and duties of the Chief Inspector, Deputy Chief Inspectors and Inspectors;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-29.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>for regulating the transfer of boilers;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-29.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>for providing for the registration and certification of boilers in accordance with the regulations made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-29.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>***</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-29.1.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>for prescribing the times within which Inspectors shall be required to examine boiler under section 7 or section 8;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-29.1.list3.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>fee payable for registration of boilers;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-29.1.list3.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>for regulating inquiries into accidents;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-29.1.list3.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the manner in which appeals shall be preferred to the Chief Inspector and the procedure to be followed for hearing such appeals;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-29.1.list3.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>for determining the mode of disposal of fees, costs and penalties levied under this Act; and</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>***</p>
            <p>***</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made by the State Government under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before the State Legislature.</p>
            <p>“(a) for prescribing the qualifications and duties of the Chief Inspector, of Deputy Chief Inspectors and of Inspectors for prescribing or constituting authorities to which they shall respectively be subordinate, and the limits of the administrative control to be exercised by such authorities;”.</p>
            <p>“(d) for requiring boilers to be in charge of persons holding certificates of proficiency or competency, and for prescribing the conditions on which such certificates may be granted;”.</p>
            <p>“(f) for prescribing the fees payable for the issue of renewed certificates, for the inspection and examination of boilers or parts thereof or drawings for steam-pipes, for the testing of welders or for any other matter which, in the opinion of the State Government, would involve time and labour and prescribing the method of determining the amount of such fees in each case;”.</p>
            <p>“(h) for constituting the appellate authority referred to in section 20, and for determining its powers and procedure;”.</p>
            <p>“(j) generally to provide for any matter which is, in the opinion of the State Government, a matter of merely local importance in the State;”.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-30">
        <num>30.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for breach of rules. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-30.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any regulation or rule made under section 28 or section 29 may direct that a person contra­vening such regulation or rule shall be punishable, in the case of a first offence, with fine which may extend to [one thousand rupees, and in the case of any subsequent offence, with fine which may extend to one lakh rupees].</p>
            <p>State Amendment</p>
            <p>Gujarat.  -</p>
            <p>In section 30,-</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-30.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>for the words "one hundred rupees", substitute the words "two hundred rupees".</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-30.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>for the words "one thousand rupees", substitute the words "two thousand rupees".</p>
            <p>Vide Gujarat Act 19 of 1990, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 8-11-1990 ).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-31">
        <num>31.</num>
        <heading>Publication of regulations and rules. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-31.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The power to make regulations and rules conferred by sections 28 and 29 shall be subject to the condition of the regulation and rules being made after previous publication.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-31.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Regulations and rules so made shall be published in the Gazette of India and the local Official Gazette, respectively, and, on such publication shall have effect as if enacted in this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-31A">
        <num>31A.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to give directions. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-31A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may give such directions as it may deem neces­sary to a State Government regarding the carrying into execution of the provisions to this Act, and the State Government shall comply with such directions.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-32">
        <num>32.</num>
        <heading>Recovery of fees etc.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-32.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>All fees, costs and penalties levied under this Act shall be recoverable as arrears of land-revenue.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-33">
        <num>33.</num>
        <heading>Applicability to the Government. -</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-33.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Save as otherwise expressly provided, this Act shall apply to boilers and boiler components belong­ing to Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-34">
        <num>34.</num>
        <heading>Exemptions. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-34.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, exempt from the operation of this Act, subject to such conditions and restrictions as it thinks fit, any boilers or classes or types of boilers used exclusively for the heating of buildings or the supply of hot water.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-34.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In case of any emergency, the State Government may, by general or special order in writing exempt any boilers or steam-pipes or any class of boilers or steam-pipes or any boiler or steam-pipe from the operation of all or any of the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-34.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the State Government is satisfied that having regard to the material design or construction of boilers and to the need for the rapid industrialisation of the country, it is necessary so to do, it may, by notification in the Official Gazette and sub­ject to such conditions as may be prescribed by regulations, exempt any boiler or boiler components in the whole or any part of the State from the operation of all or any of the provisions of this Act.</p>
            <p>“(3) If the State Government is satisfied that, having regard to the material design or construction of boilers and to the need for the rapid industrialisation of the country, it is necessary so to do, it may, by notification in the Official Gazette and subject to such conditions and restrictions as may be specified in the notification, exclude any specified class of boilers or steam-pipes in the whole or any part of the State, from the operation of all or any of the provisions of this Act.”.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-35">
        <num>35.</num>
        <heading>Repeal of enactments.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-35.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Rep. by the Repealing Act, 1927 (12 of 1927), sec. 2 and Sch.</p>
            <p>THE BOILERS ACT, 1923</p>
            <p>THE SCHEDULE.—</p>
            <p>Enactments repealed.—</p>
            <p>Rep. by the Repealing Act, 1927 (12 of 1927), sec. 2 and Sch..</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
