<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1962/1/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1962/1"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Goa, Daman And Diu (Administration) Act, 1962"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1962/1/eng@1962-03-27/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1962/1/eng@1962-03-27"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1962-03-27" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1962/1/eng@1962-03-27/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1962/1/eng@1962-03-27"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Goa, Daman And Diu (Administration) Act, 1962</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 1 OF 1962</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 27th March, 1962.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirteenth Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the administration of the Union territory of</p>
        <p>Goa, Daman and Diu and for matters connected therewith.</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:--</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Goa, Daman and Diu (Administration) Act, 1962.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 5th day of</p>
            <p>March, 1962.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" Administrator" means the Administrator of Goa, Daman  and Diu appointed by the President under article 239 of  the Constitution;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" appointed day" means the twentieth day of December,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1961">
        <num>1961.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1961.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-1961.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1961.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" Goa, Daman and Diu" means the Union territory of Goa,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Daman and Diu.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Representation in the House of the People.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be  allotted two seats to the Union territory of Goa, Daman and Diu in the</p>
            <p>House of the People.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In the Representation of the People Act, 1950 (43 of 1950),-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in section 4, in sub- section (1), after the words" to</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Dadra and Nagar Haveli", the words" to Goa, Daman and</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Diu" shall be inserted;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-3.2.list4.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>in the First Schedule,--</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-3.2.list4.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>after entry 22, the following entry shall be  inserted, namely:--</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list6">
              <listIntroduction>" 23. Goa, Daman and Diu................. 2";</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list6.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>entries 23 and 24 shall be re- numbered as  entries 24 and 25 respectively.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the Representation of the People Act, 1951 (43 of 1951),</p>
            <p>in section 4, after the words" to Dadra and Nagar Haveli", the words</p>
            <p>" to Goa, Daman and Diu" shall be inserted.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Officers and function aries in relation to Goa, Daman and Diu.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Without prejudice to the powers of the Central Government to appoint  from time to time such officers and authorities as may be necessary  for the administration of Goa, Daman and Diu, all judges, magistrates  and other officers and authorities who, immediately before the  commencement of this Act, were exercising lawful functions in  connection with the administration of Goa, Daman and Diu or any part  thereof, shall, unless otherwise directed at any time by the Central</p>
            <p>Government in relation to any such judge, magistrate or other officer  or authority, or until other provision is made by law, continue to  exercise in connection with such administration their respective  functions in the same manner and to the same extent as before such  commencement with such altered designation, if any, as that Government  may determine.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Continuance of existing laws and their adaptation.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All  laws in force immediately before the appointed day in Goa, Daman and</p>
            <p>Diu or any part thereof shall continue to be in force therein until  amended or repealed by a competent Legislature or other competent  authority.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of facilitating the application of any such  law in relation to the administration of Goa, Daman and Diu as a Union  territory and for the purpose of bringing the provisions of any such  law into accord with the provisions of the Constitution, the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, within two years from the appointed day, by order,</p>
            <p>make such adaptations and modifications, whether by way of repeal or  amendment, as may be necessary or expedient and thereupon, every such  law shall have effect subject to the adaptations and modifications so  made.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Power to extend enactments to Goa, Daman and Diu. The Central</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, extend with  such restrictions or modifications as it thinks fit, to Goa, Daman and</p>
            <p>Diu any enactment which is in force in a State at the date of the  notification.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Extension of the jurisdiction of Bombay High Court to Goa,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Daman and Diu. Rep. by the Goa, Daman and Diu Judicial Commissioner' s</p>
            <p>Court (Declaration as High Court) Act, 1964 (16 of 1964), s. 8 (w. e. f.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>- 12- 1963).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Power to construe laws. For the purpose of facilitating the  application of any law in relation to Goa, Daman and Diu, any court or  other authority may construe any such law in such manner not affecting  the substance, as may be necessary or proper to adapt it to the matter  before the court or other authority.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Validation of certain action and indemnity of officers for  certain acts.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All things done and all action taken (including any   acts of executive authority, proceedings, decrees and sentences) in or  with respect to Goa, Daman and Diu on or after the appointed day and  before the commencement of this Act, by the Administrator or any other  officer, whether civil or military, or by any other person acting  under the orders of the Administrator or such officer, which have been  done or taken in good faith and in a reasonable belief that they were  necessary for the peace and good government of Goa, Daman and Diu  shall be as valid and operative as if they had been done or taken in  accordance with law.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No suit or other legal proceeding whatsoever, whether civil  or criminal, shall lie in any court of law against the Administrator  or any other officer of Government, whether civil or military, or  against any other person acting under the orders of the Administrator  or such other officer for, or on account of, or in respect of,</p>
            <p>anything done or any action taken in Goa, Daman and Diu or any part  thereof on or after the appointed day and before the commencement of  this Act which has been done or taken in good faith and in a  reasonable belief that it was necessary for the peace and good  government of Goa, Daman and Diu:</p>
            <p>Provided that if any such suit or other legal proceeding has been  instituted before the commencement of this Act, it shall, on such  commencement, abate.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Power to remove difficulties.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any difficulty arises in  giving effect to the provisions of this Act or in connection with the  administration of Goa, Daman and Diu, the Central Government may, by  order, make such further provision as appears to it to be necessary or  expedient for removing the difficulty.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any order under sub- section (1) may be made so as to be  retrospective to any date not earlier than the appointed day.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Repeal and saving.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Goa, Daman and Diu</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.Administration">
                <num>(Administration)</num>
                <p>Ordinance, 1962 (2 of 1962), is hereby repealed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action  taken in exercise of any of the powers conferred by or under the said</p>
            <p>Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or taken in exercise of  the powers conferred by or under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
