<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1925/4/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1925/4"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Indian Soldiers (Litigation) Act, 1925"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1925/4/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1925/4/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1925/4/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1925/4/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Indian Soldiers (Litigation) Act, 1925</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called The Indian Soldiers (Litigation) Act, 1925.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India ***.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on the first day of April, 1925.</p>
            <p>The Act has been extended to the Union territory of Pondicherry subject to the modifications that (i) a reference to a law not in force or to a functionary not in existence in Pondicherry shall be construed as a reference to corresponding law in force or to corresponding functionary in existence, in Pondicherry and (ii) sub-section (3) shall be omitted—See S.O. 4, Gazette of India, 1963, Pt. II, section 3 (ii), p. 3.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“Court” means a Court other than a Criminal Court and includes any such tribunal or other authority as may be specified by the Central Government by notification in the Official Gazette being a tribunal or authority which is empowered by law to receive evidence on any matter pending before it and on the basis of such evidence to determine, after hearing the parties before it, the rights and obligations of the parties in relation to such matter;(a) “Court” means a Court other than a Criminal Court and includes any such tribunal or other authority as may be specified by the Central Government by notification in the Official Gazette being a tribunal or authority which is empowered by law to receive evidence on any matter pending before it and on the basis of such evidence to determine, after hearing the parties before it, the rights and obligations of the parties in relation to such matter;"</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“Indian soldier” means any person subject to the Army Act, 1950, or the Air Force Act 1950, or the Navy Act, 1957;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3">
              <listIntroduction>the Army Act, 1950, or the Air Force Act 1950, or the Navy Act, 1957;"</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>“proceeding” includes any suit, appeal or application.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>any reference to a decree or order of a Court shall be deemed to include a reference to a judgement, determination or award of a Court.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Circumstances in which an Indian soldier shall be deemed to be serving under special conditions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>For the purposes of this Act, an Indian soldier shall be deemed to be or, as the case may be, to have been serving—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>under special conditions (when he is or has been serving under war conditions), or overseas, or at any place beyond India, or any such place within India as may be specified by the Central Government by notification in the Official Gazette;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>under war conditions—when he is or has been, at any time during the continuance of any hostilities declared by the Central Government by notification in the Official Gazette to constitute a state of war for the purpose of this Act or at any time during a period of six months thereafter,—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>serving out of India,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>under orders to proceed on field service,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>serving with any unit which is for the time being mobilised, or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>serving under conditions which, in the opinion of the prescribed authority, preclude him from obtaining leave of absence to enable him to attend a Court as a party to any proceeding or when he is or has been at any other time serving under conditions service under which has been declared by the Central Government by notification in the Official Gazette to be service under war conditions; and</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>overseas—when he is or has been serving in any place outside India (other than Ceylon) the journey between which and India is ordinarily undertaken wholly or in part by sea.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <p>For the purposes of this section and with effect from the 3rd day of September, 1939, a soldier who is or has been a prisoner of war shall be deemed to be or to have been serving under war conditions.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Particulars to be furnished in plaints, applications or appeals to Court.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any person presenting any plaint, application or appeal to any Court has reason to believe that any adverse party is an Indian soldier who is serving under special conditions, he shall state the fact in his plaint, application or appeal.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Power of Collector to intervene in case of unrepresented Indian soldier.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any Collector has reason to believe that any Indian soldier, who ordinarily resides or has property in his district and who is a party to any proceeding pending before any Court, is unable to appear therein, the Collector may certify the facts in the prescribed manner to the Court.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Notice to be given in case of unrepresented Indian soldier.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If a Collector has certified under Section 5, or if the Court has reason to believe, that an Indian soldier, who is a party to any proceeding pending before it, is unable to appear therein, and if the soldier is not represented by any person duly authorised to appear, plead or act on his behalf, the Court shall suspend the proceeding and shall give notice thereof in the prescribed manner to the prescribed authority:—(1) If a Collector has certified under Section 5, or if the Court has reason to believe, that an Indian soldier, who is a party to any proceeding pending before it, is unable to appear therein, and if the soldier is not represented by any person duly authorised to appear, plead or act on his behalf, the Court shall suspend the proceeding and shall give notice thereof in the prescribed manner to the prescribed authority\:"</p>
            <blockList id="section-6.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that the Court may refrain from suspending the proceeding and issuing notice if—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the proceeding is a suit, appeal or application instituted or made by the soldier, alone or conjointly with others with the object of enforcing a right of pre-emption, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.1.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the interests of the soldier in the proceeding are, in the opinion of the Court, either identical with those of any other party to the proceeding and adequately represented by such other party or merely of a formal nature.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If it appear to the Court before which any proceeding is pending that an Indian soldier though not a party to the proceeding is materially concerned in the outcome of the proceeding and that his interests are likely to be prejudiced by his inability to attend, the Court may suspend the proceeding and shall give notice thereof in the prescribed manner to the prescribed authority.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Postponement of proceedings.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If, on receipt of a notice under section 6, the prescribed authority certifies in the prescribed manner to the Court in which the proceedings is pending that the soldier in respect of whom the notice was given is serving under special conditions, and that a postponement of the proceedings in respect of the soldier is necessary, in the interest of justice, the Court shall thereupon postpone the proceeding in respect of the soldier for the prescribed period, or, if no period has been prescribed, for such period as it thinks fit.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Court may proceed when no certificate received.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If, after issue of notice under section 6, the prescribed authority either certifies that the soldier is not serving under special conditions or that such postponement is not necessary, or fails to certify, in the case of a soldier resident in the district in which the Court is situate within two months or, in any other case, within three months, from the date of the issue of the notice that such postponement is necessary, the Court may, if it thinks fit, continue the proceeding.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Postponement of proceedings against Indian soldier on leave.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>When any document purporting to be signed by the Commanding Officer of an Indian soldier who is a party to any proceeding is produced by or on behalf of the soldier before the Court in which the proceeding is pending and is to the effect that the soldier—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>is on leave of absence for a period not exceeding two months, and is on the expiration of his leave to rejoin his unit with a view to proceeding on service under special conditions, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>is on sick leave for a period not exceeding three months, and is on the expiration of his leave to rejoin his unit with a view to proceeding on service under special conditions.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>the proceeding in respect of such soldier may, in any case such as if referred to in the proviso to [sub-section (1) of section 6 and shall, in any other case, be postponed in the manner provided in section 7.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Power to set aside decrees and orders, passed against an Indian soldier serving under war or special conditions.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In any proceeding before a Court in which a decree or order has been passed against any Indian soldier [*** whilst he was serving under any special conditions, the soldier or, if he is dead, his legal representative may apply to the Court which passed the decree or order for an order to set aside the same, and, if the Court after giving an opportunity to the opposite party of being heard, is satisfied that the interests of justice require that the decree or order should be set aside as against the soldier, the Court shall, subject to such conditions, if any, as it thinks fit to impose, make an order accordingly.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The period of limitation for an application under sub-section (1) shall be ninety days from the date of the decree or order, or where the summons or notice was duly served on the soldier in the proceeding in which the decree or order was passed, from the date on which the applicant had knowledge of the decree or order; and the provisions of section 5 of the Indian Limitation Act, 1908 shall apply to such applications.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When the decree or order in respect of which an application under sub-section (1) is made is of such a nature that it cannot be set aside as against the soldier only, it may be set aside as against all or any of the parties against whom it has been made.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a Court sets aside a decree or order under this section, it shall appoint a day for proceeding with the suit, appeal or application, as the case may be.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Modification of law of limitation where Indian soldier or his legal representative is a party.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>In computing the period of limitation prescribed by sub-section (2) of section 10 of this Act, the Indian Limitation Act, 1908, or any other law for the time being in force, for any suit, appeal or application to a Court, any party to which is or has been an Indian soldier, or is the legal representative of an Indian soldier, the period during which the soldier has been serving under any special conditions, and, if the soldier has died while so serving, the period from the date of his death to the date on which official intimation thereof was sent to his next-of-kin by the authorities in India, shall be excluded:11. Modification of law of limitation where Indian soldier or his legal representative is a party.—</p>
            <p>In computing the period of limitation prescribed by sub-section (2) of section 10 of this Act, the Indian Limitation Act, 1908, or any other law for the time being in force, for any suit, appeal or application to a Court, any party to which is or has been an Indian soldier, or is the legal representative of an Indian soldier, the period during which the soldier has been serving under any special conditions, and, if the soldier has died while so serving, the period from the date of his death to the date on which official intimation thereof was sent to his next-of-kin by the authorities in India, shall be excluded\:"</p>
            <p>Provided that this section shall not apply in the case of any suit, appeal or application instituted or made with the object of enforcing a right of pre-emption</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>[except where the said right accrues in such circumstances, and is in respect of agricultural land and village immovable property situated in any such area as the Central Government may, by notification4 in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Power of Court to refer questions to prescribed authorities.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any Court is in doubt whether, for the purposes of section 10 or section 11, an Indian soldier is or was at any particular time serving under special conditions, or has died while so serving, or as to the date of such death or as to the date on which official intimation of such death was sent to his next-of-kin by the authorities in India, the Court may refer the point for the decision of the prescribed authority, and the certificate of that authority shall be conclusive evidence on the point.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Rule-making power.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>[</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government *** may, by notification in the Official Gazette make rules to provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the manner and form in which any notice or certificate under this Act shall be given;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the period for which proceedings or any class of proceedings shall be postponed under section 7;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the persons who shall be the prescribed authorities for the purpose of this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>any other matter which is to be or may be prescribed; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>generally any matters incidental to the purposes of this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Power to apply the provisions of the Act to other person in the service of the Government.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>[As respects the State Public Services, the [State Government, and in other cases, the Central Government] may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that all or any of the provisions of this Act shall apply to any other class of persons in the service of Government specified in such notification in the same manner as they apply to Indian soldiers.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where, under this section, the State Government has directed that all or any of the provisions of this Act shall apply to any class of persons in the service of Government, the powers vested in the Central Government by section 3 and section 13 shall be exercised in respect of that class of persons by the [State Government.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14A">
        <num>14A.</num>
        <heading>Power to apply the provisions of the Act to members of the forces maintained by any Part B State.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Rep. by 3 A.L.O., 1956 (w.r.e.f. 1-11-1956).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Repeal of Acts 9 of 1918 and 12 of 1924.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Rep. by the Repealing Act, 1927 (12 of 1927), sec. 2 and Sch.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
