<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1980/52/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1980/52"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Sree Chitra Tirunal Institute For Medical Sciences And Technology, Trivandrum, Act, 1980"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1980/52/eng@1980-12-03/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1980/52/eng@1980-12-03"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-12-03" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1980/52/eng@1980-12-03/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1980/52/eng@1980-12-03"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Sree Chitra Tirunal Institute For Medical Sciences And Technology, Trivandrum, Act, 1980</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 52 OF 1980</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 3rd December, 1980.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty- first Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to declare the Sree Chitra Tirunal Medical Centre Society for</p>
        <p>Advanced Studies in Specialities, Trivandrum, in the State of Kerala,</p>
        <p>to be an institution of national importance and to provide for its  incorporation and matters connected therewith.</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:-</p>
        <p>Short title and commencement.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Sree Chitra Tirunal Institute for Medical Sciences and Technology,</p>
            <p>Trivandrum, Act, 1980.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date 1 as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
            <p>Declaration of the sree Chitra Tirunal medical Centre Sosity forAdvanced</p>
            <p>Studies in Specialities, Trivendrum, as an institution ofnational importance.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Declaration of the sree Chitra Tirunal medical Centre Socity  for Advanced Studies in Specialities, Trivendrum, as an institution of  national importance. Whereas the objects of the Sree Chitra Tirunal</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Medical Centre Society for Advanced Studies in Specialities,</p>
            <p>Trivandrum, in the State of Kerala, are such as to make the  institution one of national importance, it is hereby declared that the  institution, known as the Sree Chitra Tirunal Medical Centre Society  for Advanced Studies in Specialities, Trivandrum, is an institution of  national importance.</p>
            <p>Definition.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Definition. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" Chairman" means the Chairman of the Governing</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Body;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" Director" means the Director of the Institute;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" Fund" means the Fund of the Institute referred to  in section 16;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>" Governing Body" means the Governing Body of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Institute;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list4.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>" Institute" means the institution known as the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Sree Chitra Tirunal Institute for Medical Sciences and</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list7">
              <listIntroduction>Technology Trivandrum, incorporated under this Act;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list7.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>" member" means a member of the Institute;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list7.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>" President" means the President of the Institute;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list7.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>" regulation" means, a regulation made by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list9">
              <listIntroduction>Institute;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list9.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>" rule" means a rule made by the Central</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Government.</p>
            <p>Incorporation of institute.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Incorporation of institute. The Sree Chitra Tirunal Medical</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Centre Society for Advanced Studies in Specialities, Trivandrum, is  hereby constituted a body corporate by the name of Sree Chitra Tirunal</p>
            <p>Institute for Medical Sciences and Technology, Trivandrum, and as such  body corporate, it shall have perpetual succession and a common seal  with power, subject to the provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold  and dispose of property and to contract, and shall, by that name, sue  and be sued.</p>
            <p>Composition of institute.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Composition of institute. The Institute shall consist of the  following members, namely:-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the Vice- Chancellor of the Kerala University,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>ex- officio;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the Director- General of Health Services,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Government of India, ex officio;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list4.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the Director, ex- officio;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list4.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>four members to be nominated by the Central</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Government to represent respectively the Departments or,</p>
            <p>as the case may be, Ministries of that Government  dealing with Science and Technology, Health, Finance and</p>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list8">
              <listIntroduction>Education;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list8.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>two members to be nominated by the Government of  the State of Kerala to represent respectively the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Departments or, as the case may be, Ministries of that</p>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list11">
              <listIntroduction>Government dealing with Planning, Science and Technology  and Health;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list11.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>three scientists of whom two shall be medical  scientists and one shall be a social scientist, to be  nominated by the Central Government in the manner  prescribed by rules;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list11.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>three scientists representing engineering and  technology to be nominated by the Central Government in  the manner prescribed by rules;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list11.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the Head of the Biomedical Technology Wing of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list13">
              <listIntroduction>Institute, ex officio;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list13.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>three representatives of the medical faculties of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Indian Universities to be nominated by the Central</p>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list16">
              <listIntroduction>Government in the manner prescribed by rules; and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list16.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>three members of Parliament of whom two shall be  elected from among themselves by the members of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>House of the</p>
            <p>People and one from among themselves by the members of the Council of</p>
            <p>States.</p>
            <p>Term of office of and vacancies among members.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Term of office of and vacancies among members.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Save as  otherwise provided in this section, the term of office of a member  shall be five years from the date of his nomination or election.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The term of office of a member elected under clause (j) of  section 5 shall come to an end as soon as he ceases to be a member of  the House from which he was elected.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The term of office of an ex officio member shall continue so  long as he holds the office by virtue of which he is such a member.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The term of office of a member nominated or elected to fill  a casual vacancy shall continue for the remainder of the term of the  member in whose place he is nominated or elected.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.5.list1">
              <listIntroduction>An outgoing member other than a member elected under clause</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.5.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>of section 5 shall, unless the Central Government otherwise  directs, continue in office until another person is nominated as a  member in his place.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An outgoing member shall be eligible for re- nomination or  reelection.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A member may resign his office by writing under his hand  addressed to the Central Government but he shall continue in office  until his resignation is accepted by that Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The manner of filling vacancies among members shall be such  as may be prescribed by rules.</p>
            <p>President of institute.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>President of institute.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be a President of the</p>
            <p>Institute who shall be nominated by the Central Government from among  the members other than the Director.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The President shall exercise such powers and discharge such  functions as are laid down in this Act or as may be prescribed by  rules or regulations.</p>
            <p>Allowances of President and members.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Allowances of President and members. The President and other  members shall receive such allowances, if any, from the Institute as  may be prescribed by rules.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Meeting of Institute.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Meeting of Institute. The Institute shall hold its first  meeting at such time and place as may be appointed by the Central</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Government and shall observe such rules of procedure in regard to the  transaction of business at the first</p>
            <p>meeting as may be laid down by that Government; and thereafter the</p>
            <p>Institute shall meet at such times and places and observe such rules  of procedure in regard to the transaction of business at its meetings  as may be prescribed by regulations.</p>
            <p>Governing Body and Other committes of Institute.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Governing Body and Other committes of Institute.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There  shall be a Governing Body of the Institute which shall be constituted  by the Institute in such manner as may be prescribed by regulations:</p>
            <p>Provided that the number of persons who are not members of the</p>
            <p>Institute shall not exceed one- third of the total membership of the</p>
            <p>Governing Body.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Governing Body shall be the Executive Committee of the</p>
            <p>Institute and shall exercise such powers and discharge such functions  as the Institute may, by regulations made in this behalf, confer or  impose upon it.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The President shall be the Chairman of the Governing Body  and as Chairman thereof shall exercise such powers and discharge such  functions as may be prescribed by regulations.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The procedure to be followed in the exercise of its powers  and discharge of its functions by the Governing Body, and the term of  office of, and the manner of filling vacancies among, the members of  the Governing Body shall be such as may be prescribed by regulations.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to such control and restrictions as may be  prescribed by rules, the Institute may constitute as many standing  committees and as many ad hoc committees as it thinks fit for  exercising any power or discharging any function of the Institute or  for inquiring into, or reporting or advising upon, any matter which  the Institute may refer to them.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chairman and members of the Governing Body and Chairman  and members of a standing committee or an ad hoc committee shall  receive such allowances, if any, as may be prescribed by regulations.</p>
            <p>Staff of Institute.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Staff of Institute.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>There shall be a chief executive  officer of the Institute who shall be designated as the Director of  the Institute and shall, subject to such rules as may be made in this  behalf, be appointed by the Institute:</p>
            <p>Provided that the first Director of the Institute shall be  appointed by the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Director shall act as the Secretary to the Institute as  well as the Governing Body.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Director shall exercise such powers and discharge such  functions as may be prescribed by regulations or as may be delegated  to</p>
            <p>him by the Institute or the President or by the Governing Body or the</p>
            <p>Chairman.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to such rules as may be made in this behalf, the</p>
            <p>Institute may appoint such number of other officers and employees as  may be necessary for the exercise of its powers and discharge of its  functions and may determine the designations and grades of such other  officers and employees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to such rules as may be made in this behalf, the</p>
            <p>Director and other officers and employees of the Institute shall be  entitled to such salary and allowances and shall be governed by such  conditions of service in respect of leave, pension, gratuity,</p>
            <p>provident fund and other matters as may be prescribed by regulations  made in this behalf.</p>
            <p>Objects of Institute.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Objects of Institute. The objects of the Institute shall be-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to promote biomedical engineering and technology;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to provide and demonstrate high standards of  patient care in advanced medical specialities; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to develop post- graduate training programmes of  the highest quality in advanced medical specialities and  biomedical engineering and technology.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Functions of Institute.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Functions of Institute. With a view to the promotion of the  objects specified in section 12, the Institute may-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>provide for post- graduate teaching in the science  of modern medicine and other allied sciences, including  physical and biological sciences;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>provide facilities for research in the various  branches of such sciences;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>conduct experiments in integrated methods of post-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>graduate medical and technological education in order to  arrive at satisfactory standards of such education;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>prescribe courses and curricula for post- graduate  studies;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>provide for post- graduate teaching and training in  biomedical sciences and technology;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2.f.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>notwithstanding anything contained in any other  law for the time being in force, establish and maintain-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2.f.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>one or more well equipped hospitals, and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2.f.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>one or more centers for research and development  in biomedical technology;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list2.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>hold examinations and grant such degrees, diplomas  and other academic distinctions and titles in post-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>graduate medical education and biomedical technology as  may be laid down in the regulations;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list4.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>institute and appoint persons to professorships,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list6">
              <listIntroduction>readerships, lecturerships and posts of any description  in accordance with the regulations;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list6.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>receive grants from the Governments and gifts,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>donations, benefactions, bequests and transfers of  properties, both movable and immovable, from donors,</p>
            <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list9">
              <listIntroduction>benefactors, testators or transferors, as the case may  be;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list9.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>deal with any property belonging to, or vested in,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list11">
              <listIntroduction>the Institute in any manner which is considered  necessary for promoting the objects specified in  section l 2;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list11.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>demand and receive such fees and other charges as  may be prescribed by regulations; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list11.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>do all other acts and things as may be necessary to  further the objects specified in section 12</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Vesting of property.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Vesting of property. All properties which had vested in the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Sree Chitra Tirunal Medical Centre Society for Advanced Studies in</p>
            <p>Specialities, Trivandrum, immediately before the commencement of this</p>
            <p>Act, shall, on and from such commencement, vest in the Institute.</p>
            <p>Payment to Institute,</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Payment to Institute, The Central Government may, after due  appropriation made by Parliament by law in this behalf, pay to the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Institute in each financial year such sums of money and in such manner  as may be considered necessary by that Government for the exercise of  its powers and discharge of its functions under this Act.</p>
            <p>Fund of Institute.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Fund of Institute.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-16.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-16.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Institute shall maintain a Fund to  which shall be credited-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-16.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>all moneys provided by the Central Government and  the Government of Kerala;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>all fees and other charges received by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-16.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Institute</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-16.1.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>all moneys received by the Institute by way of  grants, gifts, donations, benefactions, bequests or  transfers; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.1.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>all moneys received by the Institute in any other  manner or from any other source.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All moneys credited to the Fund shall be deposited in such  banks or invested in such manner as the Institute may, with the  approval of the Central Government, decide.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Fund shall be applied towards meeting the expenses of  the Institute including expenses incurred in the exercise of its  powers and discharge of its functions under section 13.</p>
            <p>Budget of Institute.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Budget of Institute. The Institute shall prepare, in such form  and at such time every year, as may be prescribed by rules, a budget  in respect of the financial year next ensuing showing the estimated  receipts and expenditure of the Institute and shall forward to the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Central Government such number of copies thereof as may be prescribed  by rules.</p>
            <p>Account and audit.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Account and audit.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Institute shall maintain proper  accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual statement of  accounts including the balance- sheet in such form as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by rules, prescribe, and in accordance with such  general directions as may be issued by that Government, in  consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor General of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The accounts of the Institute shall be audited by the</p>
            <p>Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any expenditure incurred  by him in connection with such audit shall be payable by the Institute  to the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any person  appointed by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the</p>
            <p>Institute shall have the same rights, privileges and authority in  connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor- General of</p>
            <p>India has in connection with the audit of the Government accounts and,</p>
            <p>in particular, shall have the right to demand the production of books,</p>
            <p>accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and to  inspect the offices of the Institute as well as of the institutions  established and maintained by it.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The accounts of the Institute as certified by the</p>
            <p>Comptroller and Auditor- General of India or any other person appointed  by him in this behalf together with the audit report thereon shall be  forwarded annually to the Central Government and that Government shall  cause the same to be laid before both Houses of Parliament.</p>
            <p>Annual report.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Annual report. The Institute shall prepare for every year a  report of its activities during that year and submit the report to the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Central Government in</p>
            <p>such form and on or before such date as may be prescribed by rules and  a copy of the report shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is  received, before both Houses of Parliament.</p>
            <p>Pension and provident funds.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Pension and provident funds.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-20.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Institute shall  constitute for the benefit of its officers, teachers and other  employees in such manner and subject to such conditions as may be  prescribed by regulations, such pension and provident funds as it may  deem fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any such pension or provident fund has been  constituted, the Central Government may declare that the provisions of  the Provident Funds Act, 1925, (19 of 1925) shall apply to such fund  as if it were a Government Provident Fund.</p>
            <p>Authentication of orders and instruments of Institute.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Authentication of orders and instruments of Institute. All  orders and decisions of the Institute shall be authenticated by the  signature of the President or any other member authorised by the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Institute in this behalf, and all other instruments shall be  authenticated by the signature of the Director or any other officer of  the Institute authorised in like manner in this behalf.</p>
            <p>Acts and proceedings not to be invalidated by vacancies, etc.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Acts and proceedings not to be invalidated by vacancies, etc.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No act done or proceeding taken by the Institute, Governing Body or  any standing or ad hoc committee under this Act shall be questioned on  the ground merely of the existence of any vacancy in, or defect in the  constitution of, the Institute, Governing Body or such standing or ad  hoc committee.</p>
            <p>Grant of medical degrees, diplomas, etc, by Institute.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Grant of medical degrees, diplomas, etc., by Institute.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being  in force, the Institute shall have power to grant medical degrees,</p>
            <p>diplomas and other academic distinctions and titles under this Act.</p>
            <p>Recognition of medical qualifications granted by Institute.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Recognition of medical qualifications granted by Institute.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Indian Medical Council Act,</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1956">
        <num>1956.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1956.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>, (102 of 1956) the medical degrees and diplomas granted by the</p>
            <p>Institute under this Act shall be recognised medical qualifications  for the purposes of that Act and shall be deemed to be included in the</p>
            <p>First Schedule to that Act.</p>
            <p>Control by Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Control by Central Government. The Institute shall carry out  such directions as may be issued to it from time to time by the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Central Government for the efficient administration of this Act.</p>
            <p>Disputes between Institute and Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Disputes between Institute and Central Government. If in, or  in connection with, the exercise of its powers and discharge of its  functions by the Institute under this Act, any dispute arises between  the institute and the Central Government, the decision of the Central</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Government on such dispute shall be final.</p>
            <p>Returns and information.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Returns and information. The Institute shall furnish to the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Central Government such reports, returns and other information as that</p>
            <p>Government may require from time to time.</p>
            <p>Transfer of service of existing employees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28">
        <num>28.</num>
        <heading>Transfer of service of existing employees. Subject to the  provisions of this Act, every person who was employed in the Sree</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Chitra Tirunal Medical Centre Society for Advanced Studies in</p>
            <p>Specialities, Trivandrum, immediately before the commencement of this</p>
            <p>Act shall, on and from such commencement, become an employee of the</p>
            <p>Institute and shall hold his office or service therein by the same  tenure, at the same remuneration and upon the same terms and  conditions and with the same rights and privileges as to leave,</p>
            <p>pension, gratuity, provident fund and other matters as he would have  held the same on the date of commencement of this Act if this Act had  not been passed, and shall continue to do so unless and until his  employment is terminated or until such tenure, remuneration and terms  and conditions are duly altered by regulations:</p>
            <p>Provided that the tenure, remuneration and terms and conditions of  service of any such person shall not be altered to his disadvantage  without the previous approval of the Central Government.</p>
            <p>Continuance of facilities at Institute.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29">
        <num>29.</num>
        <heading>Continuance of facilities at Institute. The Institute shall  continue to provide facilities to the Government and people of the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-29.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>State of Kerala and the Council Government and such facilities shall  not, in any respect, be less favourable to the said Governments and  people than what were being provided to them before the commencement  of this Act and shall be made available for such period and upon such  terms and conditions (including those relating to any contributions to   be made for the provision of such facilities) as may be agreed upon  between the Institute the Government of the State of Kerala and the</p>
            <p>Central Government.</p>
            <p>power to remove difficulties.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-30">
        <num>30.</num>
        <heading>power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in  giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government  may, within a period of three years from the commencement of this Act,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-30.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>by order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions or  give such directions not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act,</p>
            <p>as appears to it to be necessary or expedient for removing the  difficulty.</p>
            <p>power to make rules.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-31">
        <num>31.</num>
        <heading>power to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-31.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government, after  consultation with the Institute, may, by notification in the Official</p>
            <p>Gazette, make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act:</p>
            <p>Provided that consultation with the Institute shall not be  necessary on the first occasion of the making of rules under this  section, but the Central Government shall take into consideration any  suggestions Which the Institute may make in relation to the amendment  of such rules after they are made.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-31.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-31.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-31.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the manner of nomination of members under clauses</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-31.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>, (g) and (i) of section 5;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-31.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the manner of filling vacancies among members  under section 6;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-31.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the powers and functions to be exercised and  discharged by the President under sub- section (2) of  section 7;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-31.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the allowances, if any, to be paid to the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-31.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>President and other members under section 8;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-31.2.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the controland restrictions in relation to the  constitution of standing and ad hoc committees under  sub- section (5) of section 10;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-31.2.list3.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the appointment of the Director under sub- section</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-31.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-31.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>of section 11;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-31.1.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the number of officers and employees that may be  appointed by the Institute and the manner of such  appointment under sub- section (4) of section 11;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-31.1.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the salaries and allowances to be paid to the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Director and other officers and employees of the</p>
            <blockList id="section-31.1.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Institute under sub- section (5) of section 11;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-31.1.list4.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the form in which, and the time at which, the  budget shall be prepared by the Institute and the number  of copies thereof to be forwarded to the Central</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-31.1.list6">
              <listIntroduction>Government under section 17;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-31.1.list6.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>the form in which an annual statement of accounts  including the balance- sheet shall be prepared by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-31.1.list8">
              <listIntroduction>Institute under sub- section (1) of section 18;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-31.1.list8.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>the form in which and the date before which, the  report of the activities of the Institute shall be  submitted to the Central Government under section 19;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-31.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-31.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>the form and manner in which reports, returns and  other information are to be furnished by the Institute  to the Central Government under section 27;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-31.1.list1.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>any other matter which has to be or may be  prescribed by rules.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Power to make regulation.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-32">
        <num>32.</num>
        <heading>Power to make regulation.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-32.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-32.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Institute may, with the  previous approval of the Central Government, make regulations  consistent with this Act and the rules made thereunder to carry out  the purposes of this Act, and without prejudice to the generality of  this power, such regulations may provide for-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-32.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the powers and functions to be exercised and  discharged by the President under sub- section (2) of  section 7;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-32.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the summoning and holding of meetings, other than  the first meeting, of the Institute under section 9, the  time and place where such meetings are to be held, the  conduct of business at such meetings and the number of  members necessary to form a quorum;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-32.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the manner of constituting the Governing Body and  standing and ad hoc committees under section 10, the  term of office of, and the manner of filling vacancies  among, the members of the Governing Body and standing  and ad hoc committees;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-32.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the powers and functions to be exercised and  discharged by the Governing Body and the Chairman under  sub- sections (2) and (3) of section 10;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-32.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the allowances, if any, to be paid to the Chairman  and the members of the Governing Body and of standing  and ad hoc committees under sub- section (6) of section</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the procedure to be followed by the Governing Body  and standing and ad hoc committees in the conduct of  their business, exercise of their powers and discharge  of their functions under section 10;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the powers and functions to be exercised and  discharged by the Director under sub- section (3) of  section 11;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the tenure of office, salaries and allowances and  other conditions of service of the Director and other  officers and employees of the Institute including  teachers appointed by the Institute under sub- section</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-10.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.5.list1">
              <listIntroduction>of section 11;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.5.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the management of the properties of the Institute  under section 13;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.5.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>the degrees, diplomas and other academic distinctions  and titles which may be granted by the Institute under  clause (g) of section 13;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.5.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>the professorships, readerships, lecturerships and  other posts which may be instituted and persons who may  be appointed to such professorships, readerships,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-10.5.list3">
              <listIntroduction>lecturerships and other posts under clause (h) of  section 13;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.5.list3.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>the fees and other charges which may be demanded  and received by the Institute under clause (k) of  section 13</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.5.list3.m">
                <num>(m)</num>
                <p>the manner in which, and the conditions subject to  which, pension and provident funds may be constituted  for the benefit of officers, teachers and other  employees of the Institute under sub- section (1) of  section 20;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.5.list3.n">
                <num>(n)</num>
                <p>matters relating to tenure of office, remuneration  and terms and conditions of service of the persons  referred to in section 28</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.5.list3.o">
                <num>(o)</num>
                <p>any other matter for which under this Act  provisions may be made by regulations.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), the  first regulations under this Act shall be made by the Central</p>
            <p>Government; and any regulations so made may be altered or rescinded  by the Institute In exercise of its power under sub- section (1).</p>
            <p>Rules and regulations to be laid before parliament.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-33">
        <num>33.</num>
        <heading>Rules and regulations to be laid before parliament. Every rule  and every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may  be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while It is in  session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in  one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the  expiry of the session immediately following the session or the  successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree In making any modi-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-33.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>fication In the rule or regulation or both Houses agree that the rule  or regulation should not be made, the rule or regulation shall  thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</p>
            <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that rule or regulation;</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
