<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-hmp/act/1979/11/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-hmp/act/1979/11"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Himachal Pradesh Prohibition of Cow Slaughter Act, 1979"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1979-06-16" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-hmp/act/1979/11/eng@1979-06-16/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-hmp/act/1979/11/eng@1979-06-16"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1979-06-16" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-hmp/act/1979/11/eng@1979-06-16/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-hmp/act/1979/11/eng@1979-06-16"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="1979-06-16" name="R.H.P. Extra" showAs="R.H.P. Extra" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preamble>
      <p>The Himachal Pradesh Prohibition of Cow Slaughter Act, 1979</p>
      <p>Act No. 11 of 1979</p>
      <p>PREAMBLE:</p>
      <p>An Act to prohibit the slaughter of cow and its progeny in Himachal Pradesh.</p>
      <p>BE it enacted by the Legislative Assembly of Himachal Pradesh in the Thirtieth Year of the Republic of India as follows:</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Himachal Pradesh Prohibition of Cow Slaughter Act, 1979.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Himachal Pradesh.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force at once.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definition.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant to the subject or context,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"beef" means flesh of cow in any form but does not include flesh of cow contained in sealed containers and imported into Himachal Pradesh;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"beef products" include extraction from beef;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>"cow" includes a bull, bullock, ox, heifer or calf;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>"prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>"slaughter" means killing by any method whatsoever and includes maiming and inflicting of physical injury which in the ordinary course will cause death;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>"Government" means the Government of Himachal Pradesh; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>"uneconomic cow" includes stray, unprotected, infirm, disabled, diseased or barren cow.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition of slaughter.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being in force or any usage or custom to the contrary, no person shall slaughter or cause to be slaughtered or offer or cause to be offered for slaughter any cow in any place in Himachal Pradesh.</p>
            <p>Provided that killing of a cow by accident or in self-defence will not be considered as slaughter under the Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Exceptions.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Nothing in section 3 shall apply to the slaughter of a cow.-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>whose suffering is such as to render its destruction desirable according to the certificate of the Veterinary Officer of the area or such other officer of the Animal Husbandry Department as may be prescribed; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>which is suffering from any contagious or infectious disease notified as such by the Government; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>which is subject to experimentation in the interest of medical and public health research by a certified medical practitioner of the Animal Husbandry Department.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where it is intended to slaughter a cow for the reasons specified in clause (a) or clause (b) of subsection (1) it shall be incumbent for a person doing so to obtain a prior permission in writing of the Veterinary Officer of the area or such other officer of the Animal Husbandry Department as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition of sale of beef.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Except as herein excepted and notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being in force no person shall sell or offer for sale or cause to be sold beef or beef products in any form except for such medicinal purposes as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Establishment of institutions.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>There shall be established by the Government, or by any local authority when so directed by the Government, institutions for the reception, maintenance and care of uneconomical cows.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Levy of fees.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government or the local authority, if so authorised, may levy such fees as may be prescribed for care and maintenance of uneconomic cows in the institution.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Penalty.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever contravenes or attempts to contravene or abets the contravention of the provisions of section 3 or 5 shall be guilty of an offence punishable with rigorous imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years, or with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever fails to lodge the information in the manner and within the time stated in subsection (2) of section 4 shall be guilty of an offence punishable with simple imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or with fine which may extend to two hundred rupees, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In any trial for an offence under subsection (1) or subsection (2) the burden of proving that the slaughtered cow belonged to the class specified in clauses (a) or (b) of subsection (1) of section 4 shall be on the accused.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Offences to be cognizable and non-bailable.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) an offence punishable under subsection (1) of section 8 shall be cognizable and non-bailable.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may make rules for the purpose of carrying into effect the previsions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing powers, such rules may provide for,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the conditions and the circumstances under which cows may be slaughtered under subsection (1) of section 4;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the manner in which diseases shall be notified under clause (b) of subsection (1) of section 4;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the manner in which permission shall be obtained under subsection (2) of section 4;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the forms and contents of the certificate mentioned in sub-clause (a) of subsection (1) of section 4 and, the authorities competent to grant it;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the manner in which and conditions under which beef or beef products are to be sold under section 5;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the matters relating to the establishment, maintenance, management, supervision and control of institutions referred to in section 6;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the duties of any officer or authority having jurisdiction under this Act, the procedure to be followed by such officer or authority; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the matters which are to be and may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this Act shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made, before the Legislative Assembly while it is in session for a total period of not less than fourteen days, which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session in which it is so laid or the session immediately following, the Assembly makes any modification in the rule or decides that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so, however, that such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Repeal and savings.-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list0.l">
                <num>(l)</num>
                <p>The Punjab Prohibition of Cow Slaughter Act, 1955 (15 of 1956) in its application to the territories added to Himachal Pradesh under section 5 of the Punjab Reorganisation Act, 1966 (31 of 1966) is hereby repealed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding such repeal anything don, action taken, rules made or notification issued in exercise of the powers conferred by or under the provisions of this Act, shall be deemed to have been done, taken, made or issued in exercise of the powers conferred by or under this Act, as if this Act was in force on the day on which such thing was done, action taken, rules made or notification issued.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
