<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1923/5/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1923/5"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Indian Boilers Act, 1923"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1923/5/eng@1923-02-23/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1923/5/eng@1923-02-23"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1923-02-23" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1923/5/eng@1923-02-23/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1923/5/eng@1923-02-23"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Indian Boilers Act, 1923</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 5 OF 1923</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 23rd February, 1923.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to consolidate and amend the law relating to steam boilers.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to consolidate and amend the law relating to  steam- boilers; it is hereby enacted as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be  called the Indian Boilers Act, 1923.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India  except the State of</p>
            <p>Jammu and Kashmir].]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date  as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.- In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant  in the subject or context,-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>" accident" means an explosion of a boiler or steam- pipe  or any damage to a boiler or steam- pipe which is  calculated to weaken the strength thereof so as to  render it liable to explode;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a.list0.aa">
                    <num>(aa)</num>
                    <p>" Board" means the Central Boilers Board constituted  under section 27A;]</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" boiler" means any closed vessel exceeding  2275  litres] in capacity which is used expressly for  generating steam under pressure  and includes any  mounting or other fitting attached to such vessel,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>which is wholly or partly under pressure when steam is  shut off;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" Chief Inspector"," Deputy Chief Inspector" and</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>" Inspector" mean, respectively, a person appointed to  be a Chief Inspector, a Deputy Chief Inspector and an</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Inspector under this Act;]</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.cc">
                <num>(cc)</num>
                <p>" economiser" means any part of a feed- pipe that is  wholly or partially exposed to the action of flue gases  for the purpose of recovery of waste heat;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.ccc">
                <num>(ccc)</num>
                <p>" feed- pipe" means any pipe or connected fitting wholly  or partly under pressure through which feed water  passes directly to a boiler and  which] does not form  an integral part thereof;]</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>" owner" includes any person using a boiler as agent of  the owner thereof and any person using a boiler which  he has hired or obtained on loan from the owner  thereof;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by regulations or rules  made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>" steam- pipe" means any pipe through which steam  passes from a boiler to a prime- mover or other user or  both, if-</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the pressure at which steam passes  through such pipe exceeds 3. 5 kilograms per square  centimetre above atmospheric pressure; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>such pipe exceeds 254 millimetres in  internal diameter;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list7">
              <listIntroduction>and includes in either case any connected fitting of a  steam- pipe;]</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list7.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>" structural alteration, addition or renewal" shall not  be deemed to include any renewal or replacement of a  petty nature when the part or fitting used for  replacement is not inferior in strength, efficiency or  otherwise to the replaced part or fitting.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2A">
        <num>2A.</num>
        <heading>Application of Act to feed- pipes. Every reference in this</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Act (except where the word' steam- pipe' is used in clause (f) of   section 2), to a steam- pipes shall be deemed to include also a  reference to a feed- pipe or feed- pipes, respectively.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2B">
        <num>2B.</num>
        <heading>Application of Act to economisers. Every reference in this</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2B.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Act to a boiler or boilers (except in clause (ccc) of section 2</p>
            <p>) shall be deemed to include also a reference to an economisers,</p>
            <p>respectively.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Limitation of application.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Nothing in this Act shall apply  in the case of any boiler or steam- pipe--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in any steam- ship as defined in section 3 of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Indian Steam- ships Act, 1884 (7 of 1884), or in any  steam- vessel as defined in section 2 of the Inland</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Steam- vessels Act, 1917 (1 of 1917); or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>belonging to, or under the control of, the Army, Navy  or Air Force; or]</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>appertaining to a sterilizer or disinfector of a type  such as is commonly used in hospitals, if the boiler  does not exceed  ninety- one litres] in capacity.]</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification  in the</p>
            <p>Official Gazette, declare that the provisions of this Act shall not  apply in the case of boilers or steam- pipes, or of any specified class  of boilers or steam- pipes, belonging to or under the control of any  railways administered  by the  Central Government] or by any State</p>
            <p>Government] or by any railway company as defined in clause (5) of  section 3 of the Indian Railways Act, 1890 (9 of 1890).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Power to limit extent. The State Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, exclude  any specified area  from the operation of all or any specified provisions of this Act.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Chief Inspector, Deputy Chief Inspectors and Inspectors.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may appoint such persons as it thinks fit to  be Inspectors for the State for the purposes of this Act, and may  define the local limits within which each Inspector shall exercise the  powers and perform the duties conferred and imposed on Inspectors by  or under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may appoint such persons as it thinks  fit to be Deputy Chief Inspectors for the State and may define the  local limits within which each Deputy Chief Inspector shall exercise  his powers and perform his duties under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every Deputy Chief Inspector may exercise the powers and  perform the duties conferred and imposed on Inspectors by or under  this Act and, in addition thereto, may exercise such powers or perform  such duties conferred or imposed on the Chief Inspector by or under  this Act, as the State Government may assign to him.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government shall appoint a person to be Chief</p>
            <p>Inspector for the State who may, in addition to the powers and duties  conferred and imposed on the Chief Inspector by or under this Act,</p>
            <p>exercise any power or perform any duty so conferred or imposed on</p>
            <p>Deputy Chief Inspectors or Inspectors.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Deputy Chief</p>
            <p>Inspectors and Inspectors shall exercise the powers and perform the  duties conferred and imposed on them by or under this Act under the  general superintendence and control of the Chief Inspector.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chief Inspector, Deputy Chief Inspectors and Inspectors  may offer such advice as they think fit to owners regarding the proper  maintenance and safe working of boilers.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chief Inspector and all Deputy Chief Inspectors and</p>
            <p>Inspectors shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of  section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition of use of unregistered or uncertificated boiler.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Save as otherwise expressly provided this Act, no owner of a boiler  shall use the boiler or permit it to be used--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>unless it has been registered in accordance with the  provisions of this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in the case of any boiler which has been transferred  from one State to another, until the transfer has been  reported in the prescribed manner;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>unless a certificate or provisional order authorizing  the use of the boiler is for the time being in force  under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>at a pressure higher than the maximum pressure recorded  in such certificate or provisional order;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>where the State Government has made rules requiring  that boilers shall be in charge of persons holding    certificates of proficiency or competency], unless  the boiler is in charge of a person holding the  certificate required by such rules:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that any boiler registered, or any boiler  certified or licensed, under any Act hereby repealed  shall be deemed</p>
            <p>to have been registered or certified, as the case may  be, under this Act:</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Registration.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The owner of any boiler which is not  registered under the provisions of this Act may apply to the Inspector  to have the boiler registered. Every such application shall be  accompanied by the prescribed fee.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On receipt of an application under sub- section (1), the</p>
            <p>Inspector shall fix a date, within thirty days or such shorter period  as may be prescribed from the date of the receipt, for the examination  of the boiler and shall give the owner thereof not less than ten days'</p>
            <p>notice of the date so fixed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On the said date the Inspector shall proceed to measure and  examine the boiler and to determine in the prescribed manner the  maximum pressure, if any, at which such boiler may be used, and shall  report the result of the examination of the Chief Inspector in the  prescribed form.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Chief Inspector, on receipt of the report, may-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>register the boiler and assign a register number  thereto either forthwith or after satisfying himself  that any structural alteration, addition or renewal  which he may deem necessary has been made in or to the  boiler or any steam- pipe attached thereto, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.4.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>refuse to register the boiler:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided that where the Chief Inspector refuses to  register a boiler, he shall forthwith communicate his  refusal to the owner of the boiler together with the  reasons therefor.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chief Inspector shall, on registering the boiler, order  the issue to the owner of a certificate in the prescribed form  authorizing the use of the boiler for a period not exceeding twelve  months at a pressure not exceeding such maximum pressure as he thinks  fit and as is in accordance with the regulations made under this Act:</p>
            <p>Provided that a certificate issued under this sub- section in  respect of an economiser  or of an unfired boiler which forms an  integral part of a processing plant in which steam is generated solely  by the use of oil, asphalt or bitumen as a heating medium] may  authorize its use for a period not exceeding twenty- four months.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Inspector shall forthwith convey to the owner of the  boiler the orders of the Chief Inspector and shall in accordance  therewith issue to the owner any certificate of which the issue has  been ordered, and, where the boiler has been registered, the owner  shall within the prescribed period cause the register number to be  permanently marked thereon in the prescribed manner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Renewal of certificate.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A certificate authorizing the use  of a boiler shall cease to be in force--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>on the expiry of the period for which it was granted;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-8.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.1.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>when any accident occurs to be boiler; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.1.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>when the boiler is moved, the boiler not being a  vertical boiler the heating surface of which is less  than  18- 58 square metres], or a portable or  vehicular boiler; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.1.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>when any structural alteration, addition or renewal is  made in or to the boiler; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.1.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>if the Chief Inspector in any particular case so  directs, when any structural alteration, addition or  renewal is made in or to any steam- pipe attached to the  boiler; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.1.list3.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>on the communication to the owner of the boiler of an  order of the Chief Inspector or Inspector prohibiting  its use on the ground that it or any steam- pipe  attached thereto is in a dangerous condition.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an order is made under clause (f) of sub- section (1),</p>
            <p>the grounds on which the order is made shall be communicated to the  owner with the order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When a certificate ceases to be in force, the owner of the  boiler may apply to the Inspector for a renewal thereof for such  period not exceeding twelve months as he may specify in the  application:</p>
            <p>Provided that where the certificate relates to an economiser    or an unfired boiler which forms an integral part of a processing  plant in which steam is generated solely by the use of oil, asphalt or  bitumen as a heating medium], the application for its renewal may be  for a period not exceeding twenty- four months.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An application under sub- section (3) shall be accompanied by  the prescribed fee and, on receipt thereof, the Inspector shall fix a  date, within thirty days or such shorter period as may be prescribed  from the date of the receipt, for the examination of the boiler and</p>
            <p>shall give the owner thereof not less than ten days' notice of the  date so fixed:</p>
            <p>Provided that, where the certificate has ceased to be in force  owing to the making of any structural alteration, addition or  renewal, the Chief Inspector may dispense with the payment of any fee:</p>
            <p>Provided further that in the case of an economiser or of an  unfired boiler which forms an integral part of a processing plant in  which steam is generated solely by the use of oil, asphalt or bitumen  as a heating medium, the date fixed for its examination shall be  within sixty days from the date of the receipt of the application and  the owner shall be given not less than thirty days' notice of the date  so fixed.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On the said date the Inspector shall examine the boiler in  the prescribed manner, and if he is satisfied that the boiler and the  steam- pipe or steam- pipes attached thereto are in good condition shall  issue a renewed certificate authorizing the use of the boiler for such  period not exceeding twelve months and at a pressure not exceeding  such maximum pressure as he thinks fit and as is in accordance with  the regulations made under this Act:</p>
            <p>Provided that a renewed certificate issued under this sub-</p>
            <p>section in respect of an economiser  or of an unfired boiler which  forms an integral part of a processing plant in which steam is  generated solely by the use of oil, asphalt or bitumen as a heating  medium] may authorize its use for a period not exceeding twenty- four  months.]</p>
            <blockList id="section-8.5.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Provided  further] that if the Inspector--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.5.list4.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-8.5.list4.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>proposes to issue any certificate--</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-8.5.list4.a.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>having validity for a less than the  period entered in the application, or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-8.5.list4.a.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>increasing or reducing the maximum  pressure at which the boiler may be used, or</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.5.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>proposes to order any structural alteration, addition  or renewal to be made in or to the boiler or any steam-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-8.5.list6">
              <listIntroduction>pipe attached thereto, or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.5.list6.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>is of opinion that the boiler is not fit for use,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>the Inspector shall, within forty- eight hours of making the  examination, inform the owner of the boiler in writing of his opinion  and the reasons therefor, and shall forthwith report the case for  orders to the Chief Inspector.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Chief Inspector, on receipt of a report under sub- section</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>may, subject to the provisions of this Act and of the regulations</p>
            <p>made hereunder, order the renewal of the certificate in such terms and  on such conditions, if any, as he thinks fit, or may refuse to renew  it:</p>
            <p>Provided that where the Chief Inspector refuses to renew a  certificate, he shall forthwith communicate his refusal to the owner  of the boiler, together with the reasons therefor.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in this section shall be deemed to prevent an owner  of a boiler from applying for a renewed certificate therefor at any  time during the currency of a certificate.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Provisional orders. Where the Inspector reports the case of  any boiler to the Chief Inspector under sub- section (3) of section 7  or sub- section (5) of section 8, he may, if the boiler is not a boiler  the use of which has been prohibited under clause (f) of sub- section</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>of section 8, grant to the owner thereof a provisional order in  writing permitting the boiler to be used at a pressure not exceeding  such maximum pressure as he thinks fit and as is in accordance with  the regulations made under the Act pending the receipt of the orders  of the Chief Inspector. Such provisional order shall cease to be in  force--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>on the expiry of six months from the date on which it  is granted, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>on receipt of the orders of the Chief Inspector, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>in any of the cases referred to in clauses (b), (c),</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>, (e) and (f) of sub- section (1) of section 8,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>and on so ceasing to be in force shall be surrendered to the</p>
            <p>Inspector.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Use of boiler pending grant of certificate.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything hereinbefore contained, when the period of a  certificate relating to a boiler has expired, the owner shall,</p>
            <p>provided that he has applied before the expiry of that period for a  renewal of the certificate, be entitled to use the boiler at the  maximum pressure entered in the former certificate pending the issue  of orders on the application.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Nothing in sub- section (1) shall be deemed to authorize the  use of a boiler in any of the cases referred to in clauses (b), (c),</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>, (e) and (f) of sub- section (1) of section 8 occurring after the  expiry of the period of the certificate.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Revocation of certificate or provisional order. The Chief</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Inspector may at any time withdraw or revoke any certificate or  provisional order on the report of an Inspector or otherwise--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>if there is reason to believe that the certificate or  provisional order has been fraudulently obtained or has  been</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>granted erroneously or without sufficient examination;</p>
            <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list4">
              <listIntroduction>or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>if the boiler in respect of which it has been granted  has sustained injury or has ceased to be in good  condition; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>where the State Government has made rules requiring  that boilers shall be in charge of persons holding    certificates of proficiency or competency], if the  boiler is in charge of a person not holding the  certificate required by such rules; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list4.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>where no such rules have been made, if the boiler is in  charge of a person who is not, having regard to the  condition of the boiler, in the opinion of the Chief</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Inspector competent to have charge thereof:</p>
            <p>Provided that where the Chief Inspector withdraws or  revokes a certificate or provisional order on the  ground specified in clause (d), he shall communicate to  the owner of the boiler his reasons in writing for the  withdrawal or revocation, and the order shall not take  effect until the expiry of thirty days from the receipt  of such communication.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Alterations and renewals to boilers. No structural  alteration, addition or renewal shall be made in or to any boiler  registered under this Act unless such alteration, addition or renewal  has been sanctioned in writing by the Chief Inspector.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Alterations and renewals to steam- pipes. Before the owner of  any boiler registered under this Act makes any structural alteration,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>addition or renewal in or to any steam- pipe attached to the boiler, he  shall transmit to the Chief Inspector a report in writing of his  intention, and shall send therewith such particulars of the proposed  alteration, addition or renewal as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Duty of owner at examination.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>On nay date fixed under  this Act for the examination of a boiler, the owner thereof shall be  bound--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to afford to the Inspector all reasonable facilities  for the examination and all such information as may  reasonably be required of him;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to have the boiler properly prepared and ready for  examination in the prescribed manner; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>in the case of an application for the registration of a  boiler, to provide such drawings, specifications,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>certificates and other particulars as may be  prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the owner fails, without reasonable cause, to comply with  the provisions of sub- section (1), the Inspector shall refuse to make  the examination and shall report the case to the Chief Inspector who  shall, unless sufficient cause to the contrary is shown, require the  owner to file a fresh application under section 7 or section 8, as the  case may be, and may forbid him to use the boiler notwithstanding  anything contained in section 10.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Production of certificates, etc. The owner of any boiler who  holds a certificate or provisional order relating thereto shall, at  all reasonable times during the period for which the certificate or  order is in force, be bound to produce the same when called upon to do  so by a District Magistrate, Commissioner of Police or Magistrate of  the first class having jurisdiction in the area in which the boiler is  for the time being, or by the Chief Inspector or by an Inspector or by  any Inspector appointed under the  Indian Factories Act, 1911 (12 of</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1911">
        <num>1911.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1911.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>). or by any person specially authorized in writing by a District</p>
            <p>Magistrate or Commissioner of Police.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Transfer of certificates, etc, If any person becomes the  owner of a boiler during the period for which a certificate or  provisional order relating thereto is in force, the preceding owner  shall be bound to make over to him the certificate or provisional  order.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Powers of entry. An Inspector may, for the purpose of  inspecting or examining a boiler or any steam- pipe attached thereto or  of seeing that any provision of this Act or of any regulation or rule  made hereunder has been or is being observed, at all reasonable times  enter any place or building within the limits of the area for which he  has been appointed in which he has reason to believe that a boiler is  in use.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Report of accidents.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any accident occurs to a boiler  or steam- pipe, the owner or person in charge thereof shall, within  twenty- four hours of the accident, report the same in writing to the</p>
            <p>Inspector. Every such report shall contain a true description of the  nature of the accident and of the injury, if any, caused thereby to  the boiler of to the steam- pipe or to any person, and shall be in  sufficient detail to enable the Inspector to judge of the gravity of  the accident.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every person shall be bound to answer truly to the best of  his knowledge and ability every question put to him in writing by the</p>
            <p>Inspector as to the cause, nature or extent of the accident.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Appeals to Chief Inspector. Any person considering himself  aggrieved by--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-19.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>an order made or purporting to be made by an Inspector  in the exercise of any power conferred by or under this</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-19.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Act, or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>a refusal of an Inspector to make any order or to issue  any certificate which he is required or enabled by or  under this Act to make or issue,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>may, within thirty days from the date on which such order or refusal  is communicated to him, appeal against the order or refusal to the</p>
            <p>Chief Inspector.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Appeals to appellate authority. Any person considering  himself aggrieved by an original or appellate order of the Chief</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-20.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Inspector--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>refusing to register a boiler or to grant or renew a  certificate in respect of a boiler; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>refusing to grant a certificate having validity for the  full period applied for; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>refusing to grant a certificate authorizing the use of  a boiler at the maximum pressure desired; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>withdrawing or revoking a certificate or provisional  order; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>reducing the amount of pressure specified in any  certificate or the period for which such certificate  has been granted; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>ordering any structural alteration, addition or renewal  to be made in or to a boiler or steam- pipe or refusing  sanction to the making of any structural alteration,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>addition or renewal in or to a boiler,</p>
            <p>may, within thirty days of the communication to him of such order;</p>
            <p>lodge with the Chief Inspector an appeal to an appellate authority to  be constituted by the State Government under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20A">
        <num>20A.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to revise order of appellate  authority.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-20A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person considering himself aggrieved by an order of  the appellate authority refusing under section 20 to interfere with an  order not to register a boiler or not to grant or renew a certificate  in respect thereof on the ground that the boiler does not conform to  the regulations made under this Act may, within two months of the  communication to him of such order, make an application to the Central</p>
            <p>Government for a revision of that order on the ground that such  boilers are in use in other countries.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-20A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Upon the receipt of such an application, the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, after calling for relevant records and other  information from the appellate authority and considering the  observations, if any, of that authority on the application and after  obtaining such technical advice as the Central Government may consider  necessary, pass such order in relation to the application, as the</p>
            <p>Central Government thinks fit; and, where the revision is allowed, the  order shall specify the terms and conditions on which any variations  from the regulations made under this Act are to be dealt with during  the examination of the boiler.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Finality of orders. An order of the Central Government  under section 20A and, save as otherwise provided in sections 19, 20  and 20A, an order of an appellate authority, or of the Chief</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Inspector, or of a Deputy Chief Inspector, or of an Inspector, shall  be final and shall not be called in question in any court.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Minor penalties. Any owner of a boiler who refuses or without  reasonable excuse neglects--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-22.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-22.paragraph-0.list0.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>to surrender a provisional order as required by section</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>, or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>to produce a certificate or provisional order when duly  called upon to do so under section 15, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>to make over to the new owner of a boiler a certificate  or provisional order as required by section 16,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall be punishable with fine which may extend to one hundred rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Penalties for illegal use of boiler. Any owner of a boiler  who, in any case in which a certificate or provisional order is  required for the use of the boiler under this Act, uses the boiler  either without any such certificate or order being in force or at a  higher pressure than that allowed thereby, shall be punishable with  fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, and, in the case of a  continuing offence, with an additional fine which may extend to one  hundred rupees for each day after the first day in regard to which he  is convicted of having persisted in the offence.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Other penalties. Any person who--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-24.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>uses or permits to be used a boiler of which he is the  owner and which has been transferred from one State to  another without such transfer having been reported as  required by section 6, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>being the owner of a boiler fails to cause the register  number allotted to the boiler under this Act to be  marked on the boiler as required by sub- section (6) of  section 7, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>makes any structural alteration, addition or renewal in  or to a boiler without first obtaining the sanction of  the Chief Inspector when so required by section 12, or  to a steam- pipe without first informing the Chief</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Inspector, when so required by section 13, or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>fails to report an accident to a boiler or steam- pipe  when so required by section 18, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>tampers with a safety valve of a boiler so as to render  it inoperative at the maximum pressure at which the use  of the boiler is authorized under this Act,  or]</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>allows another person to go inside a boiler without  effectively disconnecting the same in the prescribed  manner from any steam or hot water connection with any  other boiler or from fuel mains,]</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall be punishable with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for tampering with register mark.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-25.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever  removes, alters, defaces, renders invisible or otherwise tampers with  the register number marked on a boiler in accordance with the  provisions of this Act or any Act repealed hereby, shall be punishable  with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-25.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever fraudulently marks upon a boiler a register number  which has not been allotted to it under this Act or any Act repealed  hereby, shall be punishable with imprisonment which may extend to two  years, or with fine, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Limitation and previous sanction for prosecutions. No  prosecution for an offence made punishable by or under this Act shall  be instituted except within  twenty- four months] from the date of  the commission of the offence, and no such prosecution shall be  instituted without the previous sanction of the Chief Inspector.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Trial of offences. No offence made punishable by or under  this Act shall be tried by a Court inferior to that of a Presidency</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Magistrate or a Magistrate of the first class.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27A">
        <num>27A.</num>
        <heading>Central Boilers Board.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-27A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A Board to be called the</p>
            <p>Central Boilers Board shall be constituted to exercise the powers  conferred by section 28.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-27A.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Board shall consist of the following members, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-27A.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>such number of members, including the Chairman, not  exceeding fifteen, as the Central Government may  nominate, in the prescribed manner to represent that</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Government, the Union territories, the railways, the  coal industry, the Indian Standards Institution, the  boiler manufacturing industry, the users of boilers  and, any other interests which, in the opinion of the</p>
            <p>Central Government, ought to be represented on the</p>
            <blockList id="section-27A.2.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Board;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-27A.2.list5.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>a senior technical officer conversant with the  inspection and examination of boilers, to be nominated  by the Government of each State (other than a Union   territory).]</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any vacancy occurring in the Board  shall be filled as soon  as may be by a nomination made by the authority by whom the member  vacating office was nominated.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27A.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall have full power to regulate by means of  bye- laws or otherwise its own procedure and the conduct of all  business to be transacted by it, the constitution of committees and  sub- committees of members and the delegation to them of any of the  powers and duties of the Board.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-27A.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The powers of the Board may be exercised notwithstanding any  vacancy in the Board.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28">
        <num>28.</num>
        <heading>Power to make regulations.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-28.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-28.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The  Board] may, by  notification in the Gazette of India, make regulations  consistent  with this Act for all or any of the following purposes, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-28.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-28.1.list1.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>for laying down the standard conditions in respect of  material, design and construction which shall be  required for the purpose of enabling the registration  and certification of a boiler under this Act;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-28.1.list1.a.list0.aa">
                    <num>(aa)</num>
                    <p>for prescribing the circumstances in which, the  extent to which, and the conditions subject to which  variation</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>from the standard conditions laid down under clause (a)</p>
            <blockList id="section-28.1.list4">
              <listIntroduction>may be permitted;]</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-28.1.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>for prescribing the method of determining the maximum  pressure at which a boiler may be used;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28.1.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>for regulating the registration of boilers, prescribing  the fees payable therefor  and for the inspection and  examination of boilers or parts thereof], the drawings,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-28.1.list6">
              <listIntroduction>specifications, certificates and particulars to be  produced by the owner, the method of preparing a boiler  for examination, owner, the method of preparing a  boiler for examination, the form of the Inspector' s  report thereon, the method of marking the register  number, and the period within which such number is to  be marked on the boiler;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-28.1.list6.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>for regulating the inspection and examination of  boilers and steam- pipes, and prescribing forms of  certificates therefor;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28.1.list6.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>for ensuring the safety of persons working inside a  boiler; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28.1.list6.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>for providing for any other matter which is not, in the  opinion of the  Board], a matter of merely local or</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>State importance.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-28.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as  soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament,</p>
            <p>while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be  comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and  if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session  or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the regulation or both Houses agree that the  regulation should not be made, the regulation shall thereafter have  effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may  be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be  without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under  that regulation.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28A">
        <num>28A.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-28A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The</p>
            <blockList id="section-28A.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make  rules to provide for--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-28A.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the procedure to be followed in making applications  under section 20A and the fees payable in respect of  such applications; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28A.1.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any matter relating to the nomination of members under  clause (a) of sub- section (2) of section 27A.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-28A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under sub- section (1) shall be laid as soon  as may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is  in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in  one session or  in two or more successive sessions, and if, before  the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the  successive sessions aforesaid] both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not  be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified  form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so however, that any such  modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity  of anything previously done under that rule.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-29">
        <num>29.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-29.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Power to make rules.  (1) The State Government may,</p>
            <blockList id="section-29.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules consistent with  this Act and the regulations made thereunder for all or any of the  following purposes, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-29.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for prescribing the qualifications and duties of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Chief Inspector,  of Deputy Chief Inspectors] and of</p>
            <blockList id="section-29.1.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Inspectors,  for prescribing or constituting  authorities to which they shall respectively be  subordinate, and the limits of the administrative  control to be exercised by such authorities;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-29.1.list5.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>for regulating the transfer of boilers;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-29.1.list5.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>for providing for the registration and certification of  boilers in accordance with the regulations made under  this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-29.1.list5.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>for requiring boilers to be in charge of persons  holding  certificates of proficiency or competency],</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-29.1.list7">
              <listIntroduction>and for prescribing the conditions on which such  certificates may be granted;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-29.1.list7.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>for prescribing the times within which Inspectors shall  be required to examine boilers under section 7 or  section 8;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-29.1.list7.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>for prescribing the fees payable for the issue of  renewed certificates, for the inspection and  examination of boilers or parts thereof or drawings for  steam- pipes, for the testing of welders or for any  other matter which, in the opinion of the State</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-29.1.list9">
              <listIntroduction>Government, would involve time and labour, and for  prescribing the method of determining the amount of  such fees in each case;]</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-29.1.list9.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>for regulating inquiries into accidents;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-29.1.list9.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>for constituting the appellate authority referred to in  section 20, and for determining its powers and  procedure;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-29.1.list9.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>for determining the mode of disposal of fees, costs and  penalties levied under this Act; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-29.1.list9.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>generally to provide for any matter which is, in the  opinion of the State Government, a matter of merely  local importance in the State:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-29.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made by the State Government under this Act  shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before the State</p>
            <p>Legislature.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-30">
        <num>30.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for breach of rules. Any regulation or rule made  under section 28 or section 29  may direct that a person  contravening such regulation or rule shall be punishable, in the case  of a first offence, with fine which may extend to one hundred rupees,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-30.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>and in the case of any subsequent offence, with fine which may extend  to one thousand rupees].</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-31">
        <num>31.</num>
        <heading>Publication of regulations and rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-31.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The power to make  regulations and rules conferred by sections 28 and 29 shall be subject  to the condition of the regulations and rules being made after  previous publication.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-31.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Regulations and rules so made shall be published in the</p>
            <p>Gazette of India and the local official Gazette, respectively, and, on  such publication, shall have effect as if enacted in this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-31A">
        <num>31A.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to give directions. The</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-31A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Central Government may give such directions as it may deem necessary  to a State Government regarding the carrying into execution of the  provisions of this Act, and the State Government shall comply with  such directions.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-32">
        <num>32.</num>
        <heading>Recovery of fees, etc. All fees, costs and penalties levied  under this Act shall be recoverable as arrears of land revenue.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-33">
        <num>33.</num>
        <heading>Applicability to the Government. Save as otherwise expressly  provided, this Act shall apply to boilers and steam- pipes belonging to  the Government.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-34">
        <num>34.</num>
        <heading>Exemptions.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-34.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification  in the Official Gazette, exempt from the operation of this Act,</p>
            <p>subject to such conditions and restrictions as it thinks fit, any  boilers or classes or types of boilers used exclusively for the  heating of buildings or the supply of hot water.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-34.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Power to suspend in case of emergency. Power to  suspend in case of emergency. In case of any emergency the State</p>
            <p>Government may, by general or special order in writing, exempt any  boilers or steam- pipes or any class of boilers or steam- pipes or any  boiler or steam- pipe from the operation of all or any of the  provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-34.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the State Government is satisfied that, having regard to  the material, design or construction of boilers and to the need for  the</p>
            <p>rapid industrialisation of the country, it is necessary so to do, it  may, by notification in the Official Gazette and subject to such  conditions and restrictions as may be specified in the notification,</p>
            <p>exclude any specified class of boilers or steam- pipes in the whole or  any part of the State, from the operation of all or any of the  provisions of this Act.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-35">
        <num>35.</num>
        <heading>Repeal of enactments.-- Rep. by the Repealing Act, 1927 (12   of 1927), s. 2 and Sch.</heading>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-scheduleI">
      <doc name="scheduleI">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1923/5/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1923/5"/>
              <FRBRalias value="Schedule I"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1923/5/eng@1923-02-23/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1923/5/eng@1923-02-23"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1923/5/eng@1923-02-23/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1923/5/eng@1923-02-23"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduleI">
            <paragraph id="scheduleI.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>Enactments repealed</p>
                <p>THE SCHEDULE. Enactments repealed. Rep. by the Repealing Act,</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <section id="section-1927">
              <num>1927.</num>
              <heading>(12 of 1927), s. 2 and Sch.</heading>
            </section>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
