<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1988/51/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1988/51"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Labour Laws (Exemption From Furnishing Returns And Maintaining Registers By Certain Establishments) Act, 1988"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1988/51/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1988/51/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1988/51/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1988/51/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Labour Laws (Exemption From Furnishing Returns And Maintaining Registers By Certain Establishments) Act, 1988</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Labour Laws (Exemption from Furnishing Returns and Maintaining Registers by Certain Establishments) Act, 1988.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing contained in this Act, in relation to the Plantations Labour Act, 1951 (69 of 1951) shall extend to the State of Jammu and Kashmir.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date1 as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint, and different dates may be appointed for different States, and any reference in any provision of this Act to the commencement of this Act shall be construed as a reference to the coming into force of that provision in that State.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“employer”, in relation to a Scheduled Act, which defines such expression, has the same meaning assigned to it in that Act, and in relation to any other Scheduled Act, means the person who is required to furnish returns or maintain registers under that Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>“establishment” has the meaning assigned to it in a Scheduled Act, and includes—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>an ‘industrial or other establishment’ as defined in section 2 of the Payment of Wages Act, 1936 (4 of 1936);</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>a ‘factory’ as defined in section 2 of the Factories Act, 1948 (63 of 1948);</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>a factory, workshop or place where employees are employed or work is given out to workers, in any scheduled employment to which the Minimum Wages Act, 1948 (11 of 1948), applies;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>a ‘plantation’ as defined in section 2 of the Plantations Labour Act, 1951 (69 of 1951); and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.b.list0.v">
                    <num>(v)</num>
                    <p>a ‘newspaper establishment’ as defined in section 2 of the Working Journalists and other Newspaper Employees (Conditions of Service) and Miscellaneous Provisions Act, 1955 (45 of 1955);</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“Form” means a Form specified in the Second Schedule;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>“Scheduled Act” means an Act specified in the First Schedule and is in force on the commencement of this Act in the territories to which such Act extends generally, and includes the rules made thereunder;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>“small establishment” means an establishment in which not less than ten and not more than nineteen persons are employed or were employed on any day of the preceding twelve months;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>“very small establishment” means an establishment in which not more than nine persons are employed or were employed on any day of the preceding twelve months.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Amendment of certain labour laws.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>On and from the commencement of this Act, the Scheduled Acts shall have effect subject to the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Exemption from returns and registers required under certain labour laws.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On and from the commencement of this Act, it shall not be necessary for an employer in relation to any small establishment or very small establishment to which a Scheduled Act applies to furnish the returns or to maintain the registers required to be furnished or maintained under that Scheduled Act:</p>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that such employer—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>furnishes, in lieu of such returns, a Core Return in Form A;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-4.1.list2.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>maintains, in lieu of such registers,—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-4.1.list2.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>registers in Form B, Form C and Form D, in the case of small establishments; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-4.1.list2.b.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>register in Form E, in the case of very small establishments:</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Provided further that every such employer shall continue to—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list4.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>issue wage slips in the Form prescribed in the Minimum Wages (Central) Rules, 1950 made under sections 18 and 30 of the Minimum Wages Act, 1948 (11 of 1948) and slips relating to measurement of the amount of work done by piece-rated workers required to be issued under the Payment of Wages (Mines) Rules, 1956 made under sections 13A and 26 of the Payment of Wages Act, 1936 (4 of 1936); and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>file returns relating to accidents under sections 88 and 88A of the Factories Act, 1948 (63 of 1948) and sections 32A and 32B of the Plantations Labour Act, 1951 (69 of 1951).</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Save as provided in sub-section (1), all other provisions of a Scheduled Act, including in particular, the inspection of the registers by, and furnishing of their copies to, the authorities under that Act, shall apply to the returns and registers required to be furnished or maintained under this Act as they apply to the returns and registers under that Scheduled Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an employer in relation to a small establishment or very small establishment to which a Scheduled Act applies, furnishes returns or maintains the registers as provided in the proviso to sub-section (1), nothing contained in that Scheduled Act shall render him liable to any penalty for his failure to furnish any return or to maintain any register under that Scheduled Act,</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Savings.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The commencement of this Act shall not affect—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the previous operation of any provision of any Scheduled Act or the validity, invalidity, effect or consequence of anything done or suffered under that provision, before the relevant period;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any right, privilege, obligation or liability already acquired, accrued or incurred under any Scheduled Act, before the relevant period;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any penalty, forfeiture or punishment incurred or inflicted in respect of any offence committed under any Scheduled Act, before the relevant period;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>any investigation, legal proceeding or remedy in respect of any such right, privilege, obligation, liability, penalty, forfeiture or punishment aforesaid,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>and any such investigation, legal proceeding or remedy in respect of any such right, privilege, obligation, liability, penalty, forfeiture or punishment shall be instituted, continued or disposed of, as the case may be, in accordance with that Scheduled Act.</p>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <p>For the purpose of this section, the expression “relevant period” means the period during which an establishment is or was a small establishment or a very small establishment under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Penalty.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any employer who fails to comply with the provisions of this Act shall, on conviction, be punishable—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in the case of the first conviction, with fine which may extend to rupees five thousand; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>in the case of any second or subsequent conviction, with imprisonment for a period which shall not be less than one month but which may extend to six months or with fine which shall not be less than rupees ten thousand but may extend to rupees twenty-five thousand, or with both.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Power to amend Form.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, if it is of opinion that it is expedient so to do, by notification in the Official Gazette, amend any Form and thereupon such Form shall, subject to the provisions of sub-section (2), be deemed to have been amended accordingly.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any notification issued under sub-section (1) shall be laid before each House of Parliament, if it is sitting as soon as may be after the issue of the notification, and if it is not sitting, within seven days of its re-assembly and the Central Government shall seek the approval of Parliament to the notification by a resolution moved within a period of fifteen days beginning with the day on which the notification is so laid before the House of the People, and if Parliament makes any modification in the notification or directs that the notification should cease to have effect, the notification shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be, but without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Power to remove difficulties.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government may, by order, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, remove the difficulty:</p>
            <p>Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a period of two years from the date on which this Act receives the assent of the President.</p>
            <p>The Labour Laws (Exemption From Furnishing Returns And maintaining Registers by certain Establishments) Act, 1988</p>
            <p>First Schedule</p>
            <p>See section 2(d)</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Payment of Wages Act, 1936 (4 of 1936).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Weekly Holidays Act, 1942 (18 of 1942).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Minimum Wages Act, 1948 (11 of 1948).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Factories Act, 1948 (63 of 1948).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Plantations Labour Act, 1951 (69 of 1951).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Working Journalists and other Newspaper Employees (Conditions of Service) and Miscellaneous Provisions Act, 1955 (45 of 1955).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Contract Labour (Regulation and Abolition) Act, 1970 (37 of 1970).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Sales Promotion Employees (Conditions of Service) Act, 1976 (11 of 1976).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.9">
          <num>(9)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Equal Remuneration Act, 1976 (25 of 1976).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
