<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1948/14/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1948/14"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Damodar Valley Corporation Act, 1948"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1948/14/eng@1948-03-27/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1948/14/eng@1948-03-27"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1948-03-27" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1948/14/eng@1948-03-27/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1948/14/eng@1948-03-27"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Damodar Valley Corporation Act, 1948</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 14 OF 1948</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 27th March, 1948.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the establishment and regulation of a</p>
        <p>Corporation for the development of the Damodar Valley in the Provinces  of Bihar and West Bengal.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the establishment and  regulation of a Corporation for the development of the Damodar Valley  in the Provinces of Bihar and West Bengal:</p>
        <p>AND WHEREAS in pursuance of section 103 of the Government of</p>
        <p>India Act, 1935, (26 Geo. 5, c. 2.) resolutions have been passed by  all the Chambers of the Provincial Legislatures of the said Provinces  to the effect that certain matters dealt with in this Act which are  enumerated in the Provincial Legislative List should be regulated in  those Provinces by Act of the Dominion Legislature;</p>
        <p>It is hereby enacted as follows:-</p>
        <p>PART</p>
        <p>INTRODUCTORY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <part id="part-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="part-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>INTRODUCTORY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be  called the Damodar Valley Corporation Act, 1948.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It extends to the States of Bihar and West Bengal.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on such date  as the Central</p>
              <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint in  this behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Interpretation. In this Act, unless there is anything  repugnant in the subject or context,-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-2.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" Corporation" means the Damodar Valley Corporation;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" Damodar Valley" includes the basin of the Damodar  river and its tributaries;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" member" means a member of the Corporation and includes  the Chairman;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" participating Governments" means the Central</p>
              <p>Government, the State Government of Bihar and the State</p>
              <p>Government of West Bengal;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under  section 59;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" State Government" means the Government of Bihar or as  the case may be of West Bengal, and" State Government"</p>
              <p>means the Governments of Bihar and West Bengal;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" regulations" means the regulations made by the</p>
              <p>Corporation under section 60.</p>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>ESTABLISHMENT OF THE CORPORATION</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="part-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>ESTABLISHMENT OF THE CORPORATION</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Incorporation.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>With effect from such date  as the</p>
              <p>Central Government may, by notification in the official Gazette,</p>
              <p>appoint in this behalf, there shall be established a Corporation by  the name of the Damodar Valley Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The said Corporation shall be a body corporate having  perpetual succession and a common seal, and shall by the said name sue  and be sued.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Constitution of the Corporation.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Corporation shall  consist of a Chairman and two other members appointed by the Central</p>
              <p>Government after consultation with the State Governments.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-4.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>A person shall be disqualified for being appointed, or for  continuing as, a member of the Corporation--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>if he is a member of  Parliament] or any State</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-4.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Legislature; or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.2.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>if he has, directly or indirectly, any interest in a  subsisting contract made with, or in any work being  done for, the Corporation except as a shareholder</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>(other than a director) in an incorporated company  provided that where he is a shareholder, he shall  disclose to the Government the nature and extent of  shares held by him in such Company.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No act or proceeding of the Corporation shall be invalid by  reason only of the existence of any vacancy amongst its members or any  defect in the appointment of a member thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Conditions of service of members.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The remuneration and other conditions of service of the  members shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Appointment of officers and servants.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The secretary and  the financial adviser of the Corporation shall be appointed by the</p>
              <p>Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The secretary shall be the chief executive officer of the  corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Corporation may appoint such other officers and servants  as it considers necessary for the efficient performance of its  functions.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Conditions of service of officers and servants. The pay and  other conditions of service of the officers and servants of the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Corporation shall-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>as respects the secretary and financial adviser, be  such as may be prescribed; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>as respects the other officers and servants, be such as  may be determined by regulations.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Functions and duties of the financial adviser. The functions  and duties of the financial adviser shall be such as may be  prescribed.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>General disqualification of all officers and servants. No  person who has directly or indirectly, by himself or his partner or  agent, any share or interest in any contract, by or on behalf of the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Corporation, or in any employment under, by or on behalf of the</p>
              <p>Corporation otherwise than as an officer or servant thereof, shall  become or remain an officer or servant of the Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Appointment of Advisory Committee. Subject to any rules made  under section 59 the Corporation may from time to time appoint one or  more Advisory Committees for the purpose of securing the efficient  discharge of the functions of the Corporation, and in particular for  the purpose of securing that those functions are exercised with due  regard to the circumstances and requirements of particular local  areas.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>FUNCTIONS AND POWERS OF THE CORPORATION</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="part-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>FUNCTIONS AND POWERS OF THE CORPORATION</p>
            <p>General</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Limits of Damodar Valley and area of operations.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The</p>
              <p>Central Government shall, by notification in the Official Gazette,</p>
              <p>specify the limits of the Damodar Valley.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The corporation shall carry out all or any of its functions  and exercise all or any of its powers within the Damodar Valley.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, after consultation with the State</p>
              <p>Governments by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that the</p>
              <p>Corporation shall carry out such function and exercise such power in  such other area as may be specified therein and the area so specified  shall be called the" area of operation" of the Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Functions of the Corporation. The functions of the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Corporation shall be--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the promotion and operation of schemes for the  generation, water- supply and drainage,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the promotion and operation of schemes for the  generation, transmission and distribution of electrical  energy, both hydro- electric and thermal,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the promotion and operation of schemes for flood  control in the Damodar river and its tributaries and  the channels, if any, excavated by the Corporation in  connection with the scheme and for the improvement of  flow conditions in the Hooghly river,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the promotion and control of navigation in the Damodar  river and its tributaries and channels, if any,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the promotion of afforestation and control of soil  erosion in the Damodar Valley, and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the promotion of public health and the agricultural,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>industrial, economic and general well- being in the</p>
              <p>Damodar Valley and its area of operation.</p>
              <p>Irrigation and water- supply</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Provision for irrigation and water- supply. The Corporation  may, with the approval of the State Government concerned which shall  not be unreasonably withheld, construct canals and distributaries and  maintain and operate them:</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Provided that the State Government may, after giving notice and  subject to the payment of fair compensation, take over the maintenance  and operation of any such canal or distributary.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Rates for supply of water for irrigation.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Corporation  may, after consultation with the State Government concerned, determine  and levy rates for the bulk supply of water to that Government for  irrigation, and fix the minimum quantity of water which shall be made  available for such purpose.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The rates at which such water shall be supplied by the State</p>
              <p>Government to the cultivators and other consumers shall be fixed by  that Government after consultation with the Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Rates for supply of water for industrial and domestic  purposes. The Corporation may determine and levy rates for bulk supply  and retail distribution of water for industrial and domestic purposes  and specify the manner of recovery of such rates.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Supply of water to those whose supply has been stopped or  reduced. If, with a view to operating its schemes, the Corporation has  stopped or reduced the supply of water to any person for agricultural,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>industrial or domestic purposes which such person was, prior to such  stoppage or reduction, enjoying by virtue of any prescriptive right,</p>
              <p>the Corporation shall arrange such supply of water on the same terms  as before.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Construction of dam, etc., prohibited except with the  approval of the Corporation. Save as otherwise prescribed, no person  shall construct, operate or maintain in the Damodar Valley any dam or  other work or any installation for the extraction of water without the  consent of the Corporation.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Supply and generation of electrical energy</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Supply and generation of electrical energy. Notwithstanding  anything contained in the Indian Electricity Act, 1910 (9 of 1910), or  any licence granted thereunder--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-18.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list0.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>No person shall without the permission of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-18.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Corporation--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>sell electrical energy to any consumer in  the Damodar Valley where the energy is taken by  the consumer at a pressure of 30, 000 volts or  more;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>transmit electrical energy in the Damodar</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-18.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Valley at a pressure of 30, 000 volts or more;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list4.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>generate any electrical energy at an  installation having an aggregate capacity of more  than 10, 000 kilowatts in any part of the Damodar</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Valley lying to the north of the straight line  drawn east to west passing through a point at  latitude twenty- two degrees, fourteen minutes and  forty- seven seconds and longitude eighty- seven  degrees, fifty- one minutes and forty- two seconds  except such portion of the municipal area of</p>
              <p>Burdwan as may lie to the north of such straight  line:</p>
              <p>Provided that nothing in sub- clause (c) shall  apply to any person who was, at the commencement  of this Act, generating electrical energy at an  installation having</p>
              <p>an aggregate capacity of more than 10, 000  kilowatts, so long as the capacity of such  installation is not increased:</p>
              <blockList id="section-18.paragraph-0.list10">
                <listIntroduction>Provided further that nothing in sub- clause</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list10.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-18.paragraph-0.list10.c.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>shall apply to the power station installation  of the fertiliser factory at Sindri having an  aggregate capacity of 80, 000 kilowatts so long as  the capacity of such installation is not increased  beyond 80, 000 kilowatts.</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list10.c.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>The Corporation may sell electrical energy to any  consumer in the Damodar Valley but no such sale shall,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-18.paragraph-0.list12">
                <listIntroduction>except with the permission of the State Government  concerned, be made to any consumer requiring supply at  a pressure of less than 30, 000 volts.</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list12.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>The Corporation may, with the permission of the State</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Government concerned, extend its transmission system to  any area beyond the Damodar Valley and sell electrical  energy in such area.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Effect on existing licences.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-19.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where any licence granted  under the Indian Electricity Act, 1910 (9 of 1910), becomes  inoperative wholly or partly by virtue of the provisions of section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>, the licence shall be deemed to have been revoked or modified so as  to be consistent with those provisions.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-18.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where a licence is deemed to have been revoked under  sub- section (1) the Corporation shall purchase the undertaking of the  licencee, and where a licence is modified under that sub- section, the</p>
              <p>Corporation shall, at the option of the licensee, either purchase the  undertaking or pay fair compensation to the licensee.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The purchase price or the amount of compensation payable by  the corporation under sub- section (2) shall be such as may be agreed  to between the Corporation and the licensee or, in the event of  disagreement, as may be determined by arbitration.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Charges for supply of electrical energy. The Corporation  shall fix the schedule of charges for the supply of electrical energy,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>including the rates for bulk supply and retail distribution, and  specify the manner of recovery of such charges:</p>
              <p>Provided that the Corporation may in any contract for bulk supply  of electrical energy impose such terms and conditions including a  retail rate schedule as it may deem necessary or desirable to  encourage the use of electrical energy.</p>
              <p>Other activities</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Other activities of the Corporation.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-21.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-21.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Corporation may  establish, maintain and operate laboratories, experimental and  research stations and farms for conducting experiments and research  for--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-21.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>utilising the water, electrical energy and other  resources in the most economical manner for the  development of the Damodar Valley,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>determining the effect of its operations on the flow  conditions in the Hooghly river,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>making improvements in navigation conditions in the  port of Calcutta, and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>carrying out any other function specified under section</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Corporation may set up its own planning, designing,</p>
              <p>construction and operating agencies, or make arrangements therefor  with the participating Governments, local authorities, educational and  research institutions or any person carrying on the business of an  architect, an engineer or a contractor.</p>
              <p>Powers</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>General powers of the Corporation.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-22.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Corporation shall  have the power to do anything which may be necessary or expedient for  the purposes of carrying out its functions under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-22.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing  provision, such power shall include the power--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-22.2.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>to acquire and hold such movable and immovable property  as it may deem necessary and to lease, sell or  otherwise transfer any such property;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-22.2.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>to construct or cause to be constructed such dams,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>barrages, reservoirs, power houses, power structures,</p>
              <p>electrical transmission lines and sub- stations,</p>
              <blockList id="section-22.2.list5">
                <listIntroduction>navigation works, irrigation, navigation and drainage  canals and such other works and structures as may be  required;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-22.2.list5.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>to prevent pollution of any water under its control  and to take all measures to prevent discharges  into such water effluents which are harmful to  water supply, irrigation, public health or fish life;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-22.2.list5.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>to stock its reservoirs or water courses with fish and  to regulate or prohibit taking out fish from the water  under its control;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-22.2.list5.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>to undertake resettlement of the population displaced  by the dams, acquisition of land for reservoirs and  protection of watersheds;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-22.2.list5.vi">
                  <num>(vi)</num>
                  <p>to aid in the establishment of co- operative societies  and other organisations for the better use of  facilities made available by the Corporation;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-22.2.list5.vii">
                  <num>(vii)</num>
                  <p>to undertake measures for the prevention of malaria.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Power to close roads and open spaces.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-23.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-23.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Corporation  may, after giving notice to the persons concerned or to the public  generally,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-23.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>turn, divert or discontinue the public use of, or  permanently close, any road or any part thereof, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>discontinue the public use of, or permanently close,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>any open space or any part thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-23.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Whenever the Corporation discontinues the public use of, or  permanently closes, any road or open space the Corporation shall pay  reasonable compensation to every person--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-23.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>who was entitled, otherwise than as a licensee, to use  such road or open space or part thereof as a means of  access, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>Whose immovable property was receiving air and light on  account of such open space or part,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-23.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>and who has suffered damage--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-23.2.list3.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>in any case falling under clause (a) from such  discontinuance or closure and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.2.list3.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>in any case falling under clause (b) from the use to  which the Corporation has put such open space or part.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In determining the compensation payable to any person under  sub- section (2), the Corporation may take into consideration any  benefit accruing to such person from the construction, provision or  improvement of any other road, or open space at or about the same time  that the road or open space or part thereof, on account of which the  compensation is to be paid, is discontinued or closed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When any road or open space or any part thereof is  permanently closed under sub- section (1), the Corporation may sell or  leave such part of it as is not required for its purposes.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Powers under certain other enactments.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-24.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding  anything contained in the Acts specified in column one of Part I of  the Schedule, the Corporation may carry out all or any of the  functions and exercise all or any of the powers</p>
              <p>of a State Government in the Damodar Valley under the provisions of  such Acts specified in column two thereof against each item of column  one.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-24.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Acts specified in  column one of Part II of the Schedule, any officer authorized by the</p>
              <p>Corporation may carry out all or any of the functions and exercise all  or any of the powers of a Canal Officer, Collector, or Forest Officer,</p>
              <p>as the case may be, in the Damodar Valley under the provisions of such</p>
              <p>Acts specified in column two thereof against each item of column one.</p>
              <p>Co- operation and avoidance of submersion</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Co- operation with other authorities to minimise inconvenience  caused by submersion. The Corporation shall co- operate with the  participating Governments, railway authorities and local authorities  and bodies, with a view to minimising the inconvenience likely to be  caused by the submersion of roads and communications and shall bear  the cost of any realignment thereof or resettlement of any population  rendered necessary by such submersion.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Submersion of coal mines to be avoided by the Corporation.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Corporation shall make every endeavour to avoid submersion of coal  or mineral deposits and shall co- operate with the coal mining industry  and the bodies set up by the participating Governments to ensure the  maintenance of supplies of sand for stowing purposes in coal mines and  in other ways to minimise the inconvenience to the coal mining  industry.</p>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="part-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Expenditure till the Corporation is established. All  expenditure incurred by the Central Government for and in connection  with the establishment of the Corporation up to the date of its  establishment shall be treated as the capital provided by the Central</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government to the Corporation and such capital shall be adjusted  between the participating Governments in accordance with the  provisions of sections 30 to 36.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Vetting of property in the Corporation. All property acquired  and works constructed for the purposes of the Damodar Valley scheme  before the establishment of the Corporation shall vest in the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Corporation and all income derived and expenses incurred in this  behalf shall be brought into the books of the Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Fund of the Corporation.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-29.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Corporation shall have its  own fund and all receipts of the Corporation shall be carried thereto  and all payments by the Corporation shall be made therefrom.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except as otherwise directed by the Central Government, all  moneys belonging to that fund shall be deposited in the Reserve Bank  of India or the Agents of the Reserve Bank of India or invested in  such securities as may be approved by the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading>Liabilities of participating Governments to provide capital  to the Corporation. The participating Governments shall, as  hereinafter specified, provide the entire capital required by the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-30.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Corporation for the completion of any project undertaken by it.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading>Payment by participating Government on specified date. Each  participating Government shall provide its share of the capital on the  dates specified by the Corporation and if any Government fails to  provide such share on such dates the Corporation may raise loan to  make up the deficit at the cost of the Government concerned.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>Expenditure on objects other than irrigation, power and flood  control. The Corporation shall have power to spend such sums as it  thinks fit on objects authorized under this Act other than irrigation,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-32.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>power and flood control and such sums shall be treated as common  expenditure payable out of the fund of the Corporation before  allocation under section 32</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading>Allocation of expenditure chargeable to project on main  objects. The total capital expenditure chargeable to a project shall  be allocated between the three main objects, namely, irrigation, power  and flood control as follows, namely:-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-33.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>expenditure solely attributable to any of these  objects, including a proportionate share of overhead  and general charges, shall be charged to that object,</p>
              <p>and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-33.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>expenditure common to two or more of the said objects,</p>
              <p>including a proportionate share of overhead and general  charges, shall be allocated to each of such objects in  proportion to the expenditure which, according to the  estimates of the Corporation, would have been incurred  in constructing a separate structure solely for that  object, less any amount determined under clause (1) in  respect of that object.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-34">
          <num>34.</num>
          <heading>Capital allocated to irrigation. The total amount of capital  allocated to irrigation shall be shared between the State Governments  as follows, namely:-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-34.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the Government concerned shall be responsible for  capital cost of the works constructed exclusively for  irrigation in its State; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-34.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the balance of capital cost under irrigation for both  the States of Bihar and West Bengal shall be shared by  the State Governments in the proportion to their  guaranteed annual off- takes of water for agricultural  purposes:</p>
              <p>Provided that the divisible capital cost  under this clause shall be provisionally shared  between them in accordance with their previously  declared intentions regarding their respective  guaranteed off- takes and any payments made  accordingly shall be adjusted after the  determination of the guaranteed off- takes.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading>Capital allocated to power. The total amount of capital  allocated to power shall be shared equally between the three  participating Governments.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-36">
          <num>36.</num>
          <heading>Capital allocated to flood control. The total amount of  capital up to fourteen crores of rupees allocated to flood control  shall be shared equally between the Central Government and the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-36.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government of West Bengal and any amount in excess thereof shall be  the liability of the Government of West Bengal.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-37">
          <num>37.</num>
          <heading>Disposal of profits and deficits.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-37.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the  provisions of sub- section (2) of section 40, the net profit, if any,</p>
              <p>attributable to each of the three main objects, namely, irrigation,</p>
              <p>power and flood control, shall be credited to the participating</p>
              <p>Governments in proportion to their respective shares in the total  capital cost attributed to that object.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-37.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The net deficit, if any, in respect of any of the objects  shall be made good by the Governments concerned in the proportion  specified in sub- section (1):</p>
              <p>Provided that the net deficit in respect of flood control shall  be made good entirely by the Government of West Bengal and the Central</p>
              <p>Government shall have no share in such deficit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-38">
          <num>38.</num>
          <heading>Payment of interest. The Corporation shall pay interest on  the amount of capital provided by each participating Government at  such rate as may, from time to time, be fixed by the Central</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-38.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government and such interest shall be deemed to be part of the  expenditure of the Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-39">
          <num>39.</num>
          <heading>Interest charge and other expenses to be added to and  receipts taken for reduction of capital cost. For a period, not  exceeding fifteen years, from the establishment of the Corporation, if  the Corporation runs in deficit, the interest</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-39.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>charges and all other expenditure shall be added to the capital cost  and all receipts shall be taken in reduction of such capital cost.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-40">
          <num>40.</num>
          <heading>Provision for depreciation and reserve and other funds.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-40.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Corporation shall make provision for depreciation and for reserve  and other funds at such rates and on such terms as may be specified by  the Auditor- General of India in consultation with the Central</p>
              <p>Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-40.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The net profit for the purposes of section 37 shall be  determined after such provision has been made.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-41">
          <num>41.</num>
          <heading>Corporation' s share in betterment levy by State Governments.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-41.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>In the event of any betterment levy being imposed by a State</p>
              <p>Government, the proportionate proceeds thereof in so far as they are  attributable to the operations of the corporation shall be credited to  the Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-42">
          <num>42.</num>
          <heading>Borrowing of money.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-42.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Corporation may, with the  approval of the Central Government, borrow money in the open market or  otherwise for the purposes of carrying out its functions under this</p>
              <p>Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-43">
          <num>43.</num>
          <heading>Liability to pay Central taxes.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-43.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Corporation shall be  liable to pay any taxes on income levied by the Central Government in  the same manner and to the same extent as a company.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-43.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Governments shall not be entitled to any refund of  any such taxes paid by the Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-44">
          <num>44.</num>
          <heading>Budget.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-44.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Corporation, in consultation with the  financial adviser, shall in October each year prepare in such form as  may be prescribed a budget for the next financial year showing the  estimated receipts and expenditure and the amounts which would be  required from each of the three participating Governments during that  financial year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-44.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Printed copies of the budget shall be made available to each  of the three participating Governments by the 15th day of November  each year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-44.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The budget shall be laid before  Parliament] and the State</p>
              <p>Legislatures concerned as soon as may be after it is prepared.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-45">
          <num>45.</num>
          <heading>Annual report.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-45.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Corporation shall prepare, in such  from as may be prescribed, an annual report within six months after  the end of each</p>
              <blockList id="section-45.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>financial year giving a true and faithful account of its activities  during the previous financial year, with particular reference to--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-45.1.list2.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>irrigation;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-45.1.list2.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>water supply;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-45.1.list2.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>electrical energy;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-45.1.list2.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>flood control;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-45.1.list2.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>navigation;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-45.1.list2.vi">
                  <num>(vi)</num>
                  <p>afforestation;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-45.1.list2.vii">
                  <num>(vii)</num>
                  <p>soil erosion;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-45.1.list2.viii">
                  <num>(viii)</num>
                  <p>use of lands;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-45.1.list2.ix">
                  <num>(ix)</num>
                  <p>resettlement of displaced population;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-45.1.list2.x">
                  <num>(x)</num>
                  <p>sanitation and public health measures; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-45.1.list2.xi">
                  <num>(xi)</num>
                  <p>economic and social welfare of the people.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The annual report shall also give a true and faithful account  of the income and expenditure during the previous financial year, the  net amounts attributable to each of the three main objects and the  distribution of the capital cost between the three participating</p>
              <p>Governments and show the progressive totals from the inception of the</p>
              <p>Corporation and the up- to- date financial results.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The payments provisionally made by each of the three  participating Governments on the basis of the budget estimates shall  be adjusted as soon as possible in accordance with the allocation made  in the annual report.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Printed copies of the annual report shall be made available  to each of the three participating Governments by the 15th day of</p>
              <p>October each year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The annual report shall be laid before  Parliament] and the</p>
              <p>State Legislatures concerned as soon as may be after it is prepared.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-46">
          <num>46.</num>
          <heading>Other annual financial statements.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-46.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Corporation shall  also prepare such other annual financial statements in such form and  by such dates as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-46.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Printed copies of each such annual financial statement shall  be made available to each of the three participating Governments by  such date as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-47">
          <num>47.</num>
          <heading>Accounts and audit. The accounts of the Corporation shall be  maintained and audited in such manner as may, in consultation with the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-47.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Auditor- General of India, be prescribed.</p>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <paragraph id="part-V.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-48">
          <num>48.</num>
          <heading>Directions by the Central Government.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-48.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In discharge of its  functions the Corporation shall be guided by such instructions on  questions of policy as may be given to it by the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-48.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any dispute arises between the Central Government and the</p>
              <p>Corporation as to whether a question is or is not a question of  policy, the decision of the Central Government shall be final.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-49">
          <num>49.</num>
          <heading>Disputes between the Corporation and Governments.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-49.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Save as  otherwise expressly provided in this Act, any dispute between the</p>
              <p>Corporation and any participating Government regarding any matter  covered by this Act or touching or arising out of it shall be referred  to an arbitrator who shall be appointed by the Chief Justice of India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-49.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The decision of the arbitrator shall be final and binding on  the parties.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-50">
          <num>50.</num>
          <heading>Compulsory acquisition of land for the Corporation. Any land  required by the Corporation for carrying out its functions under this</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-50.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Act shall be deemed to be needed to be needed for a public purpose and  such land shall be acquired for the Corporation as if the provisions  of Part VII of the Land Acquisition Act, 1894 (1 of 1894), were  applicable to it and the Corporation were a company within the  meaning of clause (e) of section 3 of the said Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-51">
          <num>51.</num>
          <heading>Control of Central Government.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-51.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-51.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Central Government may  remove from the Corporation any member who in its opinion--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-51.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>refuses to act,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-51.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>has become incapable of acting,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-51.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>has so abused his position as a member as to render his  continuance on the Corporation detrimental to the  interest of the public, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-51.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>is otherwise unsuitable to continue as member.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-51.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may suspend any member pending an  enquiry against him.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-51.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No order of removal under this section shall be made unless  the member concerned has been given an opportunity to submit his  explanation to the Central Government, and when such order is passed  the seat of the member removed shall be declared vacant and another  member may be appointed under section 4 to fill up the vacancy.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-51.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A member who has been removed shall not be eligible for  reappointment as member or in any other capacity to the Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-51.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may declare void any transaction in  connection with which a member has been removed under sub- section (1).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-51.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the Corporation fails to carry out its functions, or  follow the directions issued by the Central Government under this Act,</p>
              <p>the Central Government shall have the power to remove the Chairman and  the members of the Corporation and appoint a Chairman and members in  their places.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-52">
          <num>52.</num>
          <heading>Application of certain provisions of the Indian Forest Act,</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1927">
          <num>1927.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1927.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>, to the forests of the Corporation. All acts prohibited in  respect of a reserved forest under section 26 of the Indian Forest</p>
              <p>Act, 1927 (16 of 1927.) shall be deemed to be prohibited in respect of  any forest owned by or under the supervision or control of the</p>
              <p>Corporation and all offences in respect of such forest shall be  punishable under the said Act as if they were committed in respect of  a reserved forest.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-53">
          <num>53.</num>
          <heading>Penalty. Whoever contravenes the provisions of sections 17  and 18 of this Act or any rule made thereunder shall be punished with  imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months or with fine or  with both.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-54">
          <num>54.</num>
          <heading>Procedure for prosecution. No Court shall take cognisance of  an offence under this Act except on the complaint of an officer of the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-54.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Corporation authorized by it in this behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-55">
          <num>55.</num>
          <heading>Power of entry. Any officer or servant of the Corporation  generally or specially authorized by the Corporation may at all  reasonable times enter upon any land or premises and there do such  things as may be reasonably necessary for the purpose of lawfully  carrying out any of its works or of making any survey, examination or  investigation preliminary or incidental to the exercise of powers or  the performance of functions by the Corporation under this Act.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-56">
          <num>56.</num>
          <heading>Members, officers and servants of the Corporation to be  public servants. All members, officers and servants of the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-56.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Corporation, whether appointed by the Central Government or the</p>
              <p>Corporation, shall be deemed, when acting or purporting to act in  pursuance of any of the provisions of this Act to be public servants  within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code. (45 of</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1860">
          <num>1860.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1860.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>)</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-57">
          <num>57.</num>
          <heading>Protection of action of action taken under the Act.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-57.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No  suit, prosecution, or legal proceeding shall lie against any person in  the employment of the Corporation for anything which is in good faith  done or purported to be done under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-57.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Save as otherwise provided in the Act no suit or other legal  proceeding shall lie against the Corporation for any damage caused</p>
              <p>or likely to be caused by anything in good faith done or purported to  be done under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-58">
          <num>58.</num>
          <heading>Effect of other laws. The provisions of this Act or any rule  made thereunder shall have effect notwithstanding anything contained  in any enactment other than this Act or any instrument having effect  by virtue of any enactment other than this Act.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-59">
          <num>59.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules. The Central Government may, by  notification in the official Gazette, make rules to provide for all or  any of the following matters, namely:--</heading>
          <subsection id="section-59.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the salaries and allowances and conditions of service  of members, the secretary and the financial adviser;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the functions and duties of the financial adviser;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the dams or other works or the installations which may  be constructed without the approval of the Corporation;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the forms of the budget, the annual report and the  annual financial statements and the dates by which  copies of the annual financial statements shall be made  available to the participating Governments;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the manner in which the accounts of the Corporation  shall be maintained and audited;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the appointment of an Advisory Committee; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-59.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>the punishment for breach of any rule made under this</p>
              <p>Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-60">
          <num>60.</num>
          <heading>Power to make regulations.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-60.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Corporation may, with the  previous sanction of the Central Government, by notification in the</p>
              <p>Gazette of India, make regulations for carrying out its functions  under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-60.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-60.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, in such regulation the Corporation may make provision  for--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-60.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>making of appointments and promotions of its officers  and servants;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-60.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>specifying other conditions of service of its officers  and servants;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-60.2.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>specifying the manner in which water rates and charges  for electrical energy shall be recovered;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-60.2.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>preventing the pollution of water under its control;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-60.2.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>regulating the taking out of fish from the water under  its control;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-60.2.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>regulating its proceedings and business;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-60.2.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>prescribing punishment for breach of any regulation.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-60.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All regulations made under sub- sections (1) and (2) shall, as  soon as possible, be published also in the Official Gazettes of the</p>
              <p>State Governments.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </part>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
