<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1910/10/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1910/10"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Indian Museum Act, 1910"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1910/10/eng@1910-03-18/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1910/10/eng@1910-03-18"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1910-03-18" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1910/10/eng@1910-03-18/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1910/10/eng@1910-03-18"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Indian Museum Act, 1910</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 10 OF 1910</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 18th March, 1910.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to consolidate and amend the law relating to the Indian Museum.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to consolidate and amend the law relating  to the Indian Museum; It is hereby enacted as follows:-</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Indian Museum Act, 1910.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such  date as the Central</p>
            <p>Government, by notification in the Official Gazette, may direct.</p>
            <p>INCORPORATION OF THE TRUSTEES</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Constitution and incorporation of the Trustees of the Indian</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Museum.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Trustees of the Indian Museum (hereinafter referred   to as the Trustees) shall be-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the Governor of West Bengal, ex officio chairman:</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the Secretary to the Government of India in the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Ministry concerned with matters relating to the Indian</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Museum, ex officio;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the Mayor of the Corporation of Calcutta, ex officio;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list4.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the Vice- Chancellor of the University of Calcutta, ex  officio;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list4.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the Accountant- General, West Bengal, ex officio;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list4.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>four persons to be nominated by the Central Government,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>one of whom shall be a representative of commerce and  industry chosen in consultation with the Government of</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list7">
              <listIntroduction>West Bengal;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list7.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>one person to be nominated by the Government of West</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list9">
              <listIntroduction>Bengal;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list9.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>one person to be nominated by the Council of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Asiatic Society, Calcutta:</p>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list12">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that if any of the Trustees referred to in clauses</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list12.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>, (c), (d) and (e) is unable to attend any meeting of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Trustees, he may, with the previous approval of the</p>
            <p>Chairman, authorise a person in writing to do so.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Trustees shall be a body corporate, by the name of" The</p>
            <p>Trustees of the Indian Museum", with perpetual succession and a common  seal, and in that name shall sue and be sued, and shall have power to  acquire and hold property, to enter into contracts, and to do all acts  necessary for and consistent with the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The nominated Trustees shall, save as herein otherwise  provided, hold office for a period of three years:</p>
            <p>Provided that the authority nominating a Trustee may extend his  term of office for one or more like periods.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Minimum number of Trustees and quorum.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The powers of the  said body corporate may only be exercised so long and so often as  there are  six] members thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The quorum necessary for the transaction of business at a  meeting of the Trustees shall not be less than  four].</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Power to appoint new Trustees. If a nominated Trustee-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>dies, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>is absent from the meetings of the Trustees for more  than twelve consecutive months, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>desires to be discharged, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>refuses or becomes incapable to act, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>is appointed to perform the duties of  any of the  offices specified in clauses (a) to (e) of sub- section</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of section 2],</p>
            <p>the authority which nominated the Trustee may nominate a new</p>
            <p>Trustee in his place.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Vacation of office by existing Trustees. Rep. by the Indian</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Museum (Amendment) Act. 1960 (45 of 1960), s. 5.</p>
            <p>PROPERTY AND POWERS OF THE TRUSTEES</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Property vested in or placed under the control of the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Trustees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All the property, whether movable or immovable, which at  the commencement of this Act is held by the Trustees of the Indian</p>
            <p>Museum constituted by the  Indian Museum Act, 1876 (22 of 1876), on  trust for the purposes of the said Museum shall, together with any  such</p>
            <p>property which may hereinafter be given, bequeathed, transferred or  acquired for the said purposes, vest in the Trustees of the Indian</p>
            <p>Museum constituted by this Act on trust for the purposes of the said</p>
            <p>Museum:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Trustees may expend the capital of any portion  of such property which may consist of money on the maintenance,</p>
            <p>improvement and enlargement of the collections deposited in, presented  to or purchased for, the said Museum or otherwise for the purposes of  the same as they may think fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Trustees shall have the exclusive possession, occupation  and control, for the purposes of such trust, of the land specified in  the schedule, including any buildings which may have been, or may  here- after be, erected thereon, other than those portions thereof  which have been set apart by the Trustees for the records and offices  of the Geological Survey of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Power to Trustees to exchange, sell and destroy articles in  collections. Subject to the provisions of any bye- laws made in this  behalf, the Trustees may, from time to time,-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>deliver, by way of loan, to any person the whole or any  portion of, or any article contained in, any collection  vested in them under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>exchange or sell duplicates of articles contained in  any such collection and take or purchase, in the place  of such duplicates, such articles as may in their  opinion be worthy of preservation in the Museum;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>present duplicates of articles contained in any such  collection to other Museums in  India]; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>remove and destroy any article contained in any such  collection.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Power to Trustees to make bye- laws.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Trustees may from  time to time, with the previous sanction of the Central Government,</p>
            <p>make, by notification in the Official Gazette, bye- laws] consistent  with this Act  and the rules made thereunder] for any purpose  necessary for the execution of their trust.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such  bye- laws] may provide for-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the summoning, holding and adjournment of general and  special meetings of the Trustees;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the securing of the attendance of Trustees at such  meetings;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the provision and keeping of minute- books and account-</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-8.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>books;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.2.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the compiling of catalogues;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the lending of articles contained in the collections  vested in the Trustees;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list3.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the exchange and sale, and the presentation to other</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-8.2.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Museums in  India], of duplicates of articles  contained in such collections;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.2.list5.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the removal and destruction of articles contained in  such collections; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list5.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the general management of the Museum.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government shall cause every bye- law made  under this section to be laid as soon as may be after it is made,</p>
            <p>before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total  period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two  or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session  immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the bye- law  or both Houses agree that the bye- law should not be made, the bye- law  shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no  effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that bye- law.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Powers of Trustees to appoint officers and servants.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (2), the Trustees may appoint  such officers and servants as they may consider necessary or proper  for the care or management of the trust- property, and determine their  functions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The recruitment and the conditions of service of such  officers and servants shall be regulated by rules made under this</p>
            <p>Act.]</p>
            <p>DUTIES OF THE TRUSTEES</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Budget. The Trustees shall, by such date in each financial  year as may be specified by the Central Government, submit to that</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Government for approval, in the form specified by that Government in  consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India, the  budget of the next financial year, showing the estimated receipts and  expenditure during the next financial year.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10A">
        <num>10A.</num>
        <heading>Annual report and accounts.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10A.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Trustees shall, as soon  as possible after the commencement of each financial year, submit-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10A.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to the Central Government within such time or date as  may be specified by the Central Government, a report  giving a true and full account of their activities  during the previous financial year and an account of  the activities likely to be undertaken during the  current financial year;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10A.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to such auditor as the Central Government may appoint  in this behalf, accounts of all moneys expended by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Trustees during the previous financial year, supported  by the necessary vouchers.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Trustees shall cause such report and accounts to be  published annually for general information.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Collections of Asiatic society to be kept distinguished in  the Museum.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Trustees shall cause every article in the  collections in the said Indian Museum formerly belonging to the</p>
            <p>Asiatic Society of Bengal  (now known as the Asiatic Society,</p>
            <p>Calcutta)] and all additions that may hereafter be made thereto  otherwise than by purchase under section 6, to be marked and numbered  and (subject to the provisions contained in sections 7 and 16) to be  kept and preserved in the said Museum with such marks and numbers.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An inventory of such additions shall be made by the said</p>
            <p>Society, one copy whereof shall be signed by the Trustees and  delivered to the said Society, and another copy shall be signed by the</p>
            <p>Council of the said Society and delivered to the Trustees, and shall  be kept by them along with the inventory delivered to the predecessors  in office of the Trustees when the said collections were deposited in  the said Museum.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Articles received in exchange or purchased and moneys  realised from sale to be held on trust. All objects taken in exchange  and articles purchased under section 7 and all moneys realised from  sales made in accordance with the terms of the same section shall be  held on trust and subject to powers and declarations corresponding as  nearly as may be with the trusts, powers and declarations by this Act  limited and declared.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>SUPPLEMENTAL PROVISIONS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12A">
        <num>12A.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to issue directions to</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Trustees.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-12A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the discharge of their functions under this Act, the</p>
            <p>Trustees shall be bound by such directions on questions of policy as  the Central Government may give to them from time to time:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Trustees shall be given an opportunity to  express their views before any direction is given under this sub-</p>
            <p>section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The decision of the Central Government whether a question is  one of policy or not shall be final.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Officers under Act to be public servants. All officers and  servants appointed under this Act shall be deemed to be public  servants within the meaning of the Indian Penal code;  (45 of</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1860">
        <num>1860.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1860.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Power to Trustees to keep collections not belonging to them.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything hereinbefore contained, the Trustees may, if  they think fit, with the previous sanction of the Central Government  and subject in each case to such conditions as it may approve and to  such rules as it may prescribe, assume the custody and administration  of collections which are not the property of the Trustees for the  purposes of their trust under this Act, and keep and preserve such  collections either in the Indian Museum or elsewhere:</p>
            <p>Provided that if the trust constituted by this Act is at any time  determined, any such collections shall not by reason of their then  being in the Indian Museum become the property of Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Power to Trustees to part with certain property in their  possession. Subject to such conditions as the Central Government may  approve, the Trustees may deliver possession of the whole or any part  of the property described in the schedule to such person as that</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Government may appoint.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15A">
        <num>15A.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, in  with the Trustees, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules  to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-15A.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-15A.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the recruitment and the conditions of service of the  officers and servants of the Museum;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15A.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the form and manner in which the accounts of the Museum  may be maintained and the manner in which such accounts  may be audited;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15A.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the circumstances in which and the conditions subject  to which the Trustees may assume the custody and  administration of any collections referred to in  section 14 and keep and preserve such collections;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-15A.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the conditions subject to which the Trustees may  deliver possession of any property in their possession  to any other person.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as  may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is in  one session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised  in one session or  in two or more successive sessions, and if,</p>
            <p>before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or  the successive sessions aforesaid], both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule, or both Houses agree that the rule should  not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such  modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however that  any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the  validity of anything previously done under that rule.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Property in collections on determination of trust. If the  trust constituted by this Act is at any time determined,-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-16.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the collections and additions mentioned in section 11  shall become the property of the said Asiatic Society  or their assigns, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-16.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>all the other collections then in the said Indian</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Museum shall, save as otherwise provided by section 14,</p>
            <p>become the property of Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Repeals. Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1914 (10   of 1914), s. 3 and Sch. II.</heading>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
