<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1882/15/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1882/15"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Presidency Small Cause Courts Act, 1882"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1882/15/eng@1882-03-17/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1882/15/eng@1882-03-17"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1882-03-17" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1882/15/eng@1882-03-17/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1882/15/eng@1882-03-17"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Presidency Small Cause Courts Act, 1882</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 15 OF 1882  AN ACT TO CONSOLIDATE AND AMEND THE LAW RELATING TO TH</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 17th March, 1882.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>E COURTS OFSMALL CAU</p>
        <p>Preamble. WHEREAS it is expedient to consolidate and amend the  law relating to the Courts of Small Causes established in the towns of</p>
        <p>Calcutta, Madras and Bombay; It is hereby enacted as follows:-</p>
        <p>CHAP</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title commencement. This Act may be called the Presidency</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Small Cause Courts Act, 1882; and it shall come into force on the  first day of July, 1882.</p>
              <p>But nothing herein contained shall affect the provisions of the</p>
              <p>Army Act,  section  3, or the rights or liabilities of any  person under any decree passed before that day. 44 and 45 Vict., 58.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Repeal of enactments. Rep. by the Repealing Act, 1938 (1 of</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1938">
          <num>1938.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1938.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>), s. 2 and Sch,.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Amendments of Acts. Rep. ibid.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>" Small Cause Court" and" Registrar" defined. In this Act," the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Small Cause Court" means the Court of Small Causes constituted under  this Act in the town of Calcutta, Madras or Bombay, as the case may  be,  and the expression" Registrar" includes a Deputy Registrar].</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>CONSTITUTION AND OFFICERS OF THE COURT</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>CONSTITUTION AND OFFICERS OF THE COURT</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Courts of Small Causes established. There shall be in each of  the towns of Calcutta, Madras and Bombay a Court, to be called the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Court of Small Causes of Calcutta, Madras or Bombay, as the case may  be.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Court to be deemed under superintendence, etc., of High Court.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Small Cause Court shall be deemed to be a Court subject to the  superintendence of the High Court of Judicature at Fort William,</p>
              <p>Madras or Bombay, as the case may be, within the meaning of the</p>
              <p>Letters Patent, respectively, dated the twenty- eighth day of December,</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1865">
          <num>1865.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1865.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>, for such High Courts, and within the meaning of the 1Code of</p>
              <p>Civil Procedure  and to be a Court subordinate to the High Court  within the meaning of section 6 of the Legal Practitioners Act, 1879],</p>
              <p>and the High Court shall have, in respect of the Small Cause Court,</p>
              <p>the same powers as it has under the 3twenty- fourth and twenty- fifth of</p>
              <p>Victoria, Chapter 104, section 15, in respect of Courts subject to its  appellate jurisdiction.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Appointment of Judges. There shall be appointed from time  to time a Chief Judge of the Small Cause Court and as many other</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Judges as the State Government thinks fit.]</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Rank and precedence of Judges. The Chief Judge shall be the  first of the Judges in rank and precedence.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The other Judges shall have rank and precedence as the State</p>
              <p>Government may, from time to time, direct.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8A">
          <num>8A.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-8A.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Performance of duties of absent Judge. During any  absence of the Chief Judge or any Judge of the said Court, or during  the period for which any Judge is acting as Chief Judge, the State</p>
              <p>Government may appoint any person, having  the requisite  qualifications], to act as Chief Judge or Judge of the said Court, as  the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8A.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every person so appointed shall be authorized to perform the  duties of the Chief Judge or a Judge of the said Court until the  return of the absent Chief Judge or Judge, or of the Judge acting as</p>
              <p>Chief judge, or until the State Government sees cause to cancel the  appointment of such acting Chief Judge or Judge, as the case may be.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Procedure and practice of Small Cause Court. The High</p>
              <blockList id="section-9.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Court may, from time to time, by rules 2 having the force of law,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-9.1.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>prescribe the procedure to be followed and the practice  to be observed by the Small Cause Court either in super-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>session of or in addition to any provisions which were  prescribed with respect to the procedure or practice of the</p>
              <p>Small Cause Court on or before the thirty- first day of</p>
              <blockList id="section-9.1.list6">
                <listIntroduction>December, 1894, in or under this Act or any other enactment  for the time being in force; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-9.1.list6.aa">
                  <num>(aa)</num>
                  <p>empower the Registrar to hear and dispose of  undefended suits and interlocutory applications or matters;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-9.1.list8">
                <listIntroduction>and]</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-9.1.list8.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>cancel or vary any such rule or rules.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Rules made under this section may provide, among other matters,</p>
              <p>for the exercise by one or more of the Judges of the Small Cause Court  of any powers conferred on the Small Cause Court by this Act or any  other enactment for the time being in force.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The law, and any rules and declarations made, or purporting  to be made, thereunder, with respect to procedure or practice, in  force or treated as in force in the Small Cause Court on the thirty-</p>
              <p>first day of December, 1894, shall be in force, unless and until can-</p>
              <p>celled or varied by rules made by the High Court under this section.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Chief Judge to distribute business of Court. Subject to such  rules, the Chief Judge may, from time to time, make such arrangements  as he thinks fit for the distribution of the business of the Court  among the various Judges thereof.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Procedure in case of difference of opinion. Save as  hereinafter otherwise provided, when two or more of the Judges sitting  together differ on any question, the opinion of the majority shall  prevail; and if the Court is equally divided, the Chief Judge, if he  is one of the Judges so differing, or, in his absence, the Judge first  in rank and precedence of the Judges so differing, shall have the  casting voice.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Seal to be used. The Small Cause Court shall use a seal of  such form and dimensions as are for the time being prescribed by the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>State Government.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Appointment of Registrar and other officers. There shall be  appointed an officer to be called the Registrar of the Court who shall  be the chief ministerial officer of the Court; there shall also be  appointed a Deputy Registrar and as many clerks, bailiffs and other  ministerial officers as may be necessary for the administration of  justice by the Court and for the exercise and performance of the  powers and duties conferred and imposed on it by this Act or any other  law for the time being in force.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Registrar and other officers so appointed shall exercise such  powers and discharge such duties, of a ministerial nature, as the</p>
              <p>Chief Judge may, from time to time, by rule direct.]</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Registrar may be invested with powers of a Judge in suits not  exceeding twenty rupees. The State Government may invest the Registrar  with the powers of a Judge under this Act for the trial of suits in  which the amount or value of the subject- matter does not exceed twenty  rupees And, subject to the orders of the Chief Judge, any Judge of the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Small Cause Court may, whenever he thinks fit, transfer from his own  file to the file of the Registrar any suit which the latter is  competent to try.</p>
              <p>Explanation.- For the purposes of this section an application  for possession under section 41 shall be deemed to be a suit.]</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Judge or other officer not to practise or trade. No Judge or  other officer appointed under this Act shall, during his continuance  as such Judge or officer, either by himself or as a partner of any  other person, practise or act, either directly or indirectly, as an  advocate, attorney, vakil or other legal Practitioner, or be  concerned, either on his own account or for any other person, or as  the partner of any other person, in any trade or profession.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Any such Judge or officer so practising, acting or concerned  shall be deemed to have committed an offence under section 168 of the</p>
              <p>Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</p>
              <p>Nothing herein contained shall be deemed to prohibit any such Judge or  officer from being a member of any company incorporated or registered  under Royal Charter, Letters Patent,  Act of Parliament of the United</p>
              <p>Kingdom or Central Act or Provincial Act or  State Act]].</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>LAW ADMINISTERED BY THE COURT</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>LAW ADMINISTERED BY THE COURT</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Questions arising in suits, etc., under Act to be decided  according to law administered by High Court. All questions, other  than questions relating to procedure or practice, which arise in suits  or other proceedings under this Act in the Small Cause Court shall be  dealt with and determined according to the law for the time being  administered by the High Court in the exercise of its ordinary  original civil jurisdiction.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>JURISDICTION IN RESPECT OF SUITS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>JURISDICTION IN RESPECT OF SUITS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Local limits of jurisdiction of Court. The local limits of the  jurisdiction of each of the Small Cause Courts shall be the local  limits for the time being of the ordinary original civil jurisdiction  of the High Court.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Suits in which Court has jurisdiction. Subject to the  exceptions in section 19, the Small Cause Court shall have  jurisdiction to try all suits of a civil nature-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-18.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>when the amount or value of the subject- matter does not exceed  two thousand rupees; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the cause of action has arisen, either wholly or in part,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>within the local limits of the jurisdiction of the Small Cause Court,</p>
              <blockList id="section-18.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>and the leave of the Court has, for reasons to be recorded by it in  writing, been given before the institution of the suit; or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>all the defendants, at the time of the institution of the  suit, actually and voluntarily reside, or carry on business or  personally work for gain, within such local limits; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-18.paragraph-0.list4.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>any of the defendants at the time of the institution of the  suit, actually and voluntarily resides, or carries on business or  personally works for gain, within such local limits, and either the  leave of the Court has been given before the institution of the suit,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>or the defendants who do not reside, or carry on business, or per-</p>
              <p>sonally work for gain, as aforesaid, acquiesce in such institution:</p>
              <p>Provided that where the cause of action has arisen wholly  within the local limits aforesaid, and the Court refuses to give leave  for the institution of the suit, it shall record in writing its  reasons for such refusal.]</p>
              <p>Explanation I.- When in any suit the sum claimed is, by a set- off  admitted by both parties, reduced to a balance not exceeding two  thousand rupees, the Small Cause Court shall have jurisdiction to try  such suit.</p>
              <p>Explanation II.- Where a person has a permanent dwelling at one  place and also a lodging at another place for a temporary purpose  only, he shall be deemed to reside at both places in respect of any  cause of action arising at the place where he has such temporary  lodging.</p>
              <p>Explanation III.- A Corporation or Company shall be deemed to  carry on business at its sole or principal office in  India], or, in  respect of any cause of action arising at any place where it has also  a subordinate office, at such place.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18A">
          <num>18A.</num>
          <heading>Plaintiff may abandon suit against defendant resident out  of jurisdiction. The Small Cause Court may allow a plaintiff at or  before the first hearing of a suit in which a joint and several  liability is alleged on a cause of action arising either wholly or in  part within the local limits of the jurisdiction of the Court to  abandon the suit as against any defendant who does not reside or carry  on business or personally work for gain within such local limits, and  to sue for a decree against such defendants only as do so reside,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-18A.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>carry on business or personally work for gain.]</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Suits in which Court has no jurisdiction. The Small Cause</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-19.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Court shall have no jurisdiction in-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>suits concerning the assessment or collection of the  revenue</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>suits concerning any act done by or by order of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-19.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Central Government, or the State Government;]</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>suits concerning any act ordered or done by any Judge  or judicial officer in the execution of his office, or by any  person in pursuance of any judgment or order of any Court or  any such Judge or judicial officer;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>suits for the recovery of immovable property;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list3.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>suits for the partition of immovable property;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list3.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>suits for the foreclosure or redemption of a mortgage  of immovable property;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list3.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>suits for the determination of any other right to or  interest in immovable property;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list3.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>suits for the specific performance or rescission of  contracts;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list3.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>suits to obtain an injunction;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list3.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>suits for the cancellation or rectification of  instruments;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list3.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>suits to enforce a trust;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list3.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>suits for a general average loss and suits on policies  of insurance on sea- going vessels;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list3.m">
                  <num>(m)</num>
                  <p>suits for compensation in respect of collisions on the  high seas;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list3.n">
                  <num>(n)</num>
                  <p>suits for compensation for the infringement of a  patent, copyright or trade- mark;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list3.o">
                  <num>(o)</num>
                  <p>suits for a dissolution of partnership or for an  account of partnership- transactions;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list3.p">
                  <num>(p)</num>
                  <p>suits for an account of property and its due  administration under the decree of the Court;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list3.q">
                  <num>(q)</num>
                  <p>suits for compensation for libel, slander, malicious  prosecution, adultery or breach of promise of marriage;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list3.r">
                  <num>(r)</num>
                  <p>suits for the restitution of conjugal rights,  or for a  divorce;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list3.s">
                  <num>(s)</num>
                  <p>suits for declaratory decrees;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list3.t">
                  <num>(t)</num>
                  <p>suits for possession of a hereditary office;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list3.u">
                  <num>(u)</num>
                  <p>suits against Sovereign Princes or Ruling Chiefs, or  against Ambassadors or Envoys of Foreign States;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list3.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>suits on any judgment of a High Court;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list3.w">
                  <num>(w)</num>
                  <p>suits the cognizance whereof by the Small Cause Court  is barred by any law for the time being in force.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19A">
          <num>19A.</num>
          <heading>Return of plaint. Whenever the Court finds that for  want of jurisdiction it cannot finally determine the question at issue  in the suit, it may at any stage of the proceedings return the plaint  to be presented to a Court having jurisdiction to determine the  question. When the Court so returns a plaint, it shall comply with  the provisions of the second paragraph of section 57 of the Code of</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-19A.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Civil Procedure 3 (14 of 1882) and</p>
              <p>make such order with respect to costs as it may think just, and the</p>
              <p>Court shall for the purposes of the Indian Limitation Act, 1877, 1 (15   of 1877) be deemed to have been unable to entertain the suit by reason  of defect of jurisdiction. When a plaint so returned is afterwards  presented to a High Court, credit shall be given to the plaintiff for  the amount of the court- fee paid in the Small Cause Court in respect  of the plaint in the levy of any fees which according to the practice  of the High Court are credited to the Government.]</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Court may by consent try suits beyond pecuniary limits of</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Jurisdiction. When the parties to a suit, which, if the amount or  value of the subject- matter thereof did not exceed two thousand  rupees, would be cognizable by the Small Cause Court, have entered  into an agreement 2 in writing that the Small Cause Court shall have  jurisdiction to try such suit, the Court shall have jurisdiction to  try the same, although the amount or value of the subject- matter  thereof may exceed two thousand rupees.</p>
              <p>Every such agreement shall be filed in the Small Cause Court,</p>
              <p>and, when so filed, the parties to it shall be subject to the  jurisdiction of the Court, and shall be bound by its decision in such  suit.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Suits by and against officers of Court. All suits to which an  officer of the Small Cause Court is, as such, a party, except suits in  respect of property taken in execution of its process, or the proceeds  or value thereof  and all suits where of the amount or value of the  subject- matter exceeds one thousand rupees] may be instituted in the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>High Court at the election of the plaintiff as if this Act had not  been passed.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Costs when plaintiff sues in High court in other cases  cognizable by Small Cause Court. If any suit cognizable by the Small</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Cause Court, other than a suit to which section 21 applies, is  instituted in the High Court, and if in such suit the plaintiff  obtains, in the case of a suit founded on contract, a decree for any  matter of an amount or value less than  one thousand] rupees, and in  the case of any other suit a decree for any matter of an amount or  value of less than three hundred rupees, no cost shall be allowed to  the plaintiff;</p>
              <p>and if in any such suit the plaintiff does not obtain a decree,</p>
              <p>the defendant shall be entitled to his costs  as between attorney and  client].</p>
              <p>The foregoing rules shall not apply to any suit in which the</p>
              <p>Judge who tries the same certifies that it was one fit to be brought  in the High Court.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>PROCEDURE IN SUITS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-V.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PROCEDURE IN SUITS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Portions of Civil Procedure Code extending to Court. Rep.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>by the Presidency Small Cause Courts Act, 1895 (1 of 1895), s. 12.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>No written statement except in cases of set- off. Except in  cases of set- off under the Code of Civil Procedure, (14 of 1882)</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>section 111, 1 no written statement shall be received unless required  by the Court.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Return of documents admitted in evidence. When a period of  eight days from the decision of a suit has expired without any  application for a new trial or re- hearing of such suit having been  made, or when any such application has been made within such period  and such application has been refused, or the new trial or re- hearing</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>(as the case may be) has ended, any person, whether a party to the  suit or not, desirous of receiving back any document produced by him  in the suit and placed on the record, shall, unless the document is  impounded under section 143 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 2 be  entitled to receive back the same:</p>
              <p>Provided that a document may be returned at any time before any  of such events on such terms as the Court may direct: provided also  that no document shall be returned which, by force of the decree, has  become void or useless.</p>
              <p>On the return of a document which has been admitted in evidence,</p>
              <p>a receipt shall be given, by the party receiving it, in a receipt- book  to be kept for the purpose.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Compensation payable by plaintiff to defendant in certain  cases. In any suit in which the defendant appears and does not admit  the claim, and the plaintiff does not obtain a decree for the full  amount of his claim, the Small Cause Court may in its discretion order  the plaintiff to pay to the defendant, by way of satisfaction for his  trouble and attendance, such sum as it thinks fit.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>When any claim preferred, or objection made, under section 278 of  the Code of Civil Procedure 1 is disallowed, the Small Cause Court may  in its discretion order the person preferring or making such claim or  objection to pay to the decree- holder, or to the judgment- debtor, or  to both by way of satisfaction as aforesaid, such sum or sums as it  thinks fit.</p>
              <p>And when any claim or objection is allowed the Court may award  such compensation by way of damages to the claimant or objector as it  thinks fit; and the order of the Court awarding or refusing such  compensation shall bar any suit in respect of injury caused by the  attachment.</p>
              <p>Any order under this section may, in default of payment of the  amount payable thereunder, be enforced by the person in whose favour  it is made against the person against whom it is made as if it  were a decree of the Court.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Decreeholder to accompany officer exeuting warrant. Whenever  the Small Cause Court issues a warrant for the arrest of a judgment-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>debtor or the attachment of his property, the decree- holder, or some  other person on his behalf, shall accompany the officer of the Court  entrusted with the execution of such warrant, and shall point out to  such officer the judgment- debtor or the property to be attached, as  the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Things attached to immovable property and removable by tenant  to be deemed movable in execution. When the judgment- debtor under any  decree of the Small Cause Court is a tenant of immovable property,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>anything attached to such property, and which he might before the  termination of his tenancy lawfully remove without the permission of  his landlord, shall, for the purpose of the execution of such decree    and for the purpose of deciding all questions arising in the  execution of such decree], be deemed to be movable property and may,</p>
              <p>if sold in such execution, be severed by the purchaser, but shall not  be removed by him from the property until he has done to the property  whatever the judgmentdebtor would have been bound to do to it if he  had removed such thing.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Discharge of judgment debtor on sufficient security. Whenever  any judgment- debtor, who has been arrested or whose property has been  seized in execution of a decree of the Small Cause Court, offers  security to the satisfaction of such Court for payment of the amount  which he has been ordered to pay and the costs,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-29.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>the Court may order him to be discharged or the property to be  released.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading>Court may in certain cases suspend execution of decree.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-30.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Whenever it appears to the Small Cause Court that any judgment- debtor  under its decree is unable, from sickness, poverty or other sufficient  cause, to pay the amount of the decree, or, if such Court has ordered  the same to be paid in instalments, the amount of any instalment  thereof, it may, from time to time, for such time and upon such terms  as it thinks fit, suspend the execution of such decree and discharge  the debtor, or make such order as it thinks fit.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading>Execution of decree of Small Cause Court by other Courts. If  the judgment- debtor under any decree of the Small Cause Court has  not, within the local limits of its jurisdiction, movable property  sufficient to satisfy the decree, the Court may, on the application of  the decree- holder, send the decree for execution-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-31.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-31.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-31.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>in the case of execution against immovable property  situate within such local limits-  to the Madras City Civil</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Court or the High Court of Judicature at Fort William or Bom-</p>
              <blockList id="section-31.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>bay, as the case may be];</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-31.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>in all other cases- to any Civil Court within the local  limits of whose jurisdiction such judgment- debtor, or any  movable or immovable property of such judgment- debtor, may be  found.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>The procedure prescribed by the Code of Civil Procedure 2 (14 of</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1882">
          <num>1882.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1882.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>) for the execution of decrees by Courts other than those which  made them shall be the procedure followed in such cases.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>Minors may sue in certain cases as if of full age.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-32.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Civil Procedure 2</p>
              <p>(14 of 1882) as applied by this Act, any minor may institute a suit  for any sum of money not exceeding five hundred rupees, which may be  due to him under section 70 of the Indian Contract Act, 1872, (9 of</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1872">
          <num>1872.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1872.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>) for wages or piecework or for work as a servant, in the same  manner as if he were of full age.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading>Power to delegate nonjudicial duties. Any non- judicial or  quasi- judicial act which the Code of Civil Procedure 2 (14 of 1882) as  applied by this Act requires to be done by a Judge, and any act which  may be done by a Commissioner appointed to examine and adjust accounts  under section 394 of that Code as so applied, may be done by the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-33.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Registrar of the Small Cause Court or by such other</p>
              <p>officer of that Court as that Court may, from time to time, appoint in  this behalf.</p>
              <p>The High Court may, from time to time, by rule, declare what  shall be deemed to be non- judicial and quasi- judicial acts within the  meaning of this section.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-34">
          <num>34.</num>
          <heading>Registrar to hear and determine suits like a Judge. The suits  cognizable by the Registrar under section 14 shall be heard and  determined by him in like manner in all respects as a Judge of the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-34.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Court might hear and determine the same:</p>
              <p>Proviso. Provided that, subject to the control of the Chief</p>
              <p>Judge, any Judge of the Court may, whenever he thinks fit, transfer to  his own file any suit on the file of the Registrar.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading>Registrar may execute all decrees with the same powers as a</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-35.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Judge. The Registrar may receive applications for the execution of  decrees of any value passed by the Court, and may commit and discharge  judgment- debtors, and make any order in respect thereof which a Judge  of the Court might make under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-36">
          <num>36.</num>
          <heading>Decrees and orders of Registrar to be subject to new trial as  if made by a Judge. Every decree and order made by the Registrar in  any suit or proceeding shall be subject to the same provisions in  regard to new trial as if made by a Judge of the Court.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-36.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>NEW TRIALS AND APPEALS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VI">
        <num>VI</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-VI.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>NEW TRIALS AND APPEALS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-37">
          <num>37.</num>
          <heading>General finality of decrees and orders of Small Cause Court.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-37.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Save as otherwise provided by this Chapter or by any other enactment  for the time being in force, every decree and order of the Small Cause</p>
              <p>Court in a suit shall be final and conclusive.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-38">
          <num>38.</num>
          <heading>New trial of contested cases. Where a suit has been contested  the Small Cause Court may, on the application of either party, made  within eight days from the date of the decree or order in the suit</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-38.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>(not being a decree passed under section 522 of the 2 Code of Civil</p>
              <p>Procedure), order a new trial to be held, or alter, set aside or  reverse the decree or order, upon such terms as it thinks reasonable,</p>
              <p>and may, in the meantime, stay the proceedings.</p>
              <p>Explanation.- Every suit shall be deemed to be contested in which  the decree is made otherwise than by consent of or in default of  appearance by the defendant.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-39">
          <num>39.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-39.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Removal of certain causes into High Court. In any suit  instituted in a Small Cause Court in which the amount or value of the  subject- matter exceeds the sum of one thousand rupees, the defendant  or any one of the defendants may, before the day fixed by the summons  for the appearance of the defendant or within eight days after the  service of the summons on him, whichever period shall last expire,</p>
              <p>apply ex parte on an affidavit setting forth the facts on which he  relies for his defence to a Judge of the High Court for an order  removing the cause into the High Court. 1</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-39.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Unless the Judge is of opinion that the application has  been made solely for the purpose of delay, the applicant shall be  entitled to such order as of right:</p>
              <p>Provided that the removal directed by such order shall, unless  the Judge otherwise directs, be conditional upon the applicant giving  security, to the approval of the Judge, within a reasonable time to be  prescribed in the order for the payment of the amount claimed and of  the costs which may become payable by him to the plaintiff in respect  of the said suit.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-39.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the applicant fail or neglect to complete the required  security (if any) within the prescribed time (if any), the said order  shall be discharged and the suit shall proceed in the Small Cause</p>
              <p>Court as if such order had never been made.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-39.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the plaintiff in any case which has been removed under  this section into the High Court has abandoned a portion of his claim  in order to be able to bring the suit within the jurisdiction of a</p>
              <p>Small Cause Court, he shall be permitted to revive the portion of his  claim so abandoned.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-40">
          <num>40.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-40.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Rules with respect to suits removed under the last  foregoing section. When a suit has been removed into the High Court  under the last foregoing section, it shall be heard and disposed of by  such Court in the exercise of its original jurisdiction, and the said</p>
              <p>Court shall have all the same powers and jurisdiction in respect  thereof as if it had been originally instituted in such Court.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-40.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In every suit so removed as aforesaid the affidavit filed  under section 39, subsection (1), shall be treated as a written  statement of the defendant tendered under section 110 of the Code of</p>
              <p>Civil Procedure 1 (14 of 1882) unless the Court shall otherwise order.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-40.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In every suit so removed as aforesaid credit shall be given  to the plaintiff for the amount of the court- fee paid in the Small</p>
              <p>Cause Court in respect of the plaint in the levy of any fees which  according to the practice of the High Court are payable to the</p>
              <p>Government.]</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>RECOVERY OF POSSESSION OF IMMOVABLE PROPERTY</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VII">
        <num>VII</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-VII.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>RECOVERY OF POSSESSION OF IMMOVABLE PROPERTY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-42">
          <num>42.</num>
          <heading>Service of summons. The summons shall be served on the  occupant in the manner provided by the Code of Civil Procedure 5 for  the service of a summons on a defendant.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-44">
          <num>44.</num>
          <heading>Such order to justify bailiff entering on property and giving  possession. Bar to proceedings against Judge or officer for issuing,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-44.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>etc., order or summons. Any such order shall justify the bailiff to  whom it is addressed in entering after the hour of six in the morning  and before the hour of six in the afternoon upon the property named  therein, with such assistants as he thinks necessary, and giving  possession of such property to the applicant: and no suit or  prosecution shall be maintainable against any Judge or officer of the</p>
              <p>Small Cause Court by whom any such order as aforesaid was issued, or  against any bailiff or other person by whom the same was executed, or  by whom any such summons as aforesaid was served, for the issue,</p>
              <p>execution or service of any such order or summons, by reason only that  the applicant was not entitled to the possession of the property.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-45">
          <num>45.</num>
          <heading>Applicant, if entitled to possession, not to be deemed  trespasser for any error in proceedings. Occupant may sue for  compensation. When the applicant, at the time of applying for any such  order as aforesaid, was entitled to the possession of such property,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-45.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>neither he nor any person acting in his behalf shall be deemed, on  account of any error, defect or irregularity in the mode of proceeding  to obtain possession thereunder, to be a trespasser; but any person  aggrieved may bring a suit for the recovery of compensation for any  damage which he has sustained by reason of such error, defect or  irregularity:</p>
              <p>when no such damage is proved, the suit shall be dismissed; and  when such damage is proved but the amount of the compensation assessed  by the Court does not exceed ten rupees, the Court shall award to the  plaintiff no more costs than compensation, unless the Judge who tries  the case certifies that in his opinion full costs should be awarded to  the plaintiff.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-46">
          <num>46.</num>
          <heading>Liability of applicant obtaining order when not entitled.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-46.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Nothing herein contained shall be deemed to protect any applicant  obtaining possession of any property under this Chapter from a suit by  any person deeming himself aggrieved thereby, when</p>
              <p>such applicant was not at the time of applying for such order as  aforesaid entitled to the possession of such property.</p>
              <p>Application for order in such case an act of trespass. And when  the applicant was not, at the time of applying for any such order as  aforesaid, entitled to the possession of such property, the  application for such order, though no possession is taken thereunder,</p>
              <p>shall be deemed to be an act of trespass committed by the applicant  against the occupant.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-48">
          <num>48.</num>
          <heading>Proceedings to be regulated by Code of Civil Procedure. In all  proceedings under this Chapter, the Small Cause Court shall, as far as  may be and except as herein otherwise provided, follow the procedure  prescribed for a Court of first instance by the 2Code of Civil</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-48.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Procedure.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-50">
          <num>50.</num>
          <heading>Local extent of Chapter. Saving of certain rents. This Chapter  extends to every place within the local limits of the ordinary origin-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-50.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>al civil jurisdictions of the High Courts of</p>
              <blockList id="section-50.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Judicature at Fort William, Madras and Bombay. But nothing contained  in this Chapter applies-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-50.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to any rent due to Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-50.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>to any rent which has been due for more than twelve  months before the application mentioned in section 53.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-51">
          <num>51.</num>
          <heading>Appointment of bailiffs and appraisers. Four or more  persons shall be appointed bailiffs and appraisers for the purposes of  this Chapter.]</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-52">
          <num>52.</num>
          <heading>Appointees to be public servants. The persons so appointed   shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-52.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Indian Penal Code. 45 of 1860.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-53">
          <num>53.</num>
          <heading>Application for distress warrant. Any person claiming to be  entitled to arrears of rent of any house or premises to which this</heading>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-extends">
        <num>extends</num>
        <heading>, or his duly constituted attorney, may apply to any</heading>
        <paragraph id="chapter-extends.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Judge of the Small Cause Court, or to the Registrar of the Small Cause</p>
            <p>Court, for such warrant as is hereinafter mentioned.</p>
            <p>The application shall be supported by an affidavit or affirmation  to the effect of the form (marked A) in the third schedule hereto  annexed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-54">
          <num>54.</num>
          <heading>Issue of distress warrant. The Judge or Registrar may thereupon  issue a warrant under his hand and seal and returnable within six  days, to the effect of the form (marked B) contained in the same  schedule, addressed to any one of such bailiffs.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-54.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Judge or Registrar may at his discretion, upon personal  examination of the person applying for such warrant, decline to issue  the same.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-55">
          <num>55.</num>
          <heading>Time for distress. Every distress under this Chapter shall be  made after sunrise and before sunset, and not at any other time.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-56">
          <num>56.</num>
          <heading>What places bailiff may force open. The bailiff directed to  make the distress may force open any stable, outhouse or other  building, and may also enter any dwellinghouse, the outer door of  which may be open, and may break open the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-56.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>door of any room in such dwelling- house for the purpose of seizing  property liable to be seized under this Chapter:</p>
              <p>Provided that he shall not enter or break open the door of any  room appropriated for the zenana or residence of women, which by the  usage of the country is considered private.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-57">
          <num>57.</num>
          <heading>Property which may be seized. In pursuance of the warrant  aforesaid the bailiff shall seize the movable property found in or  upon the house or premises mentioned in the warrant and belonging to  the person from whom the rent is claimed (hereinafter called the   debtor), or such part thereof as may, in the bailiff' s judgment, be  sufficient to cover the amount of the said rent, together with the  costs of the said distress:</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-57.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-57.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that the bailiff shall not seize-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-57.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>things in actual use; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-57.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>tools and implements not in use, where there is other  movable property in or upon the house or premises sufficient  to cover such amount and costs; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-57.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the debtor' s necessary wearing apparel; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-57.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>goods in the custody of the law.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-58">
          <num>58.</num>
          <heading>Impounding distress. The bailiff may impound or otherwise  secure the property so seized in or on the house or premises  chargeable with the rent.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-59">
          <num>59.</num>
          <heading>Inventory. Notice of intended appraisement and sale. On  seizing any property under section 57 the bailiff shall make an  inventory of such property and shall give a notice in writing to the  effect of the form (marked C) in the third schedule hereto annexed to  the debtor, or to any other person upon his behalf in or upon the said  house or premises.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-59.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Copies of inventory and notice to be filed. The bailiff shall, as  soon as may be, file in the Small Cause Court copies of the said  inventory and notice.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-60">
          <num>60.</num>
          <heading>Application to discharge or suspend warrant. The debtor or any  other person alleging himself to be the owner of any property seized  under this Chapter, or the duly constituted attorney of such debtor or  other person, may, at any time within five days from such seizure,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-60.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>apply to any Judge of the said Court to discharge or suspend the  warrant, or to release a distrained article, and such Judge may  discharge or suspend such warrant or release such article accordingly,</p>
              <p>upon such terms as he thinks just,</p>
              <p>and any of the Judges of the said Court may in his discretion  give reasonable time to the debtor to pay the rent due from him.</p>
              <p>Upon any such application, the costs attending it and attending  the issue and execution of the warrant shall be in the discretion of  the Judge, and shall be paid as he directs.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-61">
          <num>61.</num>
          <heading>Claim to goods distrained made by a stranger. If any claim is  made to, or in respect of, any property seized under this Chapter, or  in respect of the proceeds or value thereof, by any person not being  the debtor, the Registrar of the Small Cause Court, upon the  application of the bailiff who seized the property, may issue a  summons calling before the Court the claimant and the person who  obtained the warrant.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-61.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>And thereupon any suit which may have been brought in the High</p>
              <p>Court in respect of such claim shall be stayed, and any Judge of the</p>
              <p>High Court, on proof of the issue of such summons and that the  property was so distrained, may order the plaintiff to pay the costs  of all proceedings in such suit after the issue of such summons.</p>
              <p>And a Judge of the Small Cause Court shall adjudicate upon such  claim and make such order between the parties in respect thereof  and of the costs of the proceedings as he thinks fit;</p>
              <p>and such order shall be enforced as if it were an order made in a  suit brought in such Court.</p>
              <p>The procedure in Small Cause Courts in cases under this section  shall conform, as far as may be, to the procedure in an ordinary suit  in such Courts.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-62">
          <num>62.</num>
          <heading>Power to award compensation to debtor or claimant. In any case  under section 60 or section 61 the Judge by whom the case is heard may  award such compensation by way of damages to the applicant or claimant</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-62.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>(as the case may be) as the Judge thinks fit,</p>
              <p>and may for that purpose make any inquiry he thinks necessary:</p>
              <p>and the order of the Judge awarding or refusing such compensation  shall bar any suit for the recovery of compensation for any damage  caused by the distress.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-63">
          <num>63.</num>
          <heading>Power to transfer to High Court cases involving more than one  thousand rupees. In any case under section 60 or section 61, if the  value of the subject- matter in dispute exceeds one thousand rupees,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-63.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>the applicant or claimant may apply to the High Court to transfer the  case to itself, and the High Court, on being satisfied that it is  expedient that the case should be disposed of by itself, may direct  the case to be transferred accordingly, and may thereupon alter or set  aside any order passed in the case by a Judge of the Small Cause</p>
              <p>Court, and may make such order therein as the High Court thinks fit.</p>
              <p>Every application under this section shall be made within seven  days from the date of the seizure of the subject- matter in dispute.</p>
              <p>In granting applications under this section, the High Court may  impose such terms as to payment of, or giving security for, costs or  otherwise as it thinks fit.</p>
              <p>The procedure in cases transferred under this section shall con-</p>
              <p>form, as far as may be, to the procedure in suits before the High</p>
              <p>Court in the exercise of its ordinary original civil jurisdiction;</p>
              <p>and orders made under this section may be executed as if they were  made in the exercise of such jurisdiction, and every such order  awarding or refusing compensation shall bar any suit for the recovery  of compensation for any damage caused by the distress which gave rise  to the case wherein such order was made.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-64">
          <num>64.</num>
          <heading>Appraisement. Notice of sale. In default of any order to the  contrary by a Judge of the Small Cause Court or by the High Court, any  two of the said bailiffs may, at the expiration of five days from a  seizure of property under this Chapter, appraise the property so  seized, and give the debtor notice in writing to the effect of the  form (marked D) in the third schedule hereto annexed.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-64.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The bailiffs shall file in the Small Cause Court a copy of every  notice given under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-65">
          <num>65.</num>
          <heading>Sale. Application of proceeds. In default of any such order to  the contrary, the distrained property shall be sold on the day  mentioned in such notice, and the said bailiffs shall, on realizing  the proceeds, pay over the amount thereof to the Registrar of the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-65.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Small Cause Court; and such amount shall be applied first in payment  of the costs of the said distress and then in satisfaction of the debt;</p>
              <p>and the surplus, if any, shall be returned to the debtor:</p>
              <p>Provided that the debtor may direct that the sale shall take  place in any other manner, first giving security for any extra costs  thereby occasioned.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-66">
          <num>66.</num>
          <heading>Costs of distresses. No costs of any distress under this</heading>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-shall">
        <num>shall</num>
        <heading>be taken or demanded except those mentioned in the part</heading>
        <paragraph id="chapter-shall.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>(marked E) of the third schedule hereto annexed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-67">
          <num>67.</num>
          <heading>Account of costs and proceeds. The Registrar of the Small</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-67.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Cause Court shall keep a book in which all sums received as costs upon  distresses made under this Chapter, and all sums paid as remuneration  to the said bailiffs, and all contingent charges incurred in respect  of such distresses, shall be duly entered.</p>
              <p>He shall also enter in the said book all sums realised by sale of  the property distrained and paid over to landlords under the  provisions of this Chapter.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-68">
          <num>68.</num>
          <heading>Bar of distresses except under this Chapter. No distress shall  be levied for arrears of rent except under the provisions of this</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-68.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Chapter;</p>
              <p>Penalty for making illegal distresses. and any person, except a  bailiff appointed under section 51, levying or attempting to levy any  such distress, shall, on conviction before a Presidency Magistrate, be  liable to be punished with fine which may extend to five hundred  rupees and with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three  months, in addition to any other liability he may have incurred by his  proceedings.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>REFERENCES To HIGH COURT</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IX">
        <num>IX</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-IX.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>REFERENCES To HIGH COURT</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-69">
          <num>69.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-69.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Reference when compulsory. If two or more Judges of the</p>
              <p>Small Cause Court sit together in any suit, or in any proceeding under</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VII">
        <num>VII</num>
        <heading>of this Act, and differ in their opinion as to any  question of law or usage having the force of law or the construction  of a document, which construction may affect the merits, or if in any suit or in any such proceeding, in which the amount or  value of the subject- matter exceeds five hundred rupees, any such  question arises upon which the Court entertains reasonable doubt, and  either party so requires,</heading>
        <paragraph id="chapter-VII.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>the Small Cause Court shall draw up a statement of the facts of  the case and the point on which there is a difference of opinion or on  which doubt is entertained, and refer such statement with its own  opinion on the point for the opinion of the High Court; and the  provisions of sections 619 to 621 of the 2 Code of Civil Procedure,</p>
            <p>(14 of 1882) shall, so far as they are applicable, be deemed to apply  as if such reference had been made under section  3 of the said Code.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="chapter-VII.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When the Small Cause Court refers any question for the  opinion of the High Court as provided in sub- section (1), it shall  either reserve judgment or give judgment contingent upon such  opinion.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <section id="section-70">
          <num>70.</num>
          <heading>Security to be furnished on such reference by party against  whom contingent judgment given. When judgment is given under section 69  contingent upon the opinion of the High Court, the party against whom  such judgment is given shall at once furnish security, to be approved  by the Small Cause Court, for the costs of the reference to the High</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-70.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Court and for the amount of such judgment:</p>
              <p>Provided that no security for the amount of such judgment shall  be required in any case in which the Judge who tried the case has  ordered such amount to be paid into Court, and the same has been paid  accordingly.</p>
              <p>If no such security given, party to be deemed to have submitted  to judgment. Unless such security as aforesaid is at once furnished,</p>
              <p>the party against whom such contingent judgment has been given shall  be deemed to have submitted to the same.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>FEES AND COSTS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-X">
        <num>X</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-X.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>FEES AND COSTS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-72">
          <num>72.</num>
          <heading>Fees for processes. The fees specified in the third and  fourth columns of the fourth schedule hereto annexed shall be paid  previous to the issue in any suit or in any proceeding under Chapter</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-72.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>VII of this Act of the processes, to which the said columns  respectively relate, by the persons on whose behalf such processes are  issued, when the amount or value of the subject- matter exceeds the sum  specified in the first column, but does not exceed the sum specified  in the second column of the said schedule 1</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-74">
          <num>74.</num>
          <heading>Fees and costs of poor persons. The Small Cause Court may,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-74.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>whenever it thinks fit, receive and register suits instituted, and  applications under section 41 made by poor persons, and may issue  processes on behalf of such persons, without payment or on a part-</p>
              <p>payment of the fees mentioned in sections 71 and 72.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-75">
          <num>75.</num>
          <heading>Power to vary fees. The State Government may from time to  time, by notification in the Official Gazette, vary the amount of the  fees payable under sections 71 and 72:</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-75.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Provided that the amount of such fees shall in no case exceed the  amount prescribed by the said sections.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-76">
          <num>76.</num>
          <heading>Expense of employing legal practitioners. The expense of  employing an advocate, vakil, attorney or other legal practitioner  incurred by any party shall not be allowed as costs in any suit or in  any proceeding under Chapter VII of this Act, in the Small Cause</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-76.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Court, in which suit or proceeding the amount or value of the subject-</p>
              <p>matter does not exceed twenty rupees, unless the Court is of opinion  that the employment of such practitioner was under the circumstances  reasonable.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-77">
          <num>77.</num>
          <heading>Sections 3, 5 and 25 of Court- fees Act, 1870, saved. Nothing  contained in this Chapter shall affect the provisions of sections 3, 5  and 25 of the Court- fees Act, 1870. (7 of 1870)</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-77.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>MISCONDUCT OF INFERIOR MINISTERIAL OFFICERS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-XI">
        <num>XI</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-XI.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MISCONDUCT OF INFERIOR MINISTERIAL OFFICERS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-79">
          <num>79.</num>
          <heading>Default of bailiff or other officer in execution of order or  warrant. If any clerk, bailiff or other inferior ministerial officer of  the Small Cause Court who is employed as such in the execution of any  order or warrant, loses, by neglect, connivance or omission, an  opportunity of executing such order or warrant, he shall be liable, by  order of the Chief Judge, on the application of the person injured by  such neglect, connivance or omission, to pay such sum, not exceeding  in any case the sum for which the said order or warrant was issued,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-79.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>as, in the opinion of the Chief Judge, represents the amount of the  damage sustained by such person thereby.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-80">
          <num>80.</num>
          <heading>Extortion or default of officers. If any clerk, bailiff or  other inferior ministerial officer of the Small Cause Court is  charged with extortion or misconduct while acting under colour of its  process, or with not duly paying or accounting for any money levied by  him under its authority, the Court may inquire into such charge, and  may make such order for the repayment or payment of any money so  extorted, or of any money so levied as aforesaid, and of damages and  costs, by such officer, as it thinks fit.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-81">
          <num>81.</num>
          <heading>Court empowered to summon witnesses, etc. For the purposes  of any inquiry under this Chapter, the Small Cause Court shall have  all the powers or summoning and enforcing the attendance of witnesses  and compelling the production of documents which it possesses in suits  under this Act.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-82">
          <num>82.</num>
          <heading>Enforcement of order. Any order under this Chapter for the  payment or repayment of money may, in default of payment of the amount  payable thereunder, be enforced by the person to whom such amount is  payable as if the same were a decree of the Small Cause Court in his  favour.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-82.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>CONTEMPT OF COURT</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-XII">
        <num>XII</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-XII.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>CONTEMPT OF COURT</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-83">
          <num>83.</num>
          <heading>t</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-83.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Procedure of Court in certain cases of contempt. Record in such cases. Procedure  where Court considers that case should not be dealt withunder section 83.</p>
              <p>Discharge of offender on</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-83">
          <num>83.</num>
          <heading>to 86. Procedure of Court in certain cases of contempt.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-83.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Record in such cases. Procedure where Court considers that case  should not be dealt with under section 83. Discharge of offender on</p>
              <p>submission or apology. Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1914</p>
              <p>(10 of 1914), s. 3 and Sch. II.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-87">
          <num>87.</num>
          <heading>Imprisonment or committal of person refusing to answer or  produce document. If any witness before the Small Cause Court refuses  to answer such questions as are put to him, or to produce any document  in his possession or power which the Court requires him to produce,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-87.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>and does not offer any reasonable excuse for such refusal, the Court  may sentence him to simple imprisonment, or commit him to the custody  of an officer of the Court, for any term not exceeding seven days,</p>
              <p>unless in the mean- time such person consents to answer such questions  or to produce such document, as the case may be, after which, in the  event of his persisting in his refusal, he may be dealt with according  to the provisions of section  480 or section 482 of the Code of</p>
              <p>Criminal Procedure, 1898]. (5 of 1898)</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-88">
          <num>88.</num>
          <heading>Appeal from orders under section 87. Any person deeming  himself aggrieved by an order under  section 87 may appeal to  the High Court, and the provisions of the  Code of Criminal</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-88.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Procedure, 1898] (5 of 1898), relating to appeals shall, so far as  may be, apply to appeals under this section.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-XIII">
        <num>XIII</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-XIII.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-89">
          <num>89.</num>
          <heading>Persons by whom process may be served.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-89">
          <num>89.</num>
          <heading>Persons by whom process may be served. Notices to produce  documents, summonses to witnesses, and all other processes issued in  the exercise of any jurisdiction conferred on the Small Cause Court by  this Act, except summonses to defendants and writs of execution, may,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-89.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>if the Court by general or special order so directs, be served by such  persons as the Court, from time to time, appoints in this behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-90">
          <num>90.</num>
          <heading>Registers and returns. The Small Cause Court shall keep such  registers, books and accounts, and submit to the High Court such  statements and returns, as may, subject to the approval of the State</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-90.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government, be prescribed by the High Court.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-91">
          <num>91.</num>
          <heading>Courts to furnish records, etc., called for by State</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-91.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government or High Court. The Small Cause Court shall comply with such  requisitions as may, from time to time, be made by the State</p>
              <p>Government or High Court for records, returns and statements in such  form and manner as such Government or Court, as the case may be,</p>
              <p>thinks fit.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-92">
          <num>92.</num>
          <heading>Holidays and vacations. The Small Cause Court shall, at the  commencement of each year, draw up a list of holidays and vacations to  be observed in the Court, and shall submit the same for the approval  of the State Government.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-92.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Such list, when it has received such approval, shall be published  in the Official Gazette, and the said holidays and vacations shall be  observed accordingly.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-93">
          <num>93.</num>
          <heading>Certain persons exempt from arrest by Court. The President    the Governors of  Madras]  Bombay and  West Bengal]],</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-93.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>and the Chief Justices and Judges of the High Courts  shall  not be liable to arrest by order of the Small Cause Court.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-94">
          <num>94.</num>
          <heading>No suit to lie upon decree of court. No suit shall lie on any  decree of the Small Cause Court.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-95">
          <num>95.</num>
          <heading>Place of imprisonment. Any person ordered by the Small Cause</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-95.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Court to be imprisoned may be imprisoned in such place as the State</p>
              <p>Government, from time to time, appoints in this behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-96">
          <num>96.</num>
          <heading>Tender in suit for anything done under Act. If any person  against whom any suit is brought for anything purporting to be done by  him under this Act has, before the institution of the suit, tendered  sufficient amends to the plaintiff, the plaintiff shall not recover.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-97">
          <num>97.</num>
          <heading>Limitation of prosecutions. All prosecutions for anything  purporting to be done under this Act must be commenced within three  months after the offence was committed.</heading>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
