<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1908/15/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1908/15"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Indian Ports Act, 1908"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1908/15/eng@1908-12-18/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1908/15/eng@1908-12-18"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1908-12-18" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1908/15/eng@1908-12-18/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1908/15/eng@1908-12-18"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Indian Ports Act, 1908</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 15 OF 1908</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 18th December, 1908.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to consolidate the enactments relating to Ports and Port-</p>
        <p>charges.</p>
        <p>CHAP</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Title and extent.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the Indian Ports</p>
              <p>Act, 1908.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>It shall extend, save as otherwise appears from its subject  or context,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to the ports mentioned in the First Schedule, and to  such parts of the navigable rivers and channels leading  to such ports respectively as have been declared to be  subject to Act XXII of 1855 (for the regulation of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Ports and Port- dues) or to the Indian Ports Act, 1875,</p>
              <p>(12 of 1875.) or to the Indian Ports Act, 1889; (10 of</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1889">
          <num>1889.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1889.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1889.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>)</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1889.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>to the other ports or parts of navigable rivers or  channels to which the  Government], in exercise of  the power hereinafter conferred, extends this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-1889.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>But nothing in section 31 or section 32 shall apply to any  port, river or channel to which the section has not been specially  extended by the  Government].</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Savings. Nothing in this Act shall--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>apply to any vessel belonging to, or in the service of    the Central Government or a State Government] , or  to any vessel of war belonging to any Foreign Prince or</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>State, or</p>
              <p>Amended in Andhra Pradesh by A. P. Act 18 of 1968.</p>
              <p>Amended in Pondicherry by Pondy. Act 10 of 1969.</p>
              <p>Amended in Tamil Nadu by T. N. Act 19 of 1975.</p>
              <p>Extended to Goa, Daman and Diu with modifications, by Reg. 12 of 1962,</p>
              <p>s. 3 and Sch.</p>
              <p>The Act comes into force in Pondicherry on 1. 10. 1963 vide Reg. 7 of</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1963">
          <num>1963.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1963.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>, s. 3 and Sch. I.</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>deprive any person of any right of property or other  private right, except as hereinafter expressly  provided, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1963.paragraph-0.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>affect any law or rule relating to the customs or any  order or direction lawfully made or given pursuant  thereto.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant  in the subject or context,--</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" Magistrate" means a person exercising powers under the</p>
              <p>Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898, (5 of 1898.) not less  than those of a Magistrate of the second class, and  includes, in the towns of Calcutta, Madras and Bombay,</p>
              <p>a Presidency Magistrate:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" master", when used in relation to any vessel  or any  aircraft making use of any port], means, subject to the  provisions of any other enactment for the time being in  force, any person (except a pilot or harbour- master    of the port]) having for the time being the charge  or control of the vessel  or the aircraft, as the  case may be]:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" pilot" means a person for the time being authorized by  the  Government] to pilot vessels:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" port" includes also any part of a river or channel in  which this Act is for the time being in force:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" port- officer" is synonymous with master- attendant:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" ton" means a ton as determined or determinable by the  rules made under section 74 of the Merchant Shipping</p>
              <p>Act, 1958, for regulating the measurement of the gross  tonnage of ships:]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" vessel" includes anything made for the conveyance    mainly] by water of human beings or of property:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" major port" means any port which the Central</p>
              <p>Government may by notification in the Official Gazette  declare, or may under any law for the time being in  force have declared, to be a major port: and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" Government", as respects major ports, for all purposes,</p>
              <p>and, as respects other ports, for the purposes of  making rules under clause (p) of section 6 (1) and of  the appointment and control of port health- officers  under section 17, means the Central Government, and  save as aforesaid, means the State Government.]</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>POWERS OF THE GOVERNMENT</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>POWERS OF THE  GOVERNMENT]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Power to extend or withdraw the Act or certain portions  thereof.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The  Government] may, by notification in the</p>
              <blockList id="section-4.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Official Gazette,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.1.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>extend this Act to any port in which this Act is not in  force or to any part of any navigable river or channel  which leads to a port and in which this Act is not in  force;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.1.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>specially extend the provisions of section 31 or section</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>to any port to which they have not been so extended;</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-32.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-32.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-32.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>withdraw this Act or section 31 or section 32 from any  port or any part thereof in which it is for the time  being in force.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-32.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A notification under clause (a) or clause (b) of sub- section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>shall define the limits of the area to which it refers.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Limits defined under sub- section (2) may include any piers,</p>
              <p>jetties, landing- places, wharves, quays, docks and other works made on  behalf of the public for convenience of traffic, for safety of  vessels, or for the improvement, maintenance or good government of the  port and its approaches, whether within or without high- water mark,</p>
              <p>and, subject to any rights of private property therein, any portion of  the shore or bank within fifty yards of high- water- mark.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In sub- section (3) the expression" high- water- mark" means the  highest point reached by ordinary spring tides at any season of the  year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Alteration of limits of ports.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The  Government] may,</p>
              <p>subject to any rights of private property, alter the limits of any  port in which this Act is in force.</p>
              <p>Explanation.-- For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared  that the power conferred on the Government by this sub- section  includes the power to alter the limits of any port by uniting with  that port any other port or any part of any other port.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When the  Government] alters the limits of a port under  sub- section (1), it shall declare or describe, by notification in the</p>
              <p>Official Gazette, and by such other means, if any, as it thinks fit,</p>
              <p>the precise extent of such limits.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Power to make port- rules.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-6.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The  Government] may, in  addition to any rules which it may make under any other enactment for  the time being in force, make such rules, consistent with this Act, as  it thinks necessary for any of the following purposes, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>for regulating the time and hours at and during which,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-6.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>the speed at which, and the manner and conditions in  and on which, vessels generally or vessels of any class  defined in the rules, may enter, leave or be moved in  any port subject to this Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.1.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>for regulating the berths, stations and anchorages to be  occupied by vessels in any such port;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.1.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>for striking the yards and top masts, and for rigging- in  the booms and yards, of vessels in any such port, and  for swinging or taking- in davits, boats and other  things projecting from such vessels;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.1.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>for the removal or proper hanging or placing of anchors,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-6.1.list5">
                <listIntroduction>spars and other things being in or attached to vessels  in any such port;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.1.list5.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-6.1.list5.e.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>for regulating vessels whilst taking- in or discharging  passengers, ballast or cargo, or any particular kind of  cargo, in any such port, and the stations to be  occupied by vessels whilst so engaged;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-6.1.list5.e.list0.ee">
                      <num>(ee)</num>
                      <p>for regulating the manner in which oil or water  mixed with oil shall be discharged in any such port and  for the disposal of the same;]</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-6.1.list5.e.list0.eee">
                      <num>(eee)</num>
                      <p>for regulating the bunkering of vessels with liquid  fuel in any such port and the description of barges,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-6.1.list7">
                <listIntroduction>pipe lines or tank vehicles to be employed in such  bunkering;]</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.1.list7.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>for keeping free passages of such width as may be deemed  necessary within any such port, and along or near to  the piers, jetties, landing- places, wharves, quays,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-6.1.list9">
                <listIntroduction>docks, moorings and other works in or adjoining to the  same, and for marking out the spaces so to be kept  free;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.1.list9.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>for regulating the anchoring, fastening, mooring and  unmooring of vessels in any such port;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.1.list9.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>for regulating the moving and warping of all vessels  within any such port and the use of warps therein;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.1.list9.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>for regulating the use of the mooring buoys, chains and  other moorings in any such port;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.1.list9.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>for fixing the rates to be paid for the use of such  moorings when belonging to the  Government] or of any  boat, hawser or other thing belonging to the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-6.1.list11">
                <listIntroduction>Government;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.1.list11.jj">
                  <num>(jj)</num>
                  <p>for regulating the use of piers, jetties, landing  places, wharves, quays, warehouses and sheds when  belonging to the  Government] and for fixing the  rates to be paid for the use of the same;]</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.1.list11.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>for licensing and regulating catamarans plying for hire,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>and flats and cargo, passenger and other boats plying,</p>
              <blockList id="section-6.1.list14">
                <listIntroduction>whether for hire or not, and whether regularly or only  occasionally, in or partly within and partly without  any such port,  and for licensing and regulating the  crews of any such vessels;] and for determining the  quantity of cargo or number of passengers  or of the  crew] to be carried by any such vessels  and may by  such rules provide for the fees payable in respect of  any such license, and in the case of  vessels] plying  for hire, for the rates of hire to be charged and the  conditions under which such vessels shall be compelled  to ply for hire, and further for the conditions under  which any license may be revoked];</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.1.list14.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>for regulating the use of fires and lights within any  such port;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.1.list14.m">
                  <num>(m)</num>
                  <p>for enforcing and regulating the use of signals or  signal- lights by vessels by day or by night in any such  port;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.1.list14.n">
                  <num>(n)</num>
                  <p>for regulating the number of the crew which must be on  board any vessel afloat within the limits of any such  port;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.1.list14.o">
                  <num>(o)</num>
                  <p>for regulating the employment of persons engaged in  cleaning or painting vessels, or in working in the  bilges, boilers or double bottoms of vessels in any  such port;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.1.list14.p">
                  <num>(p)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-6.1.list14.p.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>for the prevention of danger arising to the public  health by the introduction and the spread of any  infectious or contagious disease from vessels arriving  at, or being in, any such port, and for the prevention  of the conveyance of infection or contagion by means of  any vessel sailing from any such port, and in  particular and without prejudice to the generality of  this provision, for--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-6.1.list14.p.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>the signals to be hoisted and the places of  anchorage to be taken up by such vessels having any  case, or suspected case, of any infectious or  contagious disease on board, or arriving at such port  from a port in which, or in the neighbourhood of which,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-6.1.list16">
                <listIntroduction>there is believed to be, or to have been at the time  when the vessel left such port, any infectious or  contagious disease;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.1.list16.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>the medical inspection of such vessels and of  persons on board such vessels;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.1.list16.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>the questions to be answered and the  information to be supplied by masters, pilots and other  persons on board such vessels;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.1.list16.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>the detention of such vessels and of persons  on board such vessels;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.1.list16.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>the duties to be performed in cases of any  such disease by masters, pilots and other persons on  board such vessels;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.1.list16.vi">
                  <num>(vi)</num>
                  <p>the removal to hospital or other place  approved by the health- officer and the detention  therein of any person from any such vessel who is  suffering or suspected to be suffering from any such  disease;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.1.list16.vii">
                  <num>(vii)</num>
                  <p>the cleansing, ventilation and disinfection  of such vessels or any part thereof and of any articles</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-6.1.list18">
                <listIntroduction>therein likely to retain infection or contagion, and  the destruction of rats or other vermin in such  vessels; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.1.list18.viii">
                  <num>(viii)</num>
                  <p>the disposal of the dead on such vessels;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-6.1.list20">
                <listIntroduction>and]</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.1.list20.q">
                  <num>(q)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-6.1.list20.q.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>for securing the protection from heat of the officers  and crew of vessels in any such port by requiring the  owner or master of any such vessel--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-6.1.list20.q.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>to provide curtains and double awnings for  screening from the sun' s rays such portions of the deck  as are occupied by, or are situated immediately above,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-6.1.list22">
                <listIntroduction>the quarters of the officers and crew;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.1.list22.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>to erect windsails so far as the existing  portholes or apertures in the deck admit of their being  used for ventilating the quarters of the officers and  crew;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.1.list22.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>when the deck is made of iron and not  woodsheathed, to cover with wooden planks or other  suitable non- conducting material such portions of the  deck as are situated immediately above the quarters of  the officers and crew;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.1.list22.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>when the quarters used by the crew and the  galley are separated by an iron bulk- head only, to  furnish a temporary screen of some suitable  nonconducting material between such quarters and the  galley.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The power to make rules under sub- section (1)  is subject  to the condition of the rules being made after previous publication:</p>
              <p>Provided that nothing in this sub- section shall be construed to  affect the validity of any rule in force immediately before the  commencement of the Indian Ports Act, 1889 (10 of 1889), and  continued by section 2, sub- section (2), of that Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2A">
            <num>(2A)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made by the State Government under this Act  shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before the State</p>
              <p>Legislature.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2B">
            <num>(2B)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act  shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House  of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty  days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more  successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session  immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or  both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall  thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</p>
              <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that rule].</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any person disobeys any rule made under clause (p) of sub-</p>
              <p>section (1), he shall be punishable for every such offence with fine  which may extend to one thousand rupees.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a master fails wholly or in part to do any act prescribed  by any rule made under clause (p) of sub- section (1), the health-</p>
              <p>officer shall cause such act to be done, and the reasonable expenses</p>
              <p>incurred in doing such act shall be recoverable by him from such  master.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>PORT- OFFICIALS AND THEIR POWERS AND DUTIES</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PORT- OFFICIALS AND THEIR POWERS AND DUTIES</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Appointment of conservator.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The  Government] shall  appoint some officer or body of persons to be conservator of every  port subject to this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-7.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Subject to any direction by the  Government] to the  contrary,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>in ports where there is a port- officer, the port- officer  shall be the conservator;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>in ports where there is no port- officer, but where there  is a harbour- master, the harbour- master shall be the  conservator.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where the harbour- master is not conservator, the harbour-</p>
              <p>master and his assistants shall be subordinate to, and subject to the  control of, the conservator.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The conservator shall be subject to the control of the</p>
              <p>Government], or of any intermediate authority which  the</p>
              <p>Government] may appoint.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Power of conservator to give and enforce directions for  certain specified purposes.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The conservator of any port subject to  this Act may, with respect to any vessel within the port, give  directions for carrying into effect any rule for the time being in  force therein under section 6.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any person wilfully and without lawful excuse refuses or  neglects to obey any lawful direction of the conservator, after notice  thereof has been given to him, he shall, for every such offence, be  punishable with fine which may extend to one hundred rupees, and in  the case of a continuing offence with a further fine which may extend  to one hundred rupees for every day during which, after such notice as  aforesaid, he is proved to have wilfully and without lawful excuse  continued to disobey the direction.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In case of such refusal or neglect, the conservator may do,</p>
              <p>or cause to be done, all acts necessary for the purpose of carrying  the</p>
              <p>direction into execution, and may hire and employ proper persons for  that purpose, and all reasonable expenses incurred in doing such acts  shall be recoverable by him from the person so refusing or neglecting  to obey the direction.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Power to cut warps and ropes. The conservator of any such port  may, in case of urgent necessity, cut, or cause to be cut, any warp,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>rope, cable or hawser endangering the safety of any vessel in the port  or at or near to the entrance thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Removal of obstructions within limits of port.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The  conservator may remove, or cause to be removed, any timber, raft or  other thing, floating or being in any part of any such port, which in  his opinion obstructs or impedes the free navigation thereof or the  lawful use of any pier, jetty, landing- place, wharf, quay, dock,</p>
              <p>mooring or other work on any part of the shore or bank which has been  declared to be within the limits of the port and is not private  property.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The owner of any such timber, raft or other thing shall be  liable to pay the reasonable expenses of the removal thereof, and if  such owner or any other person has without lawful excuse caused any  such obstruction or impediment, or causes any public nuisance  affecting or likely to affect such free navigation or lawful use, he  shall also be punishable with fine which may extend to one hundred  rupees.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The conservator or any Magistrate having jurisdiction over  the offence may cause any such nuisance to be abated.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Recovery of expenses of removal. If the owner of any such  timber, raft or other thing, or the person who has caused any such  obstruction, impediment or public nuisance as is mentioned in the last  foregoing section, neglects to pay the reasonable expenses incurred in  the removal thereof, within one week after demand, or within fourteen  days after such removal has been notified in the Official Gazette or  in such other manner as the  Government] by general or special order  directs, the conservator may cause such timber, raft or other thing,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>or the materials of any public nuisance so removed, or so much thereof  as may be necessary, to be sold by public auction;</p>
              <p>and may retain all the expenses of such removal and sale out of  the proceeds of the sale, and shall pay the surplus of such proceeds,</p>
              <p>or deliver so much of the thing or materials as may remain unsold, to  the person entitled to receive the same;</p>
              <p>and, if no such person appears, shall cause the same to be kept  and deposited in such manner as the  Government] directs;</p>
              <p>and may, if necessary, from time to time, realize the expenses of  keeping the same, together with the expenses of sale, by a further  sale of so much of the thing or materials as may remain unsold.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Removal of lawful obstructions.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-12.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any obstruction or  impediment to the navigation of any port subject to this Act has been  lawfully made, or has become lawful by reason of the long continuance  of such obstruction or impediment, or otherwise, the conservator shall  report the same for the information of the  Government], and shall,</p>
              <p>with the sanction of  the Government], cause the same to be removed  or altered, making reasonable compensation to the person suffering  damage by such removal or alteration.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any dispute arising concerning such compensation shall be  determined according to the law relating to like disputes in the case  of land required for public purposes.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Fouling of Government moorings.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-13.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any vessel hooks or  gets foul of any of the buoys or moorings laid down by or by the  authority of the  Government] in any such port, the master of such  vessel shall not, nor shall any other person, except in case of  emergency, lift the buoy or mooring for the purpose of unhooking or  getting clear from the same without the assistance of the conservator;</p>
              <p>and the conservator, immediately on receiving notice of such  accident, shall assist and superintend the clearing of such vessel;</p>
              <p>and the master of such vessel shall, upon demand, pay such  reasonable expenses as may be incurred in clearing the same.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any master or other person offending against the provisions  of this section shall, for every such offence, be punishable with fine  which may extend to one hundred rupees.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Raising or removal of wreck impeding navigation within limits  of port.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any vessel is wrecked, stranded or sunk in any port  in such a manner as to impede or likely to impede any navigation  thereof, the conservator shall give notice to the owner of the vessel  to raise, remove or destroy the vessel within such period as may be  specified in the notice and to furnish such adequate security to the  satisfaction of the conservator to ensure that the vessel shall be  raised, removed or destroyed within the said period:</p>
              <p>Provided that the conservator may extend such period to such  further period as he may consider necessary having regard to the  circumstances of such case and the extent of its impediment to  navigation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.1A">
            <num>(1A)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where the owner of any vessel to whom a notice has been  issued under sub- section (1) fails to raise, remove or destroy such  vessel within the period specified in the notice or the extended  period or fails to furnish the security required of him, the  conservator may cause the vessel to be raised, removed or destroyed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.1B">
            <num>(1B)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing sub-</p>
              <p>sections, if the conservator is of the opinion that any vessel which  is wrecked, stranded or sunk in any port is required to be immediately  raised, removed or destroyed for the purpose of uninterrupted  navigation in such port, he may, without giving any notice under sub-</p>
              <p>section (1), cause the vessel to be raised, removed or destroyed.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any property recovered by a conservator acting  under  sub- section (1A) or sub- section (1B)] is unclaimed or the person  claiming it fails to pay the</p>
              <p>reasonable expenses incurred by the conservator under that sub- section  and a further sum of twenty per cent. of the amount of such expenses,</p>
              <p>the conservator may sell the property by public auction, if the  property is of a perishable nature, forthwith, and, if it is not of a  perishable nature, at any time not less than  thirty days]  after  the recovery thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The expenses and further sum aforesaid shall be payable to  the conservator out of the sale- proceeds of the property, and the  balance shall be paid to the person entitled to the property  recovered, or, if no such person appears and claims the balance, shall  be held in deposit for payment, without interest, to any person  thereafter establishing his right thereto:</p>
              <p>Provided that the person makes his claim within three years from  the date of the sale.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where the sale proceeds of the property are not sufficient  to meet the expenses and further sum aforesaid, the owner of the  vessel at the time the vessel was wrecked, stranded or sunk shall be  liable to pay the deficiency to the conservator on demand, and if the  deficiency be not paid within one month of such demand the conservator  may recover the deficiency from such owner in the manner laid down in  sub- section (2) of section 57 for recovery of expenses and damages or  in any other manner according as the deficiency does not or does  exceed one thousand rupees.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Power to board vessels and enter buildings.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-15.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The  conservator or any of his assistants may, whenever he suspects that  any offence against this Act has been, or is about to be, committed,</p>
              <p>or whenever it is necessary for him so to do in the performance of any  duty imposed upon him by this Act,</p>
              <p>and the person appointed under this Act to receive any port- dues,</p>
              <p>fees or other charges payable in respect of any vessel, may, whenever  it is necessary for him so to do in the performance of any duty  imposed upon him by this Act,</p>
              <p>either alone or with any other person, board any vessel, or enter  any building or place, within the limits of any port subject to this</p>
              <p>Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the master of the vessel, or any person in possession or  occupation of the building or place, without lawful excuse, refuses</p>
              <p>to allow any such person as is mentioned in sub- section (1) to board  or enter such vessel, building or place in the performance of any duty  imposed upon him by this Act, he shall for every such offence be  punishable with fine which may extend to two hundred rupees.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Power to require crews to prevent or extinguish fire.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-16.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For  the purpose of preventing or extinguishing fire in any port subject to  this Act, the conservator or port- officer may require the master of  any vessel within the port to place at his disposal such number as he  requires, not exceeding three- fourths, of the crew then under the  orders of such master.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any master refusing or neglecting to comply with such  requisition shall be punishable with fine which may extend to five  hundred rupees, and any seaman then under his orders who, after being  directed by the master to obey the orders of the conservator or port-</p>
              <p>officer for the purpose aforesaid, refuses to obey such orders, shall  be punishable with fine which may extend to twenty- five rupees.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Appointment and powers of health- officer.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The</p>
              <p>Government] may appoint at any port subject to this Act an officer  to be called the health- officer.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A health- officer shall, subject to the control of the</p>
              <blockList id="section-17.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Government], have the following powers, within the limits of the  port for which he is appointed, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.2.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>with respect to any vessel, the powers conferred on a  shipping- master by the  Indian Merchant Shipping Act,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1859">
          <num>1859.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1859.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1859.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>, (1 of 1859.) section 71;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1859.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>power to enter on board any vessel and medically examine  all or any of the seamen or apprentices on board the  vessel;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1859.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>power to require and enforce the production of the log-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1859.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>book and any other books, papers or documents which he  thinks necessary for the purpose of enquiring into the  health and medical condition of the persons on board  the vessel;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1859.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>power to call before him and question for any such  purpose all or any of those persons and to require true  answers to any questions which he thinks fit to ask;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1859.paragraph-0.list3.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>power to require any person so questioned to make and  subscribe a declaration of the truth of the statements  made by him.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Indemnity of Government against act or default of port  official or pilot. The Government shall not be responsible for any act  or default of any conservator, port- officer or harbour- master, of any  port subject to this Act, or of any deputy or assistant of any of the  authorities aforesaid, or of any person acting under the control or  direction of any such authority, deputy or assistant, or for any act  or default of any pilot, or for any damage sustained by any vessel in  consequence of any defect in any of the moorings, hawsers or other  things belonging to the Government which may be used by the vessel:</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Provided that nothing in this section shall protect  the</p>
              <p>Government] from a suit in respect of any act done by or under the  express order or sanction of the Government.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>RULES FOR THE SAFETY OF SHIPPING AND THE CONSERVATION OF PORTS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>RULES FOR THE SAFETY OF SHIPPING AND THE CONSERVATION OF PORTS</p>
            <p>General Rules</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Injuring buoys, beacons and moorings.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-19.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No person shall,</p>
              <p>without lawful excuse, lift, injure, loosen or set adrift any buoy,</p>
              <p>beacon or mooring fixed or laid down by, or by the authority of, the</p>
              <p>Government] in any port subject to this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any person offends against the provisions of this section,</p>
              <p>he shall for every such offence be liable, in addition to the payment  of the amount of damage done, to fine which may extend to two thousand  rupees, or to imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Wilfully loosening vessel from moorings. If any person  wilfully and without lawful excuse loosens or removes from her  moorings any vessel within any such port without leave or authority  from the owner or master of the vessel, he shall, for every such  offence, be punishable with fine which may extend to two hundred  rupees, or with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six  months.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Improperly discharging ballast.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-21.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No ballast or rubbish and  no other thing likely to form a bank or shoal or to be detrimental to  navigation, shall, without lawful excuse, be cast or thrown into any  such port or into or upon any place on shore from which the same is  liable to be washed into any such</p>
              <p>port, either by ordinary or high tides, or by storms or land- floods    and no oil or water mixed with oil shall be discharged in or into  any such port, to which any rules made under clause (ee) of sub-</p>
              <p>section (1) of section 6 apply, otherwise than in accordance with such  rules].</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-21.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person who by himself or another so casts or throws any  ballast or rubbish or any such other thing  or so discharges any oil  or water mixed with oil], and the master of any vessel from which the  same is so cast,  thrown or discharged], shall be punishable with  fine which may extend to  five lakh rupees] and shall pay any  reasonable expenses which may be incurred in removing the same.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-21.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If, after receiving notice from the conservator of the port  to desist from so casting or throwing any ballast or rubbish or such  other thing  or from so discharging any oil or water mixed with  oil], any master continues so to cast  throw or discharge the same],</p>
              <p>he shall also be liable to simple imprisonment for a term which may  extend to  oneyear and to fine which may extend to five lakh rupees]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-5.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in this section applies to any case in which the  ballast or rubbish or such other thing is cast or thrown into,  or  the oil or water mixed with oil is discharged in or into], any such  port with the consent in writing of the conservator, or within any  limits within which such act may be authorized by the  Government].</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Graving vessel within prohibited limits. If any person  graves, breams or smokes any vessel in any such port, contrary to the  directions of the conservator, or at any time or within any limits at  or within which such act is prohibited by the  Government], he and  the master of the vessel shall for every such offence be punishable  with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees each.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Boiling pitch on board vessel within prohibited limits. If  any person boils or heats any pitch, tar, resin, dammer, turpentine,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>oil or other such combustible matter on board any vessel within any  such port, or at any place within its limits where such act is  prohibited by the  Government], or contrary to the directions of the  conservator, he and the master of the vessel shall for every such</p>
              <p>offence be punishable with fine which may extend to two hundred rupees  each.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Drawing spirits by unprotected artificial light. If any  person, by an unprotected artificial light, draws off spirits on board  any vessel within any port subject to this Act, he and the master of  the vessel shall for every such offence be punishable with fine which  may extend to two hundred rupees each.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Warping.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-25.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every master of a vessel in any port subject to  this Act shall, when required so to do by the conservator, permit  warps or hawsers to be made fast to the vessel for the purpose of  warping any other vessel in the port, and shall not allow any such  warp or hawser to be let go until required so to do.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A master offending against sub- section (1) shall be  punishable for every such offence with fine which may extend to two  hundred rupees.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Leaving out warp or hawser after sunset.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-26.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A master of a  vessel shall not cause or suffer any warp or hawser attached to his  vessel to be left out in any port subject to this Act after sunset in  such a manner as to endanger the safety of any other vessel navigating  in the port.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-26.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A master offending against sub- section (1) shall be  punishable for every such offence with fine which may extend to two  hundred rupees.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Discharge of fire arms in port. If any person, without lawful  excuse, discharges any firearm in any port subject to this Act, or on  or from any pier, landing- place, wharf or quay thereof, except a gun  loaded only with gun- powder for the purpose of making a signal of  distress, or for such other purpose as may be allowed by the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government], he shall for every such offence be punishable with  fine which may extend to fifty rupees.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Penalty on master omitting to take order to extinguish fire.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>If the master of any vessel in which fire takes place while lying in  any such port wilfully omits to take order to extinguish the fire or  obstructs the conservator or the port- officer, or any person acting  under the authority of the conservator or port- officer, in  extinguishing or attempting to extinguish the fire, he shall be</p>
              <p>punishable with imprisonment which may extend to six months, or with  fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Unauthorized person not to search for lost stores.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-29.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No  person, without the permission of the conservator, shall, in any port  subject to this Act, creep or sweep for anchors, cables or other  stores lost or supposed to be lost therein.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any person offends against the provisions of sub- section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to one hundred  rupees.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading>Removing stones or injuring shores of port prohibited.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-30.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No  person without the permission of the conservator shall in any port  subject to this Act remove or carry away any rock, stones, shingle,</p>
              <p>gravel, sand or soil or any artificial protection from any part of the  bank or shore of the port;</p>
              <p>and no person shall sink or bury in any part of such bank or  shore, whether the same is public or private property, any mooring-</p>
              <p>post, anchor or any other thing, or do any other thing which is likely  to injure or to be used so as to injure such bank or shore, except  with the permission of the conservator, and with the aid or under the  inspection of such person, if any, as the conservator may appoint to  take part in or overlook the performance of such work.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-30.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any person offends against sub- section (1), he shall for  every such offence be punishable with fine which may extend to one  hundred rupees and shall pay any reasonable expenses which may be  incurred in repairing any injury done by him to the bank or shore.</p>
              <p>Special Rules</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading>Moving of vessels without pilot or permission of harbour-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-31.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>master.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-31.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No vessel of the measurement of two hundred tons or  upwards shall enter, leave or be moved in any port to which this  section has been specially extended without having a pilot, harbour-</p>
              <p>master or assistant of the port- officer or harbour- master on board;</p>
              <p>and no mechanically propelled vessel of any measurement less  than two hundred tons and no other vessel of any measurement less than  two hundred tons and exceeding one hundred tons] shall enter, leave or  be moved in any such port without having a pilot, harbour- master or  assistant of the port- officer or harbour- master on board,</p>
              <p>unless authority in writing so to do has been obtained from the  conservator or some officer empowered by him to give such authority:</p>
              <p>Provided that the  Government] may, by notification in the</p>
              <p>Official Gazette, direct that in any port specified in such  notification the provisions of this sub- section shall not apply to  sailing vessels of any measurement not exceeding a measurement so  specified.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything in sub- section (1), the owner or  master of a vessel which is by that sub- section required to have a  pilot, harbour- master or assistant of the port- officer or harbour-</p>
              <p>master on board, shall be answerable for any loss or damage caused by  the vessel or by any fault of the navigation of the vessel, in the  same manner as he would have been if he had not been so required by  that sub- section:</p>
              <p>Provided that the provisions of this sub- section shall not take  effect till the first day of January, 1918, or such earlier date as  the Central Government may notify in that behalf in the Official</p>
              <p>Gazette.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any vessel, except in case of urgent necessity, enters,</p>
              <p>leaves or is moved in the port contrary to the provisions of sub-</p>
              <p>section (1), the master of the vessel shall for every such offence be  punishable with fine which may extend to two hundred rupees, unless  upon application to the proper officer the master was unable to  procure a pilot, harbour- master or assistant of the port- officer or  harbour- master to go on board the vessel.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>Provision of certain vessels with fire- extinguishing  apparatus.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-32.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every vessel exceeding the measurement of two hundred  tons and lying in any port to which this section has been specially  extended shall be provided with a proper force- pump and hose and  appurtenances, for the purpose of extinguishing any fire which may  occur on board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The master of such a vessel who, having been required by the  conservator to comply with the provisions of sub- section (1),</p>
              <p>neglects or refuses, without lawful excuse, so to do for the space of  seven days after such requisition, shall be punishable with fine which  may extend to five hundred rupees.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>PORT- DUES, FEES AND OTHER CHARGES</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-V.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PORT- DUES, FEES AND OTHER CHARGES</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading>Levy of port- dues.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-33.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of sub-</p>
              <p>section (2),] in each of the ports mentioned in the First Schedule,</p>
              <p>such port- due, not exceeding the amount specified for the port in the  third column of the schedule as the  Government] directs, shall be  levied on vessels entering the port and described in the second column  of the Schedule, but not oftener than the time fixed for the port in  the fourth column of the schedule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-33.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The  Government] may, by notification in the Official</p>
              <p>Gazette, alter or add to any entry in the First Schedule relating to  ports  in  any State] or, as the case may be, in the State], and  this power shall include the power to regroup any such ports.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-33.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-33.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>] Whenever the  Government]  declares any other port to  be subject to this Act, it may , by the same or any subsequent  declaration, further declare,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-33.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>in the terms of any of the entries in the second column  of the First Schedule, the vessels which are to be  chargeable with port- dues on entering the port,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-33.3.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the highest rates at which such dues may be levied in  respect of vessels chargeable therewith, and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-33.3.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the times at which such vessels are to be so chargeable.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-33.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>] All port- dues now leviable in any port shall continue to  be so leviable until it is otherwise declared in exercise of the  powers conferred by this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-33.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>] An order increasing or imposing port- dues under this  section shall not take effect till the expiration of thirty days</p>
              <p>from the day on which the order was published in the Official Gazette.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-34">
          <num>34.</num>
          <heading>Variation of port- dues by Government. The  Government] may,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-34.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>after consulting the authority appointed under section 36], exempt,</p>
              <p>subject to such conditions, if any, as it thinks fit to impose, any  vessel or class of vessels] entering a port subject to this Act from  payment of port- dues and cancel the exemption, or may vary the rates  at which port- dues are to be levied in the port, in such manner as,</p>
              <p>having regard to the receipts and charges on account of the port, it  thinks expedient, by reducing or raising the dues, or any of them    or may extend the periods for which any vessel or class of vessels  entering a port shall be exempt from liability to pay port- dues]:</p>
              <p>Provided that the rates shall not in any case exceed the amount  authorized to be taken by or under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading>Fees for pilot- age and certain other services.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-35.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Within any  port subject to this Act, fees may be charged for pilotage, hauling,</p>
              <p>mooring, re- mooring, hooking, measuring and other services rendered to  vessels, at such rates as the  Government] may direct.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-35.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The fees now chargeable for such services shall continue to  be chargeable unless and until they are altered in exercise of the  power conferred by sub- section (1).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-35.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Government may, in special cases, remit the whole or  any portion of the fees chargeable under sub- section (1) or sub-</p>
              <p>section (2).]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-36">
          <num>36.</num>
          <heading>Receipt, expenditure and account of port- charges.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-36.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The</p>
              <p>Government] shall appoint some officer or body of persons at every  port at which any dues, fees or other charges are authorized to be  taken by or under this Act to receive the same and, subject to the  control of the  Government], to expend the receipts on any of the  objects authorized by this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Such officer or body shall keep for the port a distinct  account, to be called the port fund account, showing, in such detail  as the  Government] prescribes, the receipts and expenditure of the  port, and shall publish annually as soon after the first day of April  as may be practicable an abstract, in such form as  the Government]</p>
              <p>prescribes, of the account for the past financial year:</p>
              <p>Provided that the port fund account for any port may, if so  authorized under the provisions of any Act relating to such port, be  merged with the general account of that port, and in such a case, the  provisions of sub- section (6) shall not apply and the provisions of  sub- sections (4) and (5) shall have effect as if for the words" the  port fund account of the port" therein, the words" the general account  of the port" had been substituted.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-36.4.list1">
                <listIntroduction>All money received under this Act at or on account of any  port subject to this Act, excluding receipts on account of pilotage  but including--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-36.4.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>fines other than those creditable to the pilotage  account of the port under sub- section (5a)],</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-36.4.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>proceeds of waifs, and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-36.4.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>any balance of the proceeds of a sale under section 14  where no right to the balance has been established on a  claim made within three years from the date of the  sale, shall be credited in the port fund account of the  port.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All expenses incurred for the sake of any such port,</p>
              <blockList id="section-36.5.list2">
                <listIntroduction>excluding expenses on account of pilotage but including--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-36.5.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the pay and allowances of all persons upon the  establishment of the port,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-36.5.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the cost of buoys, beacons, lights and all other works  maintained chiefly for the benefit of vessels being in  or entering or leaving the port or passing through the  rivers or channels leading thereto,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-36.5.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>pensions, allowances and gratuities of persons who have  been employed in the port under this or any other  enactment relating to ports and port- dues, or such  portion of those pensions, allowances and gratuities as  the  Government] may by rule determine,</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-36.5.list2.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>with the previous sanction of the  Government],</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-36.5.list4">
                <listIntroduction>contributions towards the support of public hospitals  or dispensaries suitable for the reception or relief of  seamen or otherwise towards the provision of sanitary  superintendence and medical aid for the shipping in the  port and for seamen whether ashore or afloat belonging  to vessels in the port, and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-36.5.list4.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>with the like sanction, contributions towards sailors'</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>homes, institutes, rest- houses and coffee- houses and  for other purposes connected with the health,</p>
              <p>recreation and temporal well- being of sailors,</p>
              <p>shall be charged to the port fund account of the port.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.5a">
            <num>(5a)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All fees charged for pilotage at any port subject to this</p>
              <p>Act  (other than a major port)] and all fines and penalties levied  under the Act or under any other Act relating to the port from pilots  or other persons employed in the pilot service other than fines and  penalties imposed by a Court, shall be credited to a distinct account  to be called the pilotage account of the port.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.5b">
            <num>(5b)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All sums so credited to the pilotage account may be applied,</p>
              <blockList id="section-36.5b.list2">
                <listIntroduction>in such proportions as the Government may from time to time direct, to  the following purposes, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-36.5b.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the purchase and maintenance in repair of such vessels,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>and the supply of such materials, stores or other  things as the officer or body appointed under sub-</p>
              <blockList id="section-36.5b.list5">
                <listIntroduction>section (1) may deem it necessary to purchase, maintain  or supply for the efficiency of the pilot service;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-36.5b.list5.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the payment of the salaries, wages and allowances of  pilots and other persons employed in the pilot service  or in the supervision thereof;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-36.5b.list5.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the payment of pensions, retiring gratuities,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>compassionate allowances or bonuses to pilots and other  persons engaged in the pilot service, and of the  contributions, if any, duly</p>
              <blockList id="section-36.5b.list8">
                <listIntroduction>authorized to be made in their behalf to any provident  fund or welfare fund;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-36.5b.list8.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the payment of pensions, gratuities and compassionate  allowances granted by the officer or body appointed  under sub- section (1) to pilots and other persons  engaged in the pilot service who have been injured in  the execution of their duty and to the surviving  relatives of pilots and other persons so engaged who  have been killed in the execution of their duty or who  may die while still in the service of such officer or  body;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-36.5b.list8.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the provision of educational, recreational and other  amenities for pilots and other persons employed in the  pilot service;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-36.5b.list8.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the payment of contributions or appropriations to any  special fund or funds established under the provisions  of any other Act relating to the port to which the  officer or body appointed under sub- section (1)</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-36.5b.list10">
                <listIntroduction>considers contributions or appropriations should be  made from the pilot- age account;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-36.5b.list10.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>any other expenditure which may, with the previous  sanction of the Government, be incurred in respect of  the pilot service.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.5c">
            <num>(5c)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the officer or body appointed under sub- section (1) at  any port is also the authority responsible for maintaining the general  account of the port, then notwithstanding the absence of any provision  in that behalf in the Act under which such general account is  maintained, such officer or body may, with the previous sanction of  the Government, apply any sum out of the moneys credited to such  general account towards meeting deficits, if any, in the pilotage  account of the port, or transfer the whole or any part of any surplus  funds, in the pilotage account to the general account of the port.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of any local law as to the disposal  of any balance from time to time standing to the credit of a port fund  account  or of a pilotage account], any such balance may be  temporarily invested in such manner as the  Government] may direct.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-37">
          <num>37.</num>
          <heading>Grouping of ports.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-37.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may direct that  for the purposes of the last foregoing section any number of ports    in the State not</p>
              <p>being major ports] shall be regarded as constituting a single port,</p>
              <p>and thereupon all moneys to be credited to the port fund account under  sub- section (4) of that section shall form a common port fund account  which shall be available for the payment of all expenses incurred for  the sake of any of the ports.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-37.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-37.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Where ports are grouped by or under this Act, the following  consequences ensue, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-37.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the State Government, in the exercise of its control  over expenditure debitable to the common port fund  account of the group, may  make rules with respect to  the expenditure of the fund for the sake of the several  ports of the group on the objects authorized by this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-37.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Act ; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-37.2.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the State Government may exercise its authority under  section 34 as regards all the ports in the group  collectively or as regards any of them separately.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-38">
          <num>38.</num>
          <heading>Receipts for port- charges. The person to whom any dues, fees  or other charges authorized to be taken by or under this Act are paid  shall grant to the person paying the same a proper voucher in writing  under his hand, describing the name of his office, the port or place  at which the dues, fees or other charges are paid, and the name,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-38.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>tonnage and other proper description of the vessel in respect of which  the payment is made.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-39">
          <num>39.</num>
          <heading>Master to report arrival.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-39.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Within twenty- four hours after  the arrival within the limits of any port subject to this Act of any  vessel liable to the payment of port- dues under this Act, the master  of the vessel shall report her arrival to the conservator of the port.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-39.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A master failing without lawful excuse to make such report  within the time aforesaid shall for every such offence be punishable  with fine which may extend to one hundred rupees.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-39.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing in this section applies to tug- steamers, ferry-</p>
              <p>steamers or river steamers plying to and from any of the ports subject  to this Act .</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-40">
          <num>40.</num>
          <heading>Conservator may in certain cases ascertain draught and charge  expense to master. If any vessel liable to the payment of port- dues is  in any such port without proper marks on the stem and stern posts  thereof for denoting her draught, the conservator may cause the same  to be ascertained by means of the operation of hooking, and the master  of the vessel shall be liable to pay the expenses of the operation.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-41">
          <num>41.</num>
          <heading>Ascertainment of tonnage of vessel liable to port- dues. In  order to ascertain the tonnage of any vessel liable to pay port- dues  the following rules shall be observed, namely:--</heading>
          <subsection id="section-41.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-41.1.list0">
                <item id="section-41.1.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>If the vessel is a British registered vessel or a  vessel registered under the Indian Registration of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Ships Act, 1841, (10 of 1841.) or the Indian</p>
              <p>Registration of Ships Act (1841) Amendment Act, 1850,</p>
              <p>(11 of 1850.) or under any other law for the time being  in force for the registration of vessels in  India]</p>
              <blockList id="section-41.1.list5">
                <listIntroduction>the conservator may require the owner or master of the  vessel or any person having possession of her register  to produce the register for inspection.</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-41.1.list5.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>If the owner or master or such person neglects or  refuses to produce the register or otherwise to satisfy  the conservator as to what is the true tonnage of the  vessel in respect of which the port- dues are payable,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to  one hundred rupees, and the conservator may cause the  vessel to be measured, and the tonnage thereof to be  ascertained, according to the mode of measurement  prescribed by the rules for the time being in force for  regulating the measurement of British vessels, and in  such case the owner or master of the vessel shall also  be liable to pay the expenses of the measurement.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-41.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the vessel is not a British registered vessel or a  vessel registered under the Indian Registration of</p>
              <p>Ships Act, 1841, (10 of 1841.) or the Indian</p>
              <p>Registration of Ships Act (1841) Amendment Act, 1850</p>
              <p>(11 of 1850) or under any other law for the time being  in force for the registration of vessels in  India]</p>
              <p>and the owner or master thereof fails to satisfy the  conservator as to what is her true tonnage according to  the mode of measurement prescribed by the rules for the  time being in force for regulating the measurement of</p>
              <p>British vessels, the conservator shall cause the vessel  to be measured and the tonnage thereof to be  ascertained</p>
              <p>according to the mode aforesaid, and in such case the  owner or master of the vessel shall be liable to pay  the expenses of the measurement.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-41.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the vessel is a vessel of which the tonnage cannot be  ascertained according to the mode of measurement  mentioned in clauses (1) and (2), the tonnage of the  vessel shall be determined by the conservator on such  an estimate as may seem to him to be just.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-42">
          <num>42.</num>
          <heading>Distraint and sale on refusal to pay port- charges. If the  master of any vessel in respect of which any port- dues, fees or other  charges are payable under this Act, refuses or neglects to pay the  same on demand, the authority appointed to receive such port- dues,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-42.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>fees or other charges may distrain or arrest the vessel, and the  tackle, apparel and furniture belonging thereto or any part thereof,</p>
              <p>and detain the same until the amount due is paid;</p>
              <p>and in case any part of the port- dues, fees or other charges or  of the costs of the distress or arrest or of the keeping of the vessel  or other thing distrained or arrested, remains unpaid for the space of  five days next after any such distress or arrest, may cause the vessel  or other thing distrained or arrested to be sold, and with the  proceeds of such sale may satisfy the port- dues, fees or other charges  and the costs including the costs of sale remaining unpaid, and shall  render the surplus, if any, to the master of the vessel upon demand:</p>
              <p>Provided that where such vessel or other thing is already  arrested under the order of a court or other authority, the authority  appointed to receive port- dues, fees or other charges, may sell the  vessel or other thing only with the prior permission of such court or  other authority and satisfy the port- dues, fees or other charges and  the costs including costs of sale remaining unpaid, and disburse the  surplus, if any, in accordance with the orders or directions of such  court or other authority:</p>
              <p>Provided further that the person to whom the vessel or other  thing is sold under this section shall be deemed to be the owner  thereof and registered as such under the Merchant Shipping Act,</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1958">
          <num>1958.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1958.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>]</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-43">
          <num>43.</num>
          <heading>No port- clearance to be granted until port charges are paid.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-43.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The officer of the  Government] whose duty it is to grant a port-</p>
              <blockList id="section-43.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>clearance for any vessel shall not grant such clearance--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-43.paragraph-0.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>until her owner or master, or some other person, has  paid or secured to the satisfaction of such officer the  amount of all port- dues, fees and other charges, and of  all fines, penalties and expenses to which the vessel  or her owner or master is liable under this Act; (57   and 58 Vict., c. 60.)</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-43.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>until all expenses, which by the  Merchant Shipping</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Act, 1894, section 207, are to be borne by her owner,</p>
              <p>incurred since her arrival in the port from which he  seeks clearance, have been paid.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-44">
          <num>44.</num>
          <heading>Port- charges payable in one port recoverable at any other  port.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-44.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the master of any vessel in respect of which any such sum  as is mentioned in the last foregoing section is payable causes her to  leave any port without having paid the sum, the authority appointed to  receive port- dues, fees and other charges at the port under this</p>
              <p>Act may require in writing the authority appointed to receive port-</p>
              <p>dues, fees and other charges under this Act at any other port in</p>
              <p>India] to which she may proceed, or in which she may be, to levy  the sum.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-44.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The authority to whom the requisition is directed shall  proceed to levy such sum in the manner prescribed in section 42, and a  certificate purporting to be made by the authority appointed to  receive port- dues, fees and other charges at the port where such sum  as is mentioned in the last foregoing section became payable, stating  the amount payable, shall be sufficient prima facie proof of such  amount in any proceeding under section 42 and also (in case the amount   payable is disputed) in any subsequent proceeding under section 59.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-45">
          <num>45.</num>
          <heading>Penalty for evading payment of port- charges.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-45.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the  master of a vessel evades the payment of any such sum as is mentioned  in section 43, he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to  five times the amount of the sum.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In any proceeding before a Magistrate on a prosecution under  sub- section (1), any such certificate as is mentioned in section 44,</p>
              <p>sub- section (2), stating that the master has evaded such payment,</p>
              <p>shall be sufficient prima facie proof of the evasion, unless the  master shows to the satisfaction of the Magistrate that the departure  of the vessel without payment of the sum was caused by stress of  weather, or that there was lawful or reasonable ground for such  departure.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any Magistrate having jurisdiction under this Act in any port  to which the vessel may proceed, or in which she may be found, shall  be deemed to have jurisdiction in any proceeding under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-46">
          <num>46.</num>
          <heading>Port- due on vessels in ballast. A vessel entering any port  subject to this Act  in ballast and not carrying passengers shall be  charged with a port- due at a rate to be determined by the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-46.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government] and not exceeding three- fourths of the rate with which  she would otherwise be chargeable.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-47">
          <num>47.</num>
          <heading>Port- due on vessels not discharging or taking in cargo. When  a vessel enters a port subject to this Act, but does not discharge or  take in any cargo or passengers therein (with the exception of such   unshipment and reshipment as may be necessary for purposes of repair),</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-47.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>she shall be charged with a port- due at a rate to</p>
              <p>be determined by the  Government] and not exceeding half the rate  with which she would otherwise be chargeable.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-48">
          <num>48.</num>
          <heading>Port- due not to be chargeable in certain cases. No port- due  shall be chargeable in respect of--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-48.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-48.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-48.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>any pleasure- yacht, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-48.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>any vessel which, having left any port, is compelled to  re- enter it by stress of weather or in consequence of  having sustained any damage, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-48.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>any vessel which, having entered  any port  in the  territories which, immediately before the 1st November,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1956">
          <num>1956.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1956.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>, were comprised in the States of Madras and</p>
              <p>Andhra] or the port of Gopalpur in the State of</p>
              <p>Orissa], leaves it within forty- eight hours without  discharging or taking in any passengers or cargo.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-49">
          <num>49.</num>
          <heading>Power to impose hospital port- dues.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-49.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The  Central</p>
              <p>Government] may, by notification in the Official Gazette, order that  there shall be paid in respect of every vessel entering any port  subject to this Act, within a reasonable distance of which there is a  public hospital or dispensary suitable for the reception or relief of  seamen requiring medical aid, such further port- dues not exceeding one  anna per ton as the  Central Government] thinks fit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-49.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Such port- dues shall be called hospital port- dues, and the</p>
              <p>Central Government] shall, in making any order under sub- section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-49.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, have regard to any contributions made under section 36, sub-</p>
              <p>section (5), clause (d).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-49.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An order imposing or increasing hospital port- dues shall not  take effect till the expiration of sixty days from the day on which  the order was published in the Official Gazette.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-49.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Whenever the  Central Government] is satisfied that proper  provision has been made by the owners or agents of any class of  vessels for giving medical aid to the seamen employed on board such  class of vessels, or that such provision is unnecessary in the case of  any class of vessels, it may, by notification in the Official Gazette  exempt such class of vessels from any payment under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-50">
          <num>50.</num>
          <heading>Application and account of hospital port- dues.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-50.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Hospital  port- dues shall be applied, as the  Central Government] may direct,</p>
              <p>to the support of any such hospital or dispensary as aforesaid, or  otherwise for providing sanitary superintendence and medical aid for  the shipping in the port in which they are levied and for the seamen  belonging to the vessels therein, whether such seamen are ashore or  afloat.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-50.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The  Central Government] shall publish annually in the</p>
              <p>Official Gazette, as soon after the first day of April as may be, an  account, for the past financial year, of the sums received as hospital  port- dues at each port where such dues are payable, and of the  expenditure charged against those receipts.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-50.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Such account shall be published as a supplement to the  abstract published under section 36, sub- section (2).</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>HOISTING SIGNALS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VI">
        <num>VI</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-VI.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>HOISTING SIGNALS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-51">
          <num>51.</num>
          <heading>Master to hoist number of vessel.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-51.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The master of every  inward or outward bound vessel, on arriving within signal distance of  any signal- station established within the limits of the river Hooghly,</p>
              <p>or within the limits of any part of a river or channel leading to a  port subject to this Act, shall, on the requisition of the pilot in  charge of the vessel, signify the name of the vessel by hoisting the  number by which she is known, or by adopting such other means to this  end as may be practicable and usual, and shall keep the signal flying  until it is answered from the signal- station.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-51.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the master of a vessel arriving as aforesaid offends  against sub- section (1), he shall be punishable for every such offence  with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-52">
          <num>52.</num>
          <heading>Pilot to require master to hoist number.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-52.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every pilot in  charge of a vessel shall require the number of the vessel to be duly  signalled as provided by the last foregoing section.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-52.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When, on such requisition from the pilot, the master refuses  to hoist the number of a vessel, or to adopt such other means of  making her name known as may be practicable and usual, the pilot may,</p>
              <p>on arrival at the first place of safe anchorage, anchor the vessel and  refuse to proceed on his course until the requisition has been  complied with.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-53">
          <num>53.</num>
          <heading>Penalty on pilot disobeying provisions of this Chapter. Any  pilot in charge of a vessel who disobeys, or abets disobedience to,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-53.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>any of the provisions of this Chapter shall be punishable</p>
              <p>with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees for each instance of  such disobedience or abetment, and, in addition, shall be liable to  have his authority to act as a pilot withdrawn.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>PROVISIONS WITH RESPECT TO PENALTIES</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VII">
        <num>VII</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-VII.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PROVISIONS WITH RESPECT TO PENATIES</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-54">
          <num>54.</num>
          <heading>Penalty for disobedience to rules and orders of the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-54.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government. If any person disobeys any rule or order which a</p>
              <p>Government] has made in pursuance of this Act and for the  punishment of disobedience to which express provision has not been  made elsewhere in this Act, he shall be punishable for every such  offence with fine which may extend to one hundred rupees.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-55">
          <num>55.</num>
          <heading>Offences how triable, and penalties how recovered. All  offences against this Act shall be triable by a Magistrate, and any</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-55.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Magistrate may, by warrant under his hand, cause the amount of any  fine imposed upon the owner or master of any vessel, for any offence  committed on board of the vessel or in the management thereof or  otherwise in relation thereto, whereof the owner or master is  convicted, to be levied by distress and sale of the vessel, and the  tackle, apparel and furniture thereof, or so much thereof as is  necessary.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-56">
          <num>56.</num>
          <heading>Costs of conviction.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-56.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In case of any conviction under this</p>
              <p>Act, the convicting Magistrate may order the offender to pay the costs  of the conviction in addition to any fine or expenses to which he may  be liable.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-56.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Such costs may be assessed by the Magistrate and may be  recovered in the same manner as any fine under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-57">
          <num>57.</num>
          <heading>Ascertainment and recovery of expenses and damages payable  under this Act.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-57.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any dispute arises as to the sum to be paid in  any case as expenses or damages under this Act, it shall be determined  by a Magistrate upon application made to him for that purpose by  either of the disputing parties.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-57.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Whenever any person is liable to pay any sum, not exceeding  one thousand rupees, as expenses or damages under this Act, any</p>
              <p>Magistrate, upon application made to him by the authority to whom the  sum is payable, may, in addition to or instead of any other means for  enforcing payment, recover the sum as if it were a fine.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-58">
          <num>58.</num>
          <heading>Cost of distress. Whenever any fine, expenses or damages is  or are levied under this Act, by distress and sale, the cost of the  distress and sale may be levied in addition to such fine, expenses or  damages, and in the same manner.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-59">
          <num>59.</num>
          <heading>Magistrate to determine the amount to be levied in case of  dispute. If any dispute arises concerning the amount leviable by any  distress or arrest under this Act or the costs payable under the last  foregoing section, the person making the distress or using the arrest  may detain the goods distrained or arrested, or the proceeds of the  sale thereof, until the amount to be levied has been determined by a</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-59.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Magistrate, who, upon application made to him for that purpose, may  determine the amount and award such costs to be paid by either of the  parties to the other of them as he thinks reasonable, and payment of  such cost, if not paid on demand, shall be enforced as if they were a  fine</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-60">
          <num>60.</num>
          <heading>Jurisdiction over offences beyond local limits of  jurisdiction.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-60.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person offending against the provisions of this</p>
              <p>Act in any port subject to this Act shall be punishable by any</p>
              <p>Magistrate having jurisdiction over any district or place adjoining  the port.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-60.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Such Magistrate may exercise all the powers of a Magistrate  under this Act, in the same manner and to the same extent as if the  offence had been committed locally within the limits of his  jurisdiction, notwithstanding that the offence may not have been  committed locally within such limits, and, in case any such Magistrate  exercises the jurisdiction hereby vested in him, the offence shall be  deemed, for all purposes, to have been committed locally within the  limits of his jurisdiction.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-61">
          <num>61.</num>
          <heading>Conviction to be quashed on merits only.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-61.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No conviction,</p>
              <p>order or judgment of any Magistrate under this Act shall be quashed  for error of form or procedure, but only on the merits, and it shall  not be necessary to state, on the face of the conviction, order or  judgment, the evidence on which it proceeds.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-61.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If no jurisdiction appears on the face of the conviction,</p>
              <p>order or judgment, but the depositions taken supply that defect, the  conviction, order or judgment shall be aided by what so appears in the  depositions.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>SUPPLEMENTAL PROVISIONS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VIII">
        <num>VIII</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-VIII.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>SUPPLEMENTAL PROVISIONS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-62">
          <num>62.</num>
          <heading>Hoisting unlawful colours in port.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-62.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any vessel  belonging to  any citizen of India or Commonwealth citizen], or  sailing under  Indian or British colours], hoists, carries or wears,</p>
              <p>within the limits of any port subject to this Act, any flag, jack,</p>
              <p>pennant or colours, the use whereof on</p>
              <p>board such vessel has been prohibited by the  Merchant Shipping Act,</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1894">
          <num>1894.</num>
          <heading>(57 and 58 vict., c. 60.), or any other Statute now or hereafter to  be in force, or by any proclamation made or to be made in pursuance  of any such Statute, or by any of  the regulations] in force for  the time being, the master of the vessel shall, for every such  offence, be punishable with fine which may extend to fifty rupees.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1894.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Such fine shall be in addition to any other penalty  recoverable in respect of such an offence.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1894.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The conservator of the port or any officer of  the Indian</p>
              <p>Navy] may enter on board any such vessel and seize and take away any  flag, jack, pennant or colours so unlawfully hoisted, carried or worn  on board the same.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-63">
          <num>63.</num>
          <heading>Foreign deserters. Any Magistrate, upon an application being  made to him by the Consul of any foreign Power to which section 238 of  the  Merchant Shipping Act, 1894 (57 and 58 vict., c. 60), has, by an</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-63.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Order in Council  or order], been, or shall hereafter be, declared  to be applicable, or by the representative of such Consul, and upon  complaint on oath of the description of any seaman, not being a  slave, from any vessel of such foreign Power, may, until a revocation  of such Order in Council  or order] has been publicly notified,</p>
              <p>issue his warrant for the apprehension of any such deserter, and,</p>
              <p>upon due proof of the desertion, may order him to be conveyed on  board the vessel to which he belongs or, at the instance of the</p>
              <p>Consul, to be detained in custody until the vessel is ready to sail,</p>
              <p>or, if the vessel has sailed, for a reasonable time not exceeding  one month:</p>
              <p>Provided that a deposit be first made of such sum as the</p>
              <p>Magistrate deems necessary for the subsistence of the deserter during  the detention and that the detention of the deserter shall not be  continued beyond twelve weeks.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-64">
          <num>64.</num>
          <heading>Application of sections 10 and 21.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-64.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of  sections 10 and 21 shall be applicable to all ports heretofore or  hereafter declared by the  Government] to be ports for the shipment  and landing of goods but not otherwise</p>
              <p>subject to this Act, and may be enforced by any Magistrate to whose  ordinary jurisdiction any such port is subject.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-64.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any penalties imposed by him, and any expenses incurred by  his order, under the said provisions, shall be recoverable  respectively in the manner provided in sections 55 and 57.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-64.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In any of the said ports for the shipment and landing of  goods the consent referred to in section 21, sub- section (4), may be  given by the principal officer of customs at such port or by any other  officer appointed in that behalf by the  Government].</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-65">
          <num>65.</num>
          <heading>Grant of sites for sailors' institutes. Any local authority  in which any immoveable property in or near a port is vested may,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-65.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>with the previous sanction, in the case of a cantonment authority  or the port authority of a major port, of the Central Government, and  in other cases, of the State Government], appropriate and either  retain and apply, or transfer by way of gift or otherwise, the whole  or any part of the property as a site for, or for use as, a sailors'</p>
              <p>home or other institution for the health, recreation and temporal  well- being of sailors.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-66">
          <num>66.</num>
          <heading>Exercise of powers of conservator by his assistants.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-66.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All  acts, orders, or directions by this Act authorized to be done or given  by any conservator may, subject to his control, be done or given by  any harbour- master or any deputy or assistant of such conservator or  harbour- master.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-66.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person authorized by this Act to do any act may call to  his aid such assistance as may be necessary.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-67">
          <num>67.</num>
          <heading>Service of written notices of directions. Any written notice  of a direction given under this Act, left for the master of any vessel  with any person employed on board thereof, or affixed on a conspicuous  place on board of the vessel, shall, for the purposes of this Act, be  deemed to have been given to the master thereof.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-68">
          <num>68.</num>
          <heading>Publication of orders of Government. Every declaration, order  and rule of a  Government] made in pursuance of this Act shall be  published in the Official Gazette, and a copy thereof shall be kept in  the office of the conservator and at the custom- house, if any, of  every port to which the declaration, order or rule relates, and shall  there be open at all reasonable times to the inspection of any person  without payment of any fee.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-68A">
          <num>68A.</num>
          <heading>Authorities exercising jurisdiction in ports to co-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-68A.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>operate in manoeuvres for defence of port. Every authority exercising  any powers or jurisdiction in, or relating to, any port to which this</p>
              <p>Act for the time being applies, shall, if so required by an officer  authorized by general or special order of the Central Government in  this behalf, co- operate in such manner as such officer may direct, in  carrying out any manoeuvres in connection with any scheme or  preparations for the defence of the said port in time of war, and for  this purpose shall, if so required, temporarily place at the disposal  of such officer the services of any of its staff and the use of any of  its vessels, property, equipment or other material:</p>
              <p>Provided, firstly, that if any vessels are placed at the disposal  of such officer in accordance with this section, the Central</p>
              <p>Government shall, in respect of the period during which they are so at  his disposal, bear the running expenses of such vessels, and be  responsible for any damage thereto.</p>
              <p>Explanation.-- The expression" running expenses" in this proviso  includes all outlay incurred in connection with the use of the vessels  other than any charges for their hire, or for the wages of the  officers and crews of such vessels:</p>
              <p>Provided, secondly, that any officer making a requisition under  this section shall exercise his powers in such a way as to cause as  little disturbance to the ordinary business of the port as is  compatible with the exigencies of the efficient carrying out of the  manoeuvres:</p>
              <p>Provided, thirdly, that no suit or other legal proceeding shall  lie against any authority for any default occurring by reason only of  compliance with a requisition under this section.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-68B">
          <num>68B.</num>
          <heading>Duties of the said authorities in an emergency. Whenever the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-68B.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Central Government is of opinion that an emergency has arisen which  renders it necessary that the duties imposed for the purposes  specified in section 68A on the authorities therein mentioned, or  other duties of a like nature, should be imposed on such authorities  continuously during the existence of the emergency, it may, by general  or special order, authorize any officer to require the said  authorities to perform such duties until the Central Government is of  opinion that the emergency has passed, and the said authority shall  comply accordingly, and the provisions of the said section shall apply  subject to the following modification, namely:--</p>
              <p>The Central Government shall pay any authority, on whom a  requisition has been made, such compensation for any loss or damage  attributable to such requisition, and for any services rendered or  expenditure incurred in complying therewith as, in default of agree-</p>
              <p>ment, shall be decided to be just and reasonable, having regard to the  circumstances of the case, by the arbitration of a person to be  nominated in this behalf by the Central Government, and the decision  of such person shall be final.]</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-68C">
          <num>68C.</num>
          <heading>Application of certain provisions of the Act to aircraft.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-68C.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of sections 6, 13 to 16 (both inclusive), 18, 21  and 28, sub- section (2) of section 31 and sections 33, 34, 35, 39, 42  to 48 (both inclusive) and 55 shall apply in relation to all aircraft  making use of any port subject to this Act, while on water as they  apply in relation to vessels.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-68C.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No such aircraft shall enter or leave any port subject to  this Act, except with the permission granted by the conservator of the  port or by such other officer as may be authorized in this behalf by  the conservator.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-69">
          <num>69.</num>
          <heading>Repeal. Rep. by the Repealing Act, 1938 (1 of 1938), s. 2  and Sch.</heading>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
