<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1948/61/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1948/61"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Central Silk Board Act, 1948"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1948/61/eng@1948-09-20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1948/61/eng@1948-09-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1948-09-20" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1948/61/eng@1948-09-20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1948/61/eng@1948-09-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Central Silk Board Act, 1948</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 61 OF 1948</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 20th September, 1948.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the development under Central control of the    silk industry and for that purpose to establish a Central</p>
        <p>Silk Board.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the development under</p>
        <p>Central control of the  silk industry and for that purpose to  establish a Central Silk Board;</p>
        <p>It is hereby enacted as follows:--</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and extent.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Central</p>
            <p>Silk Board Act, 1948.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India .]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Declaration as to expediency of Union control. It is hereby  declared that it is expedient in the public interest that the Union  should take under its control the silk industry.]</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant  in the subject or context,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" Board" means the Central Silk Board constituted under  this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" charkha raw silk" means raw silk reeled from silk worm  cocoons with the help of any instrument not worked by  power;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" filature raw silk" means raw silk reeled from silk worm  cocoons with the help of any instrument worked by  power;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>" power" means any form of energy which is mechanically  transmitted and is not generated by human or animal  agency, and includes electrical energy;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>" spun silk" means silk yarn spun from pierced or spoilt  cocoons, fluff from cocoons, pieces of silk, noils, or  other silk waste;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>" Standing Committee" means the Standing Committee of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Board constituted under sub- section (2) of section 6.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Constitution of the Board.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>As soon as may be after the  commencement of this Act, the Central Government shall, by  notification in the Official Gazette, constitute for the purposes of  this Act a Board to be called the Central Silk Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall be a body corporate by the name aforesaid,</p>
            <p>having perpetual succession and a common seal, with power to acquire,</p>
            <p>hold and dispose of property, both movable and immovable, and to  contract, and shall by the said name sue and be sued.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Board shall consist of the following members, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>a chairman to be appointed by the Central Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>not more than three officials to be nominated by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Central Government:</p>
            <blockList id="section-4.3.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that it shall be lawful for any such official to  depute in the prescribed circumstances another official  to attend any meeting of the Board on his behalf;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.3.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>six persons to be elected by Parliament, four from the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>House of the People by the members of the House of the</p>
            <blockList id="section-4.3.list7">
              <listIntroduction>People and two from the Council of States by the  members of the Council of States;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.3.list7.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>five persons] to be nominated by the Government of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-4.3.list9">
              <listIntroduction>Karnataka], one of whom shall represent the filature  raw silk industry and two shall represent the rest of  the sericulture industry;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.3.list9.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>one person] to be nominated by the Government of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-4.3.list11">
              <listIntroduction>Tamil Nadu];</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.3.list11.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>two persons to be nominated by the Government of West</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-4.3.list13">
              <listIntroduction>Bengal;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.3.list13.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>one person to be nominated by each of the Governments of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Andhra Pradesh], Assam, Bihar,  Gujarat],</p>
            <blockList id="section-4.3.list16">
              <listIntroduction>Madhya Pradesh and Uttar Pradesh;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.3.list16.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>one person to be nominated by the Government of Jammu  and Kashmir:--</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.3.list16.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>not more than three persons to be nominated by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-4.3.list18">
              <listIntroduction>Central Government to represent the producers of raw  silk and areas other than the States specified in  clauses (d) to (g) inclusive;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.3.list18.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>eight persons to be nominated by the Central Government,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>of whom one shall represent the spun silk industry, one  the silk throwing and twisting industry, one the silk  weaving industry, one labour; and two of them shall be  experts in sericulture.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The members of the Board shall receive from its funds such  travelling and other allowances as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Power of the Central Government in default of nominations.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any Government other than the Central Government fails to make any  nomination which it is entitled to make under sub- section (3) of  section 4 within the time prescribed in that behalf, the Central</p>
            <p>Government may make the nomination itself.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a member of the Board dies, resigns, is removed, ceases  to reside in India, or becomes incapable of acting, the authority or  body entitled to nominate the member under sub- section (3) of section</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>may nominate a person to fill the vacancy; and where such nomination  is not made within the time prescribed in that behalf, the Central</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Government on its own initiative, may make the nomination itself.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No act done by the Board shall be questioned on the ground  merely of the existence of any vacancy in, or defect in the  constitution of, the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Vice- Chairman and Standing Committee.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central</p>
            <p>Government shall appoint from among the members of the Board] a Vice-</p>
            <p>Chairman who shall exercise such of the powers and perform such of the  duties of the Chairman as may be prescribed or as may be delegated to  him by the Chairman.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board may, in its discretion, constitute a Standing</p>
            <p>Committee for the purpose of exercising such of its powers and  performing such of its duties as may be delegated by it, not being  powers or duties the delegation of which is prohibited by rules made  under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Standing Committee shall consist of the Chairman, the</p>
            <p>Vice- Chairman, and five others elected by the Board from among its  members.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Secretary of the Board. The Central Government shall   appoint a Secretary to the Board who shall, under the control and  direction of the Board, exercise such powers and perform such duties  as may be prescribed or as may be delegated to him by the Board or the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Chairman.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Functions of the Board.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be the duty of the Board  to promote the development of the  silk industry by such measures  as it thinks fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing  provision, the measures referred to therein may provide for--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>undertaking, assisting or encouraging scientific,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-8.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>technological and economic research;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.2.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>devising means for improved methods of mulberry  cultivation rearing, developing and distributing  healthy silk- worm seeds,  reeling or, as the case  may be, spinning of silk- worm cocoons and silk  waste], improving the quality and production of raw  silk, if necessary, by making it compulsory for all  raw silk to be marketed only after the same has  been tested and graded in properly equipped raw silk  conditioning houses;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list3.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>improving the marketing of raw silk;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list3.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the collection of statistics from such persons as may be  prescribed;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-8.2.list3.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>carrying out any other duties which may be vested in  the Board under rules made under this Act.]</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-8.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>It shall also be the duty of the Board--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to advise the Central Government on all matters relating  to the development of the raw silk industry,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-8.3.list3">
              <listIntroduction>including the import and export of raw silk;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-8.3.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>to prepare and furnish such  reports relating to the    silk industry as may be required by the Central</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Government from time to time.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Funds of the Board.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government shall from time  to time make grants to the Board of such sums as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may consider necessary for enabling the Board to exercise  its powers and discharge its duties under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The funds of the Board shall be kept in such bank, or  invested in such manner, as may be prescribed, and shall be expended  by the Board</p>
            <p>only in the performance of its functions under this Act or for meeting  such expenses as are authorised by this Act or by rules made  thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Imposition of cess on certain kinds of silk.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>With effect  from such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the</p>
            <p>Official Gazette appoint, there shall be levied and collected as a  cess for the purposes of this Act a duty of exercise on all filature  raw silk, and on all spun silk, reeled in the territories to which  this Act for the time being extends at such rate as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, from time to  time fix.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The said duty of excise shall be payable by the reelers of  filature raw silk or spun silk and shall be paid by them to the Board  within one month from the date of the receipt of the notice of demand  from the Board in that behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The said duty of excise may be recovered as if it were an  arrear of land revenue.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.4.list1">
              <listIntroduction>For the purpose of enabling the Board to assess the amount of  the duty of excise payable under this section by the reelers of  filature raw silk or spun silk,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.4.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the Board shall, by notification in the Official</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-10.4.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Gazette, fix the period in respect of which assessments  shall be made, and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.4.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>every reeler of filature raw silk or spun silk shall  furnish to the Board within the prescribed time a  return specifying the total amount of filature raw silk  or spun silk reeled during such period.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any reeler of filature raw silk or spun silk fails to  furnish such return within the prescribed time or furnishes a return  which the Board has reason to believe to be incorrect or defective,</p>
            <p>the Board may assess the amount payable by such reeler in such manner  as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any reeler feeling himself aggrieved by an assessment made  under this section may, within three months of the receipt of the  notice under sub- section (2), apply to the District Judge or such  other civil judicial officer as may be prescribed, for the  cancellation or modification of the assessment; and such District</p>
            <p>Judge or judicial officer shall, after giving the Board an opportunity  of being heard, pass such order as he thinks proper; and such order  shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The proceeds of the duties of excise paid to the Board  shall first be credited to the Consolidated Fund of India and the</p>
            <p>Central Government may, thereafter, from time to time, pay to the</p>
            <p>Board from and out of such proceeds such sums of money as its may  think fit.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Control by the Central Government.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All acts of the Board  shall be subject to the control of the Central Government which may  cancel, suspend or modify as it thinks fit any action taken, or order  passed, by the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The records of the Board shall be open to inspection at all  reasonable times by any officer authorized in this behalf by the</p>
            <p>Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Accounts of the Board.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board shall keep such  accounts, and in such manner and form, as may be prescribed, in  respect of all moneys received and expended by it.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The accounts of the Board shall be audited by the</p>
            <p>Comptroller and Auditor- General of India at such intervals as may be  specified by him and any expenditure incurred in connection with such  audit shall be payable by the Board to the Comptroller and Auditor-</p>
            <p>General.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any person  appointed by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the</p>
            <p>Board shall have the same rights, privileges and authority in  connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor- General of</p>
            <p>India has in connection with the audit of Government accounts, and, in  particular, shall have the right to demand the production of books,</p>
            <p>accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and to  inspect any of the offices of the Board.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The accounts of the Board as certified by the Comptroller and</p>
            <p>Auditor- General of India or any person appointed by him in this behalf  together with the audit report thereon shall be forwarded annually to  the Central Government and that Government shall cause a copy of the  same to be laid before each House of Parliament.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A copy of the accounts of the Board as so certified together  with the audit report thereon shall be forwarded simultaneously to the</p>
            <p>Board.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12A">
        <num>12A.</num>
        <heading>Annual report. The Board shall prepare for every  financial year a report of its activities and achievements during that  year and submit the report to the Central Government in such form and  on or before such date as may be prescribed, and that Government shall  cause a copy of the report to be laid before each House of</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Parliament.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Power of Central Government to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules   to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of  the foregoing power, rules made under this section may provide for all  or any of the following matters, namely:--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the term of office of members of the Board, the  circumstances in which and the authority by which  members may be removed and the filling of casual  vacancies in the Board;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>the procedure to be followed at meetings of the Board  and at the Standing Committee for the conduct of  business and the number of members which shall  form a quorum at any meeting;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list1.iii">
                <num>(iii)</num>
                <p>the maintenance by the Board of records of business  transacted by the Board and the submission of  copies thereof to the Central Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list1.iv">
                <num>(iv)</num>
                <p>the holding of a minimum number of meetings every  year;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list1.v">
                <num>(v)</num>
                <p>the power of the Board, its Chairman and Standing</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-13.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Committee with respect to the incurring of  expenditure;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.2.list3.vi">
                <num>(vi)</num>
                <p>the conditions subject to which the Board may incur  expenditure outside India;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list3.vii">
                <num>(vii)</num>
                <p>the preparation of budget estimates of receipts and  expenditure of the Board and the authority by  which the estimates are to be sanctioned;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list3.viii">
                <num>(viii)</num>
                <p>the maintenance of the accounts of income and  expenditure of the Board ;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list3.viiia">
                <num>(viiia)</num>
                <p>the form of the annual report of the Board and  the date on or before which it shall be  submitted to the Central Government;]</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list3.ix">
                <num>(ix)</num>
                <p>the deposit of the funds of the Board in bank and the  investment of such funds;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list3.x">
                <num>(x)</num>
                <p>the re- appropriation of estimated savings from one  budget head to any other budget head;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list3.xi">
                <num>(xi)</num>
                <p>the conditions subject to which the Board may borrow  funds;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list3.xii">
                <num>(xii)</num>
                <p>the conditions subject to which and the manner in  which contracts may be entered into by or on  behalf of the Board;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list3.xiii">
                <num>(xiii)</num>
                <p>the delegation to the Standing Committee or the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-13.2.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Chairman or the Vice- Chairman or members or  officers of the Board of any of the powers and  duties of the Board under this Act;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.2.list5.xiv">
                <num>(xiv)</num>
                <p>the staff which may be employed by the Board and the  pay and allowances, leave and other conditions of  service of officers and other employees of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-13.2.list7">
              <listIntroduction>Board;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.2.list7.xv">
                <num>(xv)</num>
                <p>the travelling and other allowances of members of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-13.2.list9">
              <listIntroduction>Board and of the Standing Committee;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.2.list9.xvi">
                <num>(xvi)</num>
                <p>the purposes for which funds of the Board may be  expended;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list9.xvii">
                <num>(xvii)</num>
                <p>the maintenance of the registers and other records of  the Board and of its Standing Committee;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list9.xviii">
                <num>(xviii)</num>
                <p>the collection of any information or statistics in  respect of raw silk or any product of silk;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list9.xix">
                <num>(xix)</num>
                <p>the manner in which raw silk shall be graded and  marketed;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.2.list9.xx">
                <num>(xx)</num>
                <p>any other matter which is to be or may be prescribed.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon  as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament while it  is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised  in one session or in two successive sessions, and if, before the  expiry of the session in which it is so laid or the session  immediately following both Houses agree in making any modification in  the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the  rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of  no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification  or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that ruel.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Penalties.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>] If any person--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>in any return to be furnished under this Act makes any  statement which is false and which he knows to be false  or does not believe to be ture, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>obstructs any officer of the Board in the exercise of  any power, conferred, or the discharge of any duty  imposed, on him by or under this Act, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>having the control or custody of any account book or  other record, fails to produce such book or record when  required so to do under this Act,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend  to one year, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or  with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the person committing any offence specified in sub-</p>
            <p>section (1) is a company, every person who, at the time the offence  was committed</p>
            <p>was in charge of, and was responsible to, the company for the conduct  of the business of the company as well as the company shall be deemed  to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded  against and punished accordingly:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render  any such person liable to any punishment provided in this Act, if he  proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or that he  exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (2), where  an offence under sub- section (1) has been committed by a company and  it is proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or  connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any  director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such  director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to  be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against  and punished accordingly.</p>
            <blockList id="section-14.3.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section.--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.3.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm  or other association of individuals; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-14.3.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" director" in relation to a firm means a partner in the  firm.]</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Prosecution to be with consent of Central Government. No  prosecution for any offence punsihable under this Act shall be  instituted except by, or with the consent of, the Central Government.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15A">
        <num>15A.</num>
        <heading>Jurisdiction of Courts. No Court inferior to that of a</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-15A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Presidency Magistrate or a Magistrate of the first class shall try any  offence punishable under section 14.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Bar of legal proceedings. No suit, prosecution or other legal  proceeding shall lie against the Board, or any member or officer of  the Board, for anything in good faith done or intended to be done  under this Act.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Temporary powers of the Central Government. Rep. by the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Central Silk Board (Amendment) Act, 1953 (31 of 1953), s. 11.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
