<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1933/23/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1933/23"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Murshidabad Estate Administration Act, 1933"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1933/23/eng@1933-09-21/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1933/23/eng@1933-09-21"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1933-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1933/23/eng@1933-09-21/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1933/23/eng@1933-09-21"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Murshidabad Estate Administration Act, 1933</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 23 OF 1933</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 21st September, 1933.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>AN ACT TO PROVIDE FOR THE APPOINTMENT OF A MANAGER ON BEHALF</p>
        <p>OF THESECRETARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title and extent.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Murshidabad Estate Administration Act, 1933.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to whole of India except  the territories which  immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised in Part</p>
            <p>States].]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in  the subject or context,-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>immoveable properties of the estate" means the  properties contained in the Schedules of immoveable  property annexed to the Indenture included in and  confirmed by the Murshidabad Act, 1891, (15 of 1891.)</p>
            <p>with any additional immoveable property added thereto  under sub- section (1) of section 3 of that Act, and  includes all immoveable property acquire under the  provisions of section 32 of the Land Acquisition Act,</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1894">
        <num>1894.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1894.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>; (1 of 1894.)</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-1894.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>issues and profits of the immoveable properties of  the estate" includes all money awarded under the Land</p>
            <p>Acquisition Act, 1894, (1 of 1894.) as compensation for  the acquisition of any of the immoveable properties of  the estate together with interest thereon;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1894.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" Manager" means the officer appointed under  section 3</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1894.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" Nawab Bahadur" means the Nawab Bahadur of</p>
            <p>Murshidabad for the time being;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1894.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>" Board of Revenue" means the Board of Revenue,</p>
            <p>West Bengal]</p>
            <blockList id="section-1894.6.list3">
              <listIntroduction>thirdly. so long as such management continues-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1894.6.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the Nawab Bahadur shall be incompetent to mortgage,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-1894.6.list5">
              <listIntroduction>charge, lease, settle or alienate the immoveable  properties of the estate, or to grant valid receipts for  the rents and profits arising or accruing therefrom;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1894.6.list5.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>such property shall be exempt from attachment or  sale under process of any Court; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1894.6.list5.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the Nawab Bahadur shall be incapable of entering into  any contract which may involve him in pecuniary  liability; and fourthly, any amount awarded, before the entry  of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>State Government] upon the immovable properties of the  estate, under the Land Acquisition Act, 1894, (1 of</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1894">
        <num>1894.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1894.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>) by way of compensation for immoveable properties  of the estate acquired under that Act, if the amount has  been invested in securities under section 32 of that Act  or is deposited in Court pending such investment in land  or securities, shall, together with all interest and  other proceeds thereof not already paid to any person  under the provisions of any law, be deliverable to the</p>
            <p>Manager on behalf  of the State Government] to be  disposed of in such manner as the  State Government]</p>
            <p>may think fit.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Suits and appeals during managements. So long as the  appointment of the Manager continues-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>in every suit or appeal to which     the State of  West Bengal]] in possession is a party  the Manager shall be named as'  its representative] for  the purpose of such suit or appeal;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>in every pending suit or appeal concerning the  properties under management  the State of  West</p>
            <p>Bengal] 1 in possession shall be a party in place of the</p>
            <p>Nawab Bahadur and the Manager shall be named as the  representative of  the State of  West Bengal]] in  possession for the purpose of the suit or appeal; and  no application in any such suit or appeal shall be made  to the Court on behalf of  the State of  West Bengal]</p>
            <p>] in possession except by the Manager;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>the Court upon application by the Manager or by  any party to the suit may order that the plaint or  memorandum of appeal be amended so as to conform with  the requirements of clause (1) or that the Manager be  named as the representative of the  State of West</p>
            <p>Bengal] in possession as required by clause (2) of this  section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Manager to receive rents. issues and profits.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Manager  shall receive and recover all rents, issues and profits due in respect  of the immoveable properties of the estate, and shall upon receiving  such rents, issues and profits give receipts therefor.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Manager shall receive the monthly sum of Rs. 19, 166- 10- 3  payable from the Government Treasury at Berhampore in the district of</p>
            <p>Murshidabad in  West Bengal] and shall give receipts therefor.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Application by Manager of sums received.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>From the sums  received under sub- sections (1) and (2) of section 6, the Manager  shall pay-</p>
            <p>first, to the Nawab Bahadur such monthly sum, not being  in any case less than Rs. 9, 583- 5- 4, as the State</p>
            <p>Government may fix in this behalf;</p>
            <p>secondly, the allowances, if any, payable under  section 3 of the Murshidabad Act, 1946];</p>
            <p>thirdly], the Government revenue, cesses, rates and  taxes and all debts and liabilities for the time being  due or incurred to Government or to any local authority;</p>
            <p>fourthly], in the case of property held by the Nawab</p>
            <p>Bahadur as tenant, the rent and cess due to the superior  landlord in respect of the said property;</p>
            <p>fifthly], the cost of such repairs and improvements of  the immoveable properties of the estate as appear  necessary to the Manager and are approved by the Board  of Revenue;</p>
            <p>and shall apply the residue to the discharge of the costs of the  management, to the payment of expenditure incurred in litigation and  to the settlement in accordance with the scheme approved by the Board  of Revenue under section 14 of such debts and liabilities of the Nawab</p>
            <p>Bahadur as may be established under the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), it  shall be lawful for the Manager to pay out of the sums received under  subsections (1) and (2) of section 6 any sum required to meet such  expenditure on any other object or for any other purpose as the</p>
            <p>State Government] may from time to time sanction.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Notice to claimants. As soon as may be after the publication of  the order for the appointment of a Manager under section 3 the Manager  shall publish in the prescribed manner a notice in English and Bengali  calling upon all persons having claims against the Nawab Bahadur to  notify such claims in writing to the Manager within six months from  the date of the notice.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Presentation of claims. Every such claimant shall, along with  his claim, present to the Manager full particulars thereof, together  with all documents on which he relies in support thereof, and the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Manager may refuse to receive in evidence on the claimant' s behalf at  the investigation of the claim any document not so presented.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Debt not duly notified to barred. Every debt or liability,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>except debts due or liabilities incurred to the Government or to any  local authority and rent due to a superior landlord from the Nawab</p>
            <p>Bahadur as tenant of any property, which is not duly notified to the</p>
            <p>Manager within the time and in the manner mentioned in sections 8 and</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>shall be barred:</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Provided that if the Manager is satisfied that the claimant was  for reasonable cause unable to comply with the provisions of sections</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>and 9, the Manager may admit his claim within a further period of  six months from the expiration of the period of six months specified  in section 8.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Determination of debts. The Manager shall in the prescribed  manner determine the amount of the principal of all debts and  liabilities not barred under section 10 justly due to the several  creditors of the Nawab Bahadur and to persons holding mortgages,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>charges or liens on the property of the Nawab Bahadur, and shall  determine in like manner the interest, if any, due at the date of such  determination in respect of such debts and liabilities and may reduce  the rates of interest charged as appears to him just and proper.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Power to inquire into consideration for leases, etc. The</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Manager may inquire into the sufficiency of the consideration for  which any lease, settlement, grant, mortgage, charge or lien was given  and whether it was given in contravention of the conditions of the</p>
            <p>Murshidabad Act, 1891, (15 of 1891.) and if satisfied that the con-</p>
            <p>sideration was insufficient or that such lease, settlement, grant,</p>
            <p>mortgage, charge or lien was given in contravention of the said Act  may, by order in writing, set aside or modify such lease, settlement,</p>
            <p>grant, mortgage, charge or lien; and any such order, subject to the  appeal provided in section 13, shall have the force of a decree of a  competent Civil Court and be enforceable as such.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Appeals to Board of Revenue.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>An appeal shall lie to the</p>
            <blockList id="section-13.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Board of Revenue against any order by the Manager-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>refusing to receive a document under section 9;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-13.1.list4">
              <listIntroduction>or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-13.1.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>refusing to admit a claim under the proviso to  section 10; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.1.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>determining the amount of a debt or liability or  of interest thereon, or reducing the rate of  interest, under section 11 or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.1.list4.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>setting aside or modifying a lease, settlement,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>grant, mortgage. charge or lien under section 12.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If no such. appeal is preferred within six weeks from the  date of the order, the decision of the Manager shall, subject to the  provisions of section 22, be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Scheme for settlement of debts.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When the amount due in  respect of the debts and liabilities mentioned in section 11 has been  finally determined, the Manager shall prepare and submit to the Board  of Revenue a schedule of such debts and liabilities, and a scheme for  the settlement thereof in whole or in part out of the residue referred  to in section 7 annually available during the lifetime of the Nawab</p>
            <p>Bahadur; and the Board of Revenue may approve the scheme without  modification or subject to such modification as it deems expedient.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-14.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The scheme shall provide for payment in full, as soon as may  be, of-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>first, arrears of wages due to servants of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-14.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Nawab Bahadur, determined in accordance with the  forgoing provisions, and</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-14.2.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>secondly, claims of each creditor whose claims in  the aggregate do not exceed five hundred rupees, as so  determined;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>and the scheme shall further provide that any balance left after meet-</p>
            <p>ing the above claims and each annual residue thereafter shall be dis-</p>
            <p>tributed rateably among the other creditors of the Nawab Bahadur in  payment of their claims, as so determined.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Power to call for further particulars. The Manager may from  time to time call for further and more detailed particulars of any  claim preferred before him under this Act and may at his discretion  refuse to proceed with the investigation of the claim until such  particulars are supplied.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Power to summon witnesses. The Manager may for the purpose of  any investigation under this Act summon and enforce the attendance of  witnesses and compel them to give evidence, and compel the production  of documents, by the same means and as far as possible in the same  manner as is provided in the case of a Civil Court by the Code of</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Civil Procedure, 1908. (5 of 1908.)</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Investigation to be deemed a judicial proceeding. Every  investigation conducted by the Manager with reference to any claim  preferred before him under this Act, or to any matter connected with  such claim, shall be deemed to be a judicial proceeding within the  meaning of the Indian Penal Code; (45 of 1860.) and every statement  made by any person examined by or before the Manager with reference to  any such investigation, whether upon oath or otherwise, shall be  deemed to be evidence within the meaning of the said Code.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Power to order production of accounts, papers, etc., and  evidence of title.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Collector of Murshidabad may on the  application of the Manager order all persons who are or were in the  employ of the estate of the Nawab Bahadur to attend before him; and  may order any person to deliver up any accounts, papers or moveable  property belonging to the estate or any accounts or papers relating to  the immoveable property of the estate or to any other property of the  estate which the Manager has reason to believe are in such person' s  possession or control; and may order all holders of tenures or under-</p>
            <p>tenures on any such property to produce their titles to such tenures  or undertenures.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person who refuses to comply with an order under sub-</p>
            <p>section (1) may be punished by the Collector of Murshidabad with fine  not exceeding five hundred rupees:</p>
            <p>Provided that an appeal shall lie to the Board of Revenue against  any order of fine passed by the Collector under sub- section (2).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Powers of Manager for realisation of rents, etc.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-19.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The</p>
            <p>Manager shall have, for the purpose of realising and recovering the  rents, issues and profits of the immoveable properties of the estate,</p>
            <p>the same powers as the Nawab Bahadur would have had for such purpose  had the  State Government] not entered into the said properties, and  all arrears of rent and all demands recoverable as rent, and all  interest due on such arrears or demands shall together with all costs  incurred for realising the same be recoverable as public demands.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If such properties or any part thereof be in the possession  of any mortgagee or conditional vendee, the Manager may apply to the</p>
            <p>Collector within whose jurisdiction the property is situated, and the</p>
            <p>Collector shall cause the same to be delivered to the Manager as if a  decree therefor had been made in his favour, but without prejudice</p>
            <p>to the mortgagee or vendee preferring his claim under the provisions  elsewhere contained in this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-19.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If such properties or any part thereof be in possession of a</p>
            <p>Receiver appointed by a Court, the Manager may apply to the Court, and  the Court shall cause the same to be delivered to the Manager together  with any receipts which may be in the hands of the Receiver or the</p>
            <p>Court at the time of the application.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-20">
        <num>20.</num>
        <heading>Powers to lease. The Manager may, subject to the prescribed  conditions, make settlement of all or any of the immoveable properties  of the estate and may for this purpose execute any lease or  counterpart of a lease:</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Provided that, unless the settlement is of a kind authorised by  rule made under section 28, its terms and conditions shall have been  previously approved by the State Government.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-21">
        <num>21.</num>
        <heading>Power of Manager to contract and take action for the benefit  of the estate. The Manager may enter into any contract or take any  action which in his opinion is necessary for the proper care and  management of the immoveable properties of the estate and of the  rents, issues and profits thereof or for the maintenance of the  position and dignity of the Nawab Bahadur and which is not  inconsistent with any provision of this Act or with any rule made  under section 28:</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Provided that if he is not empowered by any other provision of  this Act or by any rule made under section 28 to enter on such con-</p>
            <p>tract or to take such action he shall obtain the previous sanction of  the Board of Revenue before entering upon the contract or taking the  action.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-22">
        <num>22.</num>
        <heading>Powers of supervision and control.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-22.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All orders or  proceedings of the Manager in the exercise of his functions under this</p>
            <p>Act shall be subject to the supervision and control of the Board of</p>
            <p>Revenue.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-22.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>All orders or proceedings of the Board of Revenue under this</p>
            <p>Act shall be subject to the supervision and control of the State Gov-</p>
            <p>ernment.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-22.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The supervising authority in each case may of its own motion  review and if it thinks fit revise, modify or reverse any order of  proceeding.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-23">
        <num>23.</num>
        <heading>Manager to be deemed a public servant. The Manager shall be  deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of section 21 of the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-24">
        <num>24.</num>
        <heading>Recovery of fines. Any fine imposed under this Act shall be  recoverable as a public demand.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-25">
        <num>25.</num>
        <heading>Bar of suits, etc., against certain persons. No suit or other  legal proceeding shall lie against any person in respect of anything  which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-26">
        <num>26.</num>
        <heading>Power of State Government to make orders. If at the time of the  withdrawal of the  State Government] from entry upon the immoveable  properties of the estate, any difficulty arises in connection with the  restoration to the Nawab Bahadur or to his successor of the properties  and rights possessed and exercised by the  State Government], the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>State Government may by order authorise the doing of any matter or  thing which appears to it necessary to facilitate such restoration.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-27">
        <num>27.</num>
        <heading>Effect of withdrawal from entry by State Government.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained elsewhere in this or any other Act,</p>
            <p>the withdrawal by the  State Government] from entry upon the  immoveable properties of the estate shall not have the effect of  reviving any of the proceedings referred to in clause first of section</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>if the debt or liability in respect of which such proceedings were  instituted is barred under section 10.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Nothing in section 4 shall bar the revival after such withdrawal  of any other of the proceedings referred to in the said clause:</p>
            <p>Provided that no Court shall entertain any suit or proceeding  against the Nawab Bahadur in which the amount claimed is in excess of  the amount determined under section 11, 13 or 22, as the case may be,</p>
            <p>together with any further interest due thereon, or in which interest  is claimed at a rate higher than the rate determined as just and  proper under those sections.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-28">
        <num>28.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-28.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Board of Revenue may, with the  previous sanction of the State Government make rules for the purpose  of carrying into effect all or any of the provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-28.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing powers, such rules may provide for all or any of the follow-</p>
            <blockList id="section-28.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>ing matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-28.2.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the security to be required from subordinate  officers under Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28.2.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the procedure to be followed by the Manager in the  discharge of his functions under this Act, the accounts  which shall be kept by him, and the manner in which such  accounts shall be audited;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28.2.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the terms, conditions and limitations under which  leases may be granted;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28.2.list2.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the notices to be given under this Act and the  manner of publication of such notices;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28.2.list2.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the procedure to be followed by claimants in  presenting claims, and by the Manager in the  investigation of such claims;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28.2.list2.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the procedure to be followed in determining under  section 11 the debts and liabilities due to creditors  and other persons;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-28.2.list2.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the allowance of interest on the principal of each  of the debts and liabilities as determined under section</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>from the date on which it was incurred to the date of  the determination and on the aggregate amount of such  debts and liabilities from the date of the determination  to the date of payment;</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list0.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the preparation of the schedule of debts and  liabilities and of the scheme referred to in section 14  and the order of payment of such debts and liabilities;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list0.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>the powers of the Manager to make or sanction  settlements; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list0.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>the procedure to be followed in appeals under this</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
