<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1948/26/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1948/26"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Junagadh Administration (Property) Act, 1948"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1948/26/eng@1948-04-13/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1948/26/eng@1948-04-13"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1948-04-13" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1948/26/eng@1948-04-13/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1948/26/eng@1948-04-13"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Junagadh Administration (Property) Act, 1948</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 26 OF 1948</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 13th April, 1948.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the vesting of certain property belonging to the</p>
        <p>State of Junagadh in the Administrator appointed by the Central</p>
        <p>Government.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS on or about the 9th day of November 1947 the  administration of the State of Junagadh was handed over to the Central</p>
        <p>Government;</p>
        <p>AND WHEREAS it is necessary to provide for the vesting of certain  property belonging to the said State in the Administrator thereof, and  for certain incidental matters;</p>
        <p>It is hereby enacted as follows:--</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title. This Act may be called the Junagadh</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Administration (Property) Act, 1948.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definition. In this Act" Administrator" means the person  appointed by the Central Government to be the Administrator of the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>State of Junagadh.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Vesting and disposal of property and powers of Administrator.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time being  in force, the property described in the Schedule, whether in the name  of His Highness the Nawab of Junagadh, or the Dewan or the Private</p>
            <p>Secretary to His Highness the Nawab of Junagadh, or the Manager and</p>
            <p>Engineer- in- Chief, Junagadh State Railway, or the Chief Accounts</p>
            <p>Officer, Junagadh State, or any other person whatsoever or in the name  of more than one of them, shall be deemed on and from the 9th day of</p>
            <p>November 1947 to have vested in the Administrator, and the</p>
            <p>Administrator shall, as from that date, hold and be entitled to and  have the power to deal with and dispose of the said property as such</p>
            <p>Administrator.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing  provisions, the Administrator shall have the power to-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>receive and give full and effectual discharge for or in  respect of the bank deposits, securities and shares  described in the Schedule;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>sell, transfer or otherwise dispose of or deal with  such property.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Issue of duplicate securities. Notwithstanding anything  contained in any law for the time being in force, the Reserve Bank of</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>India shall issue to the Administrator duplicate securities in his  name in lieu of the securities specified in Part II of the Schedule as  if the securities so specified had been lost, and such duplicate  securities shall have the same effect as if they had been issued under  section 11 of the Public Debts (Central Government) Act, 1944 (18 of</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1944">
        <num>1944.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1944.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>).</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Transfers otherwise than by Administrator void. Any transfer  of, or dealing with, any of the property described in the Schedule  after the 8th day of November 1947, otherwise than by the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Administrator, shall be, and shall always be deemed to have been, void  and of no effect.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Bar of jurisdiction.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No Court shall have jurisdiction to  entertain any suit or other proceeding in respect of any of the  property described in the Schedule or to enforce any liability in  respect thereof, otherwise than at the instance of the Administrator.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any claim in respect of such property by any person other  than the Administrator may be submitted to the Central Government,</p>
            <p>whose decision in the matter shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken under this Act. No suit,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central</p>
            <p>Government, the Reserve Bank of India, any bank or company named in</p>
            <p>Parts I and III of the Schedule or any person for anything which is in  good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of any of the  provisions of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Power of the Central Government to add to the Schedule. The</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Central Government may from time to time add to the items of property  included in the Schedule by notification in the Official gazette and  on such notification such property shall be deemed to have been always  included in the Schedule.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Repeal of Ordinance No. 30 of 1947.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Junagadh</p>
            <p>Administration (Property) Ordinance, 1947, is hereby repealed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Anything done or any action taken in exercise of any power  conferred by or under the said Ordinance shall, so far as it is not  inconsistent with this Act, be deemed to have been done or taken in  exercise of the powers conferred by or under this Act as if this Act  had commenced on the 24th day of December, 1947.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
