<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1892/10/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1892/10"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Government Management Of Private Estates Act, 1892"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1892/10/eng@1892-10-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1892/10/eng@1892-10-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1892-10-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1892/10/eng@1892-10-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1892/10/eng@1892-10-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Government Management Of Private Estates Act, 1892</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 10 OF 1892</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 25th October, 1892.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the levy of a rate on private estates under the  management of the Government to meet the cost of supervision and  management.</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Title and extent.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Government</p>
            <p>Management Private Estates Act, 1892.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India except the territories  which, immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised in</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <part id="part-B">
        <num>B</num>
        <heading>States] ;</heading>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless there is something repugnant  in the subject or context,--</heading>
          <subsection id="section-2.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" immoveable property" includes land, buildings,</p>
              <p>hereditary allowances, rights to ways, lights, ferries,</p>
              <p>fisheries or any other benefit to arise out of land,</p>
              <p>and things attached to the earth or permanently  fastened to anything which is attached to the earth but  not standing timber, growing crops or grass;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>" gross income" includes all receipts of every kind in  produce or cash, except money borrowed, recoveries of  principal and the proceeds of sale of immoveable  property or of moveable property properly classed as  capital; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>" private estates under Government management" include--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>estates under the Court of Wards;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.3.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>encumbered estates under Government  management;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.3.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>estates attached for default of payment  of Government revenue;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.3.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>minors' estates placed under the  guardianship of a revenue- officer of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.3.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Government by a Civil Court;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.3.list3.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>estates managed by a Collector in  pursuance of any order made under the  Code of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Civil Procedure; and</p>
              <blockList id="section-2.3.list6">
                <listIntroduction>(14 of 1882.)</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.3.list6.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>all other estates made over to or taken  under the management of a revenue- officer of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Government as such under any law for the time  being in force or in virtue of any agreement.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Power to levy rate. It shall be lawful for the State</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government--</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>to levy on all private estates under Government  management a rate, not exceeding five per cent. on the  gross income, calculated, as nearly as may be possible,</p>
              <blockList id="section-3.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>to cover--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.1.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the cost of all Government establishments  in so far as they may be employed in the  supervision or management of such estates other  than establishments specially entertained for the  supervision or management of any particular estate  or group of estates, and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.1.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>all contingent expenditure incurred in  consequence of such supervision or management;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>from time to time to vary such rate; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>to reduce or remit such rate in any special case or  cases as may be equitable;</p>
              <p>Provided that, in deciding the amount of the rate to be levied  under this Act on any particular estate or group of estates, the State</p>
              <p>Government shall consider the expenditure incurred on special  establishments for such estate or estates.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Power to levy special charges. In cases where an officer of  the Government is employed to give legal advice or to audit accounts  on behalf of any estate, the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>State Government, if it considers the services rendered to be of a  special nature, may, in its discretion, direct a special charge to be  made against that estate on account of such services, irrespective of  the rate leviable under the last foregoing section.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Saving as to special expenditure. Nothing in this act shall  apply to the cost of establishments specially entertained or to  expenditure of any description specially incurred in respect of any  particular estate or estates.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Validation of levy of past rates. All rates for general  supervision or management levied by any State Government before the  commencement of this Act shall be deemed to have been levied under  this Act.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules. The State Government may make any rules  and issue any orders which may be necessary for carrying this Act into  effect, and which are consistent therewith.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Exemption from jurisdiction of Courts. Where any Government  establishment is employed in such supervision as aforesaid, the State</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government shall be the sole judge of the cost attributable to such  employment, and its decision thereon shall not be questioned in any</p>
              <p>Court of Law or otherwise.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Repeal. Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1914 (10 of</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1914">
          <num>1914.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1914.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>), s. 3 and Sch. II.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
