<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1962/58/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1962/58"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Warehousing Corporations Act, 1962"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1962/58/eng@1962-12-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1962/58/eng@1962-12-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1962-12-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1962/58/eng@1962-12-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1962/58/eng@1962-12-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Warehousing Corporations Act, 1962</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 58 OF 1962</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 19th December, 1962.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the incorporation and regulation of corporations  for the purpose of warehousing of agricultural produce and certain  other commodities and for matters, connected therewith.</p>
        <p>CHAP</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be  called the Warehousing Corporations Act, 1962.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It extends to the whole of India</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on such date  as the Central</p>
              <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>" agricultural produce" means any of the following  classes of commodities, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>foodstuffs, including edible oil- seeds;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>cattle fodder, including oil- cakes and  other concentrates;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a.list0.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>raw cotton, whether ginned or unginned,</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>and cotton seed;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>raw jute; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>vegetable oils;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" appropriate Government" means in relation to the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Central Warehousing Corporation, the Central</p>
              <p>Government, and in relation to a State Warehousing</p>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Corporation, the State Government;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list6.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" Central Warehousing Corporation" means the Central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list8">
                <listIntroduction>Warehousing Corporation established under section 3;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list8.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" co- operative society" means a society registered or  deemed to be registered under the Co- operative</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10">
                <listIntroduction>Societies Act, 1912 (2 of 1912), or under any other  law with respect to co- operative societies for the time  being in force in any State, which is engaged in the  processing, marketing, storage, export or import of  agricultural produce or any notified commodity or in  insurance business and includes a co- operative land  mortgage bank;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10.dd">
                  <num>(dd)</num>
                  <p>" nationalised bank" means a corresponding new bank  specified in the First Schedule to the Banking</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings)</p>
              <p>Act, 1970 (5 of 1970);  or a corresponding new bank  specified in the First Schedule to the Banking</p>
              <p>Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings)</p>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list15">
                <listIntroduction>Act, 1980 (40 of 1980).]</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list15.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>" notified commodity" means any commodity (other than   agricultural produce) which the Central Government may,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>by notification in the Official Gazette, declare to be  a notified commodity for the purposes of this Act,</p>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list18">
                <listIntroduction>being a commodity with respect to which Parliament has  power to make laws by virtue of entry 33 in List III in  the Seventh Schedule to the Constitution;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list18.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list18.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>" recognised association" means an association which is  for the time being recognised by the Central Government  under section 6 of the Forward Contracts (Regulation)</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list20">
                <listIntroduction>Act, 1952 (74 of 1952);</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list20.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>" Reserve Bank" means the Reserve Bank of India  constituted under the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list22">
                <listIntroduction>(2 of 1934);</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list22.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>" scheduled bank" means a bank for the time being  included in the Second Schedule to the Reserve Bank of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list24">
                <listIntroduction>India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934.) , and includes a  nationalised bank];</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list24.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>" State Bank" means the State Bank of India constituted  under the State Bank of India Act, 1955 (23 of 1955);</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list24.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>" State Warehousing Corporation" means a Warehousing</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list26">
                <listIntroduction>Corporation for a State established or deemed to be  established under this Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list26.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>" Warehousing Corporation" means a Warehousing</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list28">
                <listIntroduction>Corporation established or deemed to be established  under this Act; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list28.m">
                  <num>(m)</num>
                  <p>" year" means the financial year.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2A">
          <num>2A.</num>
          <heading>Construction of references to any law not in force or any  functionary not in existence in any State. Any reference in this Act  to any law which is not in force, or any functionary not in existence,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2A.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>in any State, shall, in relation to that State, be construed as a  reference to the corresponding law in force, or the corresponding  functionary in existence, in that State.]</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>THE CENTRAL WAREHOUSING CORPORATION</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>THE CENTRAL WAREHOUSING CORPORATION</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>The Central Warehousing Corporation.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>With effect from such  date  as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official</p>
              <p>Gazette, specify in this behalf, the Central Government shall  establish a Corporation by the name of the Central Warehousing</p>
              <p>Corporation which shall be a body corporate having perpetual  succession and a common seal with power to acquire, hold and dispose  of property and to contract, and may, by the said name, sue and be  sued.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The head- office of the Central Warehousing Corporation shall  be at New Delhi  or at such other place as the Central Government  may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify].</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Share capital and shareholders.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The authorised share  capital of the Central Warehousing Corporation shall be twenty crores  of rupees divided into two hundred thousand shares of the face value  of one thousand rupees each; any shares remaining to be issued may be  issued, with the sanction of the Central Government from time to time,</p>
              <p>as and when the Central Warehousing Corporation may deem fit:</p>
              <p>Provided that the Central Government may, from time to time,</p>
              <p>by order notified in the Official Gazette, increase the authorised  share capital of the Central Warehousing Corporation to such extent  and in such manner as that Government may determine.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government shall, after due appropriation made  by Parliament by law for the purpose,] subscribe for forty per cent.</p>
              <p>of the share capital issued at any time and the remaining sixty per  cent. of the share capital may be subscribed for within</p>
              <p>such period and in such proportion as may be specified by the Central</p>
              <blockList id="section-4.2.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Government, by the following institutions, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.2.list4.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the State Bank;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.2.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>other scheduled banks;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.2.list4.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>co- operative societies;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.2.list4.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>insurance companies, investment trusts and other  financial institutions;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-4.2.list4.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>recognised associations and companies dealing in  agricultural produce or any notified commodity.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any portion of the sixty per cent. of the share capital  referred to in sub- section (2) remains unallotted, it may be  subscribed for by the Central Government and the State Bank in such  proportion as may be agreed upon between them and in default of such  agreement, as may be determined by the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The shares of the Central Warehousing Corporation shall not  be transferable except to the Central Government,  the State Bank or  any other scheduled bank], any insurance company, any investment trust  or other financial institution or any co- operative society or any  recognised association or company dealing in agricultural produce or  any notified commodity, in accordance with the regulations made by the</p>
              <p>Central Warehousing Corporation under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Shares to be guaranteed by Central Government and to be  trusted or approved securities.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The shares of the Central</p>
              <p>Warehousing Corporation shall be guaranteed by the Central Government  as to the repayment of the principal and the payment of the annual  dividend at such minimum rate as may be fixed by the Central</p>
              <p>Government, by notification published in the Official Gazette, at the  time of the issue of the shares.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Acts mentioned in  this sub- section, the shares of the Central Warehousing Corporation  shall be deemed to be included among the securities enumerated in  section 20 of the Indian Trusts Act, 1882 (2 of 1882), and also to be  approved securities for the purpose of the Insurance Act, 1938 (4 of</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1938">
          <num>1938.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1938.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>) and the Banking Companies Act, 1949 (10 of 1949).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Management of Central Warehousing Corporation.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The general  superintendence and management of the affairs and business of the</p>
              <p>Central Warehousing Corporation shall vest in a board of directors  who, with the assistance of an Executive Committee and a managing  director, may exercise all the powers and</p>
              <p>discharge all the functions which may be exercised or discharged by  the Central Warehousing Corporation under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The board of directors shall act on business principles  having regard to public interest and shall be guided by such  instructions on questions of policy as may be given to them by the</p>
              <p>Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any doubt arises as to whether a question is or is not a  question of policy, the decision of the Central Government shall be  final.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Directors.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-7.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The board of directors referred to in section 6  shall consist of the following, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>six directors to be nominated by the Central Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>one director to be nominated by the National Co-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>operative Development Corporation established under the</p>
              <p>National Co- operative Development Corporation Act,</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1962">
          <num>1962.</num>
          <heading>(26 of 1962);</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-1962.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1962.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-1962.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>one director to be nominated by the State Bank;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1962.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>one director to be elected by other scheduled banks;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1962.paragraph-0.list0.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>one director to be elected by co- operative societies;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1962.paragraph-0.list0.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>one director to be elected by insurance companies,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>investment trusts and other financial institutions,</p>
              <blockList id="section-1962.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>recognised associations and companies dealing in  agricultural produce or notified commodities;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1962.paragraph-0.list3.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>a managing director, appointed by the Central Government  in consultation with the directors referred to in  clauses (a) to (f):</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1962.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that the three directors to be elected under clauses</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1962.paragraph-0.list5.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>, (e) and (f) may, for the first constitution of the board of  directors, be nominated by the Central Government in such manner as to  give representation to each class of institutions (whether they have   become shareholders of the Corporation or not) referred to in those  clauses, but a director so nominated shall hold office only until he  is replaced by a director elected as provided in that clause, and the  director so elected shall hold office only for so long as the director  replaced would have held office had he not been replaced.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-1962.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The directors referred to in clauses (d), (e) and (f) of sub-</p>
              <p>section (1) shall be elected in the prescribed manner.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1962.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If, within the period prescribed in this behalf, or within  such further period as the Central Government may allow, the  institutions referred to in clause (d) or clause (e) or clause (f) of  sub- section (1) fail to elect a director, the Central Government may  nominate a director to fill the vacancy.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1962.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The board of directors shall have a Chairman and a Vice-</p>
              <p>Chairman who shall be appointed by the Central Government from among  the directors.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1962.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1962.5.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The managing director shall--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1962.5.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>exercise such powers and perform such duties as the  board of directors or the Central Warehousing</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1962.5.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Corporation may entrust or delegate to him; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1962.5.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>receive such salary and allowances as the Central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Warehousing Corporation may, with the approval of the</p>
              <p>Central Government, fix.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1962.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The directors of the Central Warehousing Corporation other  than the managing director shall be entitled to receive by way of  remuneration such sums as the Central Warehousing Corporation may,</p>
              <p>with the approval of the Central Government, fix:</p>
              <p>Provided that no official director shall be entitled to receive  any remuneration other than the allowances, if any, admissible to him  under the rules regulating his conditions of service.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1962.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The term of office of, and the manner of filling casual  vacancies among, the directors shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Disqualification for office of director of the Central</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Warehousing Corporation. A person shall be disqualified for being  chosen as, and for being, a director of the Central Warehousing</p>
              <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Corporation--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list2.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>if he is found to be a lunatic or becomes of unsound  mind; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list2.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>if he is, or at any time has been, adjudicated  insolvent or has suspended payment of his debts or has  compounded with his creditors; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list2.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>if he is or has been convicted of any offence  involving moral turpitude and sentenced in respect  thereof to imprisonment for not less than six months,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>unless a period of five years has elapsed from the date  of expiry of the sentence; or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list4.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>if he has been removed or dismissed from the service of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Government or a Corporation owned and controlled by the</p>
              <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list7">
                <listIntroduction>Government; or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list7.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>except in the case of the managing director, if he is a  salaried official of the Central Warehousing</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-8.paragraph-0.list9">
                <listIntroduction>Corporation or any State Warehousing Corporation; or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.paragraph-0.list9.vi">
                  <num>(vi)</num>
                  <p>if he is personally interested in any subsisting  contract made with, or in any work being done for the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Central Warehousing Corporation except as a shareholder</p>
              <p>(other than a director) in any public company as  defined in the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956):</p>
              <p>Provided that where any such person is a shareholder, he shall  disclose to the Central Warehousing Corporation the nature and extent  of shares held by him in such company.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Removal of directors from office.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government  may, at any time in consultation with the Central Warehousing</p>
              <p>Corporation, remove the managing director from office after giving him  a reasonable opportunity of showing cause against the proposed  removal.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-9.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The board of directors may remove from office any director  who--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-9.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>is or has become subject to any of the disqualifications  mentioned in section 8; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-9.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>is absent without leave of the board of directors for  more than three consecutive meetings of the board  without cause sufficient in the opinion of the board,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>to exonerate his absence.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Appointment of officers, etc., and their conditions of  service.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Warehousing Corporation may appoint such  officers and other employees as it considers necessary for the  efficient performance of its functions.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every person employed by the Central Warehousing Corporation  under this Act shall be subject to such conditions of service and  shall be entitled to such remuneration as may be determined by  regulations made by the Corporation under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Functions of Central Warehousing Corporation. Subject to the  provisions of this Act, the Central Warehousing Corporation may--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>acquire and build godowns and warehouses at such  suitable places in India as it thinks fit;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>run warehouses for the storage of agricultural produce,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>seeds, manures, fertilizers, agricultural implements  and notified commodities offered by individuals, co-</p>
              <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>operative societies and other institutions;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>arrange facilities for the transport of agricultural  produce, seeds, manures, fertilizers, agricultural  implements and notified commodities to and from  warehouses;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>subscribe to the share capital of a State Warehousing</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Corporation;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list5.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>act as agent of the Government for the purposes of the  purchase, sale, storage and distribution of  agricultural produce, seeds, manures, fertilizers,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-11.paragraph-0.list7">
                <listIntroduction>agricultural implements and notified commodities; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.paragraph-0.list7.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>carry out such other functions as may be prescribed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Executive Committee.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-12.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>There shall be an Executive</p>
              <blockList id="section-12.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Committee of the Central Warehousing Corporation which shall consist  of--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12.1.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the Chairman and the Vice- Chairman of the board of  directors;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.1.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the managing director; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.1.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>two other directors chosen by the Corporation in the  prescribed manner.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chairman and the Vice- Chairman of the board of directors  shall be the Chairman and the Vice- Chairman respectively of the</p>
              <p>Executive Committee.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the general control, direction and superintendence  of the board of directors, the Executive Committee shall be competent  to deal with any matter within the competence of the Central</p>
              <p>Warehousing Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Meetings of the Corporation.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-13.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The annual general meeting  of the Central Warehousing Corporation (hereinafter referred to as the   annual general meeting) shall be held every year either at its head-</p>
              <p>office or at any other office of the Corporation within six months of  the close of the financial year, and any other general meeting may be  convened by the board of directors at any other time.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The shareholders present at the annual general meeting shall  be entitled to discuss the annual accounts, the report of the board of  directors on the working of the Corporation during the year under  report, as well as the auditors, report on the annual balance- sheet  and accounts.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The board of directors of the Central Warehousing Corporation  shall, on the requisition of one- third of the number of shareholders  of the Corporation, call a special meeting of the Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The requisition for a special meeting under sub- section (3)</p>
              <p>shall state the object of the meeting, and shall be signed by the  requisitionists and deposited at the head- office of the Corporation,</p>
              <p>and may consist of several documents in like form each signed by one  or more requisitionists.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the board of directors of the Central Warehousing</p>
              <p>Corporation do not proceed within twenty- one days from the date of the  requisition being so deposited to cause the special meeting to be  called, the requisitionists, or a majority of them, may, themselves  call the meeting, but in either case, the meeting so called shall be  held within three months from the date of the deposit of the  requisition.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Warehousing Corporation shall observe such rules  of procedure in regard to the transaction of business at its meetings</p>
              <p>(including the quorum at meetings) as may be provided by regulations  made by the Central Warehousing Corporation under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Grants and loans by the Central Government.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central</p>
              <blockList id="section-14.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in  this behalf, pay to the Central Warehousing Corporation for the  purposes of either fund maintained by the Corporation--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-14.1.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>by way of grants, such sums of money as the Central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-14.1.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Government may consider necessary; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-14.1.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>by way of loans, such grants and loans as the central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Government may make for the purposes of the</p>
              <p>Warehousing fund; and</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When making a payment under sub- section (1), the Central</p>
              <p>Government shall specify the fund for the purposes of which the  payment is made.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Corporation to maintain two funds. The Central Warehousing</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-15.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Corporation shall maintain two separate funds, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the Central Warehousing Fund (hereinafter referred to as   the Warehousing Fund); and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-15.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the General Fund.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Warehousing Fund.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-16.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-16.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>To the Warehousing Fund shall be  credited--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-16.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>all moneys and other securities transferred to the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-16.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Central Warehousing Corporation under clause (c) of  sub- section (2) of section 43;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-16.1.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>such grants and loans as the Central Government way  make for the purposes of the Warehousing Fund; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.1.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>such sums of money as may, from time to time, be  realised out of the loans made from the Warehousing</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Fund or from interest on loans or dividends on  investments made from that fund.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-16.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Warehousing Fund shall be applied--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-16.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>for advancing loans to State Governments on such terms  and conditions as the Central Warehousing Corporation  may deem fit for the purpose of enabling them to  subscribe to the share capital of State Warehousing</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-16.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Corporations;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-16.2.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>for advancing loans and granting subsidies to State</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Warehousing Corporations or to State Governments on  such terms and conditions as the Central Warehousing</p>
              <p>Corporation may deem fit for the purpose of promoting  the warehousing and storage of agricultural produce</p>
              <p>and notified commodities, otherwise than through co-</p>
              <blockList id="section-16.2.list8">
                <listIntroduction>operative societies;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-16.2.list8.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>for meeting the expenses incurred in relation to the  training of personnel, or publicity and propaganda, for  the purpose of promoting warehousing and storage of  agricultural produce and notified commodities;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.2.list8.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>for meeting the expenses, including the salary,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>allowances and other remuneration of the officers and  other employees, incurred in relation to the  administration of the Warehousing Fund.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Central Fund.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-17.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>To the General Fund shall be credited--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>all sums received by the Central Warehousing Corporation  other than those referred to in sub- section (1) of  section 16; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>such grants and loans as the Central Government may make  for the purposes of the General Fund.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-17.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The General Fund shall be applied--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>for meeting the salary, allowances and other  remuneration of the officers and other employees of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-17.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Central Warehousing Corporation;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.2.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>for meeting the other administrative expenses of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-17.2.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Corporation; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.2.list5.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>for carrying out the purposes of this Act;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that the General Fund shall not be applied for  meeting the expenses referred to in clause (c) or clause (d) of sub-</p>
              <p>section (2) of section 16.]</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>STATE WAREHOUSING CORPORATIONS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>STATE WAREHOUSING CORPORATIONS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>State Warehousing Corporations.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-18.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may,</p>
              <p>by notification in the Official Gazette and with the approval of the</p>
              <p>Central Warehousing Corporation, establish a Warehousing Corporation  for the State under such name as may be specified in the notification.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A State Warehousing Corporation established under sub- section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>shall be a body corporate by the name notified under that sub-</p>
              <p>section, having perpetual succession and a common seal, with power to  acquire, hold and dispose of property and to contract, and may, by the  said name, sue and be sued.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The head- office of a State Warehousing Corporation shall be  at such place within the State as may be notified in the Official</p>
              <p>Gazette.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- sections (1), (2)</p>
              <p>and (3), it shall not be necessary for the State Government to  establish a Corporation under sub- section (1) where, under clause (g)</p>
              <p>of sub- section (2) of section 43, a Corporation is deemed to be  established for that State under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Share capital and shareholders.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-19.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The authorised capital of  a State Warehousing Corporation shall be such sum not exceeding two  crores of rupees as may be prescribed, divided into shares of the face  value of one hundred rupees each, of which such number as may be  determined by the Corporation in consultation with the State</p>
              <p>Government shall be issued in the first instance and the remaining  shares may be issued, from time to time, as and when the Corporation  may deem fit after consultation with the Central Warehousing</p>
              <p>Corporation and with the sanction of the State Government:</p>
              <p>Provided that in respect of any State Warehousing Corporation  the Central Government may, after consultation with the State</p>
              <p>Government concerned, from time to time and by order notified in the</p>
              <p>Official Gazette, increase the maximum limit of the authorised capital  aforesaid to such extent and in such manner as the Central Government  may determine.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Of the share capital issued in the first instance and of any  subsequent issue of such capital, the Central Warehousing Corporation  shall, in any case where the State Government has subscribed for fifty  per cent. of such capital, subscribe for the remaining fifty per cent.</p>
              <p>of the capital.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Management of a state Warehousing Corporation.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-20.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The  general superintendence and management of the affairs of a State</p>
              <blockList id="section-20.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Warehousing Corporation shall vest in a board of directors which shall  consist of the following, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-20.1.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>five directors nominated by the Central Warehousing</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Corporation, of whom one shall be nominated in</p>
              <blockList id="section-20.1.list5">
                <listIntroduction>consultation with the State Bank and one at least shall  be a non- official;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-20.1.list5.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>five directors nominated by the State Government; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-20.1.list5.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>a managing director, appointed by the State Government  in consultation with the directors referred to in  clauses (a) and (b) and with the previous approval of  the Central Warehousing Corporation.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chairman of the board of directors shall be appointed by  the State Government from among the directors of the State Warehousing</p>
              <p>Corporation with the previous approval of the Central Warehousing</p>
              <p>Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-20.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The managing director shall--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-20.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>exercise such powers and perform such duties as the  board of directors or the State Warehousing Corporation  may entrust or delegate to him; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-20.3.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>receive such salary and allowances as the State</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Warehousing Corporation may, in consultation with the</p>
              <p>Central Warehousing Corporation, and with previous  approval of the State Government, fix.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The board of directors shall act on business principles  having regard to public interest and shall be guided by such  instructions on questions of policy as may be given to them by the</p>
              <p>State Government or the Central Warehousing Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any doubt arises as to whether a question is or is not a  question of policy, or, if the State Government and the Central</p>
              <p>Warehousing Corporation give conflicting instructions, the matter  shall be referred to the Central Government whose decision thereon  shall be final.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The directors of a State Warehousing Corporation, other than  the managing director, shall be entitled to receive by way of  remuneration such sums as may be prescribed:</p>
              <p>Provided that no official director shall be entitled to receive  any remuneration other than any allowances admissible to him under the  rules regulating his conditions of service.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The term of office of, and the manner of filling casual  vacancies among, directors shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Disqualification for office of director of the corporation. A</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>person shall be disqualified for being chosen as, and for being, a  director of a State Warehousing Corporation--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>if he is found to be a lunatic or becomes of unsound  mind; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>if he is, or at any time has been, adjudicated  insolvent or has suspended payment of his debts or has  compounded with his creditors; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>if he is or has been convicted of any offence  involving moral turpitude and sentenced in respect  thereof to imprisonment for not less than six months,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-21.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>unless a period of five years has elapsed from the date  of expiry of the sentence; or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list3.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>if he has been removed or dismissed from service of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Government or a corporation owned and controlled by the</p>
              <blockList id="section-21.paragraph-0.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Government; or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list6.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>except in the case of the managing director, if he is a  salaried official of the Central Warehousing</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-21.paragraph-0.list8">
                <listIntroduction>Corporation or a State Warehousing Corporation; or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list8.vi">
                  <num>(vi)</num>
                  <p>if he is personally interested in a subsisting contract  made with, or in any work being done for, the State</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Warehousing Corporation except as a shareholder (other   than a director) in any public company as defined in  the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956):</p>
              <p>Provided that where any such person is a shareholder, he shall  disclose to the Warehousing Corporation the nature and extent of the  shares held by him in such company.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Removal of directors from office.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-22.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government  may, at any time, with the previous approval of the Central</p>
              <p>Warehousing Corporation, remove the managing director from office  after giving him a reasonable opportunity of showing cause against the  proposed removal.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-22.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The board of directors may remove from office any director  who--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-22.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>is or has become subject to any of the disqualifications  mentioned in section 21; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-22.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>is absent without leave of the board of directors for  more than three consecutive meetings of the board  without cause sufficient, in the opinion of the board,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>to exonerate his absence.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Appointment of officers, etc., and their conditions of  service.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-23.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A State Warehousing Corporation may appoint such officers  and other employees as it considers necessary for the efficient  performance of its functions.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every person employed by a State Warehousing Corporation  under this Act shall be subject to such conditions of service and  shall be entitled to such remuneration as may be determined by  regulations made by the Corporation under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Functions of the State Warehousing Corporation. Subject to  the provisions of this Act, a State Warehousing Corporation may--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-24.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>acquire and build godowns and warehouses at such places  within the State as it may, with the previous approval  of the Central Warehousing Corporation, determine;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>run warehouses in the State for the storage of  agricultural produce, seeds, manures, fertilizers,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>agricultural implements and notified commodities;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>arrange facilities for the transport of agricultural  produce, seeds, manures, fertilizers, agricultural  implements and notified commodities to and from  warehouses;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>act as an agent of the Central Warehousing Corporation  or of the Government for the purposes of the purchase,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-24.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>sale, storage and distribution, of agricultural  produce, seeds, manures, fertilizers, agricultural  implements and notified commodities; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-24.paragraph-0.list4.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>carry out such other functions as may be prescribed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Executive Committee.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-25.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>There shall be an Executive</p>
              <blockList id="section-25.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Committee of a State Warehousing Corporation which shall consist of--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-25.1.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the Chairman of the board of directors;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-25.1.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the managing director; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-25.1.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>three other directors chosen in the prescribed manner,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-25.1.list4">
                <listIntroduction>of whom one shall be a director referred to in clause</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-25.1.list4.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>of sub- section (1) of section 20.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chairman of the board of directors shall be the Chairman  of the Executive Committee.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to any general or special directions as the board of  directors may, from time to time, give, the Executive Committee shall  be competent to deal with any matter within the competence of the</p>
              <p>State Warehousing Corporation.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Submission of programme of activities and financial  estimates.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-26.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every Warehousing Corporation shall prepare before the  commencement of each year a statement of programme of its activities  during the forthcoming year as well as a financial estimate in respect  thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-26.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-26.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>A statement prepared under sub- section (1) shall, not later  than three months before the commencement of each year, be submitted  for approval--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-26.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>in the case of the Central Warehousing Corporation, to  the Central Government;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>in the case of a State Warehousing Corporation, to the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Central Warehousing Corporation and the State</p>
              <p>Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-26.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The statement and the financial estimate of a Warehousing</p>
              <p>Corporation referred to in sub- section (1) may, with the approval of  the Central Government in the case of the Central Warehousing</p>
              <p>Corporation, or with the approval of the Central Warehousing</p>
              <p>Corporation and the State Government in the case of a State</p>
              <p>Warehousing Corporation, be revised by the Warehousing Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Borrowing powers of Warehousing Corporation.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-27.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A</p>
              <p>Warehousing Corporation may, in consultation with the Reserve Bank and  with the previous approval of the appropriate</p>
              <p>Government, issue and sell bonds and debentures carrying interest for  the purpose of raising funds:</p>
              <p>Provided that the total amount of bonds and debentures issued and  outstanding and of the other borrowings of the Corporation shall not  at any time exceed ten times the amount of the paid- up share capital  and the reserve fund of the Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-27.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>A Warehousing Corporation may, for the purpose of carrying  out its functions under this Act, borrow money--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-27.2.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>from the Reserve Bank, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>from the State Bank, for such periods for which, and  upon any of the securities against which, it is  authorised to advance and lend moneys, under the  provisions of  the State Bank of India Act, 1955 (23   of 1955), or]</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>from any nationalised bank, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-27.2.list1.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>from such insurance company, investment trust or other  financial institution as may be approved by the Central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Government in this behalf.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the proviso to sub- section (1), the Central</p>
              <p>Warehousing Corporation may borrow money from the Central Government  and a State Warehousing Corporation may borrow money from the State</p>
              <p>Government and the Central Warehousing Corporation on such securities  and on such terms and conditions as may be agreed upon between the  borrowing corporation and the lender, in each case.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The bonds and debentures of a Warehousing Corporation may be  guaranteed by the appropriate Government as to the repayment of  principal and the payment of interest at such rate as may be fixed by  the appropriate Government on the recommendation of the board of  directors of the Corporation at the time the bonds or debentures are  issued.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Deposit account. All moneys belonging to a Warehousing</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Corporation shall be deposited in the Reserve Bank or the State Bank    or any nationalised bank] or, subject to any rules made under this</p>
              <p>Act, in  any other scheduled bank] or co- operative bank.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Investment of funds. A Warehousing Corporation may invest its  funds in the securities of the Central or any State Government or in  such other manner as may be prescribed by the appropriate Government.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading>Disposal of profits.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-30.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every Warehousing Corporation shall  establish a reserve fund out of its annual net profits.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-30.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>After making provision for bad and doubtful debts,</p>
              <p>depreciation on assets and all other matters which are usually  provided for by companies registered and incorporated under the</p>
              <p>Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), a Warehousing Corporation may, out  of its net annual profits, declare a dividend:</p>
              <p>Provided that for so long as the reserve fund is less than the  paid- up share capital of the Central Warehousing Corporation and until  there has been repaid to the Central Government such sum, if any, as  that Government may have paid under a guarantee given in pursuance of  sub- section (1) of section 5 or sub- section (4) of section 27, the  rate of such dividend, in the case of the Central Warehousing</p>
              <p>Corporation, shall not exceed the rate guaranteed by the Central</p>
              <p>Government under sub- section (1) of section 5.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading>Accounts and audit of Warehousing Corporation.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-31.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every</p>
              <p>Warehousing Corporation shall maintain proper accounts and other  relevant records and prepare an annual statement of accounts including  the profit and loss account and the balance sheet in such form as may  be prescribed:</p>
              <p>Provided that, in the case of the Central Warehousing</p>
              <p>Corporation, the accounts relating to the Warehousing Fund and the</p>
              <p>General Fund shall be maintained separately.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The accounts of a Warehousing Corporation shall be audited by  an auditor duly qualified to act as an auditor of companies under  section 226 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The said auditor shall be appointed by the appropriate</p>
              <p>Government on the advice of the Comptroller and Auditor- General of</p>
              <p>India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The auditor shall be supplied with a copy of the annual  balance sheet and the profit and loss account of the Warehousing</p>
              <p>Corporation and it shall be his duty to examine them together with the  accounts and vouchers relating thereto, and he shall have a list  delivered to him of all books kept by the Corporation and shall at all  reasonable times have access to the books, accounts and other  documents of the Corporation and may require from any officer of</p>
              <p>the Corporation such information and explanations as the auditor may  think necessary for the performance of his duties as auditor.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-31.5.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The auditor shall make a report to the shareholders on the  accounts examined by him and on the annual balance sheet and the  profit and loss account and in every such report, he shall state  whether in his opinion the accounts give a true and fair view--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-31.5.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>in the case of the balance sheet, of the state of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Corporation' s affairs at the end of its financial year,</p>
              <blockList id="section-31.5.list4">
                <listIntroduction>and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-31.5.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>in the case of the profit and loss account, of the  profit or loss for its financial year,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>and in case he has called for any explanation or information from the  officers, whether it has been given and whether it is satisfactory.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The appropriate Government may, after consultation with the</p>
              <p>Comptroller and Auditor- General of India at any time issue directions  to the auditor requiring him to report to the appropriate Government  upon the adequacy of measures taken by a Warehousing Corporation for  the protection of its shareholders and creditors or upon the  sufficiency of his procedure in auditing the accounts of the</p>
              <p>Corporation and may enlarge or extend the scope of the audit or direct  that a different procedure in audit may be adopted or direct that any  other examination may be made by the auditor if in the opinion of the  appropriate Government public interest so requires.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A Warehousing Corporation shall send a copy of every report  of the auditor to the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and to  the Central Government at least one month before it is placed before  the shareholders.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything hereinbefore contained in this  section, the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India may, either of  his own motion or on a request received in this behalf from the  appropriate Government, undertake in respect of a Warehousing</p>
              <p>Corporation such audit and at such time as he may consider necessary:</p>
              <p>Provided that where the Central Government is required to make  any payment on account of the guarantee given by it under sub- section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of section 5, such audit shall be undertaken by the Comptroller  and Auditor- General of India or any person authorised by him in this  behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.9">
            <num>(9)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any person  authorised by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of a</p>
              <p>Warehousing Corporation shall have the same rights, privileges and  authority in connection with such audit as the Comptroller and</p>
              <p>Auditor- General has in connection with the audit of Government  accounts and in particular, shall have the right to demand the  production of books, accounts, connected vouchers and other documents  and papers and to inspect the office of the Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.10">
            <num>(10)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The annual accounts of a Warehousing Corporation together  with the audit report thereon shall be placed before the annual  general meeting of the Corporation within six months of the close of  the financial year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.11">
            <num>(11)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every audit report under this section shall be forwarded to  the appropriate Government within a month of its being placed before  the annual general meeting and that Government shall as soon  thereafter as may be cause the same to be laid before both Houses of</p>
              <p>Parliament or the Legislature of the State, as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-31A">
          <num>31A.</num>
          <heading>Returns and reports. A Warehousing Corporation shall  furnish to the appropriate Government such returns, statistics,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-31A.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>accounts and other information with respect to its property or  activities as that Government may, from time to time, require.]</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-V.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>Vacancies, etc., not to invalidate acts and proceedings of</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-32.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Warehousing Corporations. No act or proceeding of a Warehousing</p>
              <p>Corporation shall be invalid by reason only of the existence of any  vacancy among its directors or any defect in the constitution thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading>Delegation. A Warehousing Corporation may, by general or  special order in writing, delegate to the Secretary or other officer  of the Corporation, subject to such conditions and limitations, if  any, as may be specified in the order, such of its powers and  functions under this Act as it may deem necessary for the efficient  performance of its functions.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-34">
          <num>34.</num>
          <heading>Voting rights of shareholders. In any meeting of the  shareholders of a Warehousing Corporation, every member shall have one  vote in respect of each share held by him in the Corporation.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading>Disputes between Central Warehousing Corporation and State</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-35.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Warehousing Corporation. If there is any difference of opinion between  the Central Warehousing Corporation and a State Warehousing</p>
              <p>Corporation regarding their respective functions and powers under this</p>
              <p>Act, such difference shall be referred to the Central Government whose  decision thereon shall be final.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-36">
          <num>36.</num>
          <heading>Declaration of fidelity and secrecy. Every director, auditor,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-36.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>officer or other employee of a Warehousing Corporation shall, before  entering upon his duties, make a declaration of fidelity and secrecy  in the form set out in the Schedule.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-37">
          <num>37.</num>
          <heading>Indemnity of directors.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-37.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every director of a Warehousing</p>
              <p>Corporation shall be indemnified by the Corporation concerned against  all losses and expenses incurred in the discharge of his duties except  such as are caused by his own wilful act or default.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-37.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A director of a Warehousing Corporation shall not be  responsible for any other director or for any officer or other  employee of the Corporation or for any loss or expense resulting to  the Corporation by the insufficiency or deficiency of value of, or  title to, any property or security acquired or taken on behalf of the</p>
              <p>Corporation in good faith, or by the wrongful act of any person under  obligation to the Corporation or by anything done in good faith in the  execution of the duties of his office or in relation thereto.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-38">
          <num>38.</num>
          <heading>Offences.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-38.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Whoever, without the consent in writing of a</p>
              <p>Warehousing Corporation, uses the name of that Corporation in any  prospectus or advertisement, shall be punishable with imprisonment  which may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to one  thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-38.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No court shall take cognizance of any offence under sub-</p>
              <p>section (1) otherwise than on a complaint in writing by an officer  authorised in this behalf by the Warehousing Corporation concerned.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-39">
          <num>39.</num>
          <heading>Provisions relating to income- tax and super- tax. For the  purposes of the Income- tax Act, 1961 (43 of 1961), a Warehousing</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-39.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Corporation shall be deemed to be a company within the meaning of that</p>
              <p>Act and shall be liable to income- tax and super- tax accordingly on its  income, profits and gains:</p>
              <p>Provided that, in the case of the Central Warehousing</p>
              <p>Corporation, any sum paid by the Central Government under the  guarantee given in pursuance of sub- section (1) of section 5 or, in  the case of a</p>
              <p>Warehousing Corporation, any sum paid by the Central or a State</p>
              <p>Government under any guarantee given in pursuance of sub- section (4)</p>
              <p>of section 27 shall not be treated as income, profits and gains of a</p>
              <p>Warehousing Corporation, and any interest on the debentures or bonds  issued by that Corporation out of such sums shall not be treated as  expenditure incurred by it:</p>
              <p>Provided further that in the case of any shareholder or  debenture- holder, such portion of a dividend or interest as has been  paid out of any such sum advanced by the Central Government shall be  deemed to be his income from interest on securities declared to be  income- tax- free within the meaning of section 86 of that Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-40">
          <num>40.</num>
          <heading>Winding up of Warehousing Corporations. No provision of law  relating to the winding up of companies or corporations shall apply to  a Warehousing Corporation and any such Corporation shall not be placed  in liquidation save by order of the appropriate Government and in such  manner as it may direct.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-41">
          <num>41.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-41.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The appropriate Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the  purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-41.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power,</p>
              <blockList id="section-41.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>such rules may provide for--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-41.2.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the additional functions which a Warehousing Corporation  may perform;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.2.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the manner of nomination and election of the directors  of the Central Warehousing Corporation and the period  within which such directors shall be nominated or  elected;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.2.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the term of office of, and the manner of filling casual  vacancies among, and the remuneration payable to, the  directors of a Warehousing Corporation;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.2.list2.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the manner of choosing directors on the Executive</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-41.2.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Committee of a Warehousing Corporation;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-41.2.list4.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the authorised capital of a State Warehousing</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-41.2.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Corporation  within the maximum limit specified by or  under sub- section (1) of section 19];</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-41.2.list6.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>the form of the annual statement of accounts and the  balance- sheet to be prepared by a Warehousing</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-41.2.list8">
                <listIntroduction>Corporation;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-41.2.list8.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>the deposit of moneys of a Warehousing Corporation in a  scheduled bank or a co- operative bank;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-41.2.list8.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>the manner of issuing shares of a Warehousing</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Corporation, the calls to be made in respect thereof,</p>
              <blockList id="section-41.2.list11">
                <listIntroduction>and all other matters incidental to the issue of  shares;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-41.2.list11.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>the form and manner in which returns, statistics,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>accounts and other information are to be furnished,</p>
              <blockList id="section-41.2.list14">
                <listIntroduction>under section 31A, by a Warehousing Corporation;]</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-41.2.list14.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>] any other matter which has to be or may be  prescribed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-41.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made by the Central Government under this section  shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of</p>
              <p>Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty days  which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive  sessions, and  if before the expiry of the session immediately  following the session] or the successive sessions aforesaid, both</p>
              <p>Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses  agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have  effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may  be; so however that any such modification or annulment shall be  without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under  that rule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-42">
          <num>42.</num>
          <heading>Power of Warehousing Corporations to make regulations.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-42.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A</p>
              <p>Warehousing Corporation may, with the previous sanction of the  appropriate Government, by notification in the Official Gazette, make  regulations not inconsistent with this Act and the rules made  thereunder to provide for all matters for which provision is necessary  or expedient for the purposes of giving effect to the provisions of  this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-42.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-42.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such regulations may provide for--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-42.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the conditions of service of, and the remuneration  payable to, the officers and other employees of a</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-42.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Warehousing Corporation;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-42.2.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which, and the conditions subject to  which, shares of the Central Warehousing Corporation  may be transferred;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-42.2.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the manner in which meetings of a Warehousing</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-42.2.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Corporation and the Executive Committee thereof shall  be convened, the fees for attending such meetings and  the procedure to be followed thereat;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-42.2.list5.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the duties and conduct of officers and employees of a</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-42.2.list7">
                <listIntroduction>Warehousing Corporation;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-42.2.list7.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>the powers and duties which may be entrusted or  delegated to the managing director of a Warehousing</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-42.2.list9">
                <listIntroduction>Corporation;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-42.2.list9.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>generally, the efficient conduct of the affairs of a</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Warehousing Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-42.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The appropriate Government may, by notification in the</p>
              <p>Official Gazette, rescind any regulation which it has sanctioned and  thereupon the regulation shall cease to have effect.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-43">
          <num>43.</num>
          <heading>Repeal and savings.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-43.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>With effect from the date on which  the Central Warehousing Corporation is established under section 3,</p>
              <p>the Agricultural Produce (Development and Warehousing) Corporations</p>
              <p>Act, 1956 (28 of 1956), in so far as it has not been repealed by the</p>
              <p>National Co- operative Development Corporation Act, 1962 (26 of 1962),</p>
              <p>shall stand repealed:</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-43.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-43.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding such repeal,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-43.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the shares allotted and the share certificates issued by  the Central Warehousing Corporation established under  the repealed Act (hereinafter referred to as the said</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Corporation) shall be deemed to have been allotted and  issued by the Corporation established under section 3  of this Act as</p>
              <blockList id="section-43.2.list4">
                <listIntroduction>if this Act had been in force on the day on which the  shares were allotted and the share certificates were  issued;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-43.2.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>every shareholder of the said Corporation shall become  the holder of as many shares in the Corporation  established under section 3 of this Act as are  equivalent in number and value to the shares held by  him in the said Corporation;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-43.2.list4.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>all moneys and other securities belonging to the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>National Warehousing Development Fund which,</p>
              <p>immediately before the said date, was maintained by the  said Corporation shall stand transferred to and be  maintained by the Corporation established under section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>of this Act;</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>anything done or any action taken (including any  appointment, nomination, delegation, rule or regulation   made) under the repealed Act shall, in so far as it is  not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, be  deemed to have been done or taken under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list0.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>every share held by the said Corporation in a State</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Warehousing Corporation under the repealed Act shall be  deemed to be a share held by the Corporation  established under section 3 of this Act in the  corresponding State Warehousing Corporation deemed to  be established under this Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list2.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>all rights, liabilities and obligations of the said</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-3.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Corporation, whether arising out of any contract or  otherwise, shall be the rights, liabilities and  obligations respectively of the Corporation established  under section 3 of this Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.paragraph-0.list4.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>a State Warehousing Corporation established for a State  under the repealed Act shall be deemed to be the State</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Warehousing Corporation established for that State  under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
