<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1965/50/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1965/50"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Goa, Daman And Diu (Absorbed Employees) Act, 1965"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1965/50/eng@1965-12-22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1965/50/eng@1965-12-22"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1965-12-22" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1965/50/eng@1965-12-22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1965/50/eng@1965-12-22"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Goa, Daman And Diu (Absorbed Employees) Act, 1965</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 50 OF 1965</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 22nd December, 1965]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the regulation of the conditions of service  of persons absorbed for service in connection with the administration  of the Union territory of Goa, Daman and Diu and for matters connected  therewith.</p>
        <p>Be it enacted by Parliament in, the Sixteenth Year of the-</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title. This Act may be called the Goa, Daman and Diu</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>(Absorbed Employees) Act, 1965.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>absorbed employee" means a person who immediately  before the 20th day of December, 1961, was holding an  absorbed post and who on and after that date either  served or has been serving in that or any other post in  connection with the administration of the Union  territory of Goa, Daman and Diu or in any of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Departments of the Central Government;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>absorbed post" means a civil service or post  which existed under the former Portuguese Administration  in Goa, Daman and Diu immediately before the 20th day of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>December 1961.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Power to make rules regulating recruitment and  conditions of service of absorbed employees and employees of certain  corporations. The Central Government may make rules-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>for the regulation of recruitment to absorbed  posts and the conditions of service of absorbed  employees;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>for the regulation of the conditions of service of  persons who were in the service of a Corporation</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>(whether know as a junta or otherwise) immediately  before the 20th day of December, 1961, and who on or  after that date either served or have been serving in  connection with the administration of the Union  territory of Goa, Daman and Diu or in any of the</p>
            <p>Departments of the Central Government</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any such rule may be made so as to be retrospective to any  date not earlier than the 20th day of December, 1961:</p>
            <p>Provided that no person shall, by virtue of such retrospective  effect be liable to refund any amount paid to him by way of salary or  allowances or pension before the making of any such rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as  may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is  in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in  one session or in two successive sessions and if, before the expiry of  the session in which it is so laid or the session immediately follow-</p>
            <p>ing, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule, or both</p>
            <p>Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall,</p>
            <p>thereafter, have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</p>
            <p>as the case may be; so however that any such modification or annulment  shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done  under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Repeal. On the making of any rule under section 3, the  corresponding law, if any, in respect of any matter for which  provision is made in that rule, shall stand repealed with effect from  the date of the coming into force of that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of sections 6 and 24 of the General Clauses</p>
            <p>Act, 1897, (10 of 1987), shall apply to such repeal as if the rule and  the corresponding law referred to in sub- section (1) were Central</p>
            <p>Acts.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in  giving effect to the provisions of this Act or any rule made  thereunder in relation to any absorbed employee or any person referred  to in clause (b) of sub- section</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of section 3, the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by order, make such provision as appears to it to be  necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty:</p>
            <p>Provided that the power under this section shall not be  exercisable after the expiration of a period of two years from the  commencement of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
