<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1978/13/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1978/13"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Hindustan Tractors Limited (Acquisition And Transfer Ofundertaking) Act, 1978"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1978/13/eng@1978-03-31/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1978/13/eng@1978-03-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1978-03-31" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1978/13/eng@1978-03-31/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1978/13/eng@1978-03-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Hindustan Tractors Limited (Acquisition And Transfer Ofundertaking) Act, 1978</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 13 OF 1978</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 31st March, 1978.] W</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the acquisition and transfer of the undertaking  of Hindustan Tractors Limited, Vishwamitri, Vadodara, for the purpose  of ensuring the continuity of production of goods which are vital to  meet the needs of the general public and for matters connected  therewith or incidental thereto.</p>
        <p>CHAP</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the</p>
              <p>Hindustan Tractors Limited (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings)</p>
              <p>Act, 1978.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on the 1st day of April, 1978.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" appointed day" means the 1st day of April, 1978;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" Authorised Controller" means the Gujarat Agro</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Industries Corporation Limited, Ahmedabad, which took  over the management of the undertakings of the Company  by</p>
              <p>virtue of the Order of the Government of India in the</p>
              <p>Ministry of Industrial Development No. S. O 137 (E)</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18A">
          <num>18A.</num>
          <heading>IDRA 73, dated the 12th March, 1973, made under  clause (b) of sub- section (1) of section 18A of the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-18A.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-18A.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Industries (Development and Regulation) Act, 1951 (65   of 1951);</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-18A.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-18A.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>" bank" means--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-18A.paragraph-0.list1.c.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>the State Bank of India constituted under the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-18A.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>State Bank of India Act, 1955 (65 of 1951);</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-18A.paragraph-0.list3.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>a subsidiary bank as defined in the State</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Bank of India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, 1959 (38 of</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1959">
          <num>1959.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1959.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1959.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>);</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1959.paragraph-0.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>a corresponding new bank constituted under  section 3 of the Banking Companies (Acquisition and</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1959.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Transfer of Undertaking) Act, 1970 (5 of 1970);</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1959.paragraph-0.list3.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>any other bank, being a scheduled bank as  definedin clause (e) of section 2 of the Reserve Bank  of India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934);</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1959.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" Commissioner" means the Commissioner of Payments  appointed under section 16;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1959.paragraph-0.list3.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>" Company" means Hindustan Tractors Limited, being a  company as defined in the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1956">
          <num>1956.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1956.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>), and having its registered office of the  undertakings of the Company;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>" Custodian" means the Custodian appointed under sub-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>section (3) of section 10 to take over, or carry on,</p>
              <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>the management of the undertakings of the Company;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list4.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>" date of taking over" means the date on which the  management of the undertakings of the Company was taken  over by the Authorised Controller;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list4.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>" Government company" has the meaning assigned to it by  section 617 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956);</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list4.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>" notification" means a notification published in the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Official Gazette;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list6.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list8">
                <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list8.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>" specified date" means such date as the Central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list10">
                <listIntroduction>Government may, for the purpose of any provision of  this Act, by notification, specify and different dates  may be specified for different provisions of this Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list10.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>" State Government" means the State Government of Gujarat;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list10.m">
                  <num>(m)</num>
                  <p>words and expressions used erein and not defined but defined  in the Companies Act, 1956, shall have the meanings,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>respectively, assigned to them in that Act.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>ACQUISITION AND TRANSFER OF THE UNDERTAKINGS OF THE COMPANY</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>ACQUISITION AND TRANSFER OF THE UNDERTAKINGS OF THE COMPANY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Transfer to and vesting in the Central Government of the  undertakings of the Company. On the appointed day, the undertakings of  the Company, and the right, title and interest of the Company in  relation to its undertakings, shall, by virtue of this Act, stand  transferred to, and shall vest, in, the Central Government.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>General effect of vesting.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The undertakings of the Company  referred to in section 3 shall be deemed to include all assets,</p>
              <p>rights, lease- holds, powers, authorities and privileges, and all  property, movable and immovable, including, lands, buildings,</p>
              <p>workshops, stores, instruments, machinery and equipment, bank  balances, cash balances, cash on hand, reserve funds, investments and  book debts and all other rights and interests in, or arising out of,</p>
              <p>such property as were immediately before the appointed day, in the  ownership, possession, power or control of the Company, whether within  or outside India, and all books of account, registers and all other  documents of whatever nature relating thereto and shall be deemed to  include the liabilities and obligations specified in sub- section (2)</p>
              <p>of section 5.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All property as aforesaid which have vested in the Central</p>
              <p>Government under section 3 shall, by force of such vesting, be freed  and discharged from any trust, obligation, mortgage, charge, lien and  all other encumbrances affecting them, and any attachment, injunction,</p>
              <p>decree or order of any court, tribunal, officer or other authority  restricting the use of such property in any manner shall be deemed to  have been withdrawn.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where any licence or other instrument in relation to the  undertakings of the Company had been granted at any time before the  appointed day, the Company by the Central Government, a State</p>
              <p>Government or any other authority, the Central Government, the State</p>
              <p>Government of Gujarat of, as the case may be, the Government company  in which the right, title and interest of the Company in relation to  its undertakings have vested under section 7, shall, on and from the  appointed day, be deemed to be substituted in such licence or other  instrument in place of the Company referred to therein as if such  licence or other instrument had been granted to it and shall hold such  licence or the undertakings or any part thereof specified in such  other instrument for the remainder of the period for which the Company  would have held such licence or undertakings or any part thereof under  such other instrument.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every mortgagee of any property which has vested under this</p>
              <p>Act in the Central Government and every person holding any charge,</p>
              <p>lien or other interest in, or in relation to, any such property, shall  give, within such time and in such manner as may be prescribed, an  intimation to the Commissioner of such mortgage, charge, lien or other  interest.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that the  mortgagee of any property referred to in sub- section (4) or any other  person holding any charge, lien or other interest in, or in relation  to, any such property shall be entitled to claim, in accordance with  his rights and interests, payment of the mortgage money or other dues,</p>
              <p>in whole or in part, out of the amount specified in section 8, and  also out of the monies determined under section 9, but no such  mortgage, charge, lien or other interest shall be enforceable against  any property which has vested in the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If, on the appointed day, any suit, appeal or other  proceeding of whatever nature in relation to any matter specified in  sub- section (2) of section 5 in respect of the undertakings of the</p>
              <p>Company instituted or preferred by or against the Company is pending,</p>
              <p>the same shall not abate, be discontinued or be, in any way,</p>
              <p>prejudicially affected by reason of the transfer of the undertakings  of the Company or of anything contained in this Act, but the suit,</p>
              <p>appeal or other proceeding may be continued, or the State Government,</p>
              <p>or where the undertakings of the Company are directed, under section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>, vest in a Government company, that Government company.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Company to be liable for certain prior liabilities.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every  liability, other than the liability specified in sub- section (2), of  the Company in respect of any period prior to the appointed day, shall  be the liability of the Company and shall be enforceable against it  and not against the Central Government, or the State Government, or  where the undertakings of the Company are directed, under section 7,</p>
              <p>to vest in a Government company, against that Government company.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-5.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Any liability arising in respect of--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>loans advanced by the Central Government or the State</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-5.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Government, or both, to the Company (together with   interest due thereon), on or after the after of taking  over;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.2.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>loans advanced by a bank to the Company (together with   interest due thereon) on or after the date of taking  over  but excluding loans advanced, on or after  such date, by a bank to the Company to the extent such  loans have been utilised by the Company for the re-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-5.2.list5">
                <listIntroduction>payment of, or the payment of interest on, secured  loans advanced to the Company by a bank at any time  before such date];</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.2.list5.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>loans advanced by the Industrial Reconstruction</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-5.2.list7">
                <listIntroduction>Corporation of India Limited to the Company (together   with interest due thereon) on or after the date of  taking over;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.2.list7.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>wages, salaries and other dues of employees of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Company and the dues on amount of any deduction made  from wages and salaries and other dues of employees,</p>
              <blockList id="section-5.2.list10">
                <listIntroduction>relating to any period commencing on and from the date  of taking over;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.2.list10.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>any debt incurred by the Company during any period  commencing on and from the date of taking over, not  being a debt falling under clause (a), clause (b),</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>clause (c) or clause (d) or specified in Category I of  the Schedule,</p>
              <p>shall, on and from the appointed day, be the liability of the Central</p>
              <p>Government, or the State Government, or the Government company  aforesaid and shall be discharged by the Central Government or the</p>
              <p>State Government, or the Government company aforesaid as and when  repayment of such loans becomes due or as and when such wages,</p>
              <p>salaries and other dues and debt become due and payable.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-5.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>save as otherwise expressly provided in this section or  in any other provision of this Act, no liability,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>includ--</p>
              <p>ing any liability arising out of any guarantee given by  the State Government in respect of any loan or advance  given to the Company but not including the liability  specified in sub- section (2), of the Company in  relation to its undertaking in respect of any period  prior to the appointed day, shall be enfroceable  against the Central Government, or the State</p>
              <blockList id="section-5.3.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Government, or where the undertakings of the Company  are directed, under section 7, to vest in a Government  company, against that Government company;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.3.list5.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>no award, decree or order or any court, tribunal,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>officer or other authority in relation to the  undertakings of the Company, passed after the appointed  day, in respect of any matter, claim or dispute, not  being matter, claim or dispute in relation to any  matter referred to in sub- section (2), which arose  before that day, shall be enfroceable against the</p>
              <blockList id="section-5.3.list8">
                <listIntroduction>Central Government, or the State Government, or where  the undertakings of the Company are directed, under  section 7, to vest in a Government company, against  that Government company;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.3.list8.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>no liability incurred by the Company before the  appointed day, for the contravention of any provision  of law for the time being in force, shall be  enforceable against the Central Government, or the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>State Government, or where the undertakings of the</p>
              <p>Company are directed, under section 7, to vest in a</p>
              <p>Government company, against that Government company.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Vesting of the undertakings of the Company in the State</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government of Gujarat.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in  sections 3 and 4, the Central Government shall, as soon may be, after  the commencement of this Act, direct, by notification that the  undertakings of the Company, and the right, title and interest of the</p>
              <p>Company in relation to its undertakings, which have vested in the</p>
              <p>Central Government as are specified in sub- section (2) of section 5,</p>
              <p>shall, instead of continuing to vest in the Central Government, vest  in the State Government of Gujarat either on the date of the  notification or on such earlier or later date (not being a date   earlier than the appointed day) as may be specified in the  notification.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where the r right, title and interest of the Company in  relation to its undertakings and the liabilities of the Company  specified in sub- section (2) of section 5 vest in the State Government  under sub- section (1), the State Government shall, on and from the  date of such vesting, be deemed to have become the owner in relation  to such undertakings, and all the rights and liabilities of the</p>
              <p>Central Government in relation to such undertakings shall, on and from  the date of such vesting, be deemed to have become the rights and  liabilities, respectively, of the State Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Power to State Government direct vesting of the undertakings  of the Company in a Government Company.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything  contained in section 3, 4 and 6, the State Government may, if it is  satisfied that a Government company is willing to comply, or has  complied, with such terms and conditions as that Government may think  fit to impose, direct, by notification, that the undertakings of the</p>
              <p>Company, and the right, title and interest of the Company as relation  to its undertakings and such of the liabilities of the Company as  are specified in sub- section (2) of section 5, which have vested in  the Central Government under section 3 and thereafter in the State</p>
              <p>Government under section 6, shall, instead of continuing to vest in  the State Government, vest in the Government company either on the  date of the notification or on such earlier or later date (not   being a date earlier than the appointed day) as may be specifie d in  the notification.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where the right, title and interest, and the liabilities  specified in sub- section (2) of section 5, of the Company in relation  to its undertakings vest in a Government company, under sub- section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, the Government company shall, on and from the date of such  vesting, be deemed to have become the owner in relation to such  undertakings, and all the rights and liabilities of the Central</p>
              <p>Government or the State Government in relation to such undertakings  shall, on and from the date of such vesting, be deemed to have become  the rights and liabilities, respectively, of the Government company</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>PAYMENT OF AMOUNTS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PAYMENT OF AMOUNTS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Payment of amount. For the transfer to, and vesting in, the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Central Government, under section 3, of the undertakings of the</p>
              <p>Company and the right, title and interest of the Company in relation  to its undertakings,</p>
              <p>there shall be given by the Central Government to the Company, in cash  and in the manner specified in Chapter VI, an amount of rupees one  hundred and fifty lakhs.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Payment of further amount.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>for the deprivation of the</p>
              <p>Company of the management of its undertaking, there shall be given to  the Company by the Central Government an amount calculated at the rate  of rupees fifty thousand per annum for the period commencing on the  date of taking over and ending on the appointed day.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The amount specified in section 8 and the amount determined  under sub- section (1) shall carry simple interest at the rate of four  per cent. per annum for the period commencing on the appointed day and  ending on the date on which payment of such amounts is made by the</p>
              <p>Central Government to the Commissioner.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The amounts determined in accordance with the provisions of  sub- section (1) and (2) shall be given by the Central Government to  the Company in addition to the amount specified in section 8.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>MANAGEMENT, ETC., OF THE UNDERTAKINGS OF THE COMPANY</p>
              <p>COMPANY IV</p>
              <p>MANAGEMENT, ETC., OF THE UNDERTAKINGS OF THE COMPANY</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Management, etc., of the undertakings of the Company</heading>
          <subsection id="section-10.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The</p>
              <p>State Government in which the undertakings of the Company and the  right, title and interest of the Company in relation to its  undertakings vested under section 6 shall be entitled to exercise all  such powers and do all such things as the Company is authorised to  exercise and do in relation to its undertakings.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The general superintendence, direction, control and  management of the affairs and business of the undertakings of the</p>
              <p>Company, the right, title and interest in relation to which have  vested under section 3 in the Central Government and, under section 6,</p>
              <blockList id="section-10.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>in the State Government, shall,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.2.list3.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>where a direction has been made by the State Government  under sub- section (1) of section 7, vest in the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-10.2.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Government company specified in such direction; or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.2.list5.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>where no such direction has been made by the State</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Government, vest in one or more Custodians appointed  under sub- section (3),</p>
              <p>and thereupon the Government company so specified or the Custodian so  appointed shall be entitled to exercise all such powers and</p>
              <p>do all such things as the Company is authorised to exercise and do in  relation to its undertakings.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-10.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may appoint one or more individuals or a</p>
              <p>Government company as the Custodian of the undertakings of the Company  in relation to which no direction has been made by it under sub-</p>
              <p>section (1) of section 7.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Duty to deliver possession of property acquired and documents  relating thereto.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On the vesting of the management of the  undertakings of the Company in the State Government under section 6,</p>
              <p>every person in whose possession or custody or under whose control any  property referred to in sub- section (1) of section 4 may be, shall  deliver the property to the State Government forthwith.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person, who on the appointed day has in his possession or  under his control and books, documents or other papers relating to the  undertakings of the Company which has vested in the State Government  under section 6 and which belong to the Company, or, would have so  belonged if the undertakings of the Company had not vested in the</p>
              <p>State Government, shall be liable to account for the said books,</p>
              <p>documents or other papers or the State Government and shall deliver  them up to the State Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may take, or cause to be taken, all  necessary steps for securing possession of all properties which have  vested in that Government under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may issue such directions as it may  deem desirable in the circumstances of the case to the State</p>
              <p>Government as to its powers and duties and the State Government may  also, if it so desires, apply to the Central Government at any time  for instructions as to the manner in which the management of the  undertakings of the Company shall be conducted by it or in relation to  any other matter arising in the course of such management.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On the vesting of the management of the undertakings of the</p>
              <p>Company in a Government company or in the Custodian, the provisions of  sub- sections (1) to (4) shall apply to, or in realation to, the</p>
              <p>Government company or the Custodian, as the case may be, as they  apply to, or in relation to, the State Government, subject to the  modification that the references to the State Government shall be  construed as references to the Government company or the Custodian, as  the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Accounts to be rendered by the Company or any other person.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-12.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-12.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Where, in pursuance of any decree, order or injunction of any  court or otherwise,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the Authorised Controller was, after the date of taking  over and before the appointed day; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the Central Government, the State Government, or the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Government company, as the case may be, is on or after  the appointed day,</p>
              <p>prevented from taking over the management of any part of the  undertakings of the Company, the Company, or any other person in  possession, custody or control of such part, shall, within sixty days  from the appointed day, render accounts to the State Government or the</p>
              <p>Government company in relation to the period commencing on the date of  taking over and ending on the date on which such part was or is handed  over to the Authorised Controller or, as the case may be, the Central</p>
              <blockList id="section-12.1.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Government, the State Government, or the Government company, with  regard to the--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12.1.list6.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>assets and stores of the undertakings or any part  thereof, acquired, utilised or sold during the said  period; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.1.list6.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>income derived by the Company or any other person from  the undertakings or any part thereof during the said  period.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If, on examination of the accounts referred to in sub- section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, any income or moneys is or are found to have been derived by the</p>
              <p>Company or any other person from such undertakings or any part thereof  during the period referred to in that sub- section or any other moneys  are found to be payable, such income or other moneys shall be  recoverable by the Central Government, the State Government or the</p>
              <p>Government company from the Company or such other person, as the case  may be, and from the Company or such other person, as the case may be,</p>
              <p>and from the amount payable under this Act to the Company and the debt  due to the Central Government, the State Government, or the Government  company on this account shall rank as an unsecured debt.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If no account is rendered by the Company or such other person  in respect of the undertakings or any part thereof within the period  referred to in sub- section (1) or if the Central Government, the State</p>
              <p>Government or the Government company, as the case may be, has any  reason to believe that the account rendered by the Company or such  other person is incorrect or false in any material parti-</p>
              <p>cular, the Central Government, the State Government or the Government  company may refer the matter to the Commissioner and thereupon the</p>
              <p>Commissioner shall determine the income derived by the Company or such  other person from such undertakings or any part thereof during the  period referred to in sub- section (1) and take steps to recover the  said income or other moneys from the Company or such other person and  from the amount payable to the Company under this Act as if the debt  due to the Central Government, the State Government company on this  account were an unsecured debt.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No mortgage, charge, lien or other encumbrance in relation to  the undertakings of the company or any part thereof shall be binding  on the Central Government, the State Government or the Government  company, if such mortgage, charge, lien or other encumbrance was  created, at any time during the period in which the Authorised</p>
              <p>Controller was, and the Central Government, the State Government or  the Government company, as the case may be, is, prevented, by any  decree, order or injunction of any court or otherwise, from taking  over the managing of the undertakings or any part thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Accounts. The Custodian shall maintain accounts of the  undertakings of the Company in accordance with the provisions of the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956,)</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>PROVISIONS RELATING TO THE EMPLOYEES OF THE COMPANY</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-V.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PROVISIONS RELATING TO THE EMPLOYEES OF THE COMPANY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Employment of certain employees to continue.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every person  who has been, immediately before the appointed day, employed in any of  the undertakings of the Company shall become, on and from the  appointed day or such later date, as the case may be, an employee of  the State Government or, as the case may be, of the Government company  in which the right, title and interest of the Company in relation to  its undertakings, have vested under this Act, and shall hold office or  service under the State Government, or the Government company, as the  case may be, with the same rights and privileges as to pension,</p>
              <p>gratuity and other matters as would have been admissible to him if  there had been no such vesting and shall continue to do so unless and  until</p>
              <p>his employment under the State Government, or the Government company,</p>
              <p>as the case may be, is duly terminated or until his remuneration and  other conditions of service are duly altered by the State Government,</p>
              <p>or by the Government company, as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial Disputes</p>
              <p>Act, 1947 (14 of 1947), or in any other law for the time being in  force, the transfer of the services of any officer or other person  employed in any of the undertakings of the Company to the State</p>
              <p>Government, or the Government company, shall not entitle such officer  or other employee to any compensation under this Act or under any  other law for the time being in force and no such claim shall be  entertained by any court, tribunal or other authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where, under the terms of any contract of service or  otherwise, any person, whose services become transferred to the State</p>
              <p>Government, or the Government company, by reason of the provisions of  this Act, is entitled to any arrears of salary or wages or any payment  for any leave not availed of or any other payment, not being payment  by way of gratuity or pension, such person may, except to the extent  to such liability which has been taken over by the Central Government  or the State Government or the Government company under sub- section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of section 5, enforce his claim against the Company, by which he  was employed immediately before such transfer but not against the</p>
              <p>Central Government, or the State Government, or the Government  company.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Provident fund and other funds. Where moneys representing  provident fund, superannuation fund, welfare fund or other fund for  the benefit of the persons employed in any of the undertakings of the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-15.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Company have vested in an authority established under any law for the  time being in force, such moneys shall continue to vest in such  authority for the benefit of the said persons.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>COMMISSIONER OF PAYMENTS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VI">
        <num>VI</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-VI.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>COMMISSIONER OF PAYMENTS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Appointment of Commissioner of Payments.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-16.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central</p>
              <p>Government shall, for the purpose of disbursing the amounts payable  to the Company under sections 8 and 9, by notification, appoint a</p>
              <p>Commissioner of Payments.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may appoint such other persons as it  may think fit to assist the Commissioner and thereupon the</p>
              <p>Commissioner may authorise one or more of such persons also to  exercise all or any of the powers exercisable by him under this Act  and different persons may be authorised to exercise different powers.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person authorised by the Commissioner to exercise any of  the power exercisable by the Commissioner may exercise those powers in  the same manner and with the same effect as if they have been  conferred on that person directly by this Act and not by way of  authorisation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The salaries and allowances of the Commissioner and other  persons appointed under this section shall be defrayed out of the</p>
              <p>Consolidated Fund of India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Payment by the central Government to the Commissioner.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government shall, within thirty days from the specified  date , pay, in cash, to the Commissioner, for payment to the</p>
              <blockList id="section-17.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Company--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.1.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>an amount equal to the amount specified in section 8,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-17.1.list4">
                <listIntroduction>and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.1.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>an amount equal to the amount payable to the Company  under section 9.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A deposit account shall be opened by the Central Government  in favour of the Commissioner, in the Public Account of India, and  every amount paid under this Act to the Commissioner shall be  deposited by him to the credit to the said deposit account and  thereafter the said deposit account shall be operated by the</p>
              <p>Commissioner.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The interest accruing on the amounts standing to the credit  of the deposit account referred to in sub- section (2) shall enure to  the benefit of the Company.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Certain powers of the Central Government or State Government  or Government company.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-18.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government, or the State</p>
              <p>Government, or the Government company, as the case may be, shall be  entitled to receive up to the specified date, to the exclusion of all  other persons, any money due to the Company, in relation to its  undertakings which have vested in the Central Government, or the State</p>
              <p>Government, or the Government company, relised after the appointed day  notwithstanding that the relisation pertains to a period to the  appointed day.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government, or the State Government or the</p>
              <p>Government company, as the case may be, may make a claim to the</p>
              <p>Commissioner with regard to every payment made by it after the  appointed day for discharging any liability of the Company, not being  any liability specified in sub- section (2) of section 5, the relation  to any period prior to the appointed day; and every such claim shall  have priority in accordance with the priorities attaching, under this</p>
              <p>Act, to the matter in relation to which such liability has been  discharged by the Central Government, or the State Government, or the</p>
              <p>Government company.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Save as otherwise provided in this Act, the liabilities of  the Company in respect of any transaction prior to the appointed day,</p>
              <p>which have not been discharged on or before the specified date, shall  be the liabilities of the Company.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Claims to be made to be Commissioner. Every person person  having a claim against the Company shall prefer such claim before the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Commissioner within thirty days from the specified date :</p>
              <p>Provided that if the Commissioner is satisfied that the claimant  was prevented by sufficient cause from preferring the claim within the  said period of thirty days, he may entertain the claim within a  further period of thirty days and not thereafter.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Priority of claims. The claims arising out of the matters  specified in the Schedule shall have priorities in accordance with the  following principles, namely:--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-20.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>Category I shall have precedence over all other</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Categories and Category II shall have precedence over</p>
              <blockList id="section-20.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Category III, and so, on;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the claims specified in each of the Categories, except</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Category III, shall rank equally and be paid in full,</p>
              <blockList id="section-20.paragraph-0.list6">
                <listIntroduction>but, if the amount is insufficient to meet such claims  in full, they shall abate in equal proportions and be  paid accordingly;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list6.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the liabilities specified in Category III shall be  discharged, subject to the priorities specified in this  section, in accordance with the terms of the secured  loans and the priority, inter se, of such loans; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-20.paragraph-0.list6.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the question of discharging any liability with regard to  a matter specified in a lower Category shall arise only  if a</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>surplus is left after meeting all the liabilities  specified in the immediately higher Category.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Examination of claims.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-21.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On receipt of the claims and under  section 19, the Commissioner shall arrange the claims in the order of  priorities specified in the Schedule and examine the same in  accordance with such order of priorities.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-21.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If, on examination of the claims, the Commissioner is of  opinion that the amount paid to him under this Act is not sufficient  to meet the liabilities specified in any lower Category, he shall not  be required to examine the claims in respect of such lower Category.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Admission or rejection of claims.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-22.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>After examining the  claims with reference to the priorities set out in the Schedule, the</p>
              <p>Commissioners shall fix a date on or before which every claimant shall  file the proof of his claim failing which he will be excluded from the  benefit of the disbursement made by the Commissioner.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Not less than fourteen days' notice of the date so fixed  shall be given by advertisement in one issue of a daily newspaper in  the English language and in one issue of such daily newspaper in the  regional language as the Commissioner may consider suitable, and every  such notice shall call upon the claimant to file the proof of his  claim with the Commissioner within the time specified in the  advertisement.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every claimant who fails to file the proof of his claim  within the time specified by the Commissioner shall be excluded from  the disbursements made by the Commissioner.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Commissioner shall, after such investigation as may, in  his opinion, be necessary and after giving the Company an opportunity  of refuting the claim and after giving the claimant a reasonable  opportunity of being heard, in writing, admit or reject the claim in  whole or in part.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Commissioner shall have the power to regulate his own  procedure in all matters arising out of the discharge of his  functions, including the place or places at which he will hold his  sittings and shall, for the purpose of making an investigation under  this Act,</p>
              <p>have the same powers as are vested in a civil court under the Code of</p>
              <blockList id="section-22.5.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), while trying a suit, in respect  of the following matters, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-22.5.list3.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the summoning and enforcing the attendance of any  witness and examining him on oath;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-22.5.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the discovery and production of any document or other  material object producible as evidence;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-22.5.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the reception of evidence on affidavits;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-22.5.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the issuing of any commission for the examination of  witnesses.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any investigation before the Commissioner shall be deemed to  be a judicial proceeding within the meaning of sections 193 228 of the</p>
              <p>Indian Penal Code and the Commissioner shall deemed to be a civil  court for the purpose of section 195 and Chapter XXVI of the Code of</p>
              <p>Criminal Procedure, 1973 (45 of 1860).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A claimant who is dissatisfied with the decision of the</p>
              <p>Commissioner may prefer an appeal against the decision to the</p>
              <p>Principal civil court of original jurisdiction within the local limits  of whose jurisdiction the registered office of the Company is  situated:</p>
              <p>Provided that where a person who is a Judge of a High court is  appointed to be the Commissioner, the appeal shall lie to the High</p>
              <p>Court of Gujarat, and such appeal shall be heard and disposed of by  not less than two Judges of that High Court.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Disbursement of amount by the Commissioner to claimants.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>After admitting a claim under this act, the amount due in respect of  such claim shall be paid by the Commissioner to the person or persons  to whom such sums are due, and, on such payment, the liability of the</p>
              <p>Company in respect of such claim shall stand discharged.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Disbursement of amounts to the Company.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-24.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If, out of the  monies paid to him in relation to the undertakings of the Company,</p>
              <p>there is a balance left after meeting the liabilities as specified in  the Schedule, the Commissioner shall disbures such balance to the</p>
              <p>Company.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-24.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where the possession of any machinery, equipment or other  property, has vested in the Central Government, or the State</p>
              <p>Government, or the Government company, under this Act, but such  machinery, equipment or other property does not belong to the Company,</p>
              <p>it shall be lawful for the Central Government, or the State Govern-</p>
              <p>ment, or the Government company to continue to possess such machinery  or equipment or other property on the same terms and conditions under  which they were possessed by the Company immediately before the  appointed day.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Undisbursed or unclaimed amount to be deposited to the  general revenue account. Any money paid to the Commissioner which  remains undisbursed or unclaimed for a period of three years from the  last day on which the disbursement was made shall be transferred by  the Commissioner to the general revenue account of the Central</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government; but a claim to any money so transfered may be preferred to  the Central Government by the person entitled to such payment and  shall be dealt with as if such transfer had not been made, the order,</p>
              <p>if any, for payment of the claim being treated as an order for the  refund of the revenue.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Assumption of liability.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-26.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where any liability of the  company arising out of any item specified in Category I, Category II</p>
              <p>and Category III of the Schedule is not discharged fully by the</p>
              <p>Commissioner out of the amount paid to him under this Act, the</p>
              <p>Commissioner shall intimate in writing to the Central Government the  extent to that liability which remains undischarged and that liability  shall be assumed by the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-26.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On the vesting of the undertakings of the Company in the</p>
              <p>State Government or the Government company under this act, the  liability assumed by the Central Government under sub- section (1)</p>
              <p>shall be the liability of the State Government or the Government  company, as the case may be.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VII">
        <num>VII</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-VII.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Act to have over riding effect. The provision of this Act  shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith  contained in any other law for the time being in force or in any  instrument having effect by virtue of any law, other than this Act, or  in any decree or order of any court, tribunal or other authority.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Provision relating to contracts.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-28.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every contract entered  into by the Company in relation to its undertakings before the date of  taking over for any service, sale or supply and in force immediately  before the appointed day, shall, on and from the expiry of one hundred  and eighty days from the appointed day, cease to have effect unless  such contract is, before the expiry of that period, ratified, in  writing, by the Central Government, or the State Government, or the</p>
              <p>Government company, and, in ratifying such contract, the Central</p>
              <p>Government, the State Government, or the Government company, as the  case may be, may make such alterations or modifications therein as it  may think fit.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-28.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every contract entered into by the Company, or the Authorsed</p>
              <p>Controller on behalf of the Company, in relation to its undetakings,</p>
              <p>on or after the date of taking over for any service, sale or supply  and in force immediately before the appointed day shall remain in  force, unless such contract is terminated or modified or altered by  the Central Government, the State Government or the Government  company, as the case may be, within a period of one hundred and eighty  days from the appointed day.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-28.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government, the State Government or the</p>
              <p>Government company, as the case may be, shall not refuse to ratify,</p>
              <p>terminate, modify or alter a contract under sub- section (1) or sub-</p>
              <blockList id="section-28.3.list4">
                <listIntroduction>section (2)--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-28.3.list4.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>unless it is satisfied that such contract is unduly  onerous or has been entered into in bad faith or is  detrimental to the interests of the undertakings of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-28.3.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Company; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-28.3.list6.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>except after giving to the parties to such contract a  reasonable opportunity of being heard and recording in  writing its reasons for refusal to ratify the contract  or for terminating the contract or for making any  alteration or modification therein.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Transfer of assets, etc. to be void in certain cases.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-29.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except with the prior approval of the Central Government, the State</p>
              <p>Government or the Government company, neither the Company nor any part  thereof the management or the possession of which could not be taken  over by the Authorised Controller or the Central Government or the</p>
              <p>State Government or the Government company by reason of any decree,</p>
              <p>order or injunction of any court or otherwise shall, on and from the  appointed day, transfer by sale, mortgage or otherwise any property or  other</p>
              <p>assets forming part of the undertakings of the Company and any such  transfer, without such prior approval, shall be void and inoperative.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person who contravenes the provisions of sub- section (1)</p>
              <p>shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to  two years, or with fine which may extend to ten thousand rupees, or  with both.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-30.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No suit,</p>
              <p>prosecution, or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central</p>
              <p>Government or any officer of that Government, or the Custodian, or the</p>
              <p>State Government, or the Government company, or any officer of the</p>
              <p>State Government or the Government, or the State Government, or the</p>
              <p>Government company, for anything which is in good faith done or  intended to be done under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-30.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the</p>
              <p>Central Government or any officer or other employee of that</p>
              <p>Government, or the State Government, or any officer or other employee  of the State Government or of the Government company or other person  authorised by the State Government, or the Government company, for any  damage caused or likely to be caused by anything which is in good  faith done or intended to be done under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading>Penalties. Any person who,--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-31.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-31.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-31.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>having in his possession, custody or control any  property forming part of any undertaking of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Company, wrongfully withholds such property from the</p>
              <p>Central Government, or the State Government, or the</p>
              <blockList id="section-31.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Government company; or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-31.paragraph-0.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>wrongfully obtains possession of, or retains, any  property forming part of any undertaking of the Company  or wilfully withholds or fails to furnish to the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Central Government, or any person or body of persons  specified by that Government, or the State Government,</p>
              <p>or the Government company, any document relating to  such undertaking which may be in his possession,</p>
              <p>custody or control or fails to deliver to</p>
              <p>the Central Government, or the State Government, or the</p>
              <p>Government company or any person or body of persons  specified by the Central Government, or the State</p>
              <p>Government, or the Government company, any assets,</p>
              <blockList id="section-31.paragraph-0.list12">
                <listIntroduction>books of account, registers or other documents in his  possession, custody or control, relating to the  undertaking of the Company; or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-31.paragraph-0.list12.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>wrongfully removes or destroys any property forming part  of any undertaking of the Company or prefers any claims  under this Act which he knows or has reasonable cause  to believe to be false or grossly inaccurate,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to  two years, or with fine which may extend to ten thousand rupees, or  with both.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>Offences by companies.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-32.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where an offence under this Act  has been committed by a company, every person who at the time the  offence was committed was in charge of and was reaponsible to, the  company for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as the  company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be  liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:</p>
              <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render  any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the  offence was committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised  all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where  any offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it  is proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or  connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any  director, manager, secretary, or other officer of the company, such  director, manager, secretary, or other officer shall be deemed to be  guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and  punished accordingly.</p>
              <blockList id="section-32.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-32.2.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" company" means anybody corporate and includes a firm or  other association of individuals; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-32.2.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" director", in realtion to a firm, means a partner in  the firm.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading>Delegation of powers.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-33.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may, by  notification, direct that all or any of the powers exercisable by it  under this Act, other than the power conferred by section 34, may also  be exercised by such person or persons as may be specified in the  notification.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-33.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Whenever any delegation of power is made under sub- section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-33.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, the person to whom such power has been delegated shall act under  the direction, control and supervision of the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-34">
          <num>34.</num>
          <heading>Power of Central Government to make rules.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-34.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central</p>
              <p>Government may, by notification, make rules for carrying out the  provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-34.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-34.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-34.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the time within which, and the manner in which, an  intimation shall be given to the Commissioner under  sub- section (4) of section 4;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-34.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>any other matter which is required to be, or may be,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-34.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act  shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House  of Parliament, while it is in session for a total period of thirty  days, which may be comprised in one session or in two or more  successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session  immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule  or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall  thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</p>
              <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that rule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in  giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government  may, by order, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-35.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>remove the difficulty:</p>
              <p>Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a  period of two years from the appointed day.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-36">
          <num>36.</num>
          <heading>Declaration as to the policy of the State. It is hereby  declared that this Act is for giving effect to the policy of the State  towards securing the principles specified in clause (b) of article 39  of the Constitution.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-36.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Explanation.-- In this section," State" has the same meaning as in  article 12 of the Constitution.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
