<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1923/6/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1923/6"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Cantonments (House- Accommodation) Act, 1923"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1923/6/eng@1923-03-05/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1923/6/eng@1923-03-05"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1923-03-05" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1923/6/eng@1923-03-05/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1923/6/eng@1923-03-05"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Cantonments (House- Accommodation) Act, 1923</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 6 OF 1923</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 5th March, 1923.] WH</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act further to amend and to consolidate the law relating to the  provision of house- accommodation for military officers in cantonments.</p>
        <p>CHAP</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be  called the Cantonments (House- Accommodation) Act, 1923.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It extends to the whole of India   .</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on the first day of April, 1923, but  it shall not become operative in any cantonment or part of a  cantonment until the issue, or otherwise than in pursuance, of a  notification as hereinafter provided by section 3:</p>
              <p>Provided that any notification made under section 3 of the</p>
              <p>Cantonments (House- Accommodation) Act, 1902 (2 of 1902), which is in  force at the commencement of this Act, shall be deemed to be a  notification made under section 3 of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-2.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless there is anything  repugnant in the subject or context,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" Brigade area" means one of the Brigade areas, whether  occupied by a brigade or not, into which India is for  military purposes for the time being divided, and  includes any area which the Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, declare to be a</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Brigade area for all or any or the purposes of this</p>
              <blockList id="section-2.1.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.1.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" Cantonment Board" means a Cantonment Board  constituted under the Cantonments Act, 1924 (2 of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1924">
          <num>1924.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1924.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1924.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>);]</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1924.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" Command" means one of the Commands into which India is  for military purposes for the time being divided, and  includes any area which the Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, declare to be a</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1924.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Command for all or any of the purposes of this Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1924.paragraph-0.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>Officer Commanding the station] means the officer  for the time being in command of the forces in a  cantonment  or, if that Officer is the Officer</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Commanding the District, the military officer who would  be in command of those forces in the absence of the</p>
              <blockList id="section-1924.paragraph-0.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Officer Commanding the District];</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1924.paragraph-0.list6.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>" District" means one of the Districts into which India  is for military purposes for the time being divided; it  includes a Brigade area which does not form part of any  such District and any area which the Central Government  may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare  to be a District for all or any of the purposes of this</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1924.paragraph-0.list8">
                <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1924.paragraph-0.list8.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>" house" means a house suitable for occupation by a  military officer or a military mess, and includes the  land and buildings appurtenant to a house;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1924.paragraph-0.list8.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>" military officer" means a commissioned or warrant  officer of the Indian military or air forces on  military or air force duty in a cantonment,   an  officer of the Cantonments Department] and any person  in Army departmental employment whom the Officer</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1924.paragraph-0.list10">
                <listIntroduction>Commanding the District may at any time, by an order in  writing, place on the same footing as a military  officer for the purposes of this Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1924.paragraph-0.list10.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>" owner" includes the person who is receiving, or is  entitled to receive, the rent of a house, whether on  his own account or on behalf of himself and others or  as an agent or trustee, or who would so receive the  rent, or be entitled to receive it, if the house were  let to a tenant; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1924.paragraph-0.list10.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-1924.paragraph-0.list10.i.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>a house is said to be in a state of reasonable repair  when--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-1924.paragraph-0.list10.i.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>all floors, walls, pillars and arches are  sound and all roofs sound and watertight,</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-1924.paragraph-0.list10.i.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>all doors and windows are intact, properly  painted or oiled, and provided with proper locks or  bolts or other secure fastenings, and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-1924.paragraph-0.list10.i.list0.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>all rooms, out- houses and other appurtenant  buildings are properly colour- washed or white- washed.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-1924.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any question arises whether any land or building is  appurtenant to a house, it shall be decided by the  Officer</p>
              <p>Commanding the station], whose decision thereon shall, subject to  revision by the  Collector], be final.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1924.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the application of this Act to  the territories  which, immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised in  any Part B State], any reference to an enactment not in force in    those territories] shall be construed as a reference to the  corresponding law in force in  those territories].]</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>APPLICATION OF ACT</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>APPLICATION OF ACT</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Cantonments or parts of cantonments in which Act to be  operative.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The  Central Government]  may, by notification in  the Official Gazette, declare this Act to be operative in any  cantonment or part of a cantonment , other than a cantonment  situate within the limits of a presidency- town.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Before issuing a notification under sub- section (1) in  respect of any cantonment or part of a cantonment, the  Central</p>
              <p>Government] shall cause local inquiry to be made with a view to  determining whether it is expedient to issue such notification, and  what portion (if any) of the area proposed to be included therein  should be excluded therefrom.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Saving of written instruments.- Nothing in this Act shall  affect the provisions of any written  contract with the Government]</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>unless all the parties to that contract consent in writing to be bound  by the terms of this Act.]</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>APPROPRIATION OF HOUSES</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>APPROPRIATION OF HOUSES</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Liability of houses to appropriation.- Every house situate in a  cantonment or part of a cantonment in respect of which a notification  under sub- section</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of section 3 is for the time being in force  shall be liable to appropriation by  the Central Government] on a  lease in the manner and subject to the conditions hereinafter  provided.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Conditions on which houses may be appropriated.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-6.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Where--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>a military officer who is stationed in or has  been posted to the cantonment, or a President of a  military mess in the cantonment, applies in writing to  the Officer Commanding the station stating that he is  unable to secure suitable accommodation in the  cantonment for himself or the mess on reasonable terms  by the private agreement, and that no suitable house or  quarter  belonging to the Government] is available  for his occupation or for the occupation of the mess,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-6.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>and the Officer Commanding the station is satisfied on  inquiry of the truth of the facts so stated; or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.1.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the Officer Commanding the station is  satisfied on inquiry that there is not in the  cantonment a sufficient and assured supply of houses  available at reasonable rates of rent by private  agreement to meet the requirements of the military  officers and military messes whose accommodation in the  cantonment is in his opinion necessary or expedient,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>the Officer Commanding the station may, with a view to enforcing the  liability under section 5, serve a notice on the owner of any house  which appears to him to be suitable for occupation by a military  officer or a military mess, as the case may be, within the cantonment,</p>
              <p>or, of this Act is in force in part only of the cantonment, within  that part, requiring the owner to permit the house to be inspected,</p>
              <p>measured and surveyed by such person and on such date, not being less  than three clear days from the service of the notice, and at such time  between sunrise and sunset, as may be specified in the notice.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On the date and at the time so specified the owner shall be  bound to afford all reasonable facilities to the person specified in  the notice for the purpose of the inspection, measurement and survey  of the house and, if he refuses or neglects to do so, such person may,</p>
              <p>subject to any rules made under this Act, enter on the premises and do  all such things as may be reasonably necessary for the said purpose.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Procedure for taking house on lease.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-7.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>If, on the report of  such person as aforesaid, the  Officer Commanding the station] is  satisfied that the house is suitable for occupation by a military  officer or a military mess, he may  by notice--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>require the owner to execute a lease of the house to    the Central Government] for a specified period which  shall not be less than five years;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>require the existing occupier, if any, to vacate the  house; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>require the owner to execute within such time as may be  specified in the notice such repairs as may, in the  opinion of the  officer Commanding the station], be  necessary for the purpose of putting the house into a  state of reasonable repair.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every notice issued under sub- section (1) shall state the  amount of the annual rent proposed as reasonable for the house,</p>
              <p>calculated on the assumption that the owner will carry out the  required repairs, if any. It shall also contain an estimate of the  cost of such repairs.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-7.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The following shall be deemed to be conditions of every lease  executed under sub- section (1), namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-7.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>that the house shall, on the expiration of the lease, be  redelivered to the owner in a state of reasonable  repair, and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-7.3.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>that the ground and the garden, if any, appertaining to  the house shall be maintained in the condition in which  they are at the time at which the lease is executed:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that nothing in this sub- section shall be deemed to  affect the right of  the Central Government] to avoid the lease in  any such event as is specified in clause (e) of section 108 of the</p>
              <p>Transfer of Property Act, 1882 (4 of 1882).]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Procedure to be observed before taking a house on lease.-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Rep. by the Cantonments (House- Accommodation Amendment) Act, 1930 (9   of 1930), s. 5.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Sanction to be obtained before a house is occupied as a  hospital, etc. No house in any cantonment or part of a cantonment in  which this Act is operative shall, unless it was so occupied at the  date of the issue of the notification declaring this Act or the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Cantonments (House- Accommodation) Act, 1902 (2 of 1902), as the  case may be, to be operative, be occupied for the purposes of a  hospital, school, school hostel, bank, hotel, or shop, or by a  railway administration, a company or firm engaged in trade or business  or a club, without the previous sanction of the Officer Commanding the</p>
              <p>District given with the concurrence of the Commissioner or, in a State  where there are no Commissioners, of the Collector.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Houses not to be appropriated in certain cases.- No notice  shall be issued under section 7 if the house--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>was, at the date of the issue of the notification  declaring this Act or the  Cantonments (House-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Accommodation) Act, 1902 (2 of 1902), as the case may  be, to be operative in the cantonment or part of the  cantonment, or is, with such sanction as is required by  section 9, occupied as a hospital, school, school  hostel, bank, hotel or shop, and has been so occupied  continuously during the three years immediately  preceding the time when the occasion for issuing the  notice arises, or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>was, at the date of such a notification as is referred  to in clause (a), or is, with such sanction as  aforesaid, occupied by a railway administration or by a  company or firm engaged in trade or business or by a  club, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>is occupied by the owner, or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list2.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>has been appropriated by the State Government with the  concurrence of the Officer Commanding the District, or  by the Central Government, for use a public office or  for any other purpose.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Time to be allowed for giving possession of house.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a  house is unoccupied, a notice issued under section 7 may require the  owner to give possession of the same to the  officer Commanding the  station] within twenty- one days from the service of the notice.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If a house is occupied, a notice issued under section 7 shall  not require its vacation in less than thirty days from the service of  the notice.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where a notice has been issued under section 7 and the house  has been vacated in pursuance thereof, the lease shall be deemed to  have commenced on the date on which the house was so vacated.</p>
              <p>consideration under a registered lease from year to year, the Central</p>
              <p>Government shall be liable as aforesaid for the term of six months  from the date on which the house is vacated in pursuance of the  notice.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-11.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Nothing in this section shall be deemed--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to render the Central Government so liable unless an  application in writing in this behalf is made by the  owner to the  Officer Commanding the station] within  fifteen days from the service of the notice; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.3.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>to limit or otherwise affect any agreement between the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Government and the owner.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Power for owner to refer to civil court on question of rent.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-15.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the owner considers that the rent stated in a notice issued  under section 7 is not reasonable, he may, within a period of    thirty] days from the service of such notice,  refer the matter  to a civil court, in accordance with the provisions of Chapter IV]:</p>
              <p>Provided that where an appeal has been made to the Officer</p>
              <p>Commanding the District under section 30, the period of thirty days  shall be reckoned from the date on which the owner received notice of  the result of the appeal under sub- section (2) of section 32.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the owner does not make such a  reference] within the  said period, he shall be deemed to have accepted the rent so offered.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Power for owner to refer to civil court on question of  repairs.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-16.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the owner fails to execute any repairs to a house as  required by a notice issued to him under section 7, the  Officer  commanding the station] may by notice require the owner to execute the  repairs within such period, not being less than  thirty] days, as  may be specified in the notice.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If the owner objects to any requisition contained in a notice  issued under sub- section (1), he may within  thirty] days from the  service of the notice  refer the matter to a civil court in  accordance with the provisions of Chapter IV]:</p>
              <p>Provided that where an appeal has been made to the Officer</p>
              <p>Commanding the District under section 30, the period of thirty days  shall be reckoned from the date on which the owner received notice of  the result of the appeal under sub- section (2) of section 32.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Every reference under sub- section (2) shall be accompanied  by an estimate of the repairs, if any, which the owner considers  necessary in order to put the house into a state of reasonable  repair.]</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Power to have repairs executed and recover cost.- If the  owner fails to comply with a notice issued under sub- section</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of  section 16, the Military Engineer Services or the Public Works</p>
              <p>Department may, with the previous sanction of the Officer Commanding  the station and notwithstanding any right of reference conferred by  that section, cause the repairs specified in the notice to be executed  at the expense of  the Central Government], and the cost thereof,</p>
              <p>or, where a reference has been made, the amount finally determined by  the civil court, may be deducted from the rent payable to the owner.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Notice to be given of devolution of interest in house in  cantonment.- Every person on whom devolves, by transfer, by succession  or by operation of law, the interest of an owner in any house, or in  any part of any house, situate in a coantonment or part of a  cantonment in respect of which a notification under sub- section</heading>
          <subsection id="section-18.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of  section 3 is for the time being in force, shall be bound to give  notice of the fact to the  Officer Commanding the station] within  one month from the date of such devolution, and, if he, without  reasonable cause, fails to do so, he shall be punishable with fine  which may extend to fifty rupees.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>PROCEDURE IN REFERENCES</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PROCEDURE IN REFERENCES</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Jurisdiction in references.- All references under this Act  shall be made by application to, and tried by, the Court of the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>District Judge.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Procedure and powers of the Court.- References under this Act  shall be deemed to be proceedings within the meaning of section 141 of  the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), and in the trial  thereof the Court may exercise any of its powers under that Code.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Restriction of scope of inquiry.- The scope of the inquiry in  a reference under this Act shall be restricted to a consideration of  the matters referred to the Court in accordance with the provisions of  this Act.]</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>APPEALS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-V.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>APPEALS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Appeal to High Court.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-29.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An appeal shall lie to the High</p>
              <p>Court against the decision of the Court of the District Judge upon a  reference tried by it.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No appeal under this section shall be admitted unless it is  made within thirty days from the date of the decision against which it  is preferred.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-29.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An appeal preferred under this section shall be deemed to be  an appeal from an order within the meaning of section 108 of the Code  of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908).]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading>Appeal to Officer Commanding the District.- The owner or  any tenant of a house in respect of which a notice has been issued  under section 7 may, within a period of  ten days] from the date of  the service thereof, appeal to the Officer Commanding the District  against the decision of the Officer Commanding the station to  appropriate the house.]</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading>Petition of appeal.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-31.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every petition of appeal under  section 30 shall be in writing and accompanied by a copy of the notice  appealed against.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any such petition may be presented to the  Officer</p>
              <p>Commanding the station], and that officer shall be bound to forward it  to the authority empowered by section 30 to hear the appeal, and may  attach thereto any report which he may desire to make in explanation  of the notice appealed against.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any such petition is presented direct to the Officer</p>
              <p>Commanding the District and an immediate order on the petition is not  necessary, the Officer Commanding the District may refer the petition  to the  Officer Commanding the station] for report.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>Order in appeal final.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-32.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>] The decision on any such  appeal of the Officer Commanding the District  shall be final, and  shall not be questioned in any court otherwise than on the ground that  the house is situate in a cantonment, or part of a cantonment, in  which this Act is not operative:</p>
              <p>Provided that no appeal shall be decided until the appellant has  been heard or has had a reasonable opportunity of being heard in  person or through a legal practitioner  and in giving a decision the</p>
              <p>Officer Commanding the District shall record briefly the grounds  therefor].</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-32.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notice of the result of the appeal shall be given to the  appellant as soon as may be, and, where the appellant is a tenant of  the house, to the owner of the house also.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading>Suspension of action pending appeal.- Where an appeal has been  presented under section 30 within the period prescribed  therein],</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-33.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>all action on the notice shall, on the application of the appellant,</p>
              <p>be held in abeyance pending the decision of the appeal.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>SUPPLEMENTAL PROVISIONS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VI">
        <num>VI</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-VI.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>SUPPLEMENTAL PROVISIONS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-34">
          <num>34.</num>
          <heading>Service of notice and requisitions.- Every notice or  requisition prescribed by this Act shall be in writing, signed by the  person by whom it is given or made or by his duly appointed agent, and  may be served by post on the person to whom it is addressed, or, in  the case of an owner who does not reside in or near the cantonment, on  his agent appointed  in accordance with a bye- law made under clause</heading>
          <subsection id="section-34.29">
            <num>(29)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of section 282 of the Cantonments Act, 1924 (2 of 1924)].</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-34A">
          <num>34A.</num>
          <heading>Computation of periods of limitation.- The period  prescribed for making any reference or preferring any appeal under  this Act shall be computed in accordance with the provisions of the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-34A.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Indian Limitation Act, 1908 (9 of 1908).]</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading>Power for Central Government to make rules.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-35.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central</p>
              <p>Government may make rules  to carry out the purposes and objects of  this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-35.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-35.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-35.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>define the powers of entry, inspection, measurement or  survey which may be exercised in carrying out the  purposes and objects of this act or of any rule made  hereunder.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-35.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act  shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House  of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty  days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more  successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session  immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or  both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall  thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</p>
              <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that rule.]</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-36">
          <num>36.</num>
          <heading>Further provisions respecting rules.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-36.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The power to make  rules under section 35 shall be subject to the condition of the rules  being made after previous publication and of their not taking effect  until they have been published in the</p>
              <p>Official Gazette and in such other manner (if any) as the Central</p>
              <p>Government may direct.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any rule under section 35 may be general for all cantonments  or parts of cantonments  in which this Act is for the time being  operative, or may be special for any of such cantonments or parts as  the Central Government may direct.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A copy of the rules under section 35 for the time being in  force in a cantonment shall be kept open to inspection free of charge  at all reasonable times in the office of the Cantonment  Board].</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In making any rule under clause (b) of sub- section (2) of  section 35, the Central Government may direct that whoever obstructs  any person, not being a public servant within the meaning of section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860), in making any entry,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>inspection, measurement or survey, shall be punishable with fine which  may extend to fifty rupees, and, in the case of a continuing offence,</p>
              <p>with fine which, in addition to such fine as aforesaid, may extend to  five rupees for every day after the first during which such offence  continues.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-37">
          <num>37.</num>
          <heading>Inapplicability of section 556 of the Code of Criminal</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-37.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Procedure, 1898, to trials of offences.- No Judge or Magistrate shall  be deemed, within the meaning of section 556 of the Code of Criminal</p>
              <p>Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898), to be a party to, or personally  interested in, any prosecution for an offence constituted by or under  this Act merely because he is a member of the Cantonment  Board or  has ordered or approved the prosecution.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-38">
          <num>38.</num>
          <heading>Protection to persons acting under Act.- No suit or other  legal proceeding shall lie against any person for anything in good  faith done, or intended to be done, under this Act or in pursuance of  any lawful notice or order issued under this Act.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-39">
          <num>39.</num>
          <heading>Repeals. Rep. by the Repealing Act, 1927 (12 of 1927), s. 2  and Sch.</heading>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
