<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1890/20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1890/20"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The North- Western Provinces And Oudh Act, 1890"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1890/20/eng@1890-10-16/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1890/20/eng@1890-10-16"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1890-10-16" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1890/20/eng@1890-10-16/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1890/20/eng@1890-10-16"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-26" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The North- Western Provinces And Oudh Act, 1890</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 20 OF 1890</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 16th October, 1890.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the better administration of the North-</p>
        <p>Western Provinces and Oudh and to amend certain enactments in force  in those Provinces and in Oudh.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the better administration  of the territories respectively administered by the Lieutenant-</p>
        <p>Governor of the North- Western Provinces and the Chief Commissioner of</p>
        <p>Oudh, and for that purpose to amend certain enactments which are in  force in the said Provinces and in Oudh; It is hereby enacted as  follows:--</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Title. This Act may be called the North- Western Provinces and</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Oudh Act, 1890.</p>
            <p>PART</p>
            <p>THE NORTH- WESTERN PROVINCES</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <part id="part-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="part-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>THE NORTH- WESTERN PROVINCES</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>This Part shall come into force on such day  as the said</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Lieutenant- Governor may, by notification in the Official Gazette,</p>
              <p>direct.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>an</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Commencement of Part I.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>and 4. Commencement of Part I. Amendment of Act 19 of 1873.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Rep. by the United Provinces Land- revenue Act, 1901 (U. P. Act 3 of</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1901">
          <num>1901.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1901.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>).</p>
              <p>And whereas it has been determined to annex the Jhansi Division,</p>
              <p>comprising the districts of Jhansi, Jalaun and Lalatpur, to the</p>
              <p>Allahabad Division;</p>
              <p>And whereas the said Jhansi Division is a Schedule District under  the Scheduled Districts Act, 1874 (14 of 1874);</p>
              <p>And whereas it is expedient that the law in force in the same  division should, on such annexation, be the same as the law in force  in the temporarily- settled districts comprised in the Allahabad</p>
              <p>Division, and that the said division should cease to be a Scheduled</p>
              <p>District;</p>
              <p>It is hereby enacted as follows:--</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Laws in force in certain districts of the Allahabad Division  to apply to Jhansi.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All enactments which shall on the day  when  this Part comes into force be in force in the said temporarily- settled  districts and not in the said Jhansi Division shall be deemed to come  into force in that Division on and from the said day.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except the Jhansi Encumbered Estates Act, 1882  (16 of</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1882">
          <num>1882.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1882.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>), and the Jhansi and Morar Act, 1886 , (17 of 1886), all  enactments which shall on the said day  be in force in the said  division and not in the said temporarily- settled districts, including  the Jhansi Courts Act, 1867 (18 of 1867), and Act No. 27 of 1867,</p>
              <p>shall be deemed to be repealed on and from the said day  in the said  division.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Amendment of Act 16 of 1882. Rep. by the Bundelkhand</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Encumbered Estates Act, 1903 (U. P. Act 1 of 1903).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Discharge of functions assigned to Deputy Commissioner and</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Commissioner by Act 17 of 1886. The functions assigned to the Deputy</p>
              <p>Commissioner and the Commissioner by the Jhansi and Morar Act, 1886,</p>
              <p>(17 of 1886), shall be discharged by the District Judge and the</p>
              <p>High Court, respectively, and references to Courts in the Jhansi  district subordinate to the Commissioner shall be deemed to apply to  the Civil Courts established in that district under the Bengal,</p>
              <p>North- Western Provinces and Assam Civil Courts Act, 1887 (12 of</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1887">
          <num>1887.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1887.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Jhansi Division to cease to be a Scheduled District.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On  and from the said day  the said division shall cease to be a</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </part>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-scheduled">
      <doc name="scheduled">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1890/20/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1890/20"/>
              <FRBRalias value="District ."/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1890/20/eng@1890-10-16/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1890/20/eng@1890-10-16"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1890/20/eng@1890-10-16/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1890/20/eng@1890-10-16"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-26" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduled">
            <section id="section-9">
              <num>9.</num>
              <heading>Application of Act 12 of 1887 to Jhansi, and disposal of  pending cases.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-9.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-9.2.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>All cases or proceedings pending in any Civil Court in the  said division on the said day  shall be disposed of as follows:--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-9.2.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>if pending in the Court of a Tahsildar or of an</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Assistant Commissioner of the second class-- by the</p>
                  <blockList id="section-9.2.list4">
                    <listIntroduction>Munsif;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-9.2.list4.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>if pending in the Court of an Assistant Commissioner of  the first class- by the Subordinate Judge;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-9.2.list4.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>if pending in the Court of a Deputy Commissioner-- by the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-9.2.list6">
                    <listIntroduction>District Judge;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-9.2.list6.d">
                      <num>(d)</num>
                      <p>if pending in the Court of the Commissioner-- by the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>District Judge, unless the case pending is an appeal  from a decree or order of the Deputy Commissioner, in  which case the appeal shall be disposed of by the High</p>
                  <p>Court.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9.3">
                <num>(3)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>For the purposes of sections 20 to 22, both inclusive, of the</p>
                  <p>Bengal,  North- Western Provinces and Assam Civil Courts Act, 1887</p>
                  <blockList id="section-9.3.list3">
                    <listIntroduction>(12 of 1887), all decrees and orders passed by Civil Courts in the  said division and not appealed against before the said day  shall be  deemed--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-9.3.list3.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>if passed by the Court of a Tahsildar or an Assistant</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-9.3.list5">
                    <listIntroduction>Commissioner of the second class-- to have been passed  by a Munsif;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-9.3.list5.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>if passed by the Court of an Assistant Commissioner of  the first class-- to have been passed by a Subordinate</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <blockList id="section-9.3.list7">
                    <listIntroduction>Judge;</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-9.3.list7.c">
                      <num>(c)</num>
                      <p>if passed by the Court of a Deputy Commissioner or the</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                  <p>Commissioner-- to have been passed by a District Judge.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9.4">
                <num>(4)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where any Civil Court ceases by reason of the passing of this</p>
                  <p>Act to have jurisdiction with respect to any case, any proceeding in  relation to that case which, if that Court had not ceased to have  jurisdiction, might have been had therein, may be had in the Court to  which the business of the former Court is transferred by sub- section</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>; but this sub- section shall not apply to cases for which provision  is made in section 623 or section 649 of the Code of Civil Procedure.</p>
                  <p>(14 of 1882).</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-9.5">
                <num>(5)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>In the case of appeals from the decrees and orders mentioned  in sub- section (3) the period of limitation shall be calculated in  accordance with the provisions of section 15 of the Jhansi Courts Act,</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-1867">
              <num>1867.</num>
              <heading>(18 of 1867), as though this Act had not been passed.</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-1867.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>PART</p>
                  <p>OUDH</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <part id="part-II">
              <num>II</num>
              <paragraph id="part-II.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>OUDH</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-10">
                <num>10.</num>
                <heading>Commencement of Part II. This Part shall come into force on  such day  as the Chief Commissioner of Oudh may, by notification in  the Official Gazette, direct.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-11">
                <num>11.</num>
                <heading>Board of Revenue of the North- Western Provinces to be the</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Board of Revenue- of, and Chief Revenue- authority in, Oudh.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-11.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>On and  from the day on which this Part comes into force the Board of Revenue  constituted under the North- Western Provinces Land- revenue Act, 1873,</p>
                    <p>(19 of 1873.) shall be deemed to be also the Board of Revenue for  the territories administered by the Chief Commissioner of Oudh, and  shall be known and designated as the Board of Revenue of the North-</p>
                    <p>Western Provinces and Oudh.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-11.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>All references made in any enactment as amended by this Part  to the Board of Revenue shall be deemed, so far as they relate to</p>
                    <p>Oudh, to refer to the said Board.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-11.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>In any enactment for the time being in force in the  territories administered by the Chief Commissioner of Oudh, in which  the expression" Chief Revenue- authority" or" Chief Controlling</p>
                    <p>Revenue- authority" is used, the expression shall, subject to the  provisions of any enactment passed after the said day,  be  construed, so far as the said territories are concerned, as referring  to the Board of Revenue of the North- Western Provinces and Oudh.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-54">
                <num>54.</num>
                <heading>Pending appeals. All appeals pending when this Part comes  into force  from decrees or orders passed under the same Act shall  be disposed of as if this Act had not been passed:</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-54.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Provided that the  State Government] may, by order, transfer to  the District Judge any appeals then pending before the Commissioner or</p>
                    <p>Collector in cases in which the appeal will, under the Oudh Rent Act,</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-1886">
                <num>1886.</num>
                <heading/>
                <paragraph id="section-1886.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>, (22 of 1886.) as amended by this Part, lie to the District</p>
                    <p>Judge.</p>
                    <p>PART</p>
                    <p>THE NORTH- WESTERN PROVINCES AND OUDH</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
            </part>
            <part id="part-III">
              <num>III</num>
              <paragraph id="part-III.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>THE NORTH- WESTERN PROVINCES AND OUDH</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-62">
                <num>62.</num>
                <heading>Commencement of Part III. This part shall come into force on  such day  as the Lieutenant- Governor of the North- Western Provinces  and Chief Commissioner of Oudh may, by notification in the Official</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-62.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Gazette, direct.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-63">
                <num>63.</num>
                <heading>Place where the Board may sit.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-63.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Notwithstanding anything    in section 128 of the Oudh Rent Act, 1886 (22 of 1886), the Board  of Revenue of the North- Western Provinces and Oudh shall, for the  disposal of cases under those Acts, sit in such place or places in the</p>
                    <p>North- Western Provinces or Oudh as  the State Government] may, by  notification in the Official Gazette,  appoint in respect to cases  under either of those Acts.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-63.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>For the disposal of cases other than those referred to in  sub- section (1) the said Board may, subject to the orders of  the</p>
                    <p>State Government], sit in any place in the North- Western Provinces or</p>
                    <p>Oudh that the Board thinks fit.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-64">
                <num>64.</num>
                <heading>Amendment of section 4, Act 19 of 1873. Rep. by the United</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-64.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Provinces Land- revenue Act, 1901 (U. P. Act 3 of 1901).</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
            </part>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
