<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1995/39/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1995/39"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Textile Undertakings (Nationalisation) Act, 1995"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1995/39/eng@1995-09-08/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1995/39/eng@1995-09-08"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1995-09-08" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1995/39/eng@1995-09-08/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1995/39/eng@1995-09-08"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Textile Undertakings (Nationalisation) Act, 1995</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 39 OF 1995</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 8th September, 1995.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the acquisition and transfer of the textile  undertakings, and the right, title and interest of the owners in  respect of the textile undertakings, specified in the First Schedule  with a view to augmenting the production and distribution of different  varieties of cloth and yarn so as to subserve the interests of the  general Public and for matters connected therewith or incidental  thereto,</p>
        <p>WHEREAS the textile companies specified in column (3) of the</p>
        <p>First Schedule have, through their undertakings specified in column</p>
        <p>(2) of the said Schedule, been engaged in the manufacture and  production of different varieties of cloth and yarn;</p>
        <p>AND WHEREAS, pending acquisition, the management of the said  textile undertakings was taken over by the Central Government under  section 3 of the Textile Undertakings (Taking Over of Management) Act,</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1983">
        <num>1983.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1983.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>, (40 of 1983.) or under section 3 of the Laxmirattan and</p>
            <p>Atherton West Cotton Mills (Taking Over of Management) Act, 1976, (98   of 1976.) as the case may be;</p>
            <p>AND WHEREAS large sums of money have been invested with a view to  making the said textile undertakings viable;</p>
            <p>AND WHEREAS further investment of very large Sums of money is  necessary for the purpose of securing the optimum utilisation of the  available facilities for the manufacture, production. and distribution  of cloth and yarn by the said textile undertakings of the companies;</p>
            <p>AND WHEREAS such investment is also necessary for securing the  continued employment of the workmen employed in the said textile  undertakings;</p>
            <p>AND WHEREAS it is necessary in the public interest to acquire the  said textile undertakings of the textile companies to ensure that the  interest of the general public are served by the continuance by the  said undertakings of the companies of the manufacture, Production and  distribution of different varieties of cloth and yarn which are vital  to the needs of the country;</p>
            <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- sixth Year of the</p>
            <p>Republic of India as follows:-</p>
            <p>CHAP</p>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the</p>
              <p>Textile Undertakings (Nationalisation) Act, 1995.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of sections 31 and 32 shall come into force a  once and the remaining provisions of this Act shall be deemed to have  come into force on the 1st day of April, 1994.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-2.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In this Ordinance, unless the context  otherwise requires,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" appointed day" means the 1st day of April, 1994;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-2.1.list1.b.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>" bank" means-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-2.1.list1.b.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>the State Bank of India constituted under the State Bank  of India Act, 1955; (23 of 1955.)</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.1.list1.b.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>a subsidiary Bank as defined in the State Bank of India</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>(Subsidiary Banks) Act, 1959; (38 of 1959.)</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.1.list3.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>a corresponding new bank constituted under section 3 of  the Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Under-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.1.list5">
                <listIntroduction>takings) Act. 1970; (5 of 1970.)</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.1.list5.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>a corresponding new bank constituted under section 3 of  the Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Under-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.1.list7">
                <listIntroduction>takings) Act, 1980; (40 of 1980.)</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.1.list7.v">
                  <num>(v)</num>
                  <p>any other bank, being a scheduled bank as defined in  clause (e) of section 2 of the Reserve Bank of India Act,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1934">
          <num>1934.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1934.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1934.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>; (2 of 1934.)</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1934.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" Commissioner" means a Commissioner of Payments  appointed under section 17;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1934.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" Custodian" means a Custodian appointed under section 4  of the Textile Undertakings (Taking Over of Management) Act,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1983">
          <num>1983.</num>
          <heading>(40 of 1983.) or under section 4 of the Laxmirattan  and Atherton West Cotton Mills (Taking Over of Management)</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-1983.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1983.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Act, 1976, (98 of 1976.) as the case may be;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1983.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>" National Textile Corporation" means the National Textile</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Corporation Limited formed and registered under the Companies Act,</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1956">
          <num>1956.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1956.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>; (1 of 1956.)</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>" notification" means a notification published in the Official</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Gazette;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1956.paragraph-0.list3.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>" owner", when used in relation to a textile undertaking,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>means any person or firm who or which is, immediately before the  appointed day, the immediate proprietor or lessee or occupier of the  textile undertaking or any part thereof, and in the case of a textile  company which is being wound Lip or the business whereof is being  carried' on by a liquidator or receiver, includes such liquidator or  receiver, and also includes any agent or manager of such owner but  does not include any person or body of persons authorised under the</p>
              <p>Textile Undertakings (Taking Over of Management) Act, 1983 (40 of</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1983">
          <num>1983.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1983.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>) or under the Laxmirattan and Atherton West Cotton Mills (Taking</p>
              <blockList id="section-1983.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Over of Management) Act, 1976 (98 of 1976.) to take over the  management of the whole or any part of the textile undertaking;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1983.paragraph-0.list2.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>" Prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1983.paragraph-0.list2.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>" specified date" means such date as the Central Government  may, for the purpose of any provision of this Act, by notification,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1983.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>specify; and different dates may be specified for different provision  of this Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1983.paragraph-0.list4.j">
                  <num>(j)</num>
                  <p>" subsidiary textile corporation" means the National Textile</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Corporation (South Maharashtra) Limited, the, National Textile Cor-</p>
              <blockList id="section-1983.paragraph-0.list7">
                <listIntroduction>poration (Uttar Pradesh) Limited or, any other textile corporation  formed by the National Textile Corporation as its subsidiary;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1983.paragraph-0.list7.k">
                  <num>(k)</num>
                  <p>" textile" includes yarn or fabrics made either wholly or  partly of cotton, wool, jute, synthetic and artificial (man- made)</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1983.paragraph-0.list9">
                <listIntroduction>fibres;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1983.paragraph-0.list9.l">
                  <num>(l)</num>
                  <p>" textile company" means a company (being a company a company   a defined in the Companies Act. 1956) (1 of 1956.) specified in  column (3) of the First Schedule as owning the textile undertaking  specified in the corresponding entry in column (2) of that Schedule;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-1983.paragraph-0.list9.m">
                  <num>(m)</num>
                  <p>" textile undertaking" or" the textile undertaking" means an  undertaking specified in column (2) of the First Schedule, the  management of which was before the appointed day, taken over by the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Central. Government under the Textile Undertakings (Taking Over of</p>
              <p>Management) Act, 1983, (40 of 1983.) or is file case may be under the</p>
              <p>Laxmirattan and Atherton West Cotton Mills (Taking Over of Management)</p>
              <p>Act, 1976; (98 of 1976.)</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-1983.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Words and expressions used herein and rot defined but  defined in the Companies Act, 1956, (1 of 1956.) shall have the-</p>
              <p>meanings respectively assigned to them in that Act.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>ACQUISITION AND TRANSFER OF THE TEXTILE UNDERTAKINGS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>ACQUISITION AND TRANSFER OF THE TEXTILE UNDERTAKINGS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Acquisition of rights of owners and vesting of the textile  undertakings.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On the appointed day, the right, title and interest  of the owner in relation to every textile undertaking shall stand  transferred to and shall and shall vest absolutely in, the Central</p>
              <p>Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every textile undertaking which stands vested in the Central</p>
              <p>Government by virtue of sub- section (1) shall immediately after it has  so vested, stand transferred to, and vested in, the National Textile</p>
              <p>Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>General effect of vesting.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The textile undertakings  referred to in section 3 shall be deemed to include all assets,</p>
              <p>rights, lease- holds, powers, authorities and privileges and all  property, movable and immovable, including lands, buildings,</p>
              <p>workshops, stores, instruments machinery and equipment, cash balances,</p>
              <p>cash on hand, reserve funds, investments and book debts pertaining to  the textile undertakings and all other rights and interests, in, or  arising out of, such property as were immediately before the appointed  day in the ownership, possession, power or control of the textile  company in relation to the said undertakings, whether within or  outside India, and all books of account, registers and all other  documents of whatever nature relating thereto and shall also be deemed  to include the liabilities and obligations specified in sub- section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of section 5.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All property as aforesaid which have vested in the Central</p>
              <p>Government under sub- section (1) of section 3 shall, by force of such  vesting, be freed and discharged from any trust, obligation mortgage,</p>
              <p>charge, lien and all other incumbrances affecting it and any  attachment, injunction or decree or order of any court or other  authority restricting, the use of such property in any manner shall  be deemed to have been withdrawn.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where any licence or other instrument in relation to a  textile undertaking had been granted at any time before the appointed  day to the owner by the Central Government or a State Government or  any other authority, the National Textile Corporation shall, on and  from such date, be deemed to be substituted in such licence or other  instrument in place of the owner referred to therein as if such  licence or such other instrument had been granted to it and shall hold  such licence or the textile undertaking specified in such other  instrument for the remainder of the period for which the owner would  have held such licence or the textile undertaking under such other  instrument.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every mortgagee of any property which has vested under this  act in the Central Government and every person holding any charge,</p>
              <p>lien or other interest in, or in relation to, any such property shall  give, within such time and in such manner as may be prescribed. an  intimation to the Commissioner of such mortgage, charge, lien or other  interest.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that the  mortgagee of any property referred to in sub- section (2) or any other  person holding any charge, lien or other interest in, or in relation  to any such property shall be entitled to claim, in accordance with  his rights and interest payment of the mortgage money or other dues,</p>
              <p>in whole</p>
              <p>or in part, out of the amounts specified in relation to such property  in the First Schedule, but no such mortgage, charge, lien or other  interest shall be enforceable against any property which has vested in  the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If, on the appointed day, any suit, appeal or other  proceeding of whatever nature in relation to any property which has  vested in the Central Government under section 3, instituted or  preferred by or against the textile company is pending, the same shall  not abate, be discontinued or be, in any way, prejudicially affected  by reason of the transfer of the textile undertakings or of anything  contained in this act, but the suit, appeal or other proceeding may be  continued, prosecuted or enforced by or against the National Textile</p>
              <p>Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person who, on the date on which the Textile</p>
              <p>Undertakings (Nationalisation) Ordinance, 1995 (Ord. 6 of 1995.) was  promulgated, was in possession of, or had under his custody or  control, the whole or any part of any textile undertaking referred to  in section 3, the management of which could not be taken over by the</p>
              <p>Central Government by reason of any decree, order or injunction of any  court or otherwise, shall deliver forwith the possession of such  undertaking or part and all books of account, registers and all other  documents of whatever nature relating to such undertaking or part to  the Central Government or the National Textile Corporation, as the  case may be, may specify in this behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Owner to be liable for contain prior liabilities.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every  liability, other than the liability specified in sub- section (2), of  the owner of a textile undertaking, in relation to the textile  undertakings in respect of any period prior to the appointed day,</p>
              <p>shall be the liability of such owner and shall be enforceable against  him and not against the Central Government or the National Textile</p>
              <p>Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-5.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Any liability arising in respect of-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>loans advanced by the Central Government, or a State</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Government, or both, to a' textile undertaking (together with   interest due thereon) after the management of such  undertaking had been taken over by the Central Government  under section 3 of the Textile Undertakings (Taking Over of</p>
              <p>Management) Act, 1983, (49 of 1989.) or as the case may be,</p>
              <p>under section 3 of the Laxmirattan and Atherton West Cotton</p>
              <blockList id="section-5.2.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Mills (Taking Over of Management) Act, 1976; (98 of 1976.)</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.2.list6.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>amounts advanced to a textile undertaking after the  management of such undertaking had been taken over by the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Central Government under section 3 of the Textile</p>
              <p>Undertakings (Taking Over of Management) Act, 1983, (40 of</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1983">
          <num>1983.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1983.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>) or as the case may be, under section 3 of the</p>
              <p>Laxmirattan and Atherton West Cotton Mills (Taking Over of   management) Act, 1976, (98 of 1976.) by the National</p>
              <blockList id="section-1983.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Textile Corporation or by a state textile corporation, or by  both, together with interest due thereon;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1983.paragraph-0.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>wages, salaries and other dues of employees of the  textile undertaking, in repsect of any period after the  management of such undertaking had been taken over by the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Central Government,</p>
              <p>shall, on and from the appointed day, be the liability of the Central</p>
              <p>Government and shall be discharged for and on behalf of that</p>
              <p>Government, by the National Textile Corporation as and when repayment  of such</p>
              <p>loans or amounts becomes due or as and when such wages, salaries or  other dues become due and payable.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-1983.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-1983.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1983.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>save as otherwise expressly provided in this section or  in any other section of this, act, no liability, other then  the liability specified in sub- section (2), in relation to a  textile undertaking, in respect of any period prior to the  appointed day, shall be enforceable against the Central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-1983.3.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Government or the National Textile Corporation;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1983.3.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>no award, decree or order of any court, tribunal or other  authority in relation to any textile undertaking, passed  after the appointed day, in respect of any matter, claim or  dispute in relation to any matter not referred to in sub-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>section (2), which arose before that day shall be enforceable  against the Central Government or the National Textile</p>
              <blockList id="section-1983.3.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Corporation;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1983.3.list6.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>no liability of any textile undertaking or any owner  thereof in relation to any textile undertaking before the  appointed day, for the contravention of any provision of law  for the time being in force, shall be enforceable against the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Central Government or the National Textile Corporation;</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Transfer of any textile undertaking or part thereof to a  subsidiary textile Corporation.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The National Textile Corporation  may, by order in writing, transfer any textile undertaking specified  at serial numbers 1 to 13 in the First Schedule or part of any such  textile undertaking to the National Textile Corporation (South</p>
              <p>Maharashtra) Limited and any textile undertaking specified at serial  numbers 14 and 15 in the First Schedule or part of any such textile  undertaking to the National Textile Corporation (Uttar Pradesh)</p>
              <p>Limited, as the case may be, or to any other subsidiary textile  corporation and any such transfer shall be subject to such terms and  conditions as may be, specified in the said order.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The subsidiary textile corporation shall, on and from the  date of such transfer, be deemed to be substituted in the licence or  other instrument referred to in sub- section (3) of section 4 in place  of the National Textile Corporation as if such licence or other  instrument had been granted to the subsidiary textile corporation, and  shall hold such licence or other instrument for the remainder of the  period for which the National Textile Corporation would have held such  licence or other instrument.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On the transfer to a subsidiary textile, corporation of any  textile undertaking or any part thereof, the liabilities of the</p>
              <p>National Textile Corporation, referred to in sub- section (2) of  section 5, shall, in so far as they relate to the textile undertaking  or part thereof so transferred to the subsidiary textile corporation,</p>
              <p>become on and from the date of such transfer, the liabilities of the  subsidiary textile corporation and shall be discharged by the  subsidiary textile corporation as and when any such liability is  required to be discharged.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Save as otherwise expressly provided in this act, references  in this act to the National Textile Corporation shall, in respect of  any textile undertaking or any part thereof which is transferred to a  subsidiary textile corporation, be construed as references to the  subsidiary textile corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Shares to be issued by the National Textile Corporation for  the value of the assets transferred to it by the Central Government.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An amount equal to the value of the assets of a textile  undertaking transferred to, and vested in, the National Textile Cor-</p>
              <p>poration under sub- section (2) of section 3, shall be deemed to be  contribution made by the Central Government to the equity capital of  the National Textile Corporation; and for the contribution so made,</p>
              <p>the National Textile Corporation shall issue (if necessary, after   amending its memorandum and articles of association) to the Central</p>
              <p>Government paid- up shares, in its equity capital, having a face value  equal to the amount specified against the textile undertaking in the  corresponding entry in Column (4) of the First Schedule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where any liability assumed by the Central Government under  this Act, is taken over by the National Textile Corporation under  section 27, the Central Government shall surrender to that Corporation  the shares issued to it under sub- section (1) having the face value  equal to the amount to the extent to which the liability has been so  taken over by the National Textile Corporation and thereupon the share  capital of the National Textile Corporation shall, to the extent of  the face value of the shares so surrendered, stand reduced.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>PAYMENT OF AMOUNTS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PAYMENT OF AMOUNTS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Payment of amount to owners of textile undertakings. The owner  of every textile undertaking shall be given by the Central Government,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>in Cash and in the manner specified in Chapter VI, for the transfer  to, and vesting in, it, under sub- section</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of section 3, of such  textile undertaking and the right, title and interest of the owner in  relation Lo such textile undertaking, an amount equal to the amount  specified against it in the corresponding entry in column (4) of the</p>
              <p>First Schedule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Payment of further amount.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In consideration of the  retrospective operation of the provisions of sections 3, 4' and 5,</p>
              <p>there shall be given, in cash, by the Central Government, to the owner  of every textile undertaking, the management of which was taken over  by the Central Government an amount equal to an amount calculated at  the rate specified in section 5 of the Textile Undertakings (Taking</p>
              <p>Over of Management) Act, 1983, or as the case may be, as specified in  section 5 of the Laxmirattan and Atherton West Cotton Mills (Taking</p>
              <p>Over of Management) Act, 1976 for the period commencing on the  appointed day and ending on the date on which the' Textile</p>
              <p>Undertakings (Nationalisation) Ordinance, 1995 was promulgated. (40 of</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1983">
          <num>1983.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1983.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>, 98 of 1976., Ord. 6 of 1995.)</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-1983.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In addition to the amount referred to in section 8 there  shall be given by the Central Government, in cash, to the owner of  every textile undertaking, simple interest at the rate of four per  cent per annum on the amount specified against such owner in the  corresponding entry in column (4) of he First Schedule for the period  commencing on the appointed day and ending on the date on which  payment of such amount is made by the Central Government to the</p>
              <p>Commissioner.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1983.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The amount representing interest calculated at the rate  specified in subsection (2) shall be given in addition Io the amount  specified in the First Schedule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1983.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that the  liabilities of the owners in relation to the textile undertakings  which</p>
              <p>have vested in the Central Government under section 3 shall be dis-</p>
              <p>charged from the amount referred to in the First Schedule and also  from the amounts determined under sub- sections (1) and (2) in  accordance with the rights and interests of the creditors of the  owner.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>MANAGEMENT, ETC., OF TEXTILE UNDERTAKINGS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-IV.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MANAGEMENT, ETC., OF TEXTILE UNDERTAKINGS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Management, etc. of Textile undertakings. The National</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Textile Corporation or any person which that Corporation may, by order  in writing, specify, shall be entitled to ex- excise the powers of  general superintendence,. direction, control and management of the  affairs and business of a textile undertaking, the right, title and  interest of in owner in relation to which have vested in. that</p>
              <p>Corporation under sub- section (2) of section 3, and do all such things  as the owner of the textile undertaking is authorised to exercise and  do.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Special provision for disposal of assets of the textile  undertakings in certain circumstances. If the National Textile</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Corporation considers It necessary or expedient for the better  management, modernization, restructuring or revival of a textile  undertaking so to do, it may, with the previous sanction of the</p>
              <p>Central Government, transfer, mortgage; sell or otherwise dispose of  any land, plant, machinery or any other assets of any of the textile  undertakings:</p>
              <p>Provided that the proceed of no such transfer, mortgage, sale or  disposal of assets shall be utilized for any purpose other than the  purpose for which the sanction of the Central Government has been ob-</p>
              <p>tained.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Duty of persons in charge of management of textile  undertakings to deliver all assets etc. On the vesting of the  management of a textile undertaking in the National Textile</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Corporation, all persons In charge of the management of such textile  undertaking immediately before such vesting shall be bound to deliver  to the National Textile Corporation all assets, documents In their  custody relating to the textile undertaking.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Accounts. The National Textile Corporation shall maintain  the accounts of the textile undertakings in accordance with the  provisions of the Companies Act, 1956. (1 of 1956.)</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>PROVISIONS RELATING TO EMPLOYEES OF TEXTILE UNDERTAKINGS</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-V.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PROVISIONS RELATING TO EMPLOYEES OF TEXTILE UNDERTAKINGS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Employment of certain employees to continue.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every  person who is a workman within the meaning of the Industrial Disputes</p>
              <p>Act, 1947, (14 of 1947.) and has been, immediately before the  appointed day, in the employment of a textile undertaking shall  become, on and from the appointed day, an employee of the National</p>
              <p>Textile Corporation, and shall hold office or service' in the National</p>
              <p>Textile Corporation with the same rights and privileges as to pension,</p>
              <p>gratuity and</p>
              <p>other matters as would have been admissible to him if the rights in  relation to such textile undertaking had not been transferred to, and  vested in, the National Textile Corporation, and shall continue to do  so unless and until his employment in the National Textile Corporation  is duly terminated or until his remuneration, terms and conditions of  employment are duly altered by the National Textile Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every person who is not a workman within the meaning of the</p>
              <p>Industrial Disputes Act, 1947, (14 of 1947.) and who has been,</p>
              <p>immediately before the appointed day, in the employment of a textile  undertaking shall, in so far as such person is employed in connection  with the textile undertaking which has vested in the National Textile</p>
              <p>Corporation, become, as from appointed day, an employee of the</p>
              <p>National Textile Corporation and shall hold his office or service  therein by the same tenure, at the same remuneration and upon the same  terms and conditions and with the same rights and privileges as to  pension and gratuity and other matters as lie would have held the same  under the textile undertaking if it had not vested in the National</p>
              <p>Textile Corporation and shall continue to do so unless and until his  employment in the National Textile Corporation is duly terminated or  until his remuneration, terms and conditions of employment are duly  altered by the National Textile Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial</p>
              <p>Disputes Act, 1947, (14 of 1947.) or in any other law for the time  being in force, the transfer of the services of any officer or other  employee of a textile undertaking to the National Textile Corporation  shall not entitle such officer or other employee to any compensation  under this Act or any other law for the time being in force and no  such claim shall be entertained by any court, tribunal or other  authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where, under the terms of any contract of service or  otherwise, any person whose services become terminated or whose  services become transferred to the National Textile Corporation by  reason of the provisions of this Act is entitled to any arrears of  salary or wages or any payment for any leave not availed of or other  payment, not being payment by way of gratuity or pension, such person  may, except to the extent such liability has been taken over by the</p>
              <p>Central Government under section 5, enforce his claim against the  owner of the textile undertaking but not against the Central</p>
              <p>Government or the National Textile Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Provident and other funds.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-15.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where the owner of a textile  undertaking has established a provident fund, superannuation, welfare  or other fund' for the benefit of the persons employed in such textile  undertaking the monies relatable to the employees, whose services have  become transferred by or under this Act to the National Textile</p>
              <p>Corporation shall, out of the monies standing, on the appointed day,</p>
              <p>to the credit of such provident fund, superannuation, welfare or other  fund, stand transferred to, and shall vest in, the National Textile</p>
              <p>Corporation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The monies which stand transferred, under sub- section (1),</p>
              <p>to the National Textile Corporation shall be dealt with by that</p>
              <p>Corporation in such manner as maybe prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Transfer of employees to a subsidiary textile corporation.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Where any textile undertaking or any part thereof is transferred under  this Act to a subsidiary textile corporation, every person referred to  in sub- section</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-16.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>and sub- section (2) of section 14 shall, on and  from the date of such transfer, become an employee of the subsidiary  textile corporation, and the provisions of sections 14 and 15 shall  apply to such employee as they apply to an employee of the National</p>
              <p>Textile Corporation as if references in the said sections to the</p>
              <p>National Textile Corporation were references to the subsidiary textile  corporation.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>COMMISSIONERS OF PAYMENTS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VI">
        <num>VI</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-VI.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>COMMISSIONERS OF PAYMENTS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Appointment of Commissioners of Payments.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-17.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>For the  purpose of disbursing the amount payable to the owner of each textile  undertaking, the Central Government shall, by notification in the  official Gazette,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-17.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>appoint such number of persons as it may think fit to  be Commissioners, of Payments; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-17.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>define the local limits within which the Commissioners of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Payments shall exercise the powers conferred, and perform the  duties imposed, on them by or under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may appoint such other persons as if  may think fit to assist the Commissioner and thereupon the</p>
              <p>Commissioner may authorise one or more of such persons also to  exercise all or any of the powers exercisable by him under this Act,</p>
              <p>and, different persons may be authorised to exercise different powers.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person authorised by the Commissioner to exercise any  powers may exercise those powers in the same manner and with the same  effect as if they have been conferred on that person directly by this</p>
              <p>Act and not by way of authorisation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The salaries and allowances of' the Commissioner and other  persons appointed under this section shall be defrayed out of the</p>
              <p>Consolidated Fund of India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>References in this Act to the Commissioner shall, where  more than one Commissioner has been appointed,' be construed as  references, to the Commissioner in relation to the textile undertaking  within the local limits of the jurisdiction specified under clause (b)</p>
              <p>of sub- section (1).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Payment by the Central Government to the Commissioner.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-18.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government shall, within fifty days from the specified  date, pay in cash to the Commissioner, for payment to the owner of a  textile undertaking, an amount equal to the amount specified against  the textile undertaking in the First Schedule and shall also. pay to  the Commissioner such sums as may be due to the owner of a textile  undertaking under sub- sections (1) and (2) of section 9.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In relation to the textile undertakings, the management of  which was taken over by the Central Government under the Textile</p>
              <p>Undertakings (Taking Over of Management) Act, 1983, (40 of 1983.)</p>
              <p>there shall be paid by the Central Government in addition to the  amount referred to in sub- section (1), to the Commissioner, in cash,</p>
              <p>such amount payable under section 5 of that Act as remains unpaid in  relation Lo the period commencing on the date on which such management  was taken over by the Central Government and ending on the appointed  day.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In relation to the textile undertakings, the management of  which was taken over by the Central Government under the Laxmirattan  and Atherton West Cotton Mills (Taking Over or Management) Act, 1976,</p>
              <p>(98 of 1976.) there shall be paid' by the Central Government in  addition to the amount referred to in sub- section (1), to the</p>
              <p>Commissioner, in cash, such amount payable under section 5, of that</p>
              <p>Act as remains unpaid in relation to the period commencing on the date  on which such management was taken over by the Central Government and  ending on the appointed day.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A deposit account shall be opened by the Central Government,</p>
              <p>in favour of the Commissioner, in the Public Account of India, and  every amount paid under this Act to the Commissioner shall be  deposited by him to the credit of the said deposit account in the</p>
              <p>Public Account of India, and thereafter the said deposit account shall  be operated by the Commissioner.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Separate records shall be maintained by the Commissioner in  respect of each textile undertaking in relation to which payments have  been made to him under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Interest accruing on the amounts standing to the credit of  the deposit account referred to in sub- section (4) shall inure to the  benefit of the owners of the textile undertakings.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Certain powers of the National Textile Corporation.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-19.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The</p>
              <p>National Textile Corporation shall be entitled to receive, up to the  specified date, to the exclusion of all other persons, any money due  to the textile undertaking, realised after the appointed day,</p>
              <p>notwithstanding that the realisations pertain to a period prior to the  appointed day.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The National Textile Corporation may make a claim to the</p>
              <p>Commissioner with regard: to every payment made by the Custodian after  the appointed day but before the date on which the Textile</p>
              <p>Undertakings (Nationalisation) Ordinance, 1995 (Ord. 6 of 1995.) was  promulgated for discharging any liability of the owner of textile  undertaking in relation to any period prior to the appointed day, and  every such claim shall have priority, in accordance with the</p>
              <p>Priorities attaching, under this Act, to the matter in relation to  which such liability has been discharged by the Custodian.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Save as otherwise provided in this Act, the liabilities in  relation to a textile undertaking in respect of any period prior to  the appointed day which have not been discharged by the Custodian  shall be the liabilities of the owner of that textile undertaking.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Claim to be made to the Commissioner. Every person having a  claim against the owner of a textile undertaking shall prefer such  claim before the Commissioner within thirty days from the specified  date:</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Provided that if the Commissioner is satisfied that the claimant  was prevented by sufficient cause from preferring the claim within the  said period of thirty days, he may entertain the claim within a  further period of thirty days but not thereafter.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Priority of claims. The claims arising out of the matters  specified in the Second Schedule shall have priorities in accordance  with the following principles, namely:-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-21.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>category I shall have precedence over all other  categories and category II shall have precedence over  category III and so on;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the claims specified in each of the categories, except  category IV, shall rank equally and be paid in full, but if  the amount is insufficient to meet such claims in full, they  shall abate in equal proportions and be paid accordingly;.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the liabilities specified in category IV shall be  discharged, subject to the priorities specified in this  section, in accordance with the terms of the secured loans  and the priority, inter se, of such loans; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-21.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the question of payment of a liability with regard to a  matter specified in a lower category shall arise only if a  surplus is left after meeting all the liabilities specified  in the immediately higher category.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Examination of claims.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-22.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On receipt of the claims under  section 20, the Commissioner shall arrange the claims in the order of  priority specified in the Second Schedule and examine the same in  accordance with the said order.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If, on examination of the claims, the Commissioner is of the  opinion that the amount paid to him under this Act is not sufficient  to meet the liabilities specified in any lower category, the shall not  be required to examine the liabilities in respect of such lower  category.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Admission or rejection of claims.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-23.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>After examining the  claims with reference to the priority set out in the Second Schedule,</p>
              <p>the Commissioner shall fix a certain date on or before which every  claimant shall file the proof of his claim or be excluded from the  benefit of the disbursement made by the Commissioner.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Not less than fourteen days' notice of the date so fixed  shall be given by advertisement in one issue of the daily newspaper in  the English language and one issue of the daily newspaper in the  regional language as the Commissioner may consider suitable, and  every' such notice shall call upon the claimant to file the proof of  his claim with the Commissioner within the time specified in the  advertisement.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every claimant who fails to file the proof of his claim  within the time specified by the Commissioner shall be excluded from  the disbursements made by the Commissioner.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Commissioner shall, after such investigation as may, in  his opinion, be necessary and after giving the owner of the textile  undertaking an opportunity of, refuting the claim and after giving the  claimants a reasonable opportunity of being heard, in writing, admit  or reject the claim in whole or in part.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Commissioner shall have the power to regulate his own  procedure in all matters arising out of the discharge of his functions  including the place or places at which be may hold his sittings and  shall, for the purpose of making any investigation under this Act,</p>
              <p>have the same powers as are vested in a civil court tinder the Code of</p>
              <blockList id="section-23.5.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Civil Procedure, 1908, (5 of 1908.) while trying a suit, in respect  of the following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-23.5.list3.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the summoning and enforcing the attendance of any  witness and examining him on oath;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.5.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the discovery and production of any document or other  material object producible as evidence;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.5.list3.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the reception of evidence on affidavits; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-23.5.list3.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>the issuing of any commission for the examination of  witnesses</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any investigation before the Commissioner shall be deemed to  be a judicial proceeding within the meaning of sections 193 and 228 of  the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860.) and the Commissioner shall be  deemed to be a civil court for the purposes of section 195 and Chapter</p>
              <p>XXVI of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973. (2 of 1974.)</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A claimant who is dissatisfied with the decision of the</p>
              <p>Commissioner may prefer an appeal against the decision to the  principal civil court of original jurisdiction within the local limits  of whose jurisdiction the textile undertaking is situated:</p>
              <p>Provided that where a person who is a Judge of a High Court is  appointed to be the Commissioner, such appeal shall lie to the High</p>
              <p>Court for the State in which the textile undertaking is situated, and  such appeal shall be heard and disposed of by not less than two Judges  of that High Court.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Disbursement of money by the Commissioner to claimants.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>After admitting a claim under this Act, the amount due in respect of  such claim shall be credited by the Commissioner to the relevant fund  or be paid to the person or persons to whom such sums are due and on  such credit or payment the liability of the owner in respect of such  claim shall stand discharged.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Disbursement of amount to the owners.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-25.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If, out of the  monies paid to him in relation to a textile undertaking there is a  balance left after meeting the liabilities as specified in the Second</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-thecommissionershalldisbursesuchbalancetotheownerofsuchtextileundertaking">
      <doc name="thecommissionershalldisbursesuchbalancetotheownerofsuchtextileundertaking">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1995/39/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1995/39"/>
              <FRBRalias value=", the Commissioner shall disburse such balance to the owner of  such textile undertaking."/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1995/39/eng@1995-09-08/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1995/39/eng@1995-09-08"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1995/39/eng@1995-09-08/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1995/39/eng@1995-09-08"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="thecommissionershalldisbursesuchbalancetotheownerofsuchtextileundertaking">
            <subsection id="thecommissionershalldisbursesuchbalancetotheownerofsuchtextileundertaking.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Before making any payment to the owner of any textile under-</p>
                <p>taking under sub- section (1), the Commissioner shall satisfy himself  as to the right of such person to receive the whole or any part of  such amount, and in the event of there being a doubt or dispute as to  the right of the person to receive the whole or any part of the  amount, referred to in sections 8 and 9, the Commissioner shall refer  the matter to the court and make the disbursement accordance with  the decision of that court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thecommissionershalldisbursesuchbalancetotheownerofsuchtextileundertaking.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <p>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that the  entries in column (3) of the First Schedule shall not be deemed to be  conclusive as to the right, title and interest of any person in  relation to any textile undertaking specified in the corresponding  entries in column (2) of the said Schedule and evidence shall be  admissible to establish the right, title and interest of any person in  relation to such textile undertaking.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thecommissionershalldisbursesuchbalancetotheownerofsuchtextileundertaking.4">
              <num>(4)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Where any machinery, equipment or other property in a  textile undertaking has vested in the National Textile Corporation,</p>
                <p>but such machinery, equipment or other property does not belong to the  owner of such textile undertaking, the amount specified in column (4)</p>
                <p>of the First Schedule against such textile undertaking shall, on a  reference made to it by the Commissioner, be apportioned by the court  between the owner of such textile undertaking and the owner of such  machinery, equipment or other property having due regard to the value  of such machinery, equipment or other property on the appointed day.</p>
                <p>Explanation.- In this section," court", in relation to a a textile  undertaking, means the principal civil court of original jurisdiction  within the local limits of whose jurisdiction the textile undertaking  is situated.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <section id="section-26">
              <num>26.</num>
              <heading>Undisbursed or unclaimed amounts to be deposited to the  general reserve account. Any money paid to the Commissioner which  remains undisbursed or unclaimed for a period of three years from the  last day on which the disbursement was made, shall be transferred by  the Commissioner to the general revenue account of the Central</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Government but a claim to any money so transferred may be preferred to  the Central Government by the person entitled to such payment and  shall be dealt with as if such transfer had not been made, the order  if any, for payment of the claim being treated as an order for the  refund of revenue.</p>
                  <p>CHAP</p>
                  <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <chapter id="chapter-VII">
              <num>VII</num>
              <paragraph id="chapter-VII.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-27">
                <num>27.</num>
                <heading>Assumption of liability.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-27.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Where any liability of the owner  of a textile undertaking arising out of any item specified in  category I of the Second Schedule is not discharged fully by the</p>
                    <p>Commissioner out of the amount paid to him under this Act, the</p>
                    <p>Commissioner shall intimate in writing to the Central Government the  extent of the liability which remains undischarged, and that liability  shall be assumed by the Central Government.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-27.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Central Government may, by order, direct the National</p>
                    <p>Textile Corporation to take over any liability assumed by that Govern-</p>
                    <p>ment under sub- section (1), and on receipt of such direction, it shall  be the duty of the National Textile Corporation to discharge such  liability.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-28">
                <num>28.</num>
                <heading>Management to continue to vest in the Custodian until  alternative arrangements are made. Notwithstanding the vesting, under  this Act, of a textile undertaking in the National Textile</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-28.paragraph-0.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>Corporation,-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-28.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <blockList id="section-28.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0">
                          <listIntroduction>the Custodian who has been managing the affairs of such  undertaking before the date on which the Textile Undertakings</listIntroduction>
                          <item id="section-28.paragraph-0.list1.a.list0.Nationalisation">
                            <num>(Nationalisation)</num>
                            <p>Ordinance, 1995 (Ord. 6 of 1995.) was  promulgated shall, until alternative arrangements have been  made by the National Textile Corporation, continue to manage  the affairs of such undertakings as if the Custodian had been  authorised by the National Textile Corporation to manage the  affairs of such undertaking; and</p>
                          </item>
                        </blockList>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-28.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>the Custodian or any person authorised by him for this  purpose shall until alternative arrangements have been made  by the National Textile Corporation, continue to be  authorised to operate, in relation to the textile  undertaking, any account of such undertaking in a bank as if  such Custodian or the person authorised by the Custodian had  been authorised by the National Textile Corporation to  operate such account.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-29">
                <num>29.</num>
                <heading>Act to override all other enactments. The provisions of this</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-29.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Act, shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith  contained in any other law for the time being in force or in any  instrument having effect by virtue of any law other than this Act or  in any decree or order of any court, tribunal or authority.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-30">
                <num>30.</num>
                <heading>Contracts to cease to have effect unless ratified by the</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-30.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>National Textile Corporation.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-30.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every contract entered into by the  owner or occupier of any textile undertaking for any service, sale or  supply and in force immediately before the appointed day shall, on and  from the expiry of one hundred and twenty days from the date on which  the Textile Undertakings (Nationalisation) Ordinance, 1995 (Ord. 6 of</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-1995">
                <num>1995.</num>
                <heading/>
                <paragraph id="section-1995.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>) was promulgated, cease to have effect unless such contract is  before the expiry of that period, ratified, in writing, by the</p>
                    <p>National Textile Corporation and in ratifying such contract the</p>
                    <p>National Textile Corporation may make such alterations or  modifications therein as it may think fit:</p>
                    <p>Provided that the National Textile Corporation shall not omit to  ratify a contract, and shall not make may alteration or modification  in a contract, unless it is satisfied that such contract is unduly  onerous or has been entered into in bad faith or is detrimental to the  interests of the textile undertaking.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-1995.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The National Textile Corporation shall not omit to ratify a  contract or make any alteration or modification therein except after  giving to the parties to the contract a reasonable opportunity of  being hear and except after recording in writing its reasons for  refusal to ratify the contract or for making any alteration or  modification therein.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-31">
                <num>31.</num>
                <heading>Penalties. Any person who,-</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-31.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-31.paragraph-0.list0">
                      <item id="section-31.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>having in his possession, custody or control any  property forming part of a textile undertaking, wrongfully  withholds such property from the Central Government or the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-31.paragraph-0.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>National Textile Corporation, or any person authorised by  that Government or Corporation, as the case may be, in this  behalf, or</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-31.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>wrongfully obtains possession of, or retains, any property  forming part of the textile undertaking or wilfully withholds  or fails to furnish to the Central Government, the National</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Textile Corporation</p>
                    <p>or any person specified by that Government, or Corporation,</p>
                    <p>as the case may be, any document relating to such textile  undertaking which may be in his possession, custody or  control or fails to deliver to the National Textile</p>
                    <blockList id="section-31.paragraph-0.list7">
                      <listIntroduction>Corporation or any person specified by that Corporation any  assets, books of account, registers or other documents, in  his custody relating to the textile undertaking, or</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-31.paragraph-0.list7.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>wrongfully removes or destroys any property forming  part of any textile undertaking or prefers any claim under  this Act which he knows or has reasonable cause to believe to  be false or grossly inaccurate,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to  two years, or with fine which may extend to ten thousand rupees, or  with both.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-32">
                <num>32.</num>
                <heading>Offences by companies.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-32.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Where an offence under this Act  has been committed by a company, every person who at the time the  offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible to, the  company for, the conduct of the business of the company as well as the  company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be  liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:</p>
                    <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render  any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the  offence was committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised  all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-32.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where  any offence under this Act has been committed by a company and- it is  proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or  connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of any  director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such  director, manager, secretary or other officer shall be deemed to be  guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and  punished accordingly.</p>
                    <blockList id="section-32.2.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-32.2.list2.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm  or other association of individuals; and</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-32.2.list2.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner in  the firm.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-33">
                <num>33.</num>
                <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit,</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-33.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central</p>
                    <p>Government or any officer of that Government or the Custodian or the</p>
                    <p>National Textile Corporation or any subsidiary textile corporation or  any officer or other person authorised by either of such Corporations  for anything which is in good, faith done or intended to be done under  this Act.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-34">
                <num>34.</num>
                <heading>Textile companies not to be wound up by the Court. No  proceeding for the winding up of a textile company, the right, title  and interest in relation to the textile undertaking owned by which  have vested in the National Textile Corporation under this Act or for  the appointment of a receiver in respect of the business of the  textile undertaking shall lie or be proceeded with in any court except  with consent of the Central Government.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-35">
                <num>35.</num>
                <heading>Delegation of powers.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-35.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Central Government may, by  notification, direct that all or any of the powers exercisable by it  under this Act, other than the power under section 36, may also be  exercised by any person or persons as may be specified in the  notification.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Whenever any delegation of power is made under sub- section</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-35.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>, the person to whom such power has been delegated shall act under  the direction, control and supervision of the Central Government.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-36">
                <num>36.</num>
                <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-36.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Central Government may, by  notification. make rules to carry out the provisions of this Act.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-36.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-36.2.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of  the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-36.2.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>the time within which and the manner in which an  intimation referred to in subsection (4) of section 4 shall  be given;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-36.2.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>the manner in which monies in any provident or other fund  referred to in section 15 shall be dealt with;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-36.2.list1.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>any other matter which is required to be, or may be,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>prescribed.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-36.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act  shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made before each House of</p>
                    <p>Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days  which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive  sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately  following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both</p>
                    <p>Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both, Houses  agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have  effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may  be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be  without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done tinder  that rule.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-37">
                <num>37.</num>
                <heading>Power to remove difficulties.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-37.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>If any difficulty arises  in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government  may, by order not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, remove  the difficulty:</p>
                    <blockList id="section-37.1.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a  period of two years from the date on which Textile Undertakings</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-37.1.list2.Nationalisation">
                        <num>(Nationalisation)</num>
                        <p>Ordinance, 1995 (Ord. 6 of 1995.) was promulgated.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-37.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every order made under this section shall, as soon as may be  after it is made, be laid beore each House of Parliament.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-38">
                <num>38.</num>
                <heading>Repeal and saving.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-38.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-38.1.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>The Textile Undertakings</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-38.1.list1.Nationalisation">
                        <num>(Nationalisation)</num>
                        <p>Ordinance, 1995, (Ord. 6 of 1995.) is hereby  repealed.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-38.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done' Or any action  taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or  taken under the corresponding provisions, of this Act,</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
            </chapter>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
