<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1963/22/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1963/22"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Export (Quality Control And Inspection) Act, 1963"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1963/22/eng@1963-08-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1963/22/eng@1963-08-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1963-08-24" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1963/22/eng@1963-08-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1963/22/eng@1963-08-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Export (Quality Control And Inspection) Act, 1963</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 22 OF 1963</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 24th August, 1963.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fourteenth Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the sound development of the export trade of</p>
        <p>India through quality control and inspection and for matters connected  therewith.</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:--</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be  called the Export (Quality Control and Inspection) Act, 1963.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date  as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>" adjudicating authority" means the authority  specified in, or under, section 10K;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a.list0.ab">
                    <num>(ab)</num>
                    <p>" Appellate authority" means the Appellate authority  referred to in section 10M;]</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a.list0.ac">
                    <num>(ac)</num>
                    <p>]" Council" means the Export Inspection Council  established under section 3;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" export", with its grammatical variations and cognate  expressions, means taking out of India to a place  outside India;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>" inspection", in relation to a commodity, means the  process of determining whether a batch of goods in that  commodity complies with the standard specifications  applicable to it or any other specifications stipulated  in the export contract generally by inspecting either  the whole batch or a selected sample or samples which  purport to represent the whole batch;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>" notified commodity" means any commodity notified under  clause (a) of section 6;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>Act;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>" quality control" means any activity having for its  object the determination of the quality of a commodity</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>(whether during the process of manufacture or  production or</p>
            <p>subsequently) in order to ascertain whether it  satisfies the standard specifications applicable to it  or any other specifications stipulated in the export  contract and whether it may be accepted for purposes of  export.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Establishment of Export Inspection Council.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, establish,</p>
            <p>with effect from such date as may be specified in the notification, a</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Council to be known as the Export Inspection Council, which shall  consist of--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list4.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>a Chairman to be appointed by the Central Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the Director of Inspection and Quality Control, ex  officio, who shall be the Secretary;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list4.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the Honorary Adviser on Standardization to the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Government of India and Director of Indian Standards</p>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list7">
              <listIntroduction>Institution, ex officio;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list7.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the Agricultural Marketing Adviser to the Government of</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list9">
              <listIntroduction>India, ex officio;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list9.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the Director- General of Commercial Intelligence and</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list11">
              <listIntroduction>Statistics, ex officio;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list11.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>fifteen] other members nominated by the Central</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Government three of whom shall be persons representing  the agencies referred to in section 7.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Council shall be a body corporate by the name aforesaid,</p>
            <p>having perpetual succession and a common seal, with power to acquire,</p>
            <p>hold and dispose of property and to contract, and shall by the said  name sue and be sued.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The term of office of, and the manner of filling casual  vacancies among, the members of the Council referred to in clauses (a)</p>
            <p>and (f) of sub- section (1) and the travelling and daily allowances  payable to the members of the Council and the procedure to be followed  in the discharge of its functions by the Council shall be such as may  be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No act or proceeding of the Council shall be invalidated  merely by reason of any vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution  of, the Council.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to such rules as may be made by the Central</p>
            <p>Government in this behalf, the Council may appoint such officers and  other employees as it considers necessary for the purpose of  discharging its functions under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Director of Inspection and Quality Control. The Central</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Government shall appoint a Director of Inspection and Quality Control  to exercise such powers and perform such duties under this Act as may  be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Functions of the Conncil.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The functions of the Council  shall generally be to advise the Central Government regarding measures  for the enforcement of quality control and inspection in relation to  commodities intended for export and to draw up programmes therefor, to  make, with the concurrence of the Central Government, grants- in- aid to  the agencies established or recognised under section 7 and to perform  such other functions as may be assigned to it by or under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of performing its functions, the Council may  co- opt as members such number of persons as it thinks fit who have  special knowledge and practical experience in matters relating to any  commodity or trade therein and any such person shall have the right to  take part in the discussions of the Council but shall not have the  right to vote and shall not be a member for any other purpose.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Council may also constitute specialist committees for  conducting investigations on special problems connected with its  functions.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the performance of its functions under this Act, the</p>
            <p>Council shall be bound by such directions as the Central Government  may give to it in writing from time to time.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Powers of the Central Government in regard to quality control  and inspection. If the Central Government, after consulting the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-6.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Council, is of opinion that it is necessary or expedient so to do for  the development of the export trade of India, it may, by order  published in the Official Gazette,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>notify commodities which shall be subject to quality  control or inspection or both prior to export;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>specify the type of quality control or inspection which  will be applied to a notified commodity;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>establish, adopt or recognise one or more standard  specifications for a notified commodity;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>prohibit the export in the course of international trade  of a notified commodity unless it is accompanied by a  certificate issued under section 7 that the commodity  satisfies the conditions relating to quality control or  inspection, or it has affixed or applied to it a mark  or seal recognised by the Central Government as  indicating that it conforms to the standard  specifications applicable to it under clause (c).</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Machinery for quality control and inspections.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, establish, or  recognise subject to such conditions as it may deem fit, agencies for  quality control or inspection or both:</p>
            <p>Provided that if the Central Government is of opinion that any  recognition granted to any agency under this sub- section should, in  the public interest, be withdrawn, the Central Government may, after  giving a reasonable opportunity to that agency to make representations  in the matter, withdraw, by like notification, the recognition granted  to it.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any agency referred to in sub- section (1) may, on application  made to it or otherwise, hold or cause to be held such examination as  it thinks fit relating to quality control or inspection of notified  commodities, either at the time of export or earlier, in such testing  houses or by such surveyors or samplers as are approved by the Central</p>
            <p>Government in this behalf and may charge such fees as may be  prescribed for the purpose of such examination.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If, after the examination, the agency is of opinion that the  commodity satisfies the standard specifications laid down in respect  of it under section 6 or, as the case may be, any other specifications  stipulated in the export contract, it may issue a certificate that the  commodity satisfies the conditions relating to quality control and  inspection.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3A">
          <num>(3A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the agency has reason to believe that a certificate  issued under sub- section (3) has been obtained fraudulently or by  misrepresentation, or the commodity in relation to which the  certificate is issued has been changed or has deteriorated in quality,</p>
            <p>the agency may, by order amend, suspend or cancel the certificate in  such manner and subject to such procedure as may be prescribed:</p>
            <p>Provided that before amending, suspending or cancelling any such  certificate the holder thereof shall be given a reasonable opportunity  of being heard.];</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person aggrieved by the refusal of any agency referred to  in sub- section (1) to issue a certificate , or by the amendment,</p>
            <p>suspension or cancellation of a certificate under sub- section (3A),]</p>
            <p>may prefer an appeal within such time as may be prescribed to such  authority as the Central Government may, by notification in the</p>
            <p>Official Gazette, constitute for the purpose of hearing appeals.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (6), the decision of  the agency where no appeal is filed, and the decision of the appellate  authority where an appeal is filed, shall be final and shall not be  questioned in any court of law.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, at any time, call for and examine  the record of any proceeding relating to any decision of an agency or  appellate authority under this section for the purpose of satisfying  itself as to the legality or propriety of such decision and may pass  such order thereon as it thinks fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Power to recognise or establish marks to denote conformity  with standard specifications.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, recognise or establish any mark  or seal in relation to a notified commodity for the purpose of  denoting that such commodity conforms to a standard specification  applicable to it.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any such mark or seal affixed or applied to a notified  commodity or to any covering containing, or label attached to, such  commodity shall be deemed to be evidence of the commodity being in  conformity with the standard specifications applicable to it under  this Act:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing in this sub- section shall prevent any  officer of customs from examining any consignment of a notified  commodity intended for export if he has reason to believe that the  seal or mark is not genuine or has been affixed or applied  fraudulently or if such an examination is necessary for the purpose of  any other law for the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Power to obtain information from exporters, etc. The Central</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Government or any officer or authority authorised by it in this behalf  may, by notice published in the Official Gazette, require--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>persons manufacturing, dealing in or exporting notified  commodities; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-9.paragraph-0.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>such other persons as may be prescribed,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>to furnish any information, return or report which the Central</p>
            <p>Government or such officer or authority may consider necessary for  carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Finance, accounts and audit.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of enabling  the Council to discharge its functions under this Act, the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in  this behalf, pay to the Council such sums of money as that Government  considers necessary by way of grants, loans or otherwise.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purpose of discharging its functions under this Act,</p>
            <p>the Council may receive grants or donations from bodies and  institutions approved by the Central Government in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Council shall have its own fund to which shall be  credited the sums of money referred to in sub- sections (1) and (2) and  the moneys in the fund shall be applied for--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>meeting the pay and allowances of the officers and other  employees of the Council and other administrative  expenses of the Council;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>carrying out the functions of the Council under this</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Council shall prepare, before the commencement of each  financial year, a statement of programme of its activities during that  year as well as a financial estimate in respect thereof.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A statement prepared under sub- section (4) shall, not later  than three months before the commencement of each financial year, be  submitted for approval to the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Council shall maintain such accounts and prepare the  balance- sheet in such form as may, in consultation with the</p>
            <p>Comptroller and Auditor- General of India, be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The accounts of the Council shall be audited in such manner  and at such times as may, in consultation with the Comptroller and</p>
            <p>Auditor- General of India, be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10A">
        <num>10A.</num>
        <heading>Power to enter and inspect. The Director of Inspection  and Quality Control or any officer of the Central Government  authorised by him in writing in this behalf (hereinafter referred to   as the" authorised officer") may enter at any reasonable time, any  premises in which--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10A.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-10A.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any commodity which has been changed after inspection by  any agency, referred to in sub- section (1) of section 7; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10A.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any books of account or other documents or things which,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>in his opinion, will be useful for, or relevant to, any  proceeding under this Act,</p>
            <p>are suspected to have been kept or concealed, and inspect such  commodity, books of account, other documents or things and may take  such notes or extracts from such books of account or other documents  as he may think fit.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10B">
        <num>10B.</num>
        <heading>Power to search. If the authorised officer has any reason to  believe that--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10B.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10B.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-10B.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any commodity which has been changed after inspection by  any agency referred to in sub- section (1), of section 7; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10B.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any books of account or other documents or things which,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>in his opinion, will be useful for, or relevant to, any  proceeding under this Act,</p>
            <p>are secreted in any place, he may enter into and search such place or  premises for such commodity, books of account, other documents or  fsthings.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10C">
        <num>10C.</num>
        <heading>Power to seize commodities, etc.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10C.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the authorised  officer has any reason to believe that any commodity is liable to  confiscation under this Act, he may seize such commodity together with  the package, covering or receptacle, if any, in which such commodity  is found and where such commodity is found to have been mixed with any  other goods or materials, he may seize such commodity together with  the goods or materials with which it is so mixed:</p>
            <p>Provided that where it is not practicable to seize any such  commodity, the authorised officer may serve on the owner of the  commodity an order that he shall not remove, part with, or otherwise  deal with, the commodity except with the previous permission of such  authorised officer.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10C.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where any commodity is seized under sub- section (1) and no  notice in respect thereof is given under section 10L within six months  of the seizure of such commodity, it shall be returned to the person  from whose possession it was seized:</p>
            <p>Provided that the aforesaid period of six months may, on  sufficient cause being shown, be extended by the Director of</p>
            <p>Inspection and Quality Control by a further period not exceeding six  months.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10C.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The authorised officer may seize any documents or things  which, in his opinion, will be useful for, or relevant to, any  proceeding under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10C.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The person from whose custody any documents are seized under  sub- section (3) shall be entitled to make copies thereof or take  extracts therefrom in the presence of the authorised officer.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10C.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person legally entitled to the documents or things  seized under sub- section (3) objects, for any reason, to the retention  by the authorised officer of the documents or things, he may make an  application to the Central Government stating therein the reasons for  such objection and requesting for the return of the documents or  things.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10C.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On receipt of an application under sub- section (5), the</p>
            <p>Central Government may, after giving the applicant an opportunity of  being heard, pass such order as it may think fit.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10C.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10C.7.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where any document--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10C.7.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>is produced or furnished by any person or has been  seized from the custody or control of any person under this Act  or any other law for the time being in force; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10C.7.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>has been received from any place outside India (duly  authenticated by such authority or person and in such manner as   may be prescribed) in the course of the investigation of any  offence alleged to have been committed by any person against this</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Act,</p>
            <p>and such document is tendered in evidence against the person by whom  it is produced or from whom it was seized or against such person and  any other person who is jointly tried, or proceeded against, with him,</p>
            <p>the court, or, as the case may be, the adjudicating authority shall,</p>
            <blockList id="section-10C.7.list6">
              <listIntroduction>notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any other law  for the time being in force,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10C.7.list6.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>presume, unless the contrary is proved, that the signature  and every other part of such document which purports to be in the  handwriting of any particular person or which the court or the  adjudicating authority may reasonably assume to have been signed by,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-10C.7.list8">
              <listIntroduction>or to be in the handwriting of, any particular person, is under that  person' s handwriting, and, in the case of a document executed or  attested, it was executed or attested by the person by whom it  purports to have been so executed or attested;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10C.7.list8.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>admit the document in evidence notwithstanding that it is  not duly stamped, if such document is otherwise admissible in  evidence.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10D">
        <num>10D.</num>
        <heading>Power to stop and seize conveyances. Any authorise officer  may, if he has any reason to suspect that any conveyance or animal is  being, or is about to be, used for the transportation of any commodity  which is liable to confiscation under this Act and that by such  transportation any provision of this Act has been, is being, or is  about to be, contravened, at any time, stop such conveyance or animal  or, in the case of an aircraft, compel it to land, and</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10D.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10D.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-10D.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>rummage and search the conveyance or any part thereof,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10D.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>examine and search any goods or materials in the  conveyance or on the animal,</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10D.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>if it becomes necessary to stop any conveyance or  animal, he may use all lawful means for stopping it and  where such means fail, the conveyance or animal may be  fired upon,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>and where he is satisfied that it is necessary so to do to prevent the  contravention of any provision of this Act, he may seize such  conveyance or animal.</p>
            <p>Explanation.-- Any reference in this section to a conveyance  shall, unless the context otherwise requires, be construed as  including a reference to an aircraft, vehicle or vessel.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10E">
        <num>10E.</num>
        <heading>Search and seizure to be made in accordance with the Code of</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10E.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Criminal Procedure 1973. The provisions of the Code of Criminal</p>
            <p>Procedure, 1973, relating to searches and seizures shall, so far as  may be, apply to every search or seizure made under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10F">
        <num>10F.</num>
        <heading>Confiscation. Any commodity in respect of which--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10F.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10F.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-10F.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>a certificate has been obtained from an agency referred  to in sub- section (1) of section 7 fraudulently or by  misrepresentation, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10F.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any provision of this Act has been, is being, or is  attempted to be, contravened,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall, together with any package, covering or receptacle in which such  commodity is found, be liable to confiscation and, where such  commodity is so mixed with any other goods or materials that it cannot  be readily separated, such other goods or materials shall also be  liable to confiscation:</p>
            <p>Provided that where it is established to the satisfaction of the  adjudicating authority that any commodity, which is liable to  confiscation under this Act, belongs to a person other than the person  who has, by any act or omission, rendered it liable to confiscation,</p>
            <p>and such act or omission was without the knowledge or connivance of  the person to whom it belongs, such commodity shall not be ordered to  be confiscated; but such other action as is authorised by this Act may  be taken against the person who has, by such act or omission, rendered  such commodity liable to confiscation.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10G">
        <num>10G.</num>
        <heading>Confiscation of conveyance. Any conveyance or animal which  has been, is being, or is attempted to be, used for the transport of  any commodity which is liable to confiscation under this Act, shall be  liable to confiscation unless the owner of the conveyance or animal  proves that it was, is being, or is about to be, so used without the  knowledge or connivance of the owner himself, his agent, if any, and  the person in charge of the conveyance or animal and that each of them  had taken all reasonable precautions against such use:</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10G.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Provided that in the case of a conveyance or animal used for the  transport of goods or passengers for hire, the owner of the conveyance  or animal shall be given an option to pay, in lieu of confiscation of  the conveyance of animal, a fine not exceeding the value of the  commodity which has been, is being, or is attempted to be, transported  by such conveyance or animal.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10H">
        <num>10H.</num>
        <heading>Option to pay fine in lieu of confiscation. Whenever  confiscation of any commodity is authorised by this Act, the officer  adjudging it shall, without prejudice to the provisions of the proviso  to section 10G, give to the owner of the commodity an option to pay in  lieu of confiscation such fine not exceeding the value of the  commodity.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10I">
        <num>10I.</num>
        <heading>Liability to penalty. Any person,--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10I.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-10I.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>who, in relation to any commodity, does or omits to do  any act which act or omission would render such commodity liable  to confiscation under this Act, or abets the doing or omission of  such an act; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10I.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>who acquires possession of or is in any way concerned in  carrying, removing, depositing, keeping, concealing, selling or  purchasing, or in any manner dealing with, any commodity which he  knows or has reason to believe is liable to confiscation under  this Act,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall be liable to a penalty not exceeding five times the value of the  commodity or five thousand rupees, whichever is more, whether or not  such commodity has been confiscated or is available for confiscation.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10J">
        <num>10J.</num>
        <heading>Confiscation or penalty not to interfere with other  punishments. No confiscation made or penalty imposed under the  foregoing provisions of this Act shall prevent the infliction of any  other punishment to which the person affected thereby is liable under  the provisions of this Act or under any other law for the time being  in force.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10K">
        <num>10K.</num>
        <heading>Adjudication Any confiscation may be adjudged or penalty,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10K.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>may be imposed under this Act by the Director of Inspection and</p>
            <p>Quality Control, or, where he so directs, by a general or special  order, by any officer subordinate to him.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10L">
        <num>10L.</num>
        <heading>Giving of opportunity to the owner of goods, etc. No order  of adjudication of confiscation or imposing a penalty shall be made  unless the owner of the commodity, conveyance or animal or other  person concerned, is given a notice in writing--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10L.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10L.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-10L.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>informing him of the grounds on which it is proposed to  confiscate such commodity, conveyance or animal or to impose a  penalty;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10L.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>giving him a reasonable opportunity of making a  representation in writing within such reasonable time as may be  specified in the notice against the confiscation or imposition of  penalty mentioned therein, and, if he so desires, of being heard  in the matter.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10M">
        <num>10M.</num>
        <heading>Appeal.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10M.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10M.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Any person aggrieved by any decision or order  made under this Act may prefer an appeal,--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10M.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>Where the decision or order has been made by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Director of Inspection and Quality Control, to the Central</p>
            <blockList id="section-10M.1.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Government;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10M.1.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>where the decision or order has been made by any officer  subordinate to the Director of Inspection and Quality Control, to  the Director of Inspection and Quality Control,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>within a period of forty- five days from the date on which the decision  or order is served on such person:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Appellate authority may, if it is satisfied  that the appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from preferring  the appeal within the aforesaid period of forty- five days, allow such  appeal to be preferred within a further period of forty- five days:</p>
            <p>Provided further that in the case of an appeal against an order  imposing a penalty, no such appeal shall be entertained unless the  amount of the penalty has been deposited by the appellant:</p>
            <p>Provided also that where the Appellate authority is of the  opinion that the deposit to be made will cause undue hardship to the  appellant, it may, at its discretion, dispense with such deposit  either unconditionally or subject to such conditions as it may impose.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10M.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Appellate authority may, after giving to the appellant a  reasonable opportunity of being heard, if he so desires, and after  making such further inquiries, if any, as it may consider necessary,</p>
            <p>pass such orders as it thinks fit, confirming, modifying or reversing  the decision or order appealed against, or may send back the case,</p>
            <p>with such directions as it may think fit, for a fresh adjudication or  decision, as the case may be, after taking additional evidence, if  necessary:</p>
            <p>Provided that an order enhancing or imposing a penalty or  confiscating commodity of a greater value shall not be made under this  section unless the appellant has had an opportunity of making a  representation and, if he so desires, of being heard, in his defence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10N">
        <num>10N.</num>
        <heading>Powers of revision. The Central Government may, on its own  motion or otherwise, call for and examine the records of any  proceeding in which an order of adjudication of confiscation or  imposing any penalty has been made by any officer under this Act and  against which no appeal has been preferred, for the purpose of  satisfying itself as to the correctness, legality or propriety of such  order or decision and pass such orders thereon as it may think fit:</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10N.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10N.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that no decision or order shall be varied under this  section so as to prejudicially affect any person unless such person--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10N.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>has, within a period of two years from the date of such  decision or order, received a notice to show cause why such  decision or order shall not be varied, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10N.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>has been given a reasonable opportunity of making a  representation and, if he so desires, of being heard in his  defence.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10O">
        <num>10O.</num>
        <heading>Powers of adjudicating and other authorities.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10O.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10O.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Every  authority making any adjudication or hearing any appeal or exercising  any powers of revision under this Act shall have all the powers of a  civil court under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908, while trying a  suit, in respect of the following matters, namely:--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10O.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>summoning and enforcing the attendance of witnesses;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10O.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>requiring the discovery and production of any document;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10O.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>requisitioning any public record or copy thereof from  any court or office;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10O.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>receiving evidence on affidavits; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10O.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses or  documents.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10O.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every authority making any adjudication or hearing any appeal  or exercising any powers of revision under this Act shall be deemed to  be a Civil Court for the purposes of sections 345 and 346 of the Code  of Criminal Procedure, 1973.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10O.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every authority making any adjudication or hearing any appeal  or exercising any powers of revision under this Act shall have the  power to make such orders of an interim nature as it may think fit and  may also, for sufficient cause, order the stay of operation of any  decision or order.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10P">
        <num>10P.</num>
        <heading>Continuance of proceedings in the event of death or  insolvency.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10P.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10P.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where a penalty has been imposed by the adjudicating  authority and--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10P.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>no appeal against the order imposing such penalty has  been preferred to the Appellate authority and the person entitled  to file such appeal dies or is adjudicated an insolvent before  the expiry of the period within which the appeal can be  preferred; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10P.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>an appeal has been preferred to the Appellate authority  against the order imposing such penalty but the appellant dies or  is adjudicated an insolvent during the pendency of the appeal,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>then, it shall be lawful for the legal representatives of such person  or the Official Assignee or the Official Receiver as the case may be,</p>
            <p>to prefer an appeal to the Appellate authority or as the case may be  to continue the appeal before the Appellate authority in place of such  person and the provisions of section 10M shall so far as may be, apply  or continue to apply to such appeal.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10P.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The powers of the Official Assignee or the Official Receiver  under sub- section (1) shall be exercised by him subject to the  provisions of the Presidency- towns Insolvency Act, 1909, or the</p>
            <p>Provincial Insolvency Act, 1909, or the Provincial Insolvency Act,</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1920">
        <num>1920.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-1920.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>, as the case may be.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Penalty.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-11.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If any person contravenes any order under clause</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-11.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>of section 6, or fraudulently obtains a certificate under section</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading/>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>, or fraudulently affixes or applies any such mark or seal as is  referred to in sub- section (1) of section 8, he shall, on conviction,</p>
            <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list2">
              <listIntroduction>be punishable--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list2.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>for the first offence, with imprisonment for a term  which may extend to two years, or with fine which may  extend to five thousand rupees, or with both;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list2.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>for the second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment  for a term which may extend to  three years] and also  with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees and  in the absence of special and adequate reasons to be  mentioned in the judgment of the court, such  imprisonment shall not be less than three months.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-7.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person who attempts to commit or abets the commission of  an offence punishable under sub- section (1) shall be deemed to have  committed such offence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any person contravenes or attempts to contravene or abets  the contravention of any other provision of this Act or any rules or  orders made thereunder, he shall be punishable with fine which may  extend to one thousand rupees.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11A">
        <num>11A.</num>
        <heading>Penalty for contravention of order made by adjudicating  authority or Appeallate authority. If any person fails to pay the  penalty imposed by the adjudicating or the Appellate authority or  fails to comply with any direction or order made, or deemed to have  been made, under this Act, he shall, on conviction, be punishable with  imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years, or with fine,</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11B">
        <num>11B.</num>
        <heading>Offences by officers and employees of agency, etc.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-11B.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If  any officer or employee of the Council or of any agency referred to in  sub- section (1) of section 7, or any surveyor, sampler or employee of  any testing house, referred to in sub- section (2) of that section  enters into, or acquiesces in, any agreement to do, abstains from  doing, permits, conceals or connives at, any act or thing whereby any  provision of this Act is or may be contravened, he shall, on  conviction, be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may  extend to two years, or with fine which may extend to five thousand  rupees, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11B.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any officer searches or authorises any other officer of  the Central Government to search any place without having reason to  believe that any commodity, books of account or documents or things of  the nature referred to in section 10B are secreted in that place, he  shall, on conviction, be punishable with imprisonment for a term which  may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to one  thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-11B.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any officer or employee of the Council or of any agency  referred to in sub- section (1) of section 7, or any surveyor, sampler  or employee of any testing house, referred to in sub- section (2) of  that section, except in the discharge in good faith of his duty as  such officer or employee or in compliance with any requisition made  under any law for the time being in force discloses any particulars  learnt by him in his official capacity in respect of any commodity, he  shall on conviction be punishable with imprisonment for a term which  may extend to six months or with fine which may extend to one thousand  rupees or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11C">
        <num>11C.</num>
        <heading>Correction of clerical or arithmetical mistakes. Clerical or  arithmetical mistakes in any decision or order, or errors arising  therein from any accidental slip or omission may, at any time, be  corrected by the authority by which the decision or order was made  either on its own motion or on the application of the aggrieved  person:</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11C.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Provided that where any correction proposed to be made under this  section will have the effect of prejudicially affecting any person, no  such correction shall be made except after giving to that person a  reasonable opportunity of making a representation in the matter and no  such correction shall be made after the expiry of a period of two  years from the date on which such decision or order was made.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Offences by companies.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-12.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an offence under this Act  has been committed by a company, every person who, at the time the  offence was committed, was in charge of, and was responsible to, the  company for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as the  company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be  liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render  any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the  offence was committed without his knowledge or that he exercised all  due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-12.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where  an offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is  proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or  connivance of, or is attributable to any negligence on the part of,</p>
            <p>any director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such  director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed</p>
            <p>to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded  against and punished accordingly.</p>
            <blockList id="section-12.2.list4">
              <listIntroduction>Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.2.list4.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" company" means a body corporate and includes a firm or  other association of individuals; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.2.list4.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner in  the firm.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Delegation of powers. The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, direct that any power  exercisable by it under this Act shall, in relation to such matters  and subject to such conditions, if any, as may be specified in the  direction, be exercisable also by--</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-13.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the Council;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-13.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>such officer or authority subordinate to the Central</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Government, or such State Government or such officer or  authority subordinate to a State Government as may be  specified in the direction.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Procedure for prosecution. No prosecution for an offence  punishable under this Act shall be instituted except by or with the  consent of an officer authorised by the Central Government by general  or special order in this behalf.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Officers and employees of agency to be public servants. All  officers and employees of the Council or of any agency established or  recognised under sub- section</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of section 7 and all surveyors,</p>
            <p>samplers and employees of testing houses, referred to in sub- section</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>of that section shall, while acting or purporting to act in  pursuance of the provisions of this Act or any rule or order made  thereunder, be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of  section 21 of the Indian Penal Code. (45 of 1860.)</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-16.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No suit,</p>
            <p>prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Council or  any officer or employee of the Government or the Council or any agency  referred to in sub- section (1) of section 7 for anything which is in  good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any  rule or order made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the</p>
            <p>Government for any damage caused or likely to be caused by anything  which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of  this Act or any rule or order made thereunder.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16A">
        <num>16A.</num>
        <heading>Suspension, etc., of operation of the provisions of the</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16A.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-16A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the Central Government is satisfied that circumstances  exist which render it necessary or expedient so to do in the public  interest, it may, by notification in the Official Gazette, suspend or  relax to a specified extent the operation of all or any of the  provisions of this Act in respect of such notified commodity or  commodities generally or in respect of any area and for such period as  may be specified in the notification.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where the operation of any provision of this Act has, under  sub- section (1), been suspended or relaxed, such suspension or  relaxation may, at any time be removed by the Central Government by a  like notification.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-16A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every notification issued under this section shall be laid,</p>
            <p>as soon as may be after it is issued before each House of Parliament,</p>
            <p>while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be  comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and  if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session  or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the notification or both Houses agree that the  notification should not be issued, the notification shall thereafter  have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case  may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be  without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under  that notification.].</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the  purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-17.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for--</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the travelling and daily allowances payable to members  of the Council, persons co- opted under sub- section (2)</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-17.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>of section 5, and members of specialist committees  referred to in sub- section (3) of that section;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.2.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the functions of the Council and the procedure to be  followed by it;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the appointment of officers and other employees of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-17.2.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Council;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.2.list5.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the procedure to be followed for various types of  quality control and inspection;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list5.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>the conditions which a testing house, surveyor or  sampler should satisfy for purposes of approval by the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-17.2.list7">
              <listIntroduction>Central Government;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.2.list7.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <blockList id="section-17.2.list7.f.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>the fees chargeable for purposes of examination and  issue of certificates under section 7;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-17.2.list7.f.list0.ff">
                    <num>(ff)</num>
                    <p>the manner in which, and the procedure subject to  which, any certificate issued under sub- section (3) of  section 7 shall be amended, suspended or cancelled;];</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list7.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <blockList id="section-17.2.list7.g.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>the filing of appeals under section 7 and the fees  payable therefor;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-17.2.list7.g.list1.gg">
                    <num>(gg)</num>
                    <p>the authority or person by which or by whom, and the  manner in which, any document received from a place  outside India shall be authenticated;];</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list7.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the manner in which the accounts of the Council shall be  maintained and audited;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list7.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>any other matter which is required to be, or may be,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made by the Central Government under this section  shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made before each House of</p>
            <p>Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty days  which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive  sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session  immediately  following the session] or the successive sessions aforesaid, both</p>
            <p>Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses  agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have  effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may  be; so however that any such modification or annulment shall be  without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under  that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Act to override other enactments. As from the date on which a  commodity is notified under clause (a) of section 6, the provisions of  this Act or anything done or any action taken thereunder shall have  effect in relation to that commodity notwithstanding any provisions</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>(relating to quality control and inspection prior to the export of   such commodity) contained in any enactment other than this Act or in  any instrument having effect by virtue of any enactment other than  this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
