<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1890/01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1890/01"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Revenue Recovery Act, 1890"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1890/01/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1890/01/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1890/01/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1890/01/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Revenue Recovery Act, 1890</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Title, extent and commencement. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Revenue Recovery Act, 1890.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of India, except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.</p>
            <p>* * * *.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Definitions. - In this Act unless there is something repugnant in then subject or context,-</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>district includes a presidency-town;</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Collector means the chief officer in charge of the land-revenue administration of a district; and</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>defaulter means a person from whom an arrear of land-revenue, or a sum recoverable as an arrear of land-revenue, is due and includes a person who is responsible as surety for the payment of any such arrear or sum.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Recovery of public demands by enforcement other district of process in than those in which they become payable -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Where an arrear of land-revenue, or a sum recoverable as an arrear of land-revenue, is payable to a Collector by a defaulter being or having property in a district other than that in which the arrear accrued or the sum is payable, the Collector may send to the collector of that other district a certificate in the form as nearly as may be of the schedule stating-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the name of the defaulter and such other particulars as may be necessary for his identification, and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the amount payable by him and the account on which it is due.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The certificate shall be signed by the Collector making it, or by any office to whom such Collector may by order in writing delegate this duty and save as otherwise provided by this Act, shall be conclusive proof of the matters therein stated.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Collector of the other district shall on receiving the certificate proceed to recover the amount stated therein as if it were an arrear of land revenue which had accrued in his own district.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Remedy available to person denying liability to pay amount recovered under last foregoing section. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>when proceedings are taken against a person under the last foregoing section for the recovery of a amount stated in a certificate that person may if he denies his liability to pay the amount or any part thereof and pays the same under protest made in writing at the time of payment and signed by him or his agent institute a suit for the repayment of the amount or the part thereof so paid.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A suit under sub-section (1) must be instituted in a Civil Court having jurisdiction in the local area in which the officer of the Collector who made the certificate is situate, and the suit shall be determined in accordance with the law in force at the place where the arrear accrued or the liability for the payment of the sum a arose.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In the suit the plaintiff may, notwithstanding anything i8n the last foregoing section, but subject to the law in force at the place aforesaid give evidence with respect to any matter stated in the certificate.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This section shall apply if under this Act as in force as part of the law of Pakistan or Burma or under any other similar Act forming part of the law of [Pakistan or Burma, proceeding are taken against a person in Pakistan or Burma as the case may be for the recovery of an amount stated in a certificate made by a Collector in any State to which this Act extends ].</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Recovery by Collector of sums recoverable as arrears of revenue by other public officers or by local authorities. - Where any sum is recoverable as an arrear of land-revenue by any public officer other than a Collector or by any local authority the Collector of the district in which the in which the officer of that officer or authority is situate shall on the request of the officer of authority proceed to recover the sum as if it were an arrear of land revenue which had accrued in his own district and may send a certificate of the amount to be recovered to the Collector of another district under the foregoing provisions of this Act, as if the sum were payable to himself.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Property liable to sale under the Act. -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>When the Collector of a district receives a certificate under this Act he may issue a proclamation prohibiting the transfer or charging of any immovable property belonging to the defaulter in the district.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The collector may at may time by order in writing withdraw the proclamation, and it shall be deemed to be withdrawn when either the amount dated in the certificate has been recovered or the property has been sold for the recovery of that amount.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any private alienation of the property or of any interest of the defaulter therein whether by sale gift mortgage or otherwise, made after the issue of the proclamation and before the withdrawal thereof shall be void as against the [Government ], and any person who may purchase the property at a sale held for the recovery of the amount stated in the certificate.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the foregoing provisions of this section, when proceedings are taken against any immovable property under this Act for the recovery of an amount stated in a certificate the interests of the defaulted alone therein shall be so proceeded against, and no incumbrances created, grants made or contracts entered into by him in good faith shall be rendered invalid by reason only of proceedings being taken against those interests.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A proclamation under this section shall be made by beat of drum or other customary method and by the posting of a copy thereof on a conspicuous place in or near the property to which it relates.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Saving of local laws relating to revenue. - Nothing in the foregoing sections shall be construed-</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7.paragraph-0.list0">
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>to impair any security provided by, or affect the provision of, any other enactment for the time being in force for the recovery of land-revenue, or of sums recoverable as arrears of land-revenue, or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to authorise the arrest of any person for the recovery of any tax payable to the corporation, commissioner committee, board, council or person having authority over a municipality under any enactment for the time being in force.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Recovery in India of certain public demands arising beyond India - When this Act has been applied to any local area which is under the administration of the Central Government * *  but which is not part of India, an arrear of land revenue accruing in that local area, or a sum recoverable as an area of land revenue and payable to a Collector or other public officer or to a local authority in that local area, may be recovered under this Act in India.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Recovery in India of land-revenue, etc., accruing in Burma -</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may direct that an arrear of land revenue accruing in Burma or a sum recoverable in Burma as an arrear of land revenue and payable to a Collector or other public officer or to a local authority in Burma may be recovered under this Act in 3 India and thereupon such arrear or sum shall be so recoverable :</p>
            <p>Provided that the Central Government shall not give any such direction unless it is satisfied that the remedy available under section 4 of this Act in India to a person paying under protest in India an arrear accruing in Burma.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For recovering by virtue of this section any arrears of tax or penalty due under the enactment relating to income-tax or super-tax in force in Burma the Collector shall have such additional powers as he has in the case of Indian income-tax and super-tax under the proviso to section 46(2) of the Indian Income-tax Act, 1922.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Sub-section (1) and (2) shall apply in relation to Pakistan as they apply in relation to Burma.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Duty of Collectors to remit moneys Collected in certain cases - Where a Collector receives a certificate under this Act form a Collector of another [State or a Collector in Pakistan or Burma he shall remit any sum recovered by him by virtue of that certificate to that Collector after deducting his expenses in connection with the matter].</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>THE REVENUE RECOVERY ACT, 1890</p>
            <p>THE SCHEDULE</p>
            <p>CERTIFICATE</p>
            <p>See section 3, sub-section (1)</p>
            <p>From</p>
            <p>THE COLLECTOR OF</p>
            <p>To</p>
            <p>THE COLLECTOR OF</p>
            <p>Dated the of 19</p>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of the Revenue Recovery Act, 1890, the said sum is recoverable by you as if it were an arrear of land revenue which had accrued in your own district and your are hereby desired so to recover it and to remit it to my office at .</p>
            <p>A. B.,</p>
            <p>Collector of</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
