<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1998/24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1998/24"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Andhra Pradesh Industrial Workers (Representations Participation In Management And Relief) Act, 1998"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1998/24/eng@2017-05-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1998/24/eng@2017-05-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-05-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1998/24/eng@2017-05-25/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1998/24/eng@2017-05-25"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-05-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Andhra Pradesh Industrial Workers (Representations Participation In Management And Relief) Act, 1998</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>[Act No. 24 of 1998]</p>
      </longTitle>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 20th June, 1998]</docDate>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <preamble>
      <p>An Act to provide for recognition to Trade Unions with a view to facilitating collective bargaining and provide for participation of workers in management of industrial establishments, protection of works, constitution of Contingency fund to provide relief to the workmen affected by closure of Industrial establishments due to sickness or otherwise and for matters connected therewith and incidental thereto.</p>
      <p>Whereas it is considered expedient to provide statutory recognition to the unions In industrial establishments so as to facilitate collective bargaining and to promote better relations between employees and employer;</p>
      <p>And whereas, it is felt necessary to give effect to the concept of workers participation in the management of industrial establishments enshrined in Article 43-A of the Constitution of India as one of the Directive Principles of State . Policy;</p>
      <p>And whereas, it is considered that promotion of participation of workers in the management would contribute to harmonious industrial relations and serve to protect workers interests in industry;</p>
      <p>And whereas, it is considered essential to constitute an Industrial Workers Contingency Fund to provide relief to workers affected by unauthorised closures. temporary or permanent, of industrial establishment due to sickness or otherwise and to provide for their sustenance;</p>
      <p>Be it enacted by the Legislative Assembly of the State of Andhra Pradesh in the Forty ninth year of the Republic of India, as follows.--</p>
    </preamble>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <heading>Preliminary</heading>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title, extent, application and commencement</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the Andhra Pradesh Industrial Workers (Representation, Participation in Management and Relief) Act, 1998.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall extend to the whole of the State of Andhra Pradesh.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall apply to all industrial establishments and units situated in the State of Andhra Pradesh.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Government, may by notification appoint and they may appoint different dates for different provisions or different chapters.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions</heading>
          <subsection id="section-2.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless, the context otherwise, requires;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>'affected workman' means a workman who has worked for a period of ninety days within a period of one hundred and eighty days preceeding the date of closure of a closed industrial establishment;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>'authority' means the authority appointed under sub-section (1) of Section 23;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>'appellate authority' means the authority appointed under sub-sec. (2) of Section 23;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list1.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>'Board' means the board constituted under Section 42; (v) 'Closed Industrial Establishment' means an establishment wherein cessation or suspension of operation byway of lockout or otherwise, other than an authorised closure under Section 25-0 of the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947. continues for a period of sixty days, and includes lockout continued despite prohibitory orders:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that an industrial establishment in which cessation or suspension of operations take place due to a lockout declared consequent on a strike contrary to the provisions of the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947, shall not be deemed to be a closed industrial establishment for the purposes of this Act;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.1.list3.vi">
                  <num>(vi)</num>
                  <p>'Contingency Fund' means the Andhra Pradesh Industrial workers' Contingency Fund constituted under Section 38;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list3.vii">
                  <num>(vii)</num>
                  <p>'Craft Union' means a union registered under the Trade Unions Act, 1926 but whose activities are restricted to a category of the workmen employed in the industrial establishment; (viii) 'election authority' means the election authority appointed under Section 7 of this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list3.ix">
                  <num>(ix)</num>
                  <p>'employer' means the owner or person having charge of, or ultimate control over the affairs of an industrial establishment and includes the Director, Manager, Agent or any other person managing the affairs of an industrial establishment;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list3.x">
                  <num>(x)</num>
                  <p>'enterprise council' means a council constituted under Section 24, at the level of industrial establishment;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list3.xi">
                  <num>(xi)</num>
                  <p>'factory council' means a council constituted under Section 24 at the level of the Factory ;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list3.xii">
                  <num>(xii)</num>
                  <p>'Government' means the State Government of Andhra Pradesh.;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list3.xiii">
                  <num>(xiii)</num>
                  <p>'Inspector' means an Inspector appointed under Section 55;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list3.xiv">
                  <num>(xiv)</num>
                  <p>'Establishment of Industrial Establishment' means an establishment; and its one or more units in which an industry as defined in clause (j) of Section 2 of the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 is carried on; or any other establishment as the Government may, by notification, declare as such, for the purposes of this Act, but does not include those industries to which the Central Government is the appropriate Government under the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list3.xv">
                  <num>(xv)</num>
                  <p>'notification' means a notification published in the Andhra Pradesh Gazette; and the word 'notified' shall be construed accordingly;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list3.xvi">
                  <num>(xvi)</num>
                  <p>'prescribed' means prescribed by rules made by the Government under this Act; (xvii) 'recognised union' means a union which has been recognised under Chapter II of this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list3.xviii">
                  <num>(xviii)</num>
                  <p>'shop council' means a council constituted under Section 24 of this Act at the shop floor level; (xix) 'union' means a Trade Union registered under the Trade Unions Act, 1926; (Central Act. XVI of 1926).</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list3.xx">
                  <num>(xx)</num>
                  <p>'unit' means a unit of the industrial establishment as determined under Section 5;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.1.list3.xxi">
                  <num>(xxi)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-2.1.list3.xxi.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>'Workman' means any person including an apprentice employed in any industry to do any manual, unskilled, skilled, technical, operational, clerical or supervisory work for hire or reward, whether the terms of employment be express, or implied, but does not include any such persons :</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-2.1.list3.xxi.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>who is subject to the Air Force Act, 1950 or the Army Act, 1950, or the Navy Act, 1957, or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.1.list3.xxi.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>who is employed in the police service or as an officer or employee of a prison; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.1.list3.xxi.list0.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>who is employed mainly in a managerial or administrative capacity; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-2.1.list3.xxi.list0.iv">
                      <num>(iv)</num>
                      <p>who, being employed in a supervisory capacity, draws wages exceeding one thousand six hundred rupees per mensem, or exercises, either by the nature of duties attached to the office, or by reason of the powers vested in him functions mainly of a managerial nature.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The words and expressions used but not defined in this Act shall have the same meaning assigned to them in the -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.2.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>Trade Unions Act, 1926;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.2.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>Industrial Disputes Act, 1947.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <heading>Recognition of Unions</heading>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Levels of recognised unions</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Except in respect of establishments specified in the First Schedule to this Act, the recognised union shall be at the level of an Industrial establishment.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In every establishment specified in the First Schedule to this Act, there shall be a recognised union for the industrial establishment and also a recognised union for each industrial unit thereof.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Power to amend First Schedule</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Government, In consultation with the Chief Election Authority, may by notification add to, alter or amend the First Schedule from time to time.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Determination of industrial units</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The units of an establishment specified in the First Schedule shall be determined by the election authority in consultation with the employers and the unions in such industrial establishment.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An appeal against the decision of the election authority under sub-section (1) shall lie within such time as may be prescribed, to the Chief Election Authority who shall, after giving reasonable opportunity to all concerned, decide such appeal, and whose decision thereon shall be final and binding.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The units determined either under sub-section (1), or under subsection (2) shall not be altered for a period of five years.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Chief Election Authority</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Commissioner of Labour shall be the Chief Election Authority for the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Election Authorities</heading>
          <subsection id="section-7.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chief Election Authority may appoint such number of officers as he considers necessary to be the election authorities for such areas or establishments or units, as the case may be, for the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-7.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The election authority, on such appointment, may appoint such number of persons under their control to assist the election authorities to discharge their duties and perform their functions.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Powers of Election Authority</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chief Election Authority and the election authorities appointed under Section 7, shall be competent to enquire into any matter which in their opinion is relevant in performing their functions under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purpose of sub-section (1), the Chief Election Authority or the election authority is competent to require any person who, in his opinion, is able to furnish relevant information or produce relevant documents, to furnish any such information or produce any such document.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-8.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>For the purpose of any such enquiry, the Chief election authority or the election authority shall have all the powers of a Civil Court while trying a suit under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 in respect of the following matters, namely.--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person and examining him on oath;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.3.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>requiring the discovery and production of any document;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.3.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>receiving evidence on affidavits;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.3.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>requisitioning any public record or copy thereof, from any Court or office;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.3.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses or documents; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.3.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>such other matters as may be prescribed.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Registers</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Chief Election Authority may specify by order such registers and records, in such form as he may specify to be maintained for the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Returns</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every recognised union shall submit such returns, in such form, to the election authority or such other officer as may be specified by order by the Chief election authority.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Existing Recognised Unions</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, a union which has been recognised under Code of Discipline as on the date of the commencement of this Act, shall be deemed to be a recognised union and shall continue as such till the expiry of two years from the date of recognition and thereafter shall continue in accordance with the provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Application for recognition</heading>
          <subsection id="section-12.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where, in any establishment or unit more than one eligible unions are functioning any of such unions may apply to the election authority to be considered as a recognised union for such an establishment, or unit or for both as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An eligible union whose operations do not extend to the whole of the establishment but are restricted to one, or more units thereof, shall be entitled to apply for recognition only for such unit or units.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On receipt of such application, the election authority shall address all the eligible unions in the establishment or units inviting objections to be filed, if any within such period as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If no objections are received, the election authority shall grant to the applicant union a certificate of recognition for the establishment, or unit of for both as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where objections are received by the election authority, the election authority shall determine the recognised union by holding elections.</p>
              <p>Explanation.--</p>
              <blockList id="section-12.5.list3">
                <listIntroduction>For the purpose of this section, eligible union means a union.--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-12.5.list3.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>which has been functioning for not less than one year from the date of its registration; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-12.5.list3.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>which is not a craft union.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Manner of election</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The election for the purpose of granting recognition shall be held by secret ballot and in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Eligible voters</heading>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-14.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>For the purpose of election, the following workmen shall constitute the eligible voters namely.--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-14.1.list1.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>all permanent workmen; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.1.list1.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>all such casual or temporary or badli, workmen or contract labour who worked In the establishment for not less than two hundred and forty days within a continuous period of three hundred sixty and five days, preceding the date of application under sub-section (1) and Section 12:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that, such of these contract labour who have been exclusively engaged by the industrial establishment in the essential economic activity of such establishment alone shall be eligible to vote:</p>
              <p>Provided further, that such of those contract labour who are engaged in building construction activities, cleaning operations, or in such activities other than the essential economic activity of an industrial establishment shall not be eligible to vote.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If any doubt arises whether an activity is an essential economic activity or not, it shall be referred to the Commissioner of Labour whose decision thereon shall be final.</p>
              <p>Explanation.--</p>
              <p>For the purpose of this section, the expressions "permanent workmen, casual workmen, Temporary workmen and badli workmen shall have the same meaning as assigned under the Model Standing Orders prescribed under Rule 3 of the Andhra Pradesh Industrial Employment (Standing Orders) Rules, 1953 under the First Schedule to the Industrial Employment (Standing Orders) Act, 1946. The term contract labour shall have the same meaning as assigned to it under the Contract Labour (Regulation and Abolition) Act. 1970.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Declaration of results</heading>
          <subsection id="section-15.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The election authority shall declare the results of the election in such form as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The election Authority shall, soon after the declaration of the results, grant a certificate of recognition to such of the unions which secured the maximum number of votes polled.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The election authority shall communicate to the employer concerned, the results of the election and the names of the recognised union.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Recognition in case of single union</heading>
          <subsection id="section-16.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Wherein an establishment or unit only one union is registered, it may apply in the prescribed form to the election authority for recognition.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On receipt of such application, the election authority shall grant a certificate of recognition to such union in the form prescribed.</p>
              <blockList id="section-16.2.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that such certificate shall not be granted unless such union.--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-16.2.list2.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>is the only union registered:</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.2.list2.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>enjoys a membership of not less than fifteen per-cent of the eligible votes in the establishment or the unit as the case may be;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.2.list2.iii">
                  <num>(iii)</num>
                  <p>has its operations extending over the establishment or the unit as the case may be; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.2.list2.iv">
                  <num>(iv)</num>
                  <p>is not a craft union.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The election authority shall communicate to the employer concerned the name of the recognised union.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Appeal</heading>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An appeal against the results declared under sub-sec. (1) of Section 15 of grant or certificate of recognition under sub-section (2) of Section 16 shall lie within such time as may be prescribed, to the Chief election authority or to such officer as he may, by general or special order specify, who shall, after giving reasonable opportunity to all concerned decide such appeal within the prescribed period and whose decision thereon shall be final and binding.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>During the pendency of an appeal under sub-section (1), the recognised union shall continue to function as such, but it shall not enter into any agreement with the employer, unless specifically so authorised by the Commissioner of Labour.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-18">
          <num>18.</num>
          <heading>Term of recognised union</heading>
          <subsection id="section-18.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The term of a recognised union shall be for a period of two years from the date of grant of certificate of recognition; and shall continue thereafter till such time an application is made under Section 12 and till the recognised union is determined afresh:</p>
              <p>Provided that where a union is granted recognition by a decision on an appeal filed under Section 17, the term of such recognised union, shall be reckoned from the date of issue of such order.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-18.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No application made by any union, shall be entertained by the election authority during the period of two years from the date of grant of certificate of recognition; or from the date of order of the appellate authority, as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Rights of unions</heading>
          <subsection id="section-19.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every recognised union shall have such rights as specified in the Second Schedule to this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-19.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every union other than the recognised union shall have such rights as specified in the Third Schedule to this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <heading>Workers Participation in Management</heading>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Obligations of employers</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every employer of an establishment shall abide by such obligations as specified in the Fourth Schedule to this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Interpretation of provisions</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>If any doubt arises as to the interpretation of any, or all of the provisions specified in the Second, Third and Fourth Schedules to this Act, the same shall be referred to the Commissioner of Labour, whose decision thereon shall be final.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-22">
          <num>22.</num>
          <heading>Application</heading>
          <subsection id="section-22.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provisions of this Chapter shall apply to every establishment in which fifty or more workmen are employed on any day of the preceding twelve months.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-22.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The establishment to which the provisions of this Chapter apply, shall continue to be governed by the provisions of this Chapter not withstanding that number of workmen employed therein falls below fifty.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-23">
          <num>23.</num>
          <heading>Authorities</heading>
          <subsection id="section-23.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Government may, by notification appoint such officers as they consider necessary to be the authorities for the purpose of constituting the Councils under Section 24 or for the purpose of specifying Board Level participation under Section 36.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Government may, by notification appoint an appellate authority to hear and dispose of appeals under sub-section (3).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-23.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An appeal against the order of authority under sub-section (1) shall lie, within such time as may be prescribed, to the appellate authority who shall within the prescribed, period, pass an order; and whose decision thereon shall be final and binding.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-24">
          <num>24.</num>
          <heading>Constitution of councils</heading>
          <subsection id="section-24.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall be lawful for the authority appointed under sub-section (1) of Section 23 to constitute in any establishment, any or all of the following councils namely; shop council, factory council and enterprise council, to give effect to workers participation in management at shop floor level, factory level and establishment level respectively:</p>
              <p>Provided that the number of shop councils in a factory shall not exceed ten in number.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-24.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The councils constituted by the Authority under sub-section (1) shall commence functioning within forty five days from the date of orders of the authority. The employer and the union, or Unions empowered under Section 26 shall nominate, under intimation to each other and to the authority, their representatives to the membership as well as to the office of the chairman or Co-Chairman. Such nomination shall be made within a period of thirty days from the date of orders of the authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-24.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where an employer, or union, or unions fail to nominate their representatives within the period stipulated, the authority shall be competent to nominate such persons as he deems fit to represent the employer or the workmen in regard to membership as well as to the office of Chairman or Co-Chairman.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-25">
          <num>25.</num>
          <heading>Membership of the Councils</heading>
          <subsection id="section-25.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The membership of the shop council shall be five percent of the total workmen employed in the concerned shop or tweleve, whichever is less, the membership of the factory council and enterprise council shall be ten percent of the total workmen employed in the factory or the establishment, as the case may be or twenty whichever is less.</p>
              <p>Explanation.--For the purpose of this sub-section where the calculation by percentage does not result in an even number, the membership of such council shall be determined at the immediate next even number.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The membership in every council shall be in equal proportion between the representatives of the workmen and those of the employer.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The nomination of members to the factory council by employers as well as unions, shall be so made that every Chairman or Co-Chairman of a shop council is a member of the Factory Council. Similarly, the nomination to the enterprise, council shall be so made that the Chairman or Co-Chairman of the factory council is a member of the enterprise Council.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-25.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-25.4.list0">
                <item id="section-25.4.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>The membership of the shop council shall be restricted to workmen and, so far as the employers, representatives are concerned, the employees, other than workmen, connected with the concerned shop floor.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-25.4.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>The representation of workmen in the Factory Council shall be restricted to the workmen and not more than two office bearers of the union who are non-workmen. The representation of employer shall be through employees of the factory who are non-workmen.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-25.4.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>The representation of the workmen in the Enterprise Council shall be restricted to (i) workmen (ii) office bearers; not more than two in number. The employer will be entitled to nominate not more than two outside experts.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>Power to nominate</heading>
          <subsection id="section-26.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The management or its representative, duly authorised in this behalf, may nominate its representatives to the respective councils.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-26.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The representatives of the workmen shall be nominated by the recognised union :</p>
              <p>Provided that in the establishments specified in the First Schedule, the workmen's representatives for the shop council and factory council shall be nominated by the recognised union at the unit level.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-26.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where unions other than the recognised union possesses membership of not less than twenty percent of the total number of eligible voters, than the representatives of workmen to the shop, factory and enterprise council shall be nominated by the recognised union as well as such other minority unions in proportion of their respective membership.</p>
              <blockList id="section-26.3.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Explanation.--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-26.3.list2.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>for the purpose of sub-section (3), the strength in the establishment shall be the basis for nomination to enterprise council.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-26.3.list2.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>For nomination to factory council and shop councils, the strength in the establishment shall be the basis in respect of establishments other than those specified in the First Schedule. In respect of establishments specified in the First Schedule, the strength at the Industrial unit level shall be the basis for nomination to factory councils and shop councils.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-27">
          <num>27.</num>
          <heading>Term of members of councils</heading>
          <subsection id="section-27.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The term of office of the members of the shop council, factory council and enterprise council shall be for a period of two years from the date of constitution of such council:</p>
              <p>Provided that the members of the council shall continue to hold the office till a new council is reconstituted.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A member of the council nominated to fill up a casual vacancy shall hold office for the remaining period of the term of office.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-27.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A member whose term of office is completed is eligible for renomination.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-28">
          <num>28.</num>
          <heading>Resignation of membership to the councils</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>A member of the council after giving a notice of fifteen days to the Chairman, may resign his membership which shall take effect from the date of acceptance of the resignation or on the expiry of thirty days from the date of giving such notice.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-29">
          <num>29.</num>
          <heading>Cessation of membership of councils</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-29.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>If a member of a council fails to attend three consecutive meetings of the council, he shall cease to be a member of such council. However, the council may, on the request made in writing by such member, by resolution restore his membership.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-30">
          <num>30.</num>
          <heading>Nomination and term of Chairman and Co-Chairman</heading>
          <subsection id="section-30.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>There shall be a Chairman and a Co-Chairman to each council. The Chairman and Co-Chairman shall be from among the representatives of the workmen and the management. They shall hold such offices for a period of six months and at the end of such period the Chairman and the Co-Chairman shall exchange their respective offices.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-30.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The employer, or his representative, duly authorised in this behalf, may nominate the employers representative to the post of Chairman or Co-Chairman. The recognised union shall have right to nominate its representative to the post of Chairman or Co-Chairman.</p>
              <p>Explanation.--</p>
              <p>In respect of establishments specified in the First Schedule, the recognised union means the recognised union at the establishment level for enterprise councils and the recognised union at the unit level for factory council and shop council.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-30.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The workers representative will be the first Chairman of each council.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-30.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The nomination, either by the employer or the recognised union to the post of Chairman or Co-Chairman shall not be altered for period of not less than one year.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-31">
          <num>31.</num>
          <heading>Powers and functions of the Chairman</heading>
          <subsection id="section-31.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chairman shall preside over the meetings of the council and shall cause the minutes of such meetings to be recorded in such manner as may be prescribed. He shall keep the records relating to the proceedings of the meetings in his custody. He shall furnish a copy of the proceedings recorded at each meeting to the Chairman of the factory council or enterprise council or to the Chief, Executive or Managing Director, as the case may be, within the prescribed period.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-31.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>In the absence of the Chairman for a period not exceeding one week, the Co-Chairman shall preside over the meetings, if any, and shall cause the minutes to be recorded, if the absence of Chairman exceeds one week, the Co-Chairman shall discharge all the functions of the Chairman.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-32">
          <num>32.</num>
          <heading>Resignation of Chairman and Co-Chairman</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-32.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Chairman or the Co-Chairman may tender his resignation by a letter addressed to the Co-Chairman or the Chairman as the case may be. Such resignation shall be considered in the council and the council may, by a resolution recorded for the purpose, accept such resignation. The resignation tendered shall take effect from the date of such resolution or on the expiry of thirty days from the date of tendering resignation, whichever is earlier.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-33">
          <num>33.</num>
          <heading>Filling up of casual vacancy in the office of Chairman or Co-Chairman</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-33.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>During the casual vacancy in the office of Chairman or the Co-Chairman, it shall be filled by nomination of another person, who shall hold office for the residual period of the term at his predecessor.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-34">
          <num>34.</num>
          <heading>Meetings of the Council</heading>
          <subsection id="section-34.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chairman shall hold the meetings of the Council as frequently as he thinks necessary, so however, that atleast one meeting shall be held in every calendar month.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-34.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Chairman shall fix the date, time and place of every meeting and shall send notice in writing along with the list of business to be transacted at the meeting to each member atleast three days before the date fixed for such meeting.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-34.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No business shall be transacted at any meeting of the council unless on-third of the total number of members are present and also unless atleast one member each representing the workmen and the employer is present.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-34.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The matters for shop councils, factory councils and enterprise councils shall be as provided under the Fifth Schedule to this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-34.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The decisions shall be taken by majority of members present and voting. In the event of equality of votes, the Chairman shall have a casting vote. The decisions so taken shall be recorded as resolutions of the council.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-34.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The proceedings of each meeting shall be confirmed in the next meeting with or without modifications, as may be considered necessary.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-34.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The management shall provide necessary facilities for holding the meetings of the council and shall treat the time spent by the members of the council in such meetings as on duty.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-35">
          <num>35.</num>
          <heading>Resolutions of enterprise councils</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-35.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The resolutions of the Enterprise Council shall be placed before the Board of Directors by the Secretary or the chief Executive of the Board. The Board of Directors shall discuss the same at its next meeting and take appropriate decisions.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-36">
          <num>36.</num>
          <heading>Participation at Board level</heading>
          <subsection id="section-36.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The authority appointed under sub-section (1) of Section 23 is competent to specify, by an order in writing, the establishments wherein workers participation shall be introduced at the level of the Board of Directors. For this purpose, the authority shall determine the number of workmen-Directors, which shall not be less than twenty-five per cent of strength of the Board of Directors.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The representation of workmen in the Board shall be through direct election from among the eligible voters of the establishment. The workmen and the office-bearers of the unions operating in that establishment shall be eligible to contest elections.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The election specified under sub-section (2) shall be conducted by the election authority, the election shall be by secret ballot and in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-36.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An appeal against the result of elections conducted under subsection (3) shall lie, within such time as may be prescribed, to the Chief, Election Authority or such other Officer as he may, by general or special order, specify and whose decision thereon shall be final and binding.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-IV">
        <num>IV</num>
        <heading>Protection of Workers' Interests in Closed Establishments</heading>
        <section id="section-37">
          <num>37.</num>
          <heading>Application</heading>
          <subsection id="section-37.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The provision of this chapter shall apply to every establishment in which hundred or more workmen are employed on any day of the preceding twelve months:</p>
              <p>Provided that the Government may, after giving not less than one months' notice of its intention so to do, by notification, apply the provisions of this chapter to any establishment, employing such number of workmen, less than hundred, as may be specified in the notification.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-37.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An establishment to which the provisions of this chapter apply, shall continue to be governed by the provisions of this chapter notwithstanding that the number of persons employed therein falls below the number specified under sub-section (1).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-38">
          <num>38.</num>
          <heading>Fund</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-38.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Government shall, with effect from such date as may be notified, constitute a fund called the "Industrial Workers' Contingency Fund".</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-39">
          <num>39.</num>
          <heading>Contribution to the Fund</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-39.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every workmen of an establishment shall contribute every year to the fund such sum, as the Government may prescribe, which shall not be less than one percent of the minimum wages in force for the General Engineering Industry. Every employer shall, in respect of each such workman, contribute a sum equivalent to two times the workman's contribution to the fund. It shall be the duty of the employer to remit in such manner, as maybe prescribed, the employers contribution together with the contribution of the workmen to such authority as the Government may notify in this behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-40">
          <num>40.</num>
          <heading>Deduction</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-40.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding any thing contained in any other law for the time being in force, the employer shall be entitled to deduct the Workman's contribution from his wages in such manner, as may be prescribed and such deduction shall be deemed to be a deduction authorised by or under the Payment of Wages Act, 1936 Central Act, 4 of 1936.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-41">
          <num>41.</num>
          <heading>Recovery</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-41.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Any sum payable to the Fund under this Act, shall, without prejudice to any other mode of recovery be recoverable as arrears of land revenue under the Andhra Pradesh Revenue Recovery Act, 1864 Act II of 1864.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-42">
          <num>42.</num>
          <heading>Constitution of the State Board</heading>
          <subsection id="section-42.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Government shall, by notification, constitute a Board for the whole of the State to be called the Andhra Pradesh Industrial workers' Contingency Fund Board, for the purpose of administering the fund and to carry out such other functions, as are assigned to the Board by, or under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-42.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Board shall be a body corporate by the name of the Andhra Pradesh Industrial workers' contingency Fund Board having perpetual succession and a common seal, with power to acquire, hold and dispose of property, both movable and immovable, and shall, by the said name, sue and be sued.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-43">
          <num>43.</num>
          <heading>Members of the Board and term</heading>
          <subsection id="section-43.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-43.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Board shall consist of such of members as maybe prescribed from each of the following categories, namely.--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-43.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>representatives of employers and employees in equal proportion, to be nominated by the Government.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-43.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-43.1.list1.b.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>independent members, to be nominated by the Government as follows.--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-43.1.list1.b.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>Minister for Labour.--Chairman.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-43.1.list1.b.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>Commissioner of Labour.--Ex-Officio;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-43.1.list1.b.list0.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>The Secretary to Government, Finance and Planning (finance Wing) Department.--Ex-Officio;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-43.1.list1.b.list0.iv">
                      <num>(iv)</num>
                      <p>the Secretary to Government, Industries Department.--Ex-Officio;</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-43.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>An officer of the Labour Department, not below the rank of a Deputy Commissioner of Labour shall discharge the functions of Secretary to the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-43.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Save as otherwise expressly provided in this Act, the term of office of the members of the Board shall be, as maybe prescribed in this behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-44">
          <num>44.</num>
          <heading>Allowances</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-44.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The allowance if any, payable to the non-official members of the Board and the conditions of nomination of the representations of the employers and employees shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-45">
          <num>45.</num>
          <heading>Disqualification and removal</heading>
          <subsection id="section-45.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-45.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>No person shall be nominated or continued to be a member of the Board who-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-45.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>is an official, drawing salary from the Board;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-45.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>is or has been adjudged at any time insolvent or has suspended payment of his debts or has compounded with his creditors;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-45.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>is found to be of unsound mind;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-45.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>is or has been convicted by a criminal court for an offence involving moral turpitude, unless such condition has been set aside; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-45.1.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>is in arrears of any sum due to the Board.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-45.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-45.2.list1">
                <listIntroduction>The Government may remove from office any member who-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-45.2.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>is or has become subject to any of the disqualifications mentioned in sub-section (1); or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-45.2.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>is absent without leave of the Board for more than three consecutive meetings of the Board:</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Provided that before taking action under this sub-section, the member concerned shall be given an opportunity to make a representation against the action proposed.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-46">
          <num>46.</num>
          <heading>Resignation</heading>
          <subsection id="section-46.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A member may resign his office by giving notice of his intention thereof in writing to the Government, and on the acceptance of his resignation, he shall be deemed to have vacated his office as such member.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-46.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A casual vacancy in the office of a member shall be filled by nomination of another person from the concerned category and the member so nominated shall hold office for the residue period of the term of the office of his predecessor.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-46.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No act or proceeding of the Board shall be invalid merely on the ground of the existence of any vacancy, or any defect in the constitution of the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-47">
          <num>47.</num>
          <heading>Grants and loans</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-47.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Government may, from time to time make grants and advance loans to the Board to the extent of the fund available for the purposes of this Act, on such terms and conditions as the Government may, in each case, determine.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-48">
          <num>48.</num>
          <heading>Vesting of Fund</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-48.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Fund shall vest in and be held and applied by the Board as trustees for the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-49">
          <num>49.</num>
          <heading>Application of Fund</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-49.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-49.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Without prejudice to the generality of the provisions of Section 48, the Fund shall be utilised by the Board, which may-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-49.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>grant to the affected workmen such sums as the Board may decide; and such sums shall not be less than the minimum wages in force for the General Engineering Industry;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-49.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>contribute towards the share capital for the formation of an Industrial Workers Co-operative Society;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-49.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>grant such other financial assistance to the Industrial Workers Co-operative Societies; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-49.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>take such measures as the Board may consider necessary for promoting the Welfare of affected workmen.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-50">
          <num>50.</num>
          <heading>Borrowings</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-50.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Board may from time to time, with the previous sanction of the Government, and subject to such condition's as maybe specified by the Government in this behalf, borrow sums required for the purpose of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-51">
          <num>51.</num>
          <heading>Directions by the Government</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-51.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Government may from time to time, give to the Board such directions as in their opinion are necessary or expedient for incurring the expenditure from the Fund or for carrying out the purposes of this Act and it shall be the duty of the Board to comply without fail with all such directions.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-52">
          <num>52.</num>
          <heading>Assistance to affected workmen</heading>
          <subsection id="section-52.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Government may, by notification, appoint such officers as they deem fit to maintain the list of affected workmen.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-52.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall be lawful for the Government to direct the Employment Exchange to sponsor the names of affected workmen on priority basis.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-52.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Government may notify such other schemes as they consider necessary for providing assistance to the affected workmen.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-53">
          <num>53.</num>
          <heading>Audit of Accounts</heading>
          <subsection id="section-53.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The accounts of the Board shall be audited by such persons as may be appointed by the Government and any expenditure incurred in connection with such audit shall be payable by the Board to the Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-53.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The person so appointed and any other person so authorised by him in connection with such audit of accounts of the Board shall have the right to demand the production of books accounts connected vouchers and other documents and papers of the Board.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-53.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The accounts of the Board certified by the person so appointed or any other person authorised in this behalf together with the audit report thereon shall be forwarded annually to the Government.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <heading>Miscellaneous</heading>
        <section id="section-54">
          <num>54.</num>
          <heading>Act not to apply to certain classes of employers</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-54.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-54.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Nothing in this Act shall apply to-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-54.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the Indian Red Cross Society, or to any other such institutions of a like nature ;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-54.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>Universities and other Educational Institutions ;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-54.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>Religious and Charitable Institutions : and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-54.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>such other industrial establishments as the Government may by notification specify for purposes of all or any of the provisions of this Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-55">
          <num>55.</num>
          <heading>Appointment of Inspectors</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-55.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Government may by notification, appoint such persons as they think fit to be Inspectors for the purpose of this Act and may specify the limit within which they shall exercise jurisdiction.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-56">
          <num>56.</num>
          <heading>Duties of Inspectors</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-56.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-56.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>An Inspector appointed under section 55 for the purpose of ascertaining whether any of the provisions of this Act have been violated, may -</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-56.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>require an employer or union to furnish such information as he may consider necessary;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-56.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>at any reasonable tone and with such assistance as he may consider necessary enter the place of any industrial establishment a unit, or any premises connected therewith and require any person found to be in charge thereof to produce, before hits for examination of any account books, registers and other documents relating to the employment of workmen or the payment of wages in such establishment.</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-56.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>examine the employer, his agent, or servant or any other person found incharge of the industry or any premises connected therewith, or any person whom the inspector has reason to believe to be or to have been a workmen in such establishment in discharging his duties;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-56.paragraph-0.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>make copies of, or take extracts from, any book, register or other document maintained in relation to such establishments ; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-56.paragraph-0.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>exercise such other powers as may be prescribed in this behalf.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-57">
          <num>57.</num>
          <heading>Furnishing of records etc.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-57.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Any person required to produce any book, register, or other document or to give information by an Inspector under Section 56 shall comply with such requirement.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-58">
          <num>58.</num>
          <heading>Maintenance of records</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-58.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Every employer shall prepare and maintain such registers, records and other documents in such form and in such manner as may be prescribed.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-59">
          <num>59.</num>
          <heading>Power to amend Schedules</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-59.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The State Government may, if it is of the opinion that it is expedient or necessary in public interest, so to do by notification in the official Gazette, add to or alter or amend the Schedule and on any such notification being issued, the Schedule shall be deemed to have been amended accordingly.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-60">
          <num>60.</num>
          <heading>Provisions not to over ride other laws</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-60.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Save as otherwise expressly provided in this Act, the provisions of this Act shall be in addition to and not, in derogation of any other law for the time being in force relating to any establishment.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-61">
          <num>61.</num>
          <heading>Bar of Jurisdiction</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-61.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No order passed or proceedings taken under the provisions of this Act shall be called in question in any Court, in any suit, or application; and no injunction shall be granted by any Court in respect of any action taken or about to be taken in pursuance of any power conferred by or under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-62">
          <num>62.</num>
          <heading>Officers to be Public servants</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-62.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>All officers acting under this Act shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal code.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-63">
          <num>63.</num>
          <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-63.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any person for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any rule made thereunder.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-64">
          <num>64.</num>
          <heading>Penalties</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-64.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Whoever contravenes any of the provisions of this Act shall be punishable with a fine of five hundred rupees or more which may extend to five thousand rupees ; or with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with both.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-65">
          <num>65.</num>
          <heading>Cognizance of offenses</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-65.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No court shall take cognizance of any offence punishable under this Act, save on a compliant made by or under the authority of the Government.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-66">
          <num>66.</num>
          <heading>Trail of offences</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-66.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>No Court inferior to that of a Metropolitan Magistrate or a Judicial Magistrate of the First Class shall try any offence punishable under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-67">
          <num>67.</num>
          <heading>Power to remove difficulties</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-67.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Government may by notification in the Andhra Pradesh Gazette, do anything not inconsistent with such provisions which appears to them to be expedient or necessary for the purpose of removing the difficulty.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-68">
          <num>68.</num>
          <heading>Power to review the implementation of the provisions</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-68.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The Government may, from time to time, review the implementation of the provisions of this Act, in such manner, as they deem fit, and for this purpose they may constitute a committee consisting of such persons as they consider necessary.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-69">
          <num>69.</num>
          <heading>Power to make rules</heading>
          <subsection id="section-69.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Government may make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-69.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every rule made under this Act shall Immediately after it is made be laid before the legislative Assembly of the State, if it is in session and if it is not in session, in the session immediately following for a total period of fourteen days which may be comprised in one session or in two successive sessions, and if before the expiration of the session in which it is so laid or the session immediately following the Legislative Assembly agrees in making any modification in the rule or in the annulment of the rule, the rule shall from the date on which the modification or annulment is notified, have effect only in such modified form or shall stand annulled, as. the case may be, so however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-firstschedule">
      <doc name="firstschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1998/24/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1998/24"/>
              <FRBRalias value="FIRST SCHEDULE"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1998/24/eng@2017-05-25/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1998/24/eng@2017-05-25"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1998/24/eng@2017-05-25/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1998/24/eng@2017-05-25"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-05-25" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="firstschedule">
            <paragraph id="firstschedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>FIRST SCHEDULE</p>
                <p>(See Section 3)</p>
                <p>Name of the Industrial Establishment</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
            <section id="section-1">
              <num>1.</num>
              <heading>Andhra Pradesh State Road Transport Corporation.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-2">
              <num>2.</num>
              <heading>Andhra Pradesh State Electricity Board.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-3">
              <num>3.</num>
              <heading>Medical &amp; Health Department.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-4">
              <num>4.</num>
              <heading>Andhra Pradesh Dairy Development Co-operative Federation Limited.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-5">
              <num>5.</num>
              <heading>Government Printing Press.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-6">
              <num>6.</num>
              <heading>Municipal Corporation of Hyderabad.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-7">
              <num>7.</num>
              <heading>Hyderabad Metropolitan Water Works.</heading>
            </section>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-secondschedule">
      <doc name="secondschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1998/24/secondschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1998/24"/>
              <FRBRalias value="SECOND SCHEDULE"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1998/24/eng@2017-05-25/secondschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1998/24/eng@2017-05-25"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1998/24/eng@2017-05-25/secondschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1998/24/eng@2017-05-25"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-05-25" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="secondschedule">
            <paragraph id="secondschedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>SECOND SCHEDULE</p>
                <p>[See Section 19(1)]</p>
                <p>A. Rights of a Recognised Union at the Industrial Establishment Level.--</p>
                <blockList id="secondschedule.paragraph-0.list4">
                  <listIntroduction>The Union which has been conferred the status of a Recognition union in respect of an Industrial establishment shall have the right -</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="secondschedule.paragraph-0.list4.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>to raise issues and enter into collective agreements with employer on general matters concerning the terms of employment and conditions of service of workmen in an industrial establishment:</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <blockList id="secondschedule.paragraph-0.list6">
                  <listIntroduction>Provided however, that the Recognised Union shall not be entitled to either raise a demand or to enter into an agreement with the employer if an eligible union has duly made an application under sub-section (1) of Section 12 of the Act.</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="secondschedule.paragraph-0.list6.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>to collect membership fees/subscriptions payable by members to the union within the premises of the Industrial establishment.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="secondschedule.paragraph-0.list6.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>to put up a Notice Board on the premises of the Industrial establishment in which its members are employed and affix or cause to be affixed thereon notices relating to meetings, statements of accounts of its income and expenditure and other announcements which are not abusive, indecent or inflamatory or subversive to discipline.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="secondschedule.paragraph-0.list6.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>to hold discussions with the workers who are members of the union at a suitable place or places within the premises of the Industrial establishment after consulting the employer.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="secondschedule.paragraph-0.list6.v">
                    <num>(v)</num>
                    <p>to discuss with the employer or any person appointed by him for the purpose in respect of the grievances of its members employed in the Industrial establishment.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="secondschedule.paragraph-0.list6.vi">
                    <num>(vi)</num>
                    <p>to inspect by prior arrangement with the employer, any place of the Industrial establishment where any member of the union is employed.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="secondschedule.paragraph-0.list6.vii">
                    <num>(vii)</num>
                    <p>to nominate its representatives on the Works Committees constituted under Section 3 of the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="secondschedule.paragraph-0.list6.viii">
                    <num>(viii)</num>
                    <p>to nominate its representatives on Shop Councils, Factory Councils/Enterprises Councils of the Industrial establishment, provided that in respect of Industrial establishment listed in Schedule-I to this Act, the union shall nominate its representatives only to the Enterprise Councils.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="secondschedule.paragraph-0.list6.ix">
                    <num>(ix)</num>
                    <p>to nominate its representatives on other statutory Committees, if any, to be set up in the Industrial establishment. (x) to appear on behalf of the workman or workmen in any domestic/departmental enquiry held by the employer.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="secondschedule.paragraph-0.list6.xi">
                    <num>(xi)</num>
                    <p>to obtain from the employer information on any matter connected with the conditions of employment of the workmen therein:</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <p>Provided that the rights referred to in this Schedule would be without prejudice to any additional privileges being enjoyed by Recognised union at present either by award, agreement or by usage.</p>
                <p>B. Rights and Privileges of Recognised Unions for the Industrial Unit of an Industrial Establishment.</p>
                <blockList id="secondschedule.paragraph-0.list10">
                  <listIntroduction>In the Industrial establishments listed in First Schedule to this Act, the union which has been conferred the status of Recognised union for an Industrial unit shall have all the rights specifies in items i to x above, subject to the following conditions.</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="secondschedule.paragraph-0.list10.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>In respect of raising demands and entering into agreements with the employer, it shall confine itself to matters which are not of general interest having effect on all the workmen of the Industrial establishment; for example wages, bonus, allowances.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="secondschedule.paragraph-0.list10.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>The Recognised Union shall not be entitled to nominate representatives to the Enterprise Council.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-thirdschedule">
      <doc name="thirdschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1998/24/thirdschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1998/24"/>
              <FRBRalias value="THIRD SCHEDULE"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1998/24/eng@2017-05-25/thirdschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1998/24/eng@2017-05-25"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1998/24/eng@2017-05-25/thirdschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1998/24/eng@2017-05-25"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-05-25" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="thirdschedule">
            <paragraph id="thirdschedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>THIRD SCHEDULE</p>
                <p>[See Section 19 (2)]</p>
                <p>Rights and Privileges of Unions other than Unions Recognised Operating in the Industrial Establishment</p>
                <blockList id="thirdschedule.paragraph-0.list4">
                  <listIntroduction>The unions other than recognised unions operating in the Industrial Establishment have the right-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="thirdschedule.paragraph-0.list4.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>to discuss with the employer or any person appointed by him in that behalf, the individual grievances of workmen, who are its members, in respect of the matters relating to discharge, removal retrenchment, termination of service and other disciplinary matters;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="thirdschedule.paragraph-0.list4.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>to appeal on behalf of any of its members In any domestic or departmental enquiry held by the employer;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="thirdschedule.paragraph-0.list4.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>to nominate its representatives on the Shop Council, Factory Council/Enterprise Council in terms of provisions contained in sub-section (2) of Section 27 of the Act.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-fourthschedule">
      <doc name="fourthschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1998/24/fourthschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1998/24"/>
              <FRBRalias value="FOURTH SCHEDULE"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1998/24/eng@2017-05-25/fourthschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1998/24/eng@2017-05-25"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1998/24/eng@2017-05-25/fourthschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1998/24/eng@2017-05-25"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-05-25" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="fourthschedule">
            <paragraph id="fourthschedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>FOURTH SCHEDULE</p>
                <p>(See Section 20)</p>
                <p>Obligations of Employers.--</p>
                <p>The employer of an Industrial Establishment Industrial unit shall.--</p>
                <p>i. provide to the unions other than the Recognised unions with copies of any settlement arrived at with the Recognised union under Section 12 (2), 18 (1) of the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 an application made to him.</p>
                <p>ii. allow the Recognised union to inspect any place of the Industrial establishment where any of its member is employed.</p>
                <p>iii. discuss and negotiate with the Recognised union all matters relating to conditions of service of the workmen on a representation made to him.</p>
                <p>iv. provide information to the Recognised union on any matter effecting the conditions of employment of workmen.</p>
                <p>v. inform all the unions in the Industrial establishment in the event of losses for consecutive period of three months.</p>
                <p>vi. discuss with the worker's representatives in the Enterprise Council causes of such losses and the remidial steps taken.</p>
                <p>vii. give advance intimation to the Enterprise council and Factory council of the proposal to apply to the Competent Authority for retrenchment of workers/ closures of Industrial establishment or any activity; thereof, to enable consideration by the council of possible alternative measures.</p>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
    <component id="component-fifthschedule">
      <doc name="fifthschedule">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1998/24/fifthschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1998/24"/>
              <FRBRalias value="FIFTH SCHEDULE"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1998/24/eng@2017-05-25/fifthschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1998/24/eng@2017-05-25"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-anp/act/1998/24/eng@2017-05-25/fifthschedule"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-anp/act/1998/24/eng@2017-05-25"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2017-05-25" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="fifthschedule">
            <paragraph id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0">
              <content>
                <p>FIFTH SCHEDULE</p>
                <p>[See Section 34 (4)]</p>
                <blockList id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list3">
                  <listIntroduction>A. Matters for Shop Councils</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list3.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>Production facilities at the shop level.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list3.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>storage facilities at the shop level. (iii) Material economy.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list3.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>Operation Problems.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list3.v">
                    <num>(v)</num>
                    <p>Wastage control.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list3.vi">
                    <num>(vi)</num>
                    <p>Hazards.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list3.vii">
                    <num>(vii)</num>
                    <p>Safety problem.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list3.viii">
                    <num>(viii)</num>
                    <p>Quality improvement.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list3.iix">
                    <num>(iix)</num>
                    <p>Cleanliness.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list3.x">
                    <num>(x)</num>
                    <p>Month targets and production Schedules.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list3.xi">
                    <num>(xi)</num>
                    <p>Cost reduction programmes.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list3.xii">
                    <num>(xii)</num>
                    <p>Welfare measures related particularly to the Shop.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <blockList id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list5">
                  <listIntroduction>B. Matters for Factory Council Operational areas.--</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list5.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>Evolution of productivity schemes taking into account the local conditions.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list5.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>Planning, implementation.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list5.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>review of monthly targets and schedules.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list5.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>Materials supply and its short fall.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list5.v">
                    <num>(v)</num>
                    <p>storage and inventories.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list5.vi">
                    <num>(vi)</num>
                    <p>House-keeping</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list5.vii">
                    <num>(vii)</num>
                    <p>Improvements in productivity in general, and in critical areas in particular.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list5.viii">
                    <num>(viii)</num>
                    <p>Quality and technological improvements.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list5.ix">
                    <num>(ix)</num>
                    <p>Machine utilization, Knowledge and development of new products.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list5.x">
                    <num>(x)</num>
                    <p>Operational performance figures.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list5.xi">
                    <num>(xi)</num>
                    <p>Matters not resolved in the Shop Council or concerning more than one shop.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list5.xii">
                    <num>(xii)</num>
                    <p>Review of the working of the Shop Council. Personnel Matters.--</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list5.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>Absenteesim.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list5.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>Initiation and supervision of worker's training programme.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list5.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>Administration of special security schemes. Welfare areas.--</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list5.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>Operational details.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list5.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>Implementation of Welfare Schemes.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list5.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>medical benefits and transport facilities.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list5.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>Safety measures.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list5.v">
                    <num>(v)</num>
                    <p>Sports and games.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list5.vi">
                    <num>(vi)</num>
                    <p>Housing.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list5.vii">
                    <num>(vii)</num>
                    <p>Township administration, Canteen etc.,</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list5.viii">
                    <num>(viii)</num>
                    <p>Review of social education programmes.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <blockList id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list7">
                  <listIntroduction>Environmental areas.--</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list7.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>Extension activities and community development projects.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list7.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>Pollution control.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <blockList id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list9">
                  <listIntroduction>C. Matters for Enterprise Council Economic and financial areas.--</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list9.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>Profit and loss statements, balance sheets.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list9.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>Review of operating expenses, financial results, cost of sales.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list9.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>Plant performance in financial terms, labour and managerial costs, market conditions etc. (iv) Matters not resolved in the Factory Council.</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="fifthschedule.paragraph-0.list9.v">
                    <num>(v)</num>
                    <p>Review of working of Factory Council. Note.--Where there is no separate Factor" Council the matters for the Factory Council will go before the Enterprise Council.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </paragraph>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
