<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1984/17/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1984/17"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Inchek Tyres Limited And National Rubbermanufacturers Limited (Nationalisation) Act, 1984"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1984/17/eng@1984-03-31/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1984/17/eng@1984-03-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1984-03-31" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1984/17/eng@1984-03-31/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1984/17/eng@1984-03-31"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Inchek Tyres Limited And National Rubbermanufacturers Limited (Nationalisation) Act, 1984</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 17 OF 1984</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 31st March, 1984.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the acquisition and transfer of the  undertakings of the Inchek Tyres Limited and the National Rubber Manu-</p>
        <p>facturers Limited, with a view to securing the proper management of  such undertakings so as to subserve the interests of the general  public by ensuring the continued manufacture, production and  distribution of tyres, tubes and other rubber goods which are  essential to the needs of the economy of the country and for matters  connected therewith or incidental thereto.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS the Inchek Tyres Limited and the National Rubber Manufacturers</p>
        <p>Limited had been engaged in the manufacture, production and  distribution of articles mentioned in the First Schedule to the</p>
        <p>Industries (Development and Regulation) Act, 1951 (65 of 1951),</p>
        <p>namely, tyres, tubes and other rubber goods;</p>
        <p>AND WHEREAS the management of the undertakings of the Inchek Tyres</p>
        <p>Limited and the management of the undertakings of the National Rubber</p>
        <p>Manufacturers Limited were taken over by the Central Government under  the provisions of the Industries (Development and Regulation) Act,</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1951">
        <num>1951.</num>
        <heading>(65 of 1951);</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1951.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>AND WHEREAS for the purpose of securing the optimum utilisation of the  available facilities for the manufacture, production and distribution  of tyres, tubes and other rubber goods by the undertakings of the two  companies, investment of a large amount is necessary;</p>
            <p>AND WHEREAS it is necessary to acquire the undertakings of the Inchek</p>
            <p>Tyres Limited and the National Rubber Manufacturers Limited to enable  the Central Government to have such investments made and to ensure  that the interests of the general public are served by the  continuance, by the undertakings of the companies, of the manufacture,</p>
            <p>production and distribution of the aforesaid articles which are  essential to the needs of the economy of the country;</p>
            <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty- fifth Year of the</p>
            <p>Republic of India as follows:-</p>
            <p>CHAP</p>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title and commencement.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act may be called the</p>
              <blockList id="section-1.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Inchek Tyres Limited and National Rubber Manufacturers Limited</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-1.1.list2.Nationalisation">
                  <num>(Nationalisation)</num>
                  <p>Act, 1984.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-1.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 14th day of</p>
              <p>February, 1984.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" appointed day"' means the 14th day of February 1984;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" Commissioner" means the Commissioner of Payments appointed under  section 15;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" existing Government company" means a Government company which  is carrying on business on the appointed day;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" new Government company" means a Government company formed and  registered on or after the appointed day;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>" notification" means a notification published in the Official</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Gazette;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>" specified date", in relation to any provision of this Act, means  such date as the Central Government may, by notification, specify for  the purposes of that provision, and different dates may be specified  for different provisions of this Act;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>" two companies" means the Inchek Tyres Limited and the National</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Rubber Manufacturers Limited, being companies as defined in the</p>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), and having their registered offices  at" Leslie House", 19 Jawaharlal Nehru Road, Calcutta- 700013;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list5.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>words and expressions used herein and not defined but defined in  the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), shall have the meanings  respectively assigned to them in that Act.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Transfer to, and vesting in, the Central Government of the  undertakings of the two companies. On the appointed day, the  undertakings of each of the two companies, and the right, title and  interest of each of the two companies in relation to its undertakings,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>shall, by virtue of the Act, stand transferred to, and shall vest in,</p>
              <p>the Central Government.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Companies to be liable for certain prior liabilities.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every liability, other than the liability specified in sub- section</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>, of each of the two companies in respect of any period prior to  the appointed day, shall be the liability of the concerned company and  shall be enforceable against it and not against the Central</p>
              <p>Government, or where the undertakings of the two companies vest in an  existing, or a new, Government Company, against such Government  company.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any liability arising in respect of materials supplied to  either of the two companies after the management of its undertakings  had been taken over by the Central Government, shall, on and from the  appointed day, be the liability of the Central Government or of the  existing, or new, Government company aforesaid, and shall be  discharged by that Government or, as the case may be, the existing, or  new, Government company, as and when repayment for such supplies  becomes due and payable.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-5.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>save as otherwise expressly provided in this section or in  any other provision of this Act, no liability, other than the  liability specified in sub- section (2), of either of the two companies  in relation to its undertakings in respect of any period prior to the  appointed day shall be enforceable against the Central Government, or,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-5.3.list3">
                <listIntroduction>where the undertakings of the two companies vest in an existing, or a  new, Government company, against such Government company;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.3.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>no award, decree or order of any court, tribunal or other  authority in relation to the undertakings of either of the two  companies, passed on or after the appointed day, in respect of any  matter, claim or dispute, not being a matter, claim or dispute in  relation to any matter referred to in sub- section (2), which arose  before that day, shall be enforceable against the Central Government,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>or where the undertakings of the two</p>
              <p>companies vest in an existing, or a new, Government company,</p>
              <blockList id="section-5.3.list7">
                <listIntroduction>against such Government company;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.3.list7.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>no liability incurred by either of the two companies before  the appointed day, for the contravention of any provision of law for  the time being in force, shall be enforceable against the, Central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Government, or, where the undertakings of the two companies vest in  an existing, or a new, Government company, against such Government  company.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>PAYMENT OF AMOUNTS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PAYMENT OF AMOUNTS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Payment of amount. For the transfer to, and vesting in, the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Central Government, under section 3, of the undertakings of each of  the two companies, and the right, title and interest of each of the  two companies in relation to its undertakings, there shall be paid by  the Central Government to each of the two companies, in cash and in  the manner specified in Chapter VI, amount equal to the amount  specified against the name of such company in the First Schedule.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Management, etc., of the undertakings of the two companies.</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>The general superintendence, direction, control and management of the  affairs and business of the undertakings of each of the two companies,</p>
              <p>the Tight, title and interest in relation to which have vested in the</p>
              <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Central Government under section 3, shall,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list3.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>where a direction has been given by the Central Government under  sub- section (1) of section 6, vest on and from the date specified in  such direction, in the existing Government company specified therein;</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-10.paragraph-0.list5">
                <listIntroduction>or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10.paragraph-0.list5.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>where a declaration has been made under sub- section (1) of section</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>, vest, on and from the date of such declaration, in the new</p>
              <p>Government company specified therein;</p>
              <p>and thereupon the existing, or new, Government company so specified,</p>
              <p>shall be entitled to exercise, to the exclusion of all other persons  all such powers and do all such things as either, or both, of the two  companies, is or are, authorised to exercise and do in relation to its  or their undertakings.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Duty of persons in charge of management of undertakings of  the two companies to deliver all assets, etc.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On the vesting of  the management of the undertakings of the two companies in an  existing, or a new, Government company, all persons in charge of the  management of the undertakings of either of the two companies  immediately before such vesting shall be bound to deliver to such</p>
              <p>Government company, all assets, books of account, registers and other  documents in their custody relating to the undertakings.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may issue such directions as it may  deem desirable in the circumstances of the case to the existing, or  new, Government company and such Government company may also, if it is  considered necessary so to do, apply to the Central Government at any  time for instructions as to the manner in which the management of the  undertakings of the two companies shall be conducted or in relation to  any other matter arising in the course of such management.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Duty of persons account for assets, etc., in their  possession.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-12.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person who has, on the appointed day, in his  possession or under his control any assets, books, documents or other  papers relating to the undertakings owned by either of the two  companies, which have vested in the Central Government or in an  existing, or a new, Government company under this Act, shall be liable  to account for the said assets, books, documents and other papers to  the Central Government or the existing, or new, Government company, as  the case may be, and shall deliver them to the Central Government or  the existing, or new, Government company or to such person or persons  as the Central Government or the existing, or new, Government company  may specify in this behalf.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government or the Government company aforesaid  may take, or cause to be taken, all necessary steps for securing  possession of the undertakings of the two companies which have vested  in the Central Government or the Government company under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-12.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The two companies shall, within such period as the Central</p>
              <p>Government may allow in this behalf, furnish to that Government a  complete inventory of all their properties and assets, as on the  appointed day, pertaining to the undertakings which have vested in the</p>
              <p>Central Government under section 3, and, for this purpose, the Central</p>
              <p>Government or the Government company aforesaid shall afford to the two  companies all reasonable facilities.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>PROVISIONS RELATING TO EMPLOYEES OF THE TWO COMPANIES</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-V">
        <num>V</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-V.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PROVISIONS RELATING TO EMPLOYEES OF THE TWO COMPANIES</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Continuance of employees.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-13.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Every person who has been,</p>
              <blockList id="section-13.1.list2">
                <listIntroduction>immediately before the appointed day, employed in any undertaking of  either of the two companies shall become,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-13.1.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>on and from the appointed day, an employee of the Central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-13.1.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Government, and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-13.1.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>where the undertakings of the two companies are directed, under  section 6 or under section 7, to vest, in an existing, or a new,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Government company, an employee of such Government company on and from  the date of such vesting,</p>
              <p>and shall hold office or service under the Central Government or the  existing, or new, Government company, as the case may be, with the  rights and privileges as to pension, gratuity and other matters,</p>
              <p>admissible to him immediately</p>
              <p>before the appointed day, as modified by the Memorandum of Settlement  signed by the representatives of the management and the employees of  each of the two companies on the 10th day of February, 1984, and shall  continue to do so unless and until his employment under the Central</p>
              <p>Government or the existing or new, Government company, as the case may  be, is duly terminated or until his remuneration and other conditions  of service are duly altered by the Central Government, or the  existing, or new, Government company, as the case may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-13.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial Disputes</p>
              <p>Act, 1947 (14 of 1947), or in any other law for the time being in  force, the transfer of the services of any officer or other person  employed in any undertaking of either of the two companies, to the,</p>
              <p>Central Government or the existing, or new, Government company, shall  not entitle such officer or other employee to any compensation under  this Act or any other law for the time being in force and no such  claim shall be entertained by any court, tribunal or other authority.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Provident fund and other funds.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where either of the two  companies has established a provident fund, superannuation, welfare or  other fund for the benefit of the persons employed in any of its  undertakings, the moneys relatable to the officers or other employees  whose services have become transferred by or under this Act to the</p>
              <p>Central Government or an existing, or a new, Government company shall,</p>
              <p>out of the moneys standing, on the appointed day, to the credit of  such provident fund, super- annuation, welfare or other fund, stand  transferred to, and shall vest in, the Central Government or the  existing, or new, Government company, as the care may be.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The moneys which stand transferred under sub- section (1) to  the Central Government or the existing, or new, Government company, as  the case may be, shall be dealt with by that Government or the  existing, or new, Government company in such manner as may be  prescribed.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>COMMISSIONER OF PAYMENTS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-VI">
        <num>VI</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-VI.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>COMMISSIONER OF PAYMENTS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-15">
          <num>15.</num>
          <heading>Appointment of Commissioner of Payments.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-15.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central</p>
              <p>Government shall, for the purpose of disbursing the amounts payable  under sections 8 and 9 to each of the two companies, by notification,</p>
              <p>appoint a Commissioner of Payments.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government may appoint such other persons as it  may think fit to assist the Commissioner and thereupon the</p>
              <p>Commissioner may authorise one or more of such persons also to  exercise all or any of the powers exercisable by him under this Act  and different persons may be authorised to exercise different powers.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Any person authorised by the Commissioner to exercise any of  the powers exercisable by the Commissioner may exercise those powers  in the same manner and with the same effect as if they have been  conferred on that person directly by this Act and not by way of  authorisation.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-15.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The salaries and allowances of the Commissioner and other  persons appointed under this section shall be defraved out of the</p>
              <p>Consolidated Fund of India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-16">
          <num>16.</num>
          <heading>Payment by Central Government to the Commissioner.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-16.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The</p>
              <p>Central Government shall, within thirty days from the specified 1 date,</p>
              <blockList id="section-16.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>pay in cash to the Commissioner, for payment to each of the two  companies,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-16.1.list3.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>an amount equal to the amount specified against the name of such  company in the First Schedule; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-16.1.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>an amount equal to the amounts payable to each of the two company  in the First schedule; and</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>A deposit account shall be opened by the Central Government  in favour of the Commissioner in the Public Account of India and every  amount paid under this Act to the Commissioner shall be deposited by  him to the credit of the said deposit account and the said deposit  account shall be operated by the Commissioner.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Separate records shall be maintained by the Commissioner in  respect of the undertakings of each of the two companies in relation  to which payments have been made to him under this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-16.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Interest accruing on the amount standing to the credit of the  deposit account referred to in sub- section (2) shall enure to the  benefit of the two companies.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-17">
          <num>17.</num>
          <heading>Certain powers of Central Government or existing, or new,</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government company.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-17.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government or the existing, or  new, Government company, as the case may be, shall be entitled to  receive up to the specified date, to the exclusion of all other  persons, any money due to either of the two companies in relation to  its undertakings which have vested in the Central Government or the  existing, or now, Government company, as the case may be, and realised  after the appointed day notwithstanding that the realisation pertains  to a period prior to the appointed day.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Central Government, or the existing, or new, Government  company, as the case may be, may make a claim to the Commissioner with  regard to every payment made by it after the appointed day, for  discharging any liability of either of the two companies, not being  any liability specified in sub- section (2) of section 5, in relation  to any period prior to the appointed day, and every such claim shall  have priority, in accordance with the priorities attaching, under this</p>
              <p>Act, to the matter in relation to which such liability has been  discharged by the Central Government or the existing, or new,</p>
              <p>Government company.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-17.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Save as otherwise provided in this Act, the liabilities of  either of the two companies in respect of any transaction prior to the  appointed day which have not been discharged on or before the  specified date shall be the liabilities of the respective company.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-19">
          <num>19.</num>
          <heading>Priority of claims. The claims arising out of the matters  specified in the Second Schedule shall have priorities in accordance  with the following principles, namely:-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-19.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>Category I shall have precedence over all other categories and</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-19.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Category II shall have precedence over Category III, and so on;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the claims specified in each of the categories shall rank equally  and be paid in full, but, if the amount is insufficient to meet such  claims in full, they shall abate in equal proportions and be paid  accordingly; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-19.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the question of discharging any liability with regard to a matter  specified in a lower category shall arise only if a surplus is left  after meeting all the liabilities specified in the immediately higher  category.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-20">
          <num>20.</num>
          <heading>Examination of claims.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-20.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On receipt of the claims made  under section 18, the Commissioner shall arrange the claims in the  order of priorities specified in the Second Schedule and examine the  same in accordance with such order.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-20.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>If, on examination of the claims, the Commissioner is of  opinion that the amount paid to him under this Act is not sufficient to  meet the liabilities specified in any lower category, he shall not be  required to examine the claims in respect of such lower category.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-21">
          <num>21.</num>
          <heading>Admission or rejection of claims.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-21.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>After examining the  claims with reference to the priorities specified in the Second</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-thecommissionershallfixadateonorbeforewhicheveryclaimantshallfiletheproofofhisclaim">
      <doc name="thecommissionershallfixadateonorbeforewhicheveryclaimantshallfiletheproofofhisclaim">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1984/17/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1984/17"/>
              <FRBRalias value=", the Commissioner shall fix a date on or before which every  claimant shall file the proof of his claim."/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1984/17/eng@1984-03-31/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1984/17/eng@1984-03-31"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1984/17/eng@1984-03-31/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1984/17/eng@1984-03-31"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="thecommissionershallfixadateonorbeforewhicheveryclaimantshallfiletheproofofhisclaim">
            <subsection id="thecommissionershallfixadateonorbeforewhicheveryclaimantshallfiletheproofofhisclaim.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Not less than fourteen days' notice of the date so fixed  shall be given by advertisement in one issue of any daily newspaper in  the English language having circulation in the major part of the  country and in one issue of any daily newspaper in such regional  language as the Commissioner may consider suitable, and every such  notice shall call upon the claimant to file the proof of his claim  with the Commissioner within the period specified in the adver-</p>
                <p>tisement.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thecommissionershallfixadateonorbeforewhicheveryclaimantshallfiletheproofofhisclaim.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Every claimant who fails to file the proof of his claim  within the period specified by the Commissioner shall be excluded  from the disbursement made by the Commissioner.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thecommissionershallfixadateonorbeforewhicheveryclaimantshallfiletheproofofhisclaim.4">
              <num>(4)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Commissioner shall, after such investigation as may, in  his opinion, be necessary and after giving the concerned company an  opportunity of refuting the claim and after giving the claimant a  reasonable opportunity of being heard, admit or reject by order in  writing the claim in whole or in part.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thecommissionershallfixadateonorbeforewhicheveryclaimantshallfiletheproofofhisclaim.5">
              <num>(5)</num>
              <content>
                <p>The Commissioner shall have the power to regulate his own  procedure in all matters arising out of the discharge of his functions,</p>
                <p>including the place or places at which he may hold his sittings and  shall, for the purpose of making any investigation under this Act, have  the same powers as are vested in a civil court under the Code of Civil</p>
                <blockList id="thecommissionershallfixadateonorbeforewhicheveryclaimantshallfiletheproofofhisclaim.5.list3">
                  <listIntroduction>Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), while trying a suit, in respect of the  following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="thecommissionershallfixadateonorbeforewhicheveryclaimantshallfiletheproofofhisclaim.5.list3.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>the summoning and enforcing the attendance of any witness and  examining him on oath;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="thecommissionershallfixadateonorbeforewhicheveryclaimantshallfiletheproofofhisclaim.5.list3.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>the discovery and production of any document or other material  object producible as evidence;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="thecommissionershallfixadateonorbeforewhicheveryclaimantshallfiletheproofofhisclaim.5.list3.c">
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <p>the reception of evidence on affidavits;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="thecommissionershallfixadateonorbeforewhicheveryclaimantshallfiletheproofofhisclaim.5.list3.d">
                    <num>(d)</num>
                    <p>the issuing of any commission for the examination of witnesses.</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thecommissionershallfixadateonorbeforewhicheveryclaimantshallfiletheproofofhisclaim.6">
              <num>(6)</num>
              <content>
                <p>Any investigation before the Commissioner shall be deemed to  be a judicial proceeding within the meaning of sections 193 and 228 of  the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860) and the Commissioner shall be  deemed to be a civil court for the purposes of section 195 and Chapter</p>
                <p>XXVI of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="thecommissionershallfixadateonorbeforewhicheveryclaimantshallfiletheproofofhisclaim.7">
              <num>(7)</num>
              <content>
                <p>A claimant who is dissatisfied with the decision of the  commissioner may prefer an appeal against such decision to the  principal civil court of original jurisdiction within the local limits  of whose jurisdiction the registered office of the concerned company  is situated:</p>
                <p>Provided that where a person who is a Judge of a High Court is  appointed, to be the Commissioner such appeal shall lie to the High</p>
                <p>Court exercising jurisdiction over the place in which the registered  office of the concerned company is situated and such appeal shall be  heard and disposed of by not less than two Judges of that High Court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <section id="section-22">
              <num>22.</num>
              <heading>Disbursement of money by Commissioner. After admitting a  claim under this Act, the amount due in respect of such claim shall be  paid by the Commissioner to the person or persons to whom such amount  is due, and on such payment, the liability of each of the two  companies in respect of such claim shall stand discharged.</heading>
            </section>
            <section id="section-23">
              <num>23.</num>
              <heading>Disbursement of amounts to the companies.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-23.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>If, out of the  moneys paid to him in relation to the undertakings of either of the  two companies, there is a balance left after meeting the liabilities  as specified in the Second Schedule, the Commissioner shall disburse  such balance to the concerned company.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-23.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Where the possession of any machinery, equipment or other  property has vested in the Central Government or the existing, or new,</p>
                  <p>Government company under this Act, but such machinery, equipment or  other property does not belong to either of the two companies, it  shall be lawful for the Central Government or the existing, or new,</p>
                  <p>Government company, as the case may be, to continue to possess such  machinery or equipment or other property on the same terms and  conditions under which they were possessed by either of the two  companies immediately before the appointed day.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-24">
              <num>24.</num>
              <heading>Undisbursed or unclaimed amount to be deposited with the  general revenue account. Any money paid to the Commissioner which  remains undisbursed or unclaimed on the date immediately preceding  the date on which the office of the Commissioner is finally wound up,</heading>
              <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>shall be, transferred by the Commissioner, before his office is  finally wound up, to the general revenue account of the Central</p>
                  <p>Government; but a claim to any money so transferred may he preferred  to the Central Government by the person entitled to such payment and  shall be dealt with as if such transfer had not been made, and the  order, if any, for the payment of the claim being treated as an order  for the refund of revenue.</p>
                  <p>CHAP</p>
                  <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </section>
            <chapter id="chapter-VII">
              <num>VII</num>
              <paragraph id="chapter-VII.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-25">
                <num>25.</num>
                <heading>Act to have over- riding effect. The provisions of this Act  shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith  contained in any other law for the time being in force or in any  instrument having effect by virtue of any law, other than this Act, or  in any decree or order of any court, tribunal or other authority.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-26">
                <num>26.</num>
                <heading>Contracts to cease to have effect unless ratified by the</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Central Government or existing, or New, Government company. Every  contract entered into by either of the two companies in relation to  any of its undertakings which has vested in the Central Government  under section 3 for any service, sale or supply, and in force  immediately before the appointed, day, shall, on and from the expiry  of a period of one hundred and eighty days from such day, cease to  have effect unless such contract is, before the expiry of that period,</p>
                    <p>ratified, in writing, by the Central Government or the existing, or  new, Government company and in ratifying such contract, the Central</p>
                    <p>Government or the existing, or new, Government company may make such  alteration or modification therein as it may think fit:</p>
                    <p>Provided that the Central Government or the existing, or new,</p>
                    <blockList id="section-26.paragraph-0.list5">
                      <listIntroduction>Government company shall not omit to ratify a contract and shall not  make any alteration or modification in a contract-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list5.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>unless it is satisfied that such contract is unduly onerous, or  has been entered into in bad faith, or is detrimental to the interests  of the Central Government or such Government company; and</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list5.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>except after giving the parties to the contract a reasonable oppor-</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>tunity of being beard and except after recording in writing its  reasons for refusal to ratify the contract or for making any  alteration or modification therein.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-27">
                <num>27.</num>
                <heading>Penalties. Any person who,-</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-27.paragraph-0.list0">
                      <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>having in his possession, custody or control any property forming  part of any undertaking of either of the two companies, wrongfully  withholds such property from the Central Government or the existing,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-27.paragraph-0.list2">
                      <listIntroduction>or new, Government company; or</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>wrongfully obtains possession of, or retains, any property forming  part of any undertaking of either of the two companies; or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list2.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>wilfully withholds or fails to furnish to the Central Government or  the existing, or new, Government company or any person or body of  persons specified by that Government or Government company, any  document relating to such undertaking, which may be in his posses-</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-27.paragraph-0.list4">
                      <listIntroduction>sion, custody or control; or</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list4.d">
                        <num>(d)</num>
                        <p>fails to deliver to the Central Government or the existing, or  new, Government company, as the case may be, or any person or body of  persons specified by that Government, or Government company, any  assets, books of account, registers or other documents in his  possession, custody or control, relating to the undertakings of either  of the two companies; or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list4.e">
                        <num>(e)</num>
                        <p>wrongfully removes or destroys any property forming part of any  undertaking of either of the two companies or prefers any claim which  he knows or has reasonable cause to believe to be false or grossly  inaccurate.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to  two years, or with fine which may extend to ten thousand rupees, or  with both.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-28">
                <num>28.</num>
                <heading>Offences by companies.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-28.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Where an offence under this Act  has been committed by a company, every person who, at the time the  offence was committed, was in charge of, and was responsible to, the  company for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as the  company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be  liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly-:</p>
                    <p>Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render  any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the  offence was committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised  all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-28.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where  any offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is  proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or  connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any  director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such  director, manager, secretary or other</p>
                    <p>officer shall be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be  liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.</p>
                    <blockList id="section-28.2.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-28.2.list3.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm or other  association of individuals; and</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-28.2.list3.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner in the firm.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-29">
                <num>29.</num>
                <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-29.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>No suit,</p>
                    <p>prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central</p>
                    <p>Government or the existing, or new, Government company or any officer  or other employee of that Government or the Government company or any  person authorised by that Government or Government company for  anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this</p>
                    <p>Act.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-29.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>No suit, or other legal proceeding, shall lie against the</p>
                    <p>Central Government or the existing, or new, Government company, or any  officer or other employee of that Government or Government company or  any person authorised by that Government or Government company for any  damage caused or likely to be caused by anything which is in good  faith done or intended to be done under this Act.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-30">
                <num>30.</num>
                <heading>Delegation of powers.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-30.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Central Government may, by  notification, direct that all or any of the powers exercisable by it  under this Act, other than the powers conferred by this section,</p>
                    <p>section 31 or section 32, may also be exercised by such person or  persons as may be specified in the notification.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-30.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Whenever any delegation of power is made under sub- section</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-30.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>, the person to whom such power has been delegated shall act under  the direction, control and supervision of the Central Government.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-31">
                <num>31.</num>
                <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-31.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Central Government may, by  notification, make rules for carrying out the provisions of this Act.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-31.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-31.2.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the  foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the  following matters, namely:-</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-31.2.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>the time within which, and the manner in which, an intimation  referred to in sub- section (3) of section 4 shall be given;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-31.2.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>the manner in which the moneys in any provident fund or other fund  referred to in section 14 shall be dealt with;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-31.2.list1.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>any other matter which is required to be, or may be, prescribed.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-31.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act  shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House  of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty  days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more  successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session  immediately following the session or the successive sessions  aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or  both Houses agree that the rule should not he made, the rule shall  thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect,</p>
                    <p>as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or  annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything  previously done under that rule.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-33">
                <num>33.</num>
                <heading>Repeal and saving.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-33.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Inchek Tyres Limited and National</p>
                    <p>Rubber Manufacturers Limited (Nationalisation) Ordinance, 1984 (4 of</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-1984">
                <num>1984.</num>
                <heading/>
                <paragraph id="section-1984.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>), is hereby repealed.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-1984.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action  taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or  taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
            </chapter>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
