<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1957/44/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1957/44"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Public Employment (Requirement As To Residence) Act, 1957"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1957/44/eng@1957-12-07/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1957/44/eng@1957-12-07"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1957-12-07" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1957/44/eng@1957-12-07/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1957/44/eng@1957-12-07"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Public Employment (Requirement As To Residence) Act, 1957</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 44 OF 1957</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 7th December, 1957.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to make in pursuance of clause (3) of article 16 of the</p>
        <p>Constitution special provisions for requirement as to residence in  regard to certain classes of public employment in certain areas and to  repeal existing laws prescribing any such requirement.</p>
        <p>Be it enacted by Parliament in the Eighth Year of the Republic of</p>
        <p>India as follows:-</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Short title and commencement. This Act may be called the</p>
            <p>Public Employment (Requirement as to Residence) Act, 1957.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into force on such date  as the Central</p>
            <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Repeal of existing laws prescribing requirements as to  residence. Upon the commencement of this Act, any law then in force in  any State or Union territory by virtue of clause (b) of article 35 of  the Constitution prescribing, in regard to a class or classes of  employment or appointment to an office under the Government of, or any  local or other authority within, that State or Union territory, any  requirement as to residence therein prior to such employment or  appointment shall cease to have effect and is hereby repealed.</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading/>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Power to make rules in respect of certain classes of public  employment in certain areas. The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules prescribing, in  regard to appointments to-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>any subordinate service or post under the State</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Government of Andhra Pradesh, or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>any subordinate service, or post under the control of the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Administrator of Himachal Pradesh, Manipur or Tripura, or</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list5.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>any service or post under a  local or other authority]</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>(other than a cantonment board) within the Telangana</p>
            <p>area of Andhra Pradesh or within the Union territory of</p>
            <p>Himachal Pradesh, Manipur or Tripura,</p>
            <p>any requirement as to residence within' the Telangana area or the said</p>
            <p>Union territory, as the case may be, prior to such appointment.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this section,-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>" Himachal Pradesh" includes the territories  specified in sub- section (1) of section 5 of the Punjab</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Reorganisation Act, 1966;] (31 of 1966).</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list3.aa">
                <num>(aa)</num>
                <p>]" subordinate service or post" means any service or post  appointments to which are not notified in the Official</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Gazette but includes any service of tehsildars;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list5.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>" Telangana area" comprises all the territories specified in  sub- section (1) of section 3 of the States</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Reorganisation Act, 1956. (37 of 1956).</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Parliamentary scrutiny of rules. Every rule made under this</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each</p>
            <p>House of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of  thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two successive  sessions, and if before the expiry of the session in which it is so  laid or the session immediately following, both Houses agree in  making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the  rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in  such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however  that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to  the validity of anything previously done under that rule.]</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Duration of Section 3 and rules. Section 3 and all rules made  thereunder shall cease to have effect on the expiration of  fifteen  years] from the commencement of this Act, but such cesser shall not  affect the validity of any appointment previously made in pursuance of  the said rules.</heading>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
