<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-asm/act/1951/1/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-asm/act/1951/1"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Assam Drugs (Control) Act, 1950"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-asm/act/1951/1/eng@2016-12-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-asm/act/1951/1/eng@2016-12-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-12-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-asm/act/1951/1/eng@2016-12-19/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-asm/act/1951/1/eng@2016-12-19"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-12-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Assam Drugs (Control) Act, 1950</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <longTitle>
        <p>(Assam Act I of 1951)</p>
        <p>Preamble</p>
        <p>An Act to provide for the control of the sale, supply and distribution of drugs</p>
        <p>Whereas it is expedient to control the sale, supply and distribution of drugs;</p>
        <p>It is hereby enacted as follows:</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title, extent and commencement.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-1.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Assam Drugs (Control) Act, 1950.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It extends to the whole of the State of Assam.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-1.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall come into ce at once.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Interpretation.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context -</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>"dealer" means a person carrying on, either personally or through any other person, the business of selling any drugs whether wholesale or retail;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>"drugs" means any drug as defined in Cl. (b) of S. 3 of the Drugs Act, 1940 (Act XXIII of 1943), in respect of which a declaration has been made under S. 3;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>"offer sale" includes a reference to an intimation by a person of the price proposed by him for sale of any drug, made by the publication of a price list, by exposing the drug sale in association with a mark indicating price, by the furnishing of a quotation or otherwise howsoever;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>"producer" includes a manufacturer;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A drug shall be deemed to be in the possession of a person -</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>when it is held on behalf of that person by another person or when held by that person on behalf of another person;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.2.list1.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>notwithstanding that it is mortgaged to another person.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Drugs to which this Act applies.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-3.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification in the official Gazette, declare any drug to be a drug to which this Act shall apply.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Fixing of maximum prices and maximum quantities which may be held or sold.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification in the</p>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list2">
              <listIntroduction>official Gazette, fix in respect of any drugs-</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the maximum price or rate which may be charged by a dealer or producer;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the maximum quantity which may at any one time be possessed by a dealer or producer;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the maximum quantity which may in any one transaction be sold to any person.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The prices or rates and the quantities fixed in respect of any drug under this section may be different in different localities or for different classes of dealers or producers.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Restrictions of sale, etc., where maximum is fixed under S. 4.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>No dealer or producer shall -</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>sell, agree to sell, offer sale, or otherwise dispose of to any person any drug for a price or at a rate exceeding the maximum fixed by notification under Cl. (a) of sub-S. (1) of S. 4;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>have in his possession at any time a quantity of any drug exceeding the maximum fixed by notification under Cl. (b) of sub-S. (1) of S. 4; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>sell, agree to sell or offer sale to any person in any one transaction a quantity of any drugs exceeding the maximum fixed by notification under Cl. (c) of sub-S. (1) of S. 4.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>General limitation on quantity which may be possessed at one time.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No person shall have in his possession at any one time a greater quantity of any drug to which this section applied than the quantity necessary for his reasonable needs.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>This section shall apply only to such drugs as the State Government may, by order published in the official Gazette, specify for the purpose:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing contained in this section shall apply to a dealer or producer in respect of any drug sold or produced by him.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Duty to declare possession of excess stocks.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any person having in his possession a quantity of any drug exceeding that permitted by or under this Act shall forthwith report the fact to the State Government or other officer empowered in this behalf by the State Government and shall take such action as to the storage, distribution or disposal of the excess quantity as the State Government may direct.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Refusal to sell.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-8.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No dealer or producer shall, unless previously authorized to do so by the State Government without sufficient cause, refuse to sell to any person any drug within the limits as to quantity, if any, imposed by this Act.</p>
            <p>Explanation.</p>
            <p>The possibility or expectation of obtaining a higher price for drug at a later date shall not be deemed to be a sufficient cause the purpose of this section.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Cash memorandum to be given of certain sales.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every dealer or producer when selling any drug for cash shall, if the amount of the purchase is five rupees or more, in all cases, and, if the amount of the purchase is less than five rupees, when so requested by the purchaser, give to the purchaser a cash memorandum containing particulars of the transaction.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification in the official Gazette, prescribe the particulars to be contained in any such memorandum.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may, by notification in the official Gazette, exempt, specified areas, classes of dealers or producers or classes of drugs from operation of this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Marking of prices and exhibiting price list.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may direct dealers or producers in general, or any dealer or producers in general, or any dealer or producer in particular, to mark any drug exposed or intended for sale with the sale price or to exhibit on the premises a price list of drugs held for sale, and may further give directions as to the manner in which any such direction as aforesaid is to be carried out.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No dealer shall destroy, efface or alter any label or mark affixed to drug and indicating the price marked by a producer.</p>
            <p>Under this section the Government is empowered to direct dealers or producers, to mark the drug with the sale prices or exhibit on the premises prices list of drugs held for sale.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Obligation to state price separately on composite offer.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where a dealer or producer, makes an offer to enter into a transaction for a consideration to be given as a whole in respect both of a sale of any drug and of some other matter, the dealer or producer making the offer shall state in writing the price which he assigns to that drug, if he is required to do so by any person to whom the offer is made, and the offer shall be deemed for the purposes of this Act to be an offer to sell that drug at the price so stated.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Prohibition or regulation of the disposal of drugs.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1">
              <listIntroduction>If in the opinion of the State Government it is necessary or expedient so to do, they may, by order in writing -</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>prohibit the disposal of any drug except in such circumstances and under such conditions as may be specified in the order;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-12.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>direct the sale of any drug to such dealer or class of dealers and in such quantities as may be specified in the order.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>and make such further orders as appear to them to be necessary or expedient in connection with any order issued under this section.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Penalties.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-13.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Whoever contravenes and of the provisions of this Act, fails to comply with any direction made under authority conferred by this Act, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years or with fine or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A Court convicting any person of an offence punishable under this Act may order that the whole or any part of the stock of drugs in respect of which the offence committed shall be forfeited to the Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-13.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>It shall be a defence for a person charged with a contravention of any of the provisions of this section to prove that, in relation to the matter in respect of which he is charged, he acted in the course of his employment as a servant or agent of another person on the instructions of his employers or of some other specified person.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Offence by Corporations.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Where a person committing an offence punishable under this Act is a company or an association or a body of persons, whether incorporated or not, every Director, Manager, Secretary, Agent or other officer or person concerned with the management thereof, shall, unless he proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or that he has exercised all due diligence to prevent its commission, be deemed to be guilty of such offence.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Procedure.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No person other than a Police Officer of or above the rank of an Inspector of Police or an Officer not below the rank of an Inspector of Police authorised in this behalf by the State Government by notification in the official Gazette, shall investigate any offence under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No prosecution for any offence punishable under this Act shall be instituted except with the previous sanction of the District Magistrate.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Powers of search and seizure.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any person competent to investigate any offence under this Act may search any place in which he has reason to believe that an offence under this Act has bee, or is being committed and take possession of any stock of drugs in respect of which the offence has been or is being committed and the provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (Act V of 1898), shall so far as may be applicable apply to any search and seizure under this Act as they apply to any search or seizure made under the authority of a warrant issued under S. 98 of that Code.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
        <subsection id="section-17.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The State Government may make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-17.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of</p>
            <blockList id="section-17.2.list2">
              <listIntroduction>the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters namely:</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-17.2.list2.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the maintenance by dealers and producers generally, or by any dealer or producer in particular, of records of all sale and purchases transactions made by them;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list2.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the furnishing of any information as may be required with respect to the business carried on by any dealer or producer;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-17.2.list2.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the inspection of any books of account or other documents belonging to, or under the control of, any dealer or producer.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any person for anything in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Saving of other laws.</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The provisions of this Act shall be in addition to and not in derogation of any other law for the time being in force regulating any of the matters dealt with in this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
