<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1955/57/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1955/57"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Citizenship Act, 1955"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1955/57/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1955/57/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1955/57/eng@1980-01-01/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1955/57/eng@1980-01-01"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-12-19" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Citizenship Act, 1955</shortTitle>
      </p>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Short title.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>This Act may be called the Citizenship Act, 1955.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Interpretation.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-2.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“a Government in India” means the Central Government or a State Government;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.1.list1.b.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>“illegal migrant” means a foreigner who has entered into India—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.1.list1.b.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>without a valid passport or other travel documents and such other document or authority as may be prescribed by or under any law in that behalf; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-2.1.list1.b.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>with a valid passport or other travel documents and such other document or authority as may be prescribed by or under any law in that behalf but remains therein beyond the permitted period of time;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>“Indian consulate” means the office of any consular officer of the Government of India where a register of births is kept, or where there is no such office, such office as may be prescribed;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <blockList id="section-2.1.list1.e.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>“minor” means a person who has not attained the age of eighteen years:</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-2.1.list1.e.list1.ee">
                    <num>(ee)</num>
                    <p>“overseas citizen of India” means a person registered as an overseas citizen of India by the Central Government under section 7A;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>“person” does not include any company or association or body of individuals, whether incorporated or not;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-2.1.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act;</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-2.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>***</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-2.1.list3.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>“undivided India” means India as defined in the Government of India Act, 1935, as originally enacted.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Statement of Objects and Reasons The Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 2005</p>
            <p>To expand the scope of grant of Overseas Citizenship of India to Persons of Indian Origin of all countries except Pakistan and Bangladesh.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purposes of this Act, a person born aboard a regis­tered ship or aircraft, or aboard an unregistered ship or air­craft of the Government of any country, shall be deemed to have been born in the place in which the ship or aircraft was regis­tered or, as the case may be, in that country.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any reference in this Act to the status or description of the father of a person at the time of that person’s birth shall, in relation to a person born after the death of his father, be construed as a reference to the status or description of the father at the time of the father’s death; and where that death occurred before, and the birth occurs after, the commencement of this Act, the status or description which would have been appli­cable to the father had he died after the commencement of this Act shall be deemed to be the status or description applicable to him at the time of his death.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-2.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purposes of this Act, a person shall be deemed to be of full age if he is not a minor and of full capacity if he is not of unsound mind.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Citizenship by birth.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-3.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Except as provided in sub-section (2), every person born in India,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>on or after the 26th day of January, 1950, but before the 1st day of July, 1987;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>on or after the 1st day of July, 1987, but before the commencement of the Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 2003 and either of whose parents is a citizen of India at the time of his birth;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <blockList id="section-3.1.list1.c.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>on or after the commencement of the Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 2003, where—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-3.1.list1.c.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>both of his parents are citizens of India; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-3.1.list1.c.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>one of whose parents is a citizen of India and the other is not an illegal migrant at the time of his birth,</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall be a citizen of India by birth.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-3.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-3.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A person shall not be a citizen of India by virtue of this sec­tion if at the time of his birth—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>either his father or mother possesses such immunity from suits and legal process as is accorded to an envoy of a foreign sovereign power accredited to the President of India and he or she, as the case may be, is not a citizen of India; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-3.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>his father or mother is an enemy alien and the birth occurs in a place then under occupation by the enemy.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Citizenship by descent.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-4.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A person born outside India shall be a citizen of India by descent,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>on or after the 26th day of January, 1950, but before the 10th day of December, 1992, if his father is a citizen of India at the time of his birth; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>on or after the 10th day of December, 1992, if either of his parents is a citizen of India at the time of his birth:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that if the father of a person referred to in clause (a) was a citizen of India by descent only, that person shall not be a citizen of India by virtue of this section un­less—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>his birth is registered at an Indian consulate within one year of its occurrence or the commencement of this Act, whichever is later, or, with the permission of the Central Government, after the expiry of the said period; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>his father is, at the time of his birth, in service under a Government in India:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list5">
              <listIntroduction>Provided further that if either of the parents of a person referred to in clause (b) was a citizen of India by descent only, that person shall not be a citizen of India by virtue of this section un­less—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list5.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>his birth is registered at an Indian consulate within one year of its occurrence or on or after the 10th day of December, 1992, whichever is later, or, with the permission of the Central Government, after the expiry of the said period; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list5.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>either of his parents is, at the time of his birth, in service under a Government in India:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-4.1.list7">
              <listIntroduction>Provided also that on or after the commencement of the Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 2003, a person shall not be a citizen of India by virtue of this section, unless his birth is registered at an Indian consulate in such form and in such manner, as may be prescribed,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-4.1.list7.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>within one year of its occurrence or the commencement of the Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 2003, whichever is later; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-4.1.list7.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>with the permission of the Central Government, after the expiry of the said period:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Provided also that no such birth shall be registered unless the parents of such person declare, in such form and in such manner as may be prescribed, that the minor does not hold the passport of another country.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.1A">
          <num>(1A)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A minor who is a citizen of India by virtue of his section and is also a citizen of any other country shall cease to be a citizen of India if he does not renounce the citizenship or nationality of another country within six months of attaining full age.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the Central Government so directs, a birth shall be deemed for the purposes of this section to have been registered with its permission, notwithstanding that its permission was not obtained before the registration.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-4.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>For the purposes of the proviso to sub-section (1), any</p>
            <p>person born outside undivided India who was, or was deemed to be, a citizen of India at the commencement of the Constitution shall be deemed to be a citizen of India by descent only.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Citizenship by registration.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-5.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-5.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Subject to the provisions of this section and such other conditions and restrictions as may be prescribed, the Central Government may, on an application made in this behalf, register as a citizen of India any person not being an illegal migrant who is not already such citizen by virtue of the Constitution or of any other provision of this Act if he belongs to any of the following categories, namely:—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>a person of Indian origin who are ordinarily resident in India for seven years before making an application for registration;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>a person of Indian origin who is ordinarily resident in any country or place outside undivided India;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>a person who is married to a citizen of India and is ordinarily resident in India for seven years before making an application for registration;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>minor children of persons who are citizens of India;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>a person of full age and capacity whose parents are registered as citizens of India under clause (a) of this sub-section or sub-section (1) of section 6;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>a person of full age and capacity who, or either of his parents, was earlier citizen of independent India, and has been residing in India for one year immediately before making an application for registration;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>a person of full age and capacity who has been registered as an overseas citizen of India for five years, and who has been residing in India for</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>one year before making an application for registration. 3one year before making an application for registration."</p>
            <p>Statement of Objects and Reasons [The Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 2005</p>
            <p>To reduce the period of residence in India from two years to one year for the persons registered as Overseas Citizens of India to acquire Indian citizenship.</p>
            <p>Explanation 1.—</p>
            <blockList id="section-5.1.list7">
              <listIntroduction>For the purposes of clauses (a) and (c), an applicant shall be deemed to be ordinarily resident in India if—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-5.1.list7.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>he has resided in India throughout the period of twelve months immediately before making an application for registration; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-5.1.list7.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>he has resided in India during the eight years immediately preceding the said period of twelve months for a period of not less than six years.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Explanation 2.—</p>
            <p>For the purposes of this sub-section, a person shall be deemed to be of Indian origin if he, or either of his parents, was born in undivided India or in such other territory which became part of India after the 15th day of August, 1947.]</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No person being of full age shall be registered as a citizen of India under sub-section (1) until he has taken the oath of allegiance in the form specified in the Second Schedule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>No person who has renounced, or has been deprived of, his Indian citizenship or whose Indian citizenship has terminated, under this Act shall be registered as a citizen of India under sub-section (1) except by order of the Central Government.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, if satisfied that there are special circumstances justifying such registration, cause any minor to be registered as a citizen of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A person registered under this section shall be a citizen of India by registration as from the date on which he is so regis­tered; and a person registered under the provisions of clause(b)(ii) of article 6 or article 8 of the Constitution shall be deemed to be a citizen of India by registration as from the commencement of the Constitution or the date on which he was so registered, whichever may be later.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-5.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the Central Government is satisfied that circumstances exist which render it necessary to grant exemption from the residential requirement under clause (c) of sub-section (1) to any person or a class of persons, it may, for reasons to be recorded in writing, grant such exemption.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Citizenship by naturalisation.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where an application is made in the prescribed manner by any person of full age and capacity</p>
            <p>not being an illegal migrant for the grant of a certificate of naturalisation to him, the Central Government may, if satisfied that the applicant is quali­fied for naturalisation under the provisions of the Third Sched­ule, grant to him a certificate of naturalisation:</p>
            <p>Provided that, if in the opinion of the Central Government, the applicant is a person who has rendered distinguished service to the cause of science, philosophy, art, literature, world peace or human progress generally, it may waive all or any of the condi­tions specified in the Third Schedule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The person to whom a certificate of naturalisation is granted under sub-section (1) shall, on taking the oath of allegiance in the form specified in the Second Schedule, be a citizen of India by naturalisation as from the date on which that certificate is granted.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6A">
        <num>6A.</num>
        <heading>Special provisions as to citizenship of persons covered by the Assam Accord.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-6A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6A.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>For the purposes of this section—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6A.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>“Assam” means the territories included in the State of Assam immediately before the commencement of the Citizenship (Amend­ment) Act, 1985;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6A.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>“detected to be a foreigner” means detected to be a foreigner in accordance with the provisions of the Foreigners Act, 1946 (31 of 1946) and the Foreigners (Tribunals) Order, 1964 by a Trib­unal constituted under the said Order;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6A.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>“specified territory” means the territories included in Bangladesh immediately before the commencement of the Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 1985;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6A.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>a person shall be deemed to be of Indian origin, if he, or either of his parents for any of his grandparents was born in undivided India;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6A.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>a person shall be deemed to have been detected to be a for­eigner on the date on which a Tribunal constituted under the Foreigners (Tribunals) Order, 1964 submits its opinion to the effect that he is a foreigner to the officer or authority con­cerned.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of sub-sections (6) and (7), all persons of Indian origin who came before the 1st day of January, 1966 to Assam from the specified territory (including such of those whose names were included in the electoral rolls used for the purposes of the General Election to the House of the People held in 1967) and who have been ordinarily resident in Assam since the dates of their entry into Assam shall be deemed to be citizens of India as from the 1st day of January, 1966.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6A.3.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Subject to the provisions of sub-sections (6) and (7), every person of Indian origin who—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6A.3.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>came to Assam on or after the lst day of January, 1966 but before the 25th day of March, 1971 from the specified territory; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6A.3.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>has, since the date of his entry into Assam, been ordinarily resident in Assam; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6A.3.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>has been detected to be a foreigner,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>shall register himself in accordance with the rules made by the Central Government in this behalf under section 18 with such authority (thereafter in this sub-section referred to as the registering authority) as may be specified in such rules and if his name is included in any electoral roll for any Assembly or Parliamentary constituency in force on the date of such detec­tion, his name shall be deleted therefrom.</p>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <blockList id="section-6A.3.list5">
              <listIntroduction>In the case of every person seeking registration under this sub-section, the opinion of the Tribunal constituted under the Foreigners (Tribunals) Order, 1964 holding such person to be a foreigner, shall be deemed to be sufficient proof of the requirement under clause (c) of this sub-section and if any question arises as to whether such person complies with any other requirement under this sub-section, the registering authority shall,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6A.3.list5.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>if such opinion contains a finding with respect to such other requirement, decide the question in conformity with such finding;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6A.3.list5.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>if such opinion does not contain a finding with respect to such other requirement, refer the question to a Tribunal consti­tuted under the said Order hang jurisdiction in accordance with such rules as the Central Government may make in this behalf under section 18 and decide the question in conformity with the opinion received on such reference.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6A.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A person registered under sub-section (3) shall have, as from the date on which he has been detected to be a foreigner and till the expiry of a period of ten years from that date, the same rights and obligations as a citizen of India (including the right to obtain a passport under the Passports Act, 1967 (15 of 1967) and the obligations connected therewith), but shall not be enti­tled to have his name included in any electoral roll for any Assembly or Parliamentary constituency at any time before the expiry of the said period of ten years.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6A.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>A person registered under sub-section (3) shall be deemed to be a citizen of India for all purposes as from the date of expiry of a period of ten years from the date on which he has been detected to be a foreigner.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6A.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6A.6.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Without prejudice to the provisions of section 8,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6A.6.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>if any person referred to in sub-section (2) submits in the prescribed manner and form and to the prescribed authority within sixty days from the date of commencement of the Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 1985, for year a declaration that he does not wish to be a citizen of India, such person shall not be deemed to have become a citizen of India under that sub-section;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6A.6.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>If any person referred to in sub-section (3) submits in the prescribed manner and form and to the prescribed authority within sixty days from the date of commencement the Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 1985, for year or from the date on which he has been detect­ed to be a foreigner, whichever is later, a declaration that he does not wish to be governed by the provisions of that sub-sec­tion and sub-sections (4) and (5), it shall not be necessary for such person to register himself under sub-section (3).</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>Explanation.—</p>
            <p>Where a person required to file a declaration under this sub-section does not have the capacity to enter into a contract, such declaration may be filed on his behalf by any person competent under the law for the time being in force to act on his behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6A.7">
          <num>(7)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-6A.7.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Nothing in sub-sections (2) to (6) shall apply in relation to any person—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-6A.7.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>who, immediately before the commencement of the Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 1985, for year is a citizen of India;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-6A.7.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>who was expelled from India before the commencement of the Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 1985, for year under the Foreigners Act, 1946 (31 of 1946).</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-6A.8">
          <num>(8)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Save as otherwise expressly provided in this section, the provisions of this section shall have effect notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being in force.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Citizenship by incorporation of territory.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>If any territory becomes a part of India, the Central Government may, by order notified in the Official Gazette, specify the persons who shall be citizens of India by reason of their connection with that territory; and those persons shall be citizens of India as from the date to be specified in the order.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7A">
        <num>7A.</num>
        <heading>Registration of overseas citizens of India. —</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7A.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>The Central Government may, subject to such conditions and restrictions as may be prescribed, on an application made in this behalf, register any person as an overseas citizen of India—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7A.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-7A.1.list1.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>any person of full age and capacity,—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-7A.1.list1.a.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <p>who is citizen of another country, but was a citizen of India at the time of, or at any time after, the commencement of the Constitution; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-7A.1.list1.a.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>who is citizen of another country, but was eligible to become a citizen of India at the time of the commencement of the Constitution; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-7A.1.list1.a.list0.iii">
                    <num>(iii)</num>
                    <p>who is citizen of another country, but belonged to a territory that became part of India after the 15th day of August, 1947; or</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-7A.1.list1.a.list0.iv">
                    <num>(iv)</num>
                    <p>who is a child or a grand-child of such a citizen; or</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7A.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>a person, who is a minor child of a person mentioned in clause (a):</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-7A.1.list3">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that no person, who is or had been a citizen of Pakistan, Bangladesh or such other country as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify, shall be eligible for registration as an overseas citizen of India.</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7A.1.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>grant of multiple entry lifelong visa for visiting India for any purpose;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7A.1.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>exemption from registration with Foreign Regional Registration Officer or Foreign Registration Officer for any length of stay in India ; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7A.1.list3.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>parity with Non-Resident Indians in respect of all facilities available to them in economic, financial and educational fields except in matters relating to the acquisition of agricultural or plantation properties.</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7A.1.list3.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-7A.1.list3.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>parity with non-resident Indian in respect of,—</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-7A.1.list3.a.list0.i">
                    <num>(i)</num>
                    <blockList id="section-7A.1.list3.a.list0.i.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>entry fees to be charged for visiting the national monuments, historical sites and museums in India ;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-7A.1.list3.a.list0.i.list1.i">
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <p>doctors, dentists, nurses and pharmacists;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-7A.1.list3.a.list0.i.list1.ii">
                        <num>(ii)</num>
                        <p>advocates;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-7A.1.list3.a.list0.i.list1.iii">
                        <num>(iii)</num>
                        <p>architects;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-7A.1.list3.a.list0.i.list1.iv">
                        <num>(iv)</num>
                        <p>chartered accountants;</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </item>
                  <item id="section-7A.1.list3.a.list0.ii">
                    <num>(ii)</num>
                    <p>pursuing the following professions in India , in pursuance of the provisions contained in the relevant Acts, namely:—</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7A.1.list3.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>to appear for the All India Pre-Medical Test or such other tests to make them eligible for admission in pursuance of the provisions contained in the relevant Acts.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7B">
        <num>7B.</num>
        <heading>Conferment of rights on overseas citizens of India.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7B.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Notwith-standing anything contained in any other law for the time being in force, an overseas citizen of India shall be entitled to such rights other than the rights specified under sub-section (2) as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7B.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7B.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>An overseas citizen of India shall not be entitled to the rights conferred on a citizen of India—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7B.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>under article 16 of the Constitution with regard to equality of opportunity in matters of public employment;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7B.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>under article 58 of the Constitution for election as President:</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7B.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>under article 66 of the Constitution for election of Vice-President;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7B.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>under article 124 of the Constitution for appointment as a Judge of the Supreme Court;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7B.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>under article 217 of the Constitution for appointment as a Judge of the High Court;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7B.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>under section 16 of the Representation of the People Act, 1950 (43 of 1950) in regard to registration as a voter;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7B.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>under sections 3 and 4 of the Representation of the People Act, 1951 (43 of 1951) with regard to the eligibility for being a member of the House of the People or of the Council of States, as the case may be;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7B.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>under sections 5, 5A and 6 of the Representation of the People Act, 1951 (43 of 1951) with regard to the eligibility for being a member of the Legislative Assembly or a Legislative Council, as the case may be, of a State;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7B.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>for appointment to public services and posts in connection with the affairs of the Union or of any State except for appointment in such services and posts as the Central Government may by special order in that behalf specify.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7B.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every notification issued under sub-section (1) shall be laid before each House of Parliament.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7C">
        <num>7C.</num>
        <heading>Renunciation of overseas citizenship.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-7C.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any overseas citizen of India of full age and capacity makes in the prescribed manner a declaration renouncing his overseas citizenship of India, the declaration shall be registered by the Central Government, and; upon such registration, that person shall cease to be an overseas citizen of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-7C.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where a person ceases to be an overseas citizen of India under sub-section (1), every minor child of that person registered as an overseas citizen of India, shall thereupon cease to be an overseas citizen of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7D">
        <num>7D.</num>
        <heading>Cancellation of registration as overseas citizen of India.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-7D.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by order, cancel the registration granted under sub-section</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-7D.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-7D.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>of section 7A if it is satisfied that—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-7D.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the registration as an overseas citizen of India was obtained by means of fraud, false representation or the concealment of any material fact; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7D.1.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the overseas citizen of India has shown disaffection towards the Constitution of India as by law established; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7D.1.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the overseas citizen of India has, during any war in which India may be engaged, unlawfully traded or communicated with an enemy or been engaged in, or associated with, any business or commercial activity that was to his knowledge carried on in such manner as to assist an enemy in that war; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7D.1.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the overseas citizen of India has, within five years after registration under sub-section (1) of section 7A has been sentenced to imprisonment for a term of not less than two years; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-7D.1.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>it is necessary so to do in the interest of the sovereignty and integrity of India, the security of India, friendly relations of India with any foreign country, or in the interests of the general public.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Renunciation of citizenship.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-8.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any citizen of India of full age and capacity,</p>
            <p>*** makes in the prescribed manner a declaration renouncing his Indian Citizenship, the declaration shall be registered by the prescribed authority; and, upon such registra­tion, that person shall cease to be a citizen of India:</p>
            <p>Provided that if any such declaration is made during any war in which India may be engaged, registration thereof shall be with­held until the Central Government otherwise directs.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-8.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Where</p>
            <p>a person ceases to be a citizen of India under sub-section (1) every minor child of that person shall thereupon cease to be a citizen of India:</p>
            <p>Provided that any such child may, within one year after attaining full age, make a declaration</p>
            <p>in the prescribed form and manner that he wishes to resume Indian citizenship and shall thereupon again become a citizen of India.</p>
            <p>***</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Termination of citizenship.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-9.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any citizen of India who by naturalisation, registration or otherwise voluntarily acquires, or has at any time between the 26th January, 1950 and the commence­ment of this Act, voluntarily acquired the citizenship of another country shall, upon such acquisition or, as the case may be, such commencement, cease to be a citizen of India:</p>
            <p>Provided that nothing in this sub-section shall apply to a citi­zen of India who, during any war in which India may be engaged, voluntarily acquires, the citizenship of another country, until the Central Government otherwise directs.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-9.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If any question arises as to whether, when or how any</p>
            <p>citizen of India has acquired the citizenship of another country, it shall be deter­mined by such authority, in such manner, and having regard to such rules of evidence, as may be prescribed in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>Deprivation of citizenship.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-10.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.1.list1">
              <listIntroduction>A citizen of India who is such by naturalisation or by virtue only of clause (c) of article 5 of the Constitution or by registration otherwise than under clause (b) (ii) of article 6 of the Constitution or clause</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.1.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>of sub-section (1) of section 5 of this Act, shall cease to be a citizen of India, if he is deprived of that citizenship by an order of the Central Government under this section.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-10.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>Subject to the provisions of this section, the Central Gov­ernment may, by order, deprive any such citizen of Indian citi­zenship, if it is satisfied that—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>the registration or certificate of naturalisation was ob­tained by means of fraud, false representation or the concealment of any material fact; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>that citizen has shown himself by act or speech to be dis­loyal or disaffected towards the Constitution of India as by law established; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>that citizen has, during any war in which India may be en­gaged unlawfully traded or communicated with an enemy or been engaged in, or associated with, any business that was to his knowledge carried on in such manner as to assist an enemy in that war; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>that citizen has, within five years after registration or naturalisation, been sentenced in any country to imprisonment for a term of not less than two years; or</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-10.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>that citizen has been ordinarily resident out of India for a continuous period of seven years, and during that period, has neither been at any time a student of any educational institution in a country outside India or in the service of a Government in India or of an international organisation of which India is a member, nor registered annually in the prescribed manner at an Indian consulate his intention to retain his citizenship of India.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government shall not deprive a person of citizen­ship under this section unless it is satisfied that it is not conducive to the public good that the person should continue to be a citizen of India.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Before making an order under this section, the Central Gov­ernment shall give the person against whom the order is proposed to be made notice in writing informing him of the ground on which it is proposed to be made and, if the order is proposed to be made on any of the grounds specified in sub-section (2) other than clause (e) thereof, of his right, upon making application therefor in the prescribed manner, to have his case referred to a committee of inquiry under this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>If the order is proposed to be made against a person on any of the grounds specified in sub-section (2) other than clause (e) thereof and that person so applies in the prescribed manner, the Central Government shall, and in any other case it may, refer the case to a Committee of Inquiry consisting of a chairman (being a person who has for at least ten years held a judicial office) and two other members appointed by the Central Government in this behalf.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-10.6">
          <num>(6)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Committee of Inquiry shall, on such reference, hold the inquiry in such manner as may be prescribed and submit its report to the Central Government; and the Central Government shall ordinarily be guided by such report in making an order under this section.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Commonwealth citizenship.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Rep. by the Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 2003 (6 of 2004), sec. 10.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Power to confer rights of Indian citizen or citizens of certain countries.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Rep. by the Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 2003 (6 of 2004), sec. 10.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Certificate of Citizenship in case of doubt.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-13.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, in such cases as it thinks fit, certify that a person, with respect to whose citizenship of India a doubt ex­ists, is a citizen of India; and a certificate issued under this section shall, unless it is proved that it was obtained by means of fraud, false representation or concealment of any material fact, be conclusive evidence that person was such a citizen on the date thereof, but without prejudice to any evidence that he was such a citizen at an earlier date.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Disposal of application under</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-14.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>sections 5, 6 and 7A.—</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <subsection id="section-14.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The prescribed authority or the Central Government may, in its dis­cretion, grant or refuse an application under</p>
            <p>section 5, 6 or section 7A and shall not be required to assign any reasons for such grant or refusal.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Subject to the provisions of section 15 the decision of the prescribed authority or the Central Government on any such appli­cation as aforesaid shall be final and shall not be called in question in any court.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14A">
        <num>14A.</num>
        <heading>Issue of national identity cards.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-14A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may compulsorily register every citizen of India and issue national identity card to him.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may maintain a National Register of Indian Citizens and for that purpose establish a National Registration Authority.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14A.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On and from the date of commencement of the Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 2003, the Registrar General, India, appointed under sub-section (1) of section 3 of the Registration of Births and Deaths Act, 1969 (18 of 1969) shall act as the National Registration Authority and he shall function as the Registrar General of Citizen Registration.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14A.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may appoint such other officers and staff as may be required to assist the Registrar General of Citizen Registration in discharging his functions and responsibilities.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-14A.5">
          <num>(5)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The procedure to be followed in compulsory registration of the citizens of India shall be such as may be prescribed.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>Revision.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person aggrieved by an order made under this Act by the prescribed authority or any officer or other authority (other than the Central Government) may, within a period of thirty days from the date of the order, make an appli­cation to the Central Government for revision of that order:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Central Government may entertain the applica­tion after the expiry of the said period of thirty days, if it is satisfied that the applicant was prevented by sufficient cause from making the application in time.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On receipt of any such application under sub-section (1), the Central Government shall, after considering the application of the aggrieved person and any report thereon which the officer or authority making the order may submit, make such order in rela­tion to the application as it deems fit, and the decision of the Central Government shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15A">
        <num>15A.</num>
        <heading>Review.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-15A.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Any person aggrieved by an order made by the Central Government, may within thirty days from the date of such order, make an application for review of such order:</p>
            <p>Provided that the Central Government may entertain application after the expiry of the said period of thirty days, if it is satisfied that the applicant was prevented by sufficient cause from making the application in time:</p>
            <p>Provided further that an application for a review of an order passed in terms of the provisions of section 14A shall be disposed of in the manner provided for in the procedure as may be laid down under clause (ia) of sub-section (2) of section 18.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-15A.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <p>On receipt of an application under sub-section (1), the Central Government shall, make such order as it deems fit, and the decision of the Central Government on such review shall be final.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>Delegation of power.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-16.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by order, direct that any power which is conferred on it by any of the provisions of this Act other than those of section 10 and section 18 shall, in such circumstances and under such conditions, if any, as may be specified in the order, be exercisable also by such officer or authority as may be so specified.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-17">
        <num>17.</num>
        <heading>Offences.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-17.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Any person who, for the purpose of procuring anything to be done or not to be done under this Act, knowingly makes any representation which is false in a material particular shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to</p>
            <p>five years, or</p>
            <p>with fine which may extend to fifty thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-18">
        <num>18.</num>
        <heading>Power to make rules.—</heading>
        <subsection id="section-18.1">
          <num>(1)</num>
          <content>
            <p>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.2">
          <num>(2)</num>
          <content>
            <blockList id="section-18.2.list1">
              <listIntroduction>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-18.2.list1.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <blockList id="section-18.2.list1.a.list0">
                  <listIntroduction>the registration of anything required or authorized under this Act to be registered, and the conditions and restrictions in regard to such registration;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-18.2.list1.a.list0.aa">
                    <num>(aa)</num>
                    <p>the form and manner in which a declaration under sub-section (1) of section 4 shall be made;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.2.list1.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>the forms to be used and the registers to be maintained under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.2.list1.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>the administration and taking of oaths of allegiance under this Act and the time within which, and the manner in which, such oaths shall be taken and recorded;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.2.list1.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>the giving of any notice required or authorized to be given by any person under this Act;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.2.list1.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <blockList id="section-18.2.list1.e.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>the cancellation of the registration of, and the cancellation and amendment of certificate of naturalisation relating to, persons deprived of citizenship under this Act, and the deliver­ing up of such certificates for those purposes;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-18.2.list1.e.list1.ee">
                    <num>(ee)</num>
                    <p>the manner and form in which and the authority to whom declarations referred to in clauses (a) and (b) of sub-section (b) of section 6A shall be submitted and other matters connected with such declarations;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.2.list1.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>the registration at Indian consulates of the births and deaths of persons of any class or description born or dying outside India;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.2.list1.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>the levy and collection of fees in respect of applications, registrations, declarations and certificates under this Act, in respect of the taking of an oath of allegiance, and in respect of the supply of certified or other copies of documents;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.2.list1.h">
                <num>(h)</num>
                <p>the authority to determine the question of acquisition of citizenship of another country, the procedure to be followed by such authority and rules of evidence relating to such cases;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.2.list1.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <blockList id="section-18.2.list1.i.list2">
                  <listIntroduction>the procedure to be followed by the committees of inquiry appointed under section 10 and the conferment on such committees of any of the powers, rights and privileges of civil court;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="section-18.2.list1.i.list2.ia">
                    <num>(ia)</num>
                    <p>the procedure to be followed in compulsory registration of the citizens of India under sub-section (5) of section 14A;</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.2.list1.j">
                <num>(j)</num>
                <p>the manner in which applications for revision may be made and the procedure to be followed by the Central Government in dealing with such applications; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-18.2.list1.k">
                <num>(k)</num>
                <p>any other matter which is to be, or may be, prescribed under this Act.</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.3">
          <num>(3)</num>
          <content>
            <p>In making any rule under this section, the Central Government may provide that breach thereof shall be punishable with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees:</p>
            <p>Provided that any rule made in respect of a matter specified in clause (ia) of sub-section (2) may provide that a breach thereof shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three months, or with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees, or with both.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
        <subsection id="section-18.4">
          <num>(4)</num>
          <content>
            <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
          </content>
        </subsection>
      </section>
      <section id="section-19">
        <num>19.</num>
        <heading>Repeals.—</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-19.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>Repealed by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1960 (Act 58 of 1960), sec. 2 and the First Schedule (w.e.f. 26-10-1960).</p>
            <p>The Citizenship Act, 1955</p>
            <p>***</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>The First Schedule omitted by Act 6 of 2004, sec. 16 (w.e.f. 3-12-2004).</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Citizenship Act, 1955</p>
            <p>The Second Schedule</p>
            <p>See sections 5(2) and 6(2)</p>
            <p>Oath of Allegiance</p>
            <p>I, A/B.............................do solemnly affirm (or swear) that i will bear true faith and allegiance to the Constitution of India as by law established, and that i will faithfully observe the laws of India and fulfil my duties as a citizen of India.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Subs. by Act 6 of 2004, sec. 17, for the Second Schedule (w.e.f. 3-12-2004).</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Citizenship Act, 1955</p>
            <p>The Third Schedule</p>
            <p>See section 6(1)</p>
            <p>Qualifications for naturalisation</p>
            <p>The qualifications for naturalisation of a person</p>
            <blockList id="section-1.paragraph-0.list6">
              <listIntroduction>*** are—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list6.a">
                <num>(a)</num>
                <p>that he is not a subject or citizen of any country where citizens of India are prevented by law or practice of that coun­try from becoming subjects or citizens of that country by natu­ralisation;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list6.b">
                <num>(b)</num>
                <p>that, if he is a citizen of any country,</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-1.paragraph-0.list8">
              <listIntroduction>he undertakes to renounce the citizenship of that country in the event of his application for Indian citizenship being accepted;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list8.c">
                <num>(c)</num>
                <p>that he has either resided in India or been in the service of a Government in India or partly the one and partly the other, throughout the period of twelve months immediately preceding the date of the application;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list8.d">
                <num>(d)</num>
                <p>that during the</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>fourteen years immediately preceding the said period of twelve months, he has either resided in India or been in the service of a Government in India, or partly the one and partly the other, for periods amounting in the aggregate to not less than</p>
            <blockList id="section-1.paragraph-0.list11">
              <listIntroduction>eleven years;</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list11.e">
                <num>(e)</num>
                <p>that he is of good character;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list11.f">
                <num>(f)</num>
                <p>that he has an adequate knowledge of a language specified in the Eighth Schedule to the Constitution; and</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list11.g">
                <num>(g)</num>
                <p>that in the event of a certificate of naturalisation being granted to him, he intends to reside in India, or to enter into or continue in, service under a Government in India or under an international organisation of which India is a member or under a society, company or body of persons established in India:</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <blockList id="section-1.paragraph-0.list13">
              <listIntroduction>Provided that the Central Government may, if in the special circumstances of any particular case it thinks fit,—</listIntroduction>
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list13.i">
                <num>(i)</num>
                <p>allow a continuous period of twelve months ending not more than six months before the date of the application to be reckoned, for the purposes of clause (c) above, as if it had immediately preceded that date;</p>
              </item>
              <item id="section-1.paragraph-0.list13.ii">
                <num>(ii)</num>
                <p>allow periods of residence or service earlier than</p>
              </item>
            </blockList>
            <p>fif­teen years before the date of the application to be reckoned in computing the aggregate mentioned in clause (d) above.</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>The words “who is not a citizen of a country specified in the First Schedule” omitted by Act 6 of 2004, sec. 18 (w.e.f. 3-12-2004). tc " 1. The words “who is not a citizen of a country specified in the First Schedule” omitted by Act 6 of 2004, sec. 18 (w.e.f. 3-12-2004)."</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Subs. by Act 6 of 2004, sec. 18, for “he has renounced the citizenship of that country in accordance with the law therein in force in that behalf and has notified such renunciation to the Central Government” (w.e.f. 3-12-2004). tc " 2. Subs. by Act 6 of 2004, sec. 18, for “he has renounced the citizenship of that country in accordance with the law therein in force in that behalf and has notified such renunciation to the Central Government” (w.e.f. 3-12-2004)."</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Subs. by Act 6 of 2004, sec. 18, for “twelve years” (w.e.f. 3-12-2004). tc " 3. Subs. by Act 6 of 2004, sec. 18, for “twelve years” (w.e.f. 3-12-2004)."</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>Subs. by Act 6 of 2004, sec. 18, for “nine years” (w.e.f. 3-12-2004) tc " 4. Subs. by Act 6 of 2004, sec. 18, for “nine years” (w.e.f. 3-12-2004)"</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Subs. by Act 6 of 2004, sec. 18, for “thirteen years” (w.e.f. 3-12-2004). tc " 5. Subs. by Act 6 of 2004, sec. 18, for “thirteen years” (w.e.f. 3-12-2004)."</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>The Citizenship Act, 1955</p>
            <p>***</p>
            <p>—————</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>The Fourth Schedule omitted by Act 32 of 2005, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 28-6-2005). Earlier the Fourth Schedule was inserted by Act 6 of 2004, sec. 19 (w.e.f. 3-12-2004). The Fourth Schedule, for omission, stood as under:</heading>
        <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>“The Fourth Schedule</p>
            <p>See section 2(1)(gg)</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
      </section>
      <section id="section-1">
        <num>1.</num>
        <heading>Australia</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-2">
        <num>2.</num>
        <heading>Canada</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-3">
        <num>3.</num>
        <heading>Finland</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-4">
        <num>4.</num>
        <heading>France</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-5">
        <num>5.</num>
        <heading>Greece</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-6">
        <num>6.</num>
        <heading>Ireland</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-7">
        <num>7.</num>
        <heading>Israel</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-8">
        <num>8.</num>
        <heading>Italy</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-9">
        <num>9.</num>
        <heading>Netherlands</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-10">
        <num>10.</num>
        <heading>New Zealand</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-11">
        <num>11.</num>
        <heading>Portugal</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-12">
        <num>12.</num>
        <heading>Republic of Cyprus</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-13">
        <num>13.</num>
        <heading>Sweden</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-14">
        <num>14.</num>
        <heading>Switzerland</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-15">
        <num>15.</num>
        <heading>United Kingdom</heading>
      </section>
      <section id="section-16">
        <num>16.</num>
        <heading>United States of America.”</heading>
      </section>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
