<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1986/69/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1986/69"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The State Of Arunachal Pradesh Act, 1986"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1986/69/eng@1986-12-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1986/69/eng@1986-12-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="1986-12-24" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1986/69/eng@1986-12-24/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1986/69/eng@1986-12-24"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The State Of Arunachal Pradesh Act, 1986</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 69 OF 1986</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 24th December, 1986.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty- seventh Year of the</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to provide for the establishment of the State of Arunachal</p>
        <p>Pradesh and for matters connected therewith.</p>
        <p>Republic of India as follows:--</p>
        <p>PART</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <part id="part-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="part-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title. This Act may be called the State of Arunachal</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-1.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Pradesh Act, 1986.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise  requires,--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" Administrator" means the Administrator appointed by the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>President under article 239;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" appointed day"  means the day which the Central</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" article" means an article of the Constitution;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" Election Commission" means the Election Commission  appointed by the President under article 324;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>" existing Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh" means  the Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh as existing immediately  before the appointed day;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list4.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>" law" includes any enactment, ordinance, regulation,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>order, bye- law, rule, scheme, notification or other instrument  having, immediately before the appointed day, the force of law in  the whole or any part of the existing Union territory of</p>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list7">
                <listIntroduction>Arunachal Pradesh;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list7.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>" sitting member", in relation to either House of</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Parliament or of the Legislative Assembly of the existing Union  territory of Arunachal Pradesh, means a person who, immediately  before the appointed day, is a member of that House or that</p>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10">
                <listIntroduction>Assembly;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list10.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>" treasury" includes a sub- treasury.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>ESTABLISHMENT OF THE STATE OF ARUNACHAL PRADESH</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="part-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>ESTABLISHMENT OF THE STATE OF ARUNACHAL PRADESH</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Establishment of the State of Arunachal Pradesh. On and from  the appointed day, there shall be established a new State, to be known  as the State of Arunachal Pradesh comprising the territories which  immediately before that day were comprised in the existing Union  territory of Arunachal Pradesh.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Amendment of First Schedule to the Constitution. On and from  the appointed day, in the First Schedule to the Constitution,--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-4.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>under the heading" I. THE STATES", after entry 23, the  following entry shall be inserted, namely:--</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-4.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>" 24. Arunachal Pradesh The territories specified in  section 7 of the North- Eastern Areas (Reorganisation) Act, 1971.";</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-4.paragraph-0.list2.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>under the heading" II. THE UNION TERRITORIES", entry 8  relating to Arunachal Pradesh shall be omitted.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>PART</p>
              <p>REPRESENTATION IN THE LEGISLATURES</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </part>
      <part id="part-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="part-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>REPRESENTATION IN THE LEGISLATURES</p>
            <p>The Council of States</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Amendment of Fourth Schedule to the Constitution. On and from  the appointed day, in the Fourth Schedule to the Constitution, in the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-5.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Table,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-5.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>entries 24 and 25 shall be re- numbered as entries 25 and</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-26">
          <num>26.</num>
          <heading>respectively, and before entry 25 as so re- numbered, the  following entry shall be inserted, namely:--</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-26.paragraph-0.list1">
                <listIntroduction>" 24. Arunachal Pradesh...... 1";</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-26.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>entry 26 shall be omitted.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Allocation of sitting member.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On and from the appointed  day, the sitting member of the Council of States representing the  existing Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh shall be deemed to have  been duly elected under clause (4) of article 80 to fill the seat  allotted to the State of Arunachal Pradesh in that Council.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The term of office of such sitting member shall remain  unaltered.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Amendment of section 27A of Act 43 of 1950. On and from the  appointed day, in section 27A of the Representation of the People Act,</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1950">
          <num>1950.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1950.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>, in sub- section (4), for the words" The electoral college for  each of the Union territories of Arunachal Pradesh and Pondicherry",</p>
              <p>the words" The electoral college for the Union territory of</p>
              <p>Pondicherry" shall be substituted.</p>
              <p>The House of the People</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Allocation of seats in the existing House of the people.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On and from the appointed day, the allocation of seats to the State of</p>
              <p>Arunachal Pradesh in the House of the People shall be two; and the</p>
              <p>First Schedule to the Representation of the People Act, 1950 (43 of</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-1950">
          <num>1950.</num>
          <heading/>
          <paragraph id="section-1950.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>), shall be deemed to be amended accordingly.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-1950.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On and from the appointed day, the two parliamentary  constituencies of the existing Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh  shall be deemed to be the parliamentary constituencies of the State of</p>
              <p>Arunachal Pradesh and the Delimitation of Parliamentary and Assembly</p>
              <p>Constituencies Order, 1976, shall be construed accordingly.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Provision as to sitting members. The sitting members of the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-9.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>House of the People representing the constituencies which, on the  appointed day, by virtue of the provisions of section 8 become the  constituencies of the State of Arunachal Pradesh shall be deemed to  have been elected under sub- clause (a) of clause</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of article 81 to  the House of the People by those constituencies.</p>
              <p>The Legislative Assembly</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Provision as to Legislative Assembly. The total number  of seats in the Legislative Assembly of the State of Arunachal</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Pradesh, to be filled by persons chosen by direct election from asse-</p>
              <p>mbly constituencies shall be sixty, out of which fifty- nine seats  shall be reserved for the Scheduled Tribes; and the provisions of the</p>
              <p>Representation of the People Act, 1950 (43 of 1950) shall be deemed  to be amended accordingly.]</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Provisional Legislative Assembly.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-11.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding  anything contained in this Act (including provisions relating to the  strength of the Legislative Assembly of the State of Arunachal</p>
              <p>Pradesh), on and from the appointed day and until the Legislative</p>
              <p>Assembly of that State has been duly constituted and summoned to meet  for the first session, there shall be a provisional Legislative</p>
              <blockList id="section-11.1.list4">
                <listIntroduction>Assembly  which shall consist of--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-11.1.list4.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>members elected by the territorial constituencies of; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-11.1.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>members nominated to,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>the Legislative Assembly of the existing Union territory of</p>
              <p>Arunachal Pradesh].</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-11.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The period of five years referred to in clause (1) of article</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-172">
          <num>172.</num>
          <heading>shall, in the case of the provisional Legislative Assembly  referred to in sub- section (1), be deemed to have commenced on the day  on which the duration of the existing Legislative Assembly of the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-172.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh commenced under section 5 of the</p>
              <p>Government of Union Territories Act, 1963 (20 of 1963).</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
          <subsection id="section-172.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For so long as the provisional Legislative Assembly cons-</p>
              <blockList id="section-172.3.list2">
                <listIntroduction>tituted under this section is in existence,--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-172.3.list2.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>it shall be deemed to be the Legislative Assembly of the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>State of Arunachal Pradesh duly constituted under the Constitu-</p>
              <p>tion and shall be competent to discharge all the functions of a</p>
              <blockList id="section-172.3.list6">
                <listIntroduction>Legislative Assembly of a State under the Constitution; and</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-172.3.list6.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>the members thereof, referred to in clause (a) of sub-</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>section (1), shall be deemed to be the members of the Legislative</p>
              <p>Assembly of the State of Arunachal Pradesh duly elected under the</p>
              <p>Constitution].</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Speaker and Deputy Speaker. The persons who immediately  before the appointed day are the Speaker and the Deputy Speaker of the</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-12.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Legislative Assembly of the Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh,</p>
              <p>shall be the Speaker and the Deputy Speaker, respectively, of the  provisional Legislative Assembly of the State of Arunachal Pradesh on  and from that day.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Rules of procedure. The rules of procedure and conduct of  business of the Legislative Assembly of the existing Union territory  of Arunachal Pradesh as in force immediately before the appointed day  shall, until rules are made under clause</heading>
          <subsection id="section-13.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>of article 208, be the  rules of procedure and conduct of business of the provisional</p>
              <p>Legislative Assembly of the State of Arunachal Pradesh, subject to  such modifications and adaptations as may be made therein by the</p>
              <p>Speaker thereof.</p>
              <p>Delimitation of constituencies</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Delimitation of constituencies.</heading>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The Election Commission  shall, in the manner herein provided, distribute, whether before or  after the appointed day, the seats assigned to the Legislative</p>
              <p>Assembly of the State of Arunachal Pradesh under section 10 to single-</p>
              <p>member territorial constituencies and delimit them having regard to  the provisions of the Constitution and to the following provisions,</p>
              <blockList id="section-14.1.list4">
                <listIntroduction>namely:--</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-14.1.list4.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>all constituencies shall, as far as practicable, be  geographically compact areas, and in delimiting them regard shall  be had to physical features, existing boundaries of  administrative units, facilities of communication and public  convenience; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-14.1.list4.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>constituencies in which seats are reserved for the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </part>
    </body>
  </act>
  <components>
    <component id="component-scheduled">
      <doc name="scheduled">
        <meta>
          <identification source="#slaw">
            <FRBRWork>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1986/69/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1986/69"/>
              <FRBRalias value="Tribes shall, as far as practicable, be located in  areas where the proportion of their population to the total  population is the largest."/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
            </FRBRWork>
            <FRBRExpression>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1986/69/eng@1986-12-24/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1986/69/eng@1986-12-24"/>
              <FRBRdate date="1980-01-01" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
              <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
            </FRBRExpression>
            <FRBRManifestation>
              <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/1986/69/eng@1986-12-24/schedules"/>
              <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/1986/69/eng@1986-12-24"/>
              <FRBRdate date="2016-09-21" name="Generation"/>
              <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
            </FRBRManifestation>
          </identification>
        </meta>
        <mainBody>
          <article id="scheduled">
            <subsection id="scheduled.2">
              <num>(2)</num>
              <content>
                <blockList id="scheduled.2.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>For the purpose of assisting it in the performance of its  functions under sub- section (1), the Election Commission shall  associate with itself as associate members,--</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="scheduled.2.list1.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>the sitting members of the House of the People referred  to in section 9; and</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="scheduled.2.list1.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>such six of the members of the Legislative Assembly of  the existing Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh or, as the case  may be, the provisional Legislative Assembly referred to in  section 11 as the Speaker thereof may nominate:</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <p>Provided that none of the associate members shall have a right to  vote or to sign any decision of the Election Commission.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduled.3">
              <num>(3)</num>
              <content>
                <p>If, owing to death or resignation, the office of an associate  member falls vacant, it shall be filled, if practicable, in accordance  with the provisions of sub- section (2).</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduled.4">
              <num>(4)</num>
              <content>
                <blockList id="scheduled.4.list1">
                  <listIntroduction>The Election Commission shall--</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="scheduled.4.list1.a">
                    <num>(a)</num>
                    <p>publish its proposals for the delimitation of  constituencies together with the dissenting proposals, if any, of  any associate member who desires publication thereof, in the</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <blockList id="scheduled.4.list3">
                  <listIntroduction>Official Gazette and in such other manner as the Commission may  consider fit, together with a notice inviting objections and  suggestions in relation to the proposals and specifying a date on  or after which the proposals will be further considered by it;</listIntroduction>
                  <item id="scheduled.4.list3.b">
                    <num>(b)</num>
                    <p>consider all objections and suggestions which may have  been received by it before the date so specified;</p>
                  </item>
                  <item id="scheduled.4.list3.c">
                    <num>(c)</num>
                    <p>after considering all objections and suggestions which  may have been received by it before the date so specified,</p>
                  </item>
                </blockList>
                <p>determine by one or more orders the delimitation of  constituencies and cause such order or orders to be published in  the Official Gazette; and upon such publication, the order or  orders shall have the full force of law and shall not be called  in question in any court.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <subsection id="scheduled.5">
              <num>(5)</num>
              <content>
                <p>As soon as may be after such publication, every such order  relating to assembly constituencies shall be laid before the</p>
                <p>Legislative Assembly of the existing Union territory of Arunachal</p>
                <p>Pradesh or, as the case may be, the provisional Legislative Assembly  referred to in section 11.</p>
              </content>
            </subsection>
            <section id="section-15">
              <num>15.</num>
              <heading>Power of Election Commission to maintain delimitation orders  up- to- date.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-15.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <blockList id="section-15.1.list1">
                    <listIntroduction>The Election Commission may, from time to time, by  notification in the Official Gazette,--</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-15.1.list1.a">
                      <num>(a)</num>
                      <p>correct any printing mistake in any order made under  section 14 or any error arising therein from inadvertent slip or  omission;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-15.1.list1.b">
                      <num>(b)</num>
                      <p>where the boundaries or name of any territorial division  mentioned in any such order are or is altered, make such  amendments as appear to it to be necessary or expedient for  bringing such order up- to- date.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-15.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>Every notification under this section relating to an assembly  constituency shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is issued,</p>
                  <p>before the Legislative Assembly of the existing Union territory of</p>
                  <p>Arunachal Pradesh, the provisional Legislative Assembly referred to in  section 11 or the Legislative Assembly of the State of Arunachal</p>
                  <p>Pradesh, as the case may be.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-16">
              <num>16.</num>
              <heading>Amendment of Scheduled Castes Orders.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-16.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>On and from the  appointed day, the Constitution (Scheduled Castes) Order, 1950, shall  stand amended as directed in the First Schedule.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-16.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>On and from the appointed day, the Constitution (Scheduled</p>
                  <p>Castes) (Union Territories) Order, 1951, shall stand amended as  directed in the Second Schedule.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <section id="section-17">
              <num>17.</num>
              <heading>Amendment of Scheduled Tribes Orders.</heading>
              <subsection id="section-17.1">
                <num>(1)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>On and from the  appointed day, the Constitution (Scheduled Tribes) Order, 1950, shall  stand amended as directed in the Third Schedule.</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
              <subsection id="section-17.2">
                <num>(2)</num>
                <content>
                  <p>On and from the appointed day, the Constitution (Scheduled</p>
                  <p>Tribes) (Union Territories) Order, 1951, shall stand amended as  directed in the Fourth Schedule.</p>
                  <p>PART</p>
                  <p>HIGH COURT</p>
                </content>
              </subsection>
            </section>
            <part id="part-IV">
              <num>IV</num>
              <paragraph id="part-IV.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>HIGH COURT</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-18">
                <num>18.</num>
                <heading>Common High Court for Assam, Nagaland, Meghalaya, Manipur,</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-18.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Tripura, Mizoram and Arunachal Pradesh.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-18.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-18.1.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>On and from the appointed  day,--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-18.1.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>there shall be a common High Court for the States of</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Assam, Nagaland, Meghalaya, Manipur, Tripura, Mizoram and</p>
                    <p>Arunachal Pradesh to be called the Gauhati High Court (the High</p>
                    <p>Court of Assam, Nagaland, Meghalaya, Manipur, Tripura, Mizoram   and Arunachal Pradesh) (hereinafter referred to as the common</p>
                    <blockList id="section-18.1.list6">
                      <listIntroduction>High Court);</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-18.1.list6.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>the Judges of the High Court of Assam, Nagaland,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Meghalaya, Manipur, Tripura and Mizoram holding office  immediately before that day shall, unless they have elected  otherwise, become on that day the Judges of the common High</p>
                    <p>Court.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-18.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The expenditure in respect of the salaries and allowances of  the Judges of the common High Court shall be allocated amongst the</p>
                    <p>States of Arunachal Pradesh, Assam, Manipur, Meghalaya, Mizoram,</p>
                    <p>Nagaland and Tripura in such proportion as the President may, by  order, determine.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-19">
                <num>19.</num>
                <heading>Provision as to advocates.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-19.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-19.1.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>On and from the appointed  day,--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-19.1.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>in the Advocates Act, 1961 (25 of 1961), in section 3,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>in sub- section (1), for clause (b), the following clause shall be  substituted, namely:--</p>
                    <p>" (b) for the States of Arunachal Pradesh, Assam,</p>
                    <p>Manipur, Meghalaya, Mizoram, Nagaland and Tripura to be  known as the Bar Council of Assam, Nagaland, Meghalaya,</p>
                    <blockList id="section-19.1.list6">
                      <listIntroduction>Manipur, Tripura, Mizoram and Arunachal Pradesh;";</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-19.1.list6.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>the Bar Council of Assam, Nagaland, Meghalaya, Manipur,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Tripura and Mizoram shall be deemed to be the Bar Council of</p>
                    <p>Assam, Nagaland, Meghalaya, Manipur, Tripura, Mizoram and</p>
                    <p>Arunachal Pradesh.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-19.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Any person who, immediately before the appointed day, is an  advocate entitled to practise in the High Court of Assam, Nagaland,</p>
                    <p>Meghalaya, Manipur, Tripura and Mizoram shall be entitled to practise  as an advocate in the common High Court.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-19.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>All persons who, immediately before the appointed day, are  advocates on the roll of the Bar Council of Assam, Nagaland,</p>
                    <p>Meghalaya, Manipur, Tripura and Mizoram shall, as from that day,</p>
                    <p>become advocates on the roll of the Bar Council of Assam, Nagaland,</p>
                    <p>Meghalaya, Manipur, Tripura, Mizoram and Arunachal Pradesh.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-19.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The right of audience in the common High Court shall be  regulated in accordance with the like principles as, immediately  before the appointed day, are in force with respect to the right of  audience in the High Court of Assam, Nagaland, Meghalaya, Manipur,</p>
                    <p>Tripura and Mizoram:</p>
                    <p>Provided that as among the Advocates- General of the States of</p>
                    <p>Arunachal Pradesh, Assam, Manipur, Meghalaya, Mizoram, Nagaland and</p>
                    <p>Tripura, the right of audience shall be determined with reference to  their dates of enrolment as advocates.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-20">
                <num>20.</num>
                <heading>Practice and procedure in the common High Court. Subject to  the provisions of this Part, the law in force immediately before the  appointed day with respect to practice and procedure in the High Court  of Assam, Nagaland, Meghalaya, Manipur, Tripura and Mizoram shall,</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-20.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>with the necessary modifications, apply in relation to the common High</p>
                    <p>Court.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-21">
                <num>21.</num>
                <heading>Custody of Seal of the common High Court. The law in force  immediately before the appointed day with respect to the custody of  the Seal of the High Court of Assam, Nagaland, Meghalaya, Manipur,</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-21.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Tripura and Mizoram shall, with the necessary modifications, apply  with respect to the custody of the Seal of the common High Court.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-22">
                <num>22.</num>
                <heading>Form of writs and other processes. The law in force  immediately before the appointed day with respect to the form of writs  and other processes used, issued or awarded by the High Court of</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-22.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Assam, Nagaland, Meghalaya, Manipur, Tripura and Mizoram shall, with  necessary modifications, apply with respect to the form of writs and  other processes used, issued or awarded by the common High Court.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-23">
                <num>23.</num>
                <heading>Powers of Judges. The law in force immediately before the  appointed day with respect to the powers of the Chief Justice, single</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-23.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Judges and division courts of the High Court of Assam, Nagaland,</p>
                    <p>Meghalaya, Manipur, Tripura and Mizoram and with respect to all  matters, ancillary to the exercise of those powers shall, with the  necessary modifications, apply in relation to the common High Court.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-24">
                <num>24.</num>
                <heading>Principal seat and other places of sitting of the common High</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-24.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Court.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-24.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The principal seat of the common High Court shall be at the  same place at which the principal seat of the High Court of Assam,</p>
                    <p>Nagaland, Meghalaya, Manipur, Tripura and Mizoram is located  immediately before the appointed day.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-24.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The President may, by notified order, provide for the  establishment of a permanent bench or benches of the common High Court  at one or more places within the territories to which the jurisdiction  of the High Court extends, other than the principal seat of the High</p>
                    <p>Court, and for any matters connected therewith:</p>
                    <p>Provided that before issuing any order under this sub- section,</p>
                    <p>the President shall consult the Chief Justice of the common High Court  and the Governor of the State in which the bench or benches is or are  proposed to be established.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-24.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1) or sub-</p>
                    <p>section (2), the Judges and division courts of the common High Court  may also sit at such other place or places in the States of Assam,</p>
                    <p>Nagaland, Meghalaya, Manipur, Tripura, Mizoram and Arunahal Pradesh as  the Chief Justice may, with the approval of the Governor of the State  concerned, appoint.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-25">
                <num>25.</num>
                <heading>Procedure as to appeals to Supreme Court. The law in force  immediately before the appointed day relating to appeals to the</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-25.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Supreme Court from the High Court of Assam, Nagaland, Meghalaya,</p>
                    <p>Manipur, Tripura and Mizoram and the Judges and division courts  thereof shall, with the necessary modifications, apply in relation to  the common High Court.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-26">
                <num>26.</num>
                <heading>Transfer of proceedings from the High Court of Assam,</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-26.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Nagaland, Meghalaya, Manipur, Tripura and Mizoram to the common High</p>
                    <p>Court.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-26.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>All proceedings pending in the High Court of Assam,</p>
                    <p>Nagaland, Meghalaya, Manipur, Tripura and Mizoram immediately before  the appointed day shall, from such day, stand transferred to the  common High Court.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-26.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every proceeding transferred under sub- section (1) shall be  disposed of by the common High Court as if such proceeding was  entertained by that High Court.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-27">
                <num>27.</num>
                <heading>Interpretation. For the purposes of section 26,--</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-27.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-27.paragraph-0.list0">
                      <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>proceedings shall be deemed to be pending in a court  until that court has disposed of all issues between the parties,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>including any issues with respect to the taxation of the costs of  the proceedings and shall include appeals, applications for leave  to appeal to the</p>
                    <blockList id="section-27.paragraph-0.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>Supreme Court, applications for review, petitions for revision  and petitions for writs; and</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-27.paragraph-0.list3.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>references to a High Court shall be construed as  including references to a Judge or division court thereof; and  references to an order made by a court or a Judge shall be  construed as including references to a sentence, judgment or  decree passed or made by that court or Judge.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-28">
                <num>28.</num>
                <heading>Right to appear or to act in proceedings transferred to the  common High Court. Any person who, immediately before the appointed  day, is an advocate entitled to practise in the High Court of Assam,</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-28.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Nagaland, Meghalaya, Manipur, Tripura and Mizoram and was authorised  to appear or to act in any proceedings transferred from the said High</p>
                    <p>Court to the common High Court under section 26 shall have the right  to appear or to act, as the case may be, in the common High Court in  relation to those proceedings.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-29">
                <num>29.</num>
                <heading>Saving. Nothing in this Part shall affect the application to  the common High Court of any provisions of the Constitution, and this</heading>
              </section>
            </part>
            <part id="part-shall">
              <num>shall</num>
              <heading>have effect subject to any provision that may be made on or  after the appointed day with respect to that High Court by any</heading>
              <paragraph id="part-shall.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>Legislature or other authority having power to make such provisions.</p>
                  <p>PART</p>
                  <p>AUTHORISATION OF EXPENDITURE AND DISTRIBUTION OF REVENUES</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
            </part>
            <part id="part-V">
              <num>V</num>
              <paragraph id="part-V.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>AUTHORISATION OF EXPENDITURE AND DISTRIBUTION OF REVENUES</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-30">
                <num>30.</num>
                <heading>Authorisation of expenditure pending its sanction by the</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-30.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Legislature.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-30.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The President may, at any time before the appointed  day, authorise by order such expenditure from the Consolidated Fund of  the State of Arunachal Pradesh as he deems necessary for a period of  not more than six months beginning with the appointed day, pending the  sanction of such expenditure by the Legislative Assembly of the State  of Arunachal Pradesh:</p>
                    <p>Provided that the Governor of Arunachal Pradesh may, afer the  appointed day, authorise by order such further expenditure as he deems  necessary from the Consolidated Fund of the State of Arunachal Pradesh  for any period not extending beyond the said period of six months.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-30.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The President or, as the case may be, the Governor of</p>
                    <p>Arunachal Pradesh shall make separate orders under sub- section (1) in  respect of periods falling in different financial years.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-31">
                <num>31.</num>
                <heading>Reports relating to the accounts of the existing Union  territory of Arunachal Pradesh.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-31.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The reports of the Comptroller and</p>
                    <p>Auditor- General of India referred to in section 49 of the Government  of Union Territories Act, 1963 (20 of 1963), relating to the accounts  of the exising Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh in respect of any  period prior to the appointed day, shall be submitted to the Governor  of Arunachal Pradesh who shall cause them to be laid before the</p>
                    <p>Legislative Assembly of the State.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-31.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-31.2.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>The Governor may, by order,--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-31.2.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>declare any expenditure incurred out of the Consolidated</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Fund of the existing Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh on any  service in respect of any period prior to the appointed day  during the financial year 1986- 87 or in respect of any earlier  financial year in</p>
                    <blockList id="section-31.2.list4">
                      <listIntroduction>excess of the amount granted for that service and for that year  as disclosed in the reports referred to in sub- section (1) to  have been duly authorised, and</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-31.2.list4.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>provide for any action to be taken on any matter arising  out of the said reports.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-32">
                <num>32.</num>
                <heading>Allowances and privileges of Governor of Arunachal Pradesh.</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-32.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>The allowances and privileges of the Governor of Arunachal Pradesh  shall, until, the Governors (Emoluments, Allowances and Privileges)</p>
                    <p>Act, 1982 (46 of 1982), comes into force, be such as the President  may, by order, determine.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-33">
                <num>33.</num>
                <heading>Distribution of revenues. The President shall, by order,</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-33.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>determine the grants- in- aid of the revenues of the State of Arunachal</p>
                    <p>Pradesh and the share of that State in the Union duties of excise,</p>
                    <p>estate duty and taxes on income and for that purpose amend thereby the  relevant provisions of the Additional Duties of Excise (Goods of</p>
                    <p>Special Importance) Act, 1957 (58 of 1957), the Union Duties of</p>
                    <blockList id="section-33.paragraph-0.list5">
                      <listIntroduction>Excise (Distribution) Act, 1979 (24 of 1979), the Estate Duty</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-33.paragraph-0.list5.Distribution">
                        <num>(Distribution)</num>
                        <p>Act, 1962 (9 of 1962), and the Constitution</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>(Distribution of Revenues) Order, 1985 in such manner as he thinks  fit.</p>
                    <p>PART</p>
                    <p>ASSETS AND LIABILITIES</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
            </part>
            <part id="part-VI">
              <num>VI</num>
              <paragraph id="part-VI.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>ASSETS AND LIABILITIES</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-34">
                <num>34.</num>
                <heading>Property, assets, rights, liabilities, obligations, etc.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-34.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>All such property and assets within the existing Union territory of</p>
                    <p>Arunachal Pradesh as are held immediately before the appointed day by  the Union for purposes of governance of that Union territory shall, on  and from that day, pass to the State of Arunachal Pradesh unless the  purposes for which such property and assets are so held are Union  purposes:</p>
                    <p>Provided that the cash balances in the treasuries in the existing</p>
                    <p>Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh before the appointed day shall,</p>
                    <p>as from that day, vest in the State of Arunachal Pradesh.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-34.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-34.2.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>All rights, liabilities and obligations (other than those   relatable to, or in connection with, a Union purpose), whether arising  out of any contract or otherwise, which are, immediately before the  appointed day,--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-34.2.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>the rights, liabilities and obligations of the Central</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-34.2.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>Government arising out of, or in connection with, the governance  of the existing Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh; or</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-34.2.list3.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>the rights, liabilities and obligations of the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Administrator of the existing Union territory of Arunachal</p>
                    <p>Pradesh in his capacity as such or of the Government of that</p>
                    <p>Union territory, shall, on and from the appointed day, be the  rights, liabilities and obligations of the Government of the</p>
                    <p>State of Arunachal Pradesh.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-34.3">
                  <num>(3)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-34.3.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>The right to recover arrears of--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-34.3.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>any tax or duty being a tax or duty enumerated in the</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-34.3.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>State List in the Seventh Schedule to the Constitution; or</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-34.3.list3.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>any duty referred to in article 268; or</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-34.3.list3.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <p>any tax under the Central Sales Tax Act, 1956 (74 of</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-1956">
                <num>1956.</num>
                <heading/>
                <paragraph id="section-1956.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>),</p>
                    <p>which have fallen due in the existing Union territory of</p>
                    <p>Arunachal Pradesh, shall pass to the State of Arunachal Pradesh.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
                <subsection id="section-1956.4">
                  <num>(4)</num>
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-1956.4.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>The provisions of this section shall not apply to, or in  relation to,--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-1956.4.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>any institution, undertaking or project the expenditure  in relation to which is, immediately before the appointed day,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-1956.4.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>met from and out of the Consolidated Fund of India;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-1956.4.list3.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>any property which has been placed by the Union at the  disposal of the administration of the existing Union territory of</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Arunachal Pradesh subject to the condition that the ownership  thereof will continue to vest in the Union.</p>
                    <blockList id="section-1956.4.list6">
                      <listIntroduction>Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section,--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-1956.4.list6.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>" liability" includes liability in respect of any civil  deposit, local fund deposit, charitable or other endowment,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-1956.4.list8">
                      <listIntroduction>provident fund account, pension or actionable wrong;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-1956.4.list8.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>" Union purposes" means the purposes of Government  relatable to any of the matters mentioned in the Union List.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>PART</p>
                    <p>PROVISIONS AS TO SERVICES</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
            </part>
            <part id="part-VII">
              <num>VII</num>
              <paragraph id="part-VII.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>PROVISIONS AS TO SERVICES</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-35">
                <num>35.</num>
                <heading>Provision relating to All- India Services. Every member of the</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-35.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Indian Administrative Service, the Indian Police Service and the</p>
                    <p>Indian Forest Service who, immediately before the appointed day, is  holding any post in the existing Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh  shall, until otherwise directed by the Central Government, be deemed  to be on deputation, on and from the appointed day, to the Government  of the State of Arunachal Pradesh on the same terms and conditions of  service as are applicable to him under the relevant cadre rules:</p>
                    <p>Provided that the period of such deputation shall in no case  extend beyond a period of three years from the appointed day.</p>
                    <p>Explanation.-- In this section," cadre rules" means the Indian</p>
                    <blockList id="section-35.paragraph-0.list5">
                      <listIntroduction>Administrative Service (Cadre) Rules, 1954, the Indian Police Service</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-35.paragraph-0.list5.Cadre">
                        <num>(Cadre)</num>
                        <p>Rules, 1954 or the Indian Forest Service (Cadre) Rules, 1966,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>as the case may be.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-36">
                <num>36.</num>
                <heading>Provisions relating to other services.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-36.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every person who  immediately before the appointed day is serving in connection with the  affairs of the Union under the administrative control of the</p>
                    <p>Administrator of the existing Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh  shall, unless otherwise directed by an order of the Central</p>
                    <p>Government, be deemed to have been allocated for service as from that  day in connection with the affairs of the State of Arunachal Pradesh:</p>
                    <p>Provided that no directions shall be issued under this section  after the expiry of a period of one year from the appointed day.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-36.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The provisions of this section shall not apply in relation to  persons to whom the provisions of section 35 apply.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-37">
                <num>37.</num>
                <heading>Other provisions as to services.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-37.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Nothing in this section  or section 36 shall be deemed to affect on or after the appointed day,</p>
                    <p>the operation of the provisions of Chapter I of Part XIV of the</p>
                    <p>Constitution in relation to determination of the conditions of service  of persons serving in connection with the affairs of the State of</p>
                    <p>Arunachal Pradesh:</p>
                    <p>Provided that the conditions of service applicable immediately  before the appointed day in the case of any person referred to in  section 36 shall not be varied to his disadvantage except with the  previous approval of the Central Government.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-37.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>All services prior to the appointed day rendered by a person  deemed to have been allocated under section 36 in connection with the  administration of the existing Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh,</p>
                    <p>shall be deemed to have been rendered in connection with the affairs  of the State of Arunachal Pradesh for the purposes of the rules  regulating his conditions of service.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-38">
                <num>38.</num>
                <heading>Provisions as to continuance of officers in same posts. Every  person who, immediately before the appointed day, is holding or  discharging the duties of any post or office in connection with the  affairs of the existing Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh shall  continue to hold the same post or office and shall be deemed, on and  from that day, to have been duly appointed to the post or office by  the Government of, or other appropriate authority in, the State of</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-38.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Arunachal Pradesh on the same terms and conditions of appointment and  on the same tenure as he was holding the post or office immediately  before that day:</p>
                    <p>Provided that nothing in this section shall be deemed to prevent  a competent authority on or after the appointed day from passing in  relation to such person any order affecting his continuance in such  post or office.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-39">
                <num>39.</num>
                <heading>Advisory Committees. The Central Government may, by order,</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-39.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-39.paragraph-0.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>establish one or more Advisory Committees for the purpose of assisting  it in regard to--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-39.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>the discharge of its functions under this Part; and</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-39.paragraph-0.list1.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>the ensuring of fair and equitable treatment to all  persons affected by the provisions of this Part and the proper  consideration of any representations made by such persons.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-40">
                <num>40.</num>
                <heading>Prohibition of representation after certain period.</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-40.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any law or rule  for the time being in force, no representation shall lie against any  order passed under the provisions of this Part on the expiry of three  months from the date of publication or service, whichever is earlier,</p>
                    <p>of such order:</p>
                    <p>Provided that the Central Government may, suo motu or otherwise  and for reasons to be recorded, re- open any matter and pass such  orders thereon as may appear to it to be appropriate if it is  satisfied that it is necessary so to do in order to prevent any  miscarriage of justice to any affected person.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-41">
                <num>41.</num>
                <heading>Power of Central Government to give direcions. The Central</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-41.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Government may give such directions to the Government of the State of</p>
                    <p>Arunachal Pradesh as may appear to it to be necessary for the purpose  of giving effect to the foregoing provisions of this Part and the</p>
                    <p>State Government shall comply with such directions.</p>
                    <p>PART</p>
                    <p>LEGAL AND MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
            </part>
            <part id="part-VIII">
              <num>VIII</num>
              <paragraph id="part-VIII.paragraph-0">
                <content>
                  <p>LEGAL AND MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS</p>
                </content>
              </paragraph>
              <section id="section-42">
                <num>42.</num>
                <heading>Amendment of article 210, article 239A and article 240 of the</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-42.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-42.paragraph-0.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>Constitution. On and from the appointed day,--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-42.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>in article 210, in clause (2), in the second proviso,</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>for the words" Legislature of the State of Mizoram", the words</p>
                    <p>" Legislatures of the States of Arunachal Pradesh and Mizoram"</p>
                    <blockList id="section-42.paragraph-0.list5">
                      <listIntroduction>shall be substituted;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-42.paragraph-0.list5.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>in article 239A, in clause (1), for the words",</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Pondicherry and Arunachal Pradesh", the words" and Pondicherry"</p>
                    <blockList id="section-42.paragraph-0.list8">
                      <listIntroduction>shall be substituted;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-42.paragraph-0.list8.c">
                        <num>(c)</num>
                        <blockList id="section-42.paragraph-0.list8.c.list0">
                          <listIntroduction>in article 240, in clause (1),--</listIntroduction>
                          <item id="section-42.paragraph-0.list8.c.list0.i">
                            <num>(i)</num>
                            <p>entry (g) shall be omitted;</p>
                          </item>
                          <item id="section-42.paragraph-0.list8.c.list0.ii">
                            <num>(ii)</num>
                            <p>in the provisos, for the words" Pondicherry or</p>
                          </item>
                        </blockList>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>Arunachal Pradesh", the words" or Pondicherry" shall be  substituted.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-43">
                <num>43.</num>
                <heading>Amendment of Act 28 of 1958. On and from the appointed day,</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-43.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>in the Armed Forces (Special Powers) Act, 1958, in the long title and  in sub- section (2) of section 1, for the words" Assam, Manipur,</p>
                    <p>Meghalaya, Mizoram, Nagaland and Tripura and the Union territory of</p>
                    <p>Arunachal Pradesh", the words" Arunachal Pradesh, Assam, Manipur,</p>
                    <p>Meghalaya, Mizoram, Nagaland and Tripura" shall be substituted.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-44">
                <num>44.</num>
                <heading>Amendment of Act 20 of 1963. On and from the appointed day,</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-44.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-44.paragraph-0.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>in the Government of Union territories Act, 1963,--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-44.paragraph-0.list1.i">
                        <num>(i)</num>
                        <p>in clause (h) of sub- section (1) of section 2, for the  words", Pondicherry and Arunachal Pradesh", the words" and</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <blockList id="section-44.paragraph-0.list3">
                      <listIntroduction>Pondicherry" shall be substituted;</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-44.paragraph-0.list3.ii">
                        <num>(ii)</num>
                        <p>in section 33, in sub- section (2), the proviso shall be  omitted;</p>
                      </item>
                      <item id="section-44.paragraph-0.list3.iii">
                        <num>(iii)</num>
                        <p>in section 44, sub- section (2) shall be omitted.</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-45">
                <num>45.</num>
                <heading>Amendment of Act 84 of 1971. On and from the appointed day,</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-45.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <blockList id="section-45.paragraph-0.list1">
                      <listIntroduction>in the North- Eastern Council Act, 1971,--</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-45.paragraph-0.list1.a">
                        <num>(a)</num>
                        <p>in section 2, for clauses (b) and (c), the following  clause shall be substituted, namely:--</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>' (b)" north- eastern area" means the area comprising the</p>
                    <p>States of Arunachal Pradesh, Assam, Manipur, Meghalaya,</p>
                    <blockList id="section-45.paragraph-0.list5">
                      <listIntroduction>Mizoram, Nagaland and Tripura.';</listIntroduction>
                      <item id="section-45.paragraph-0.list5.b">
                        <num>(b)</num>
                        <p>in section 3, in sub- section (1), for clause (b), the  following clause shall be substituted, namely:--</p>
                      </item>
                    </blockList>
                    <p>" (b) the Chief Ministers of the States of Arunachal</p>
                    <p>Pradesh, Assam, Manipur, Meghalaya, Mizoram, Nagaland and</p>
                    <p>Tripura.".</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-46">
                <num>46.</num>
                <heading>Continuance of existing laws and their adaptations.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-46.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>All  laws in force, immediately before the appointed day, in the existing</p>
                    <p>Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh shall continue to be in force in  the State of Arunachal Pradesh until altered, repealed or amended by a  competent Legislature or other competent authority.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-46.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>For the purpose of facilitating the application in relation  to the State of Arunachal Pradesh of any law made before the appointed  day, the appropriate Government may, within two years from that day,</p>
                    <p>by order, make such adaptations and modifications of the law, whether  by way of repeal or amendment, as may be necessary or expedient, and  thereupon every such law shall have effect subject to the adaptations  and modifications so made until altered, repealed or amended by a  competent Legislature or other competent authority.</p>
                    <p>Explanation.-- In this section, the expression" appropriate</p>
                    <p>Government" means, as respects any law relating to a matter enumerated  in the Union List in the Seventh Schedule to the Constitution, the</p>
                    <p>Central Government and as respects any other law, the Government of  the State of Arunachal Pradesh.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-47">
                <num>47.</num>
                <heading>Power to construe laws. Notwithstanding that no provision or  insufficient provision has been made under section 46 for the  adaptation of a law made before the appointed day, any court, tribunal  or authority required or empowered to enforce such law may, for the  purpose of facilitating its application in relation to the State of</heading>
                <paragraph id="section-47.paragraph-0">
                  <content>
                    <p>Arunachal Pradesh, construe the law in such manner not affecting the  substance as may be necessary or proper in regard to the matter before  the court, tribunal or authority, as the case may be.</p>
                  </content>
                </paragraph>
              </section>
              <section id="section-48">
                <num>48.</num>
                <heading>Provisions as to continuance of courts, etc. All courts and  tribunals and all authorities discharging lawful functions throughout  the existing Union territory of Arunachal Pradesh or any part thereof  immediately before the appointed day shall, unless their continuance  is inconsistent with the provisions of this Act or until other  provision is made by a competent Legislature or other competent  authority, continue to exercise their respective functions.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-49">
                <num>49.</num>
                <heading>Effect of provisions of Act inconsistent with other laws. The  provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything  inconsistent therewith contained in any other law.</heading>
              </section>
              <section id="section-50">
                <num>50.</num>
                <heading>Power to remove difficulties.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-50.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>If any difficulty arises in  giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the President may, by  order, do anything not inconsistent with such provisions which appears  to him to be necessary or expedient for the purpose of removing the  difficulty:</p>
                    <p>Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of  three years from the appointed day.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-50.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every order made under this section shall be laid before each</p>
                    <p>House of Parliament.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
              <section id="section-51">
                <num>51.</num>
                <heading>Power to make rules.</heading>
                <subsection id="section-51.1">
                  <num>(1)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>The Central Government may, by  notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to give effect to the  provisions of this Act.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
                <subsection id="section-51.2">
                  <num>(2)</num>
                  <content>
                    <p>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as  may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is  in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised  in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before  the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the  successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any  modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not  be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified  form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any  such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the  validity of anything previously done under that rule.</p>
                  </content>
                </subsection>
              </section>
            </part>
          </article>
        </mainBody>
      </doc>
    </component>
  </components>
</akomaNtoso>
