<akomaNtoso xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.akomantoso.org/2.0 akomantoso20.xsd">
  <act contains="originalVersion">
    <meta>
      <identification source="#slaw">
        <FRBRWork>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2002/69/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2002/69"/>
          <FRBRalias value="The Suppression Of Unlawful Acts Against Safety Of Maritime Navigation and Fixed Platforms On Continental Shelf Act, 2002"/>
          <FRBRdate date="" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRcountry value="in"/>
        </FRBRWork>
        <FRBRExpression>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2002/69/eng@2002-12-20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2002/69/eng@2002-12-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2002-12-20" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#council"/>
          <FRBRlanguage language="eng"/>
        </FRBRExpression>
        <FRBRManifestation>
          <FRBRthis value="/in-union/act/2002/69/eng@2002-12-20/main"/>
          <FRBRuri value="/in-union/act/2002/69/eng@2002-12-20"/>
          <FRBRdate date="2017-01-25" name="Generation"/>
          <FRBRauthor href="#slaw"/>
        </FRBRManifestation>
      </identification>
      <publication date="" name="" showAs="" number=""/>
      <references source="#this">
        <TLCOrganization id="slaw" href="https://github.com/longhotsummer/slaw" showAs="Slaw"/>
        <TLCOrganization id="council" href="/ontology/organization/za/council" showAs="Council"/>
      </references>
    </meta>
    <preface>
      <p class="title">
        <shortTitle>The Suppression Of Unlawful Acts Against Safety Of Maritime Navigationand Fixed Platforms On Continental Shelf Act, 2002</shortTitle>
      </p>
      <p class="number">
        <docNumber>ACT NO. 69 OF 2002</docNumber>
      </p>
      <p class="DateOfEnactment">
        <docDate>[ 20th December, 2002.]</docDate>
      </p>
      <preamble>
        <formula name="EnactingText">
          <p>BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third Year of the Republic of</p>
        </formula>
      </preamble>
      <longTitle>
        <p>An Act to give effect to the International Maritime Organisation</p>
        <p>Convention for Suppression of Unlawful Acts Against the Safety of</p>
        <p>Maritime Navigation and the Protocol for the Suppression of Unlawful</p>
        <p>Acts Against the Safety of Fixed Platforms Located on the Continental</p>
        <p>Shelf and for matters connected therewith.</p>
        <p>WHEREAS a Convention for the Suppression of Unlawful Acts Against the</p>
        <p>Safety of Maritime Navigation and the Protocol for the Suppression of</p>
        <p>Unlawful Acts Against the Safety of Fixed Platforms Located on the</p>
        <p>Continental Shelf were signed at Rome on the 10 h day of March, 1988;</p>
        <p>AND WHEREAS India, having acceded to the said Convention and the</p>
        <p>Protocol, should make provisions for giving effect thereto and for  matters connected therewith;</p>
        <p>India as follows:-</p>
        <p>CHAP</p>
        <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
      </longTitle>
    </preface>
    <body>
      <chapter id="chapter-I">
        <num>I</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-I.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>PRELIMINARY</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-1">
          <num>1.</num>
          <heading>Short title, extent, application and commencement.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-1.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>This Act  may be called the Suppression of Unlawful Acts Against Safety of</p>
              <p>Maritime Navigation and Fixed Platforms on Continental Shelf Act,</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2002">
          <num>2002.</num>
          <heading/>
          <subsection id="section-2002.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It extends to the whole of India including the limit of the  territorial waters, the continental shelf, the exclusive economic zone  or any other maritime zone of India within the meaning of section 2 of  the Territorial Waters, Continental Shelf, Excl sive Economic Zone and  other Maritime Zones Act, 1976 (80 of 1976).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2002.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2002.3.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Save as otherwise provided, it shall apply-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2002.3.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>to any offence under section 3 committed outside India by any  person;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2002.3.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>to a ship, if that ship is navigating or scheduled to navigate  into, through or from waters beyond the outer limits of the  territorial waters of India, or the lateral limits of its territorial  waters with adjacent States;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2002.3.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>when the offence is committed on board a ship in the territorial  waters of India or against a fixed platform located on the Continental</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Shelf of India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2002.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2002.4.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (3), this Act  shall apply only to offences committed by an offender or alleged  offender,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2002.4.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>when such an offender is found in the territory of a Convention</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2002.4.list3">
                <listIntroduction>State;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2002.4.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>when such an offender is found in the territory of a Protocol</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-2002.4.list5">
                <listIntroduction>State in whose internal water or territorial waters or continental  shelf the fixed platform is located; or</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-2002.4.list5.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>when such an offender is found in the territory of a State other  than the State referred to in clause (a) or clause (b).</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-2002.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government  may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-2">
          <num>2.</num>
          <heading>Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-2.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>" Code" means the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974);</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>" Continental Shelf of India" shall have the meaning assigned to it  in the Territorial Waters, Continental Shelf, Exclusive Economic Zone  and other Maritime Zones Act, 1976 (80 of 1976);</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-2.paragraph-0.list0.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>" Convention" means the Convention for the Suppression of Unlawful</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>Acts Against the Safety of Maritime Navigation, signed at Rome on the</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10th">
          <num>10th.</num>
          <heading>day of March, 1988 as amended from time to time;</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10th.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-10th.paragraph-0.list0">
                <item id="section-10th.paragraph-0.list0.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>" Convention State" means a State Party to the Convention;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10th.paragraph-0.list0.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>" fixed platform" means an artificial island, installation or  structure permanently attached to the seabed for the purpose of  exploration for, or exploitation of resources or for other economic  purposes;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10th.paragraph-0.list0.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>" Protocol" means the Protocol for the Suppression of Unlawful Acts</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-10th.paragraph-0.list2">
                <listIntroduction>Against the Safety of Fixed Platforms Located on the Continental Shelf  adopted at Rome on the 10th day of March, 1988 as amended from time to  time;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-10th.paragraph-0.list2.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <p>" Protocol State" means a State Party to the Protocol;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-10th.paragraph-0.list2.h">
                  <num>(h)</num>
                  <p>" ship" means a vessel of any type whatsoever not permanently  attached to the seabed and includes dynamically supported craft,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>submersibles, or any other floating craft.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>OFFENCES</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-II">
        <num>II</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-II.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>OFFENCES</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-3">
          <num>3.</num>
          <heading>Offences against ship, fixed platform, cargo of a ship, maritime  navigational facilities, etc.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-3.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Whoever unlawfully and  intentionally-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>commits an act of violence against a person on board a fixed  platform or a ship which is likely to endanger the safety of the fixed  platform or, as the case may be, safe navigation of the ship shall be  punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to ten years  and shall also be liable to fine;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>destroys a fixed platform or a ship or causes damage to a fixed  platform or a ship or cargo of the ship in such manner which is likely  to endanger the safety of such platform or safe navigation of such  ship shall be punished with imprisonment for lif;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>seizes or exercises control over a fixed platform or a ship by  force or threatens or in any other form intimidates shall be punished  with imprisonment for life;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.1.list1.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>places or causes to be placed on a fixed platform or a ship, by  any means whatsoever, a device or substance which is likely to destroy  that fixed platform or that ship or cause damage to that fixed  platform or that ship or its cargo which endangers o is likely to  endanger that fixed platform or the safe navigation of that ship shall  be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to fourteen  years;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.1.list1.e">
                  <num>(e)</num>
                  <p>destroys or damages maritime navigational facilities or interferes  with their operation if such act is likely to endanger the safe  navigation of a ship shall be punished with imprisonment for a term  which may extend to fourteen years;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.1.list1.f">
                  <num>(f)</num>
                  <p>communicates information which he knows to be false thereby  endangering the safe navigation of a ship shall be punished with  imprisonment for a term which may extend to fourteen years and shall  also be liable to fine;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.1.list1.g">
                  <num>(g)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-3.1.list1.g.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>in the course of commission of or in attempt to commit, any of the  offences specified in clauses (a) to (d) in connection with a fixed  platform or clauses (a) to (f) in connection with a ship-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-3.1.list1.g.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>causes death to any person shall be punished with death;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3.1.list1.g.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>causes grievous hurt to any person shall be punished with  imprisonment for a term which may extend to fourteen years;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3.1.list1.g.list0.iii">
                      <num>(iii)</num>
                      <p>causes injury to any person shall be punished with imprisonment  for a term which may extend to ten years;</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3.1.list1.g.list0.iv">
                      <num>(iv)</num>
                      <p>seizes or threatens a person shall be punished with imprisonment  for a term which may extend to ten years; and</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3.1.list1.g.list0.v">
                      <num>(v)</num>
                      <p>threatens to endanger a ship or a fixed platform shall be punished  with imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years.</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Whoever attempts to commit, or abets the commission of, an offence  punishable under sub- section (1) shall be deemed to have committed  such offence and shall be punished with the punishment provided for  such offence.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Whoever unlawfully or intentionally threatens a person to compel  that person to do or refrain from doing any act or to commit any  offence specified in clause (a), clause (b) or clause (c) of  sub- section (1), if such threat is likely to endanger the s fe  navigation of a ship or safety of a fixed platform shall be punished  with the punishment provided for such offence.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.4">
            <num>(4)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.4.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Where any act referred to in sub- section (1) is committed,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.4.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <blockList id="section-3.4.list1.a.list0">
                    <listIntroduction>against or on board-</listIntroduction>
                    <item id="section-3.4.list1.a.list0.i">
                      <num>(i)</num>
                      <p>an Indian ship at the time of commission of the offence; or</p>
                    </item>
                    <item id="section-3.4.list1.a.list0.ii">
                      <num>(ii)</num>
                      <p>any ship in the territory of India including its territorial  waters;</p>
                    </item>
                  </blockList>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.4.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>by a stateless person,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>such act shall be deemed to be an offence committed by such person for  the purposes of this Act.</p>
              <p>Explanation.- In this sub- section, the expression" stateless person"</p>
              <p>means a person whose habitual residence is in India but he does not  have nationality of any country.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.5">
            <num>(5)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Where an offence under sub- section (1) is committed and the person  accused of or suspected of the commission of such offence is present  in the territory of India and is not extradited to any Convention</p>
              <p>State or Protocol State, as the case may be, s ch person shall be  dealt with in India in accordance with the provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.6">
            <num>(6)</num>
            <content>
              <p>On being satisfied that the circumstances so warrant, the Central</p>
              <p>Government or any other authority designated by it shall take the  person referred to in sub- section (5) and present in the territory of</p>
              <p>India into custody or take measures, in accorda ce with the law for  the time being in force, to ensure his presence in India for such time  as is necessary to enable any criminal or extradition proceeding to be  instituted:</p>
              <p>Provided that when a person is taken into custody under this  sub- section, it shall be necessary for the Central Government or any  other authority designated by it to notify the Government of any  jurisdiction over the offence committed or suspected to have been  committed by the person in custody. Convention State or Protocol</p>
              <p>State which have also establi hed</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.7">
            <num>(7)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (8), where an offence  under sub- section (1) is committed outside India, the person  committing such offence may be dealt with in respect thereof as if  such offence had been committed at any place within India at which he  may be found.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-3.8">
            <num>(8)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-3.8.list1">
                <listIntroduction>No court shall take cognizance of an offence punishable under this  section which is committed outside India unless-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-3.8.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>such offence is committed on a fixed platform or on board a ship  flying the Indian flag at the time the offence is committed;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.8.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>such offence is committed on board a ship which is for the time  being chartered without crew to a lessee who has his principal place  of business, or where he has no such place of business, his permanent  residence, is in India; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-3.8.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the alleged offender is a citizen of India or is on a fixed  platform or on board a ship in relation to which such offence is  committed when it enters the territorial waters of India or is found  in India.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-4">
          <num>4.</num>
          <heading>Conferment of powers of investigation.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-4.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding  anything contained in the Code, for the purpose of this Act, the</p>
              <p>Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette,</p>
              <p>confer on any gazetted officer of the Coast Guard or any other  gazetted officer of the Central Government powers of arrest,</p>
              <p>investigation and prosecution exercisable by a police officer under  the Code.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-4.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>All officers of police and all officers of Government are hereby  required and empowered to assist the officer of the Central Government  referred to in sub- section (1), in the execution of provisions of this</p>
              <p>Act.</p>
              <p>Explanation.- For the purpose of this section," officer of the Coast</p>
              <p>Guard" means an officer as defined in clause (q) of section 2 of the</p>
              <p>Coast Guard Act, 1978 (30 of 1978).</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-5">
          <num>5.</num>
          <heading>Designated Courts.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-5.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purpose of providing for speedy  trial, the State Government shall, with the concurrence of the Chief</p>
              <p>Justice of the High Court, by notification in the Official Gazette,</p>
              <p>areas as may be specified in the notification. specify a Court of</p>
              <p>Session to be a Designated Cour for such area or</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-5.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code, a Designated Court  shall, as far as practicable, hold the trial on a day- to- day basis.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-6">
          <num>6.</num>
          <heading>Offence triable by Designated Court.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-6.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-6.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything  contained in the Code,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>all offences under this Act shall be triable only by the</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-6.1.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Designated Court specified under sub- section (1) of section 5;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.1.list3.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>where a person accused of or suspected of the commission of an  offence under this Act is forwarded to a Magistrate under sub- section</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>or sub- section (2A) of section 167 of the Code, such Magistrate  may authorise the detention of such person in suc custody as he thinks  fit for a period not exceeding fifteen days in the whole where such</p>
              <p>Magistrate is a Judicial Magistrate and seven days in the whole where  such Magistrate is an Executive Magistrate:</p>
              <blockList id="section-6.2.list3">
                <listIntroduction>Provided that where such Magistrate considers,-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.2.list3.i">
                  <num>(i)</num>
                  <p>when such person is forwarded to him as aforesaid; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.2.list3.ii">
                  <num>(ii)</num>
                  <p>upon or at any time before the expiry of the period of detention  authorised by him,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <blockList id="section-6.2.list5">
                <listIntroduction>that the detention of such person is unnecessary, he shall order such  person to be forwarded to the Designated Court having the  jurisdiction;</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-6.2.list5.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>the Designated Court may exercise, in relation to the person  forwarded to it under clause (b), the same power which a Magistrate  having jurisdiction to try a case may exercise under section 167 of  the Code, in relation to an accused person in such ca e who has been  forwarded to him under that section;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-6.2.list5.d">
                  <num>(d)</num>
                  <p>a Designated Court may, upon a perusal of a complaint made by an  officer of the Central Government or the State Government, as the case  may be, authorised in this behalf, take cognizance of that offence  without the accused being committed to it for rial.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-6.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>When trying an offence under this Act, a Designated Court may also  try an offence other than an offence under this Act, with which the  accused may, under the Code, be charged at the same trial.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-7">
          <num>7.</num>
          <heading>Application of Code to proceedings before a Designated Court.- Save  as otherwise provided in this Act, the provisions of the Code shall  apply to the proceedings before a Designated Court and the person  conducting a prosecution before a Designated Court shall be deemed to  be a Public Prosecutor.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-8">
          <num>8.</num>
          <heading>Provision as to bail.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-8.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-8.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>Notwithstanding anything in the Code, no  person accused of an offence punishable under this Act shall, if in  custody, be released on bail or on his own bond unless-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-8.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>the Public Prosecutor has been given an opportunity to oppose the  application for such release; and</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-8.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>where the Public Prosecutor opposes the application, the Court is  satisfied that there are reasonable grounds for believing that he is  not guilty of such offence and that he is not likely to commit any  offence while on bail.</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The limitations on granting of bail specified in sub- section (1)</p>
              <p>are in addition to the limitations under the Code or any other law for  the time being in force on granting of bail.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-8.3">
            <num>(3)</num>
            <content>
              <p>Nothing contained in this section shall be deemed to affect the  special powers of the High Court regarding bail under section 439 of  the Code.</p>
              <p>CHAP</p>
              <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
      <chapter id="chapter-III">
        <num>III</num>
        <paragraph id="chapter-III.paragraph-0">
          <content>
            <p>MISCELLANEOUS</p>
          </content>
        </paragraph>
        <section id="section-9">
          <num>9.</num>
          <heading>Provisions as to extradition.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-9.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>The offences under section 3  shall be deemed to have been included as extraditable offences and  provided for in all the extradition treaties made by India with</p>
              <p>Convention States or Protocol States and which extend to and are  binding on, India on the date of commencement of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-9.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>For the purposes of the application of the Extradition Act, 1962</p>
              <p>(34 of 1962) to offences under this Act, any ship registered in a</p>
              <p>Convention State or Protocol State shall, at any time while that ship  is plying, be deemed to be within the jurisdictio of that Convention</p>
              <p>State or Protocol State, whether or not it is for the time being also  within the jurisdiction of any other country.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-10">
          <num>10.</num>
          <heading>Contracting parties to Convention or Protocol.- The Central</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-10.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, certify as to  which are the Convention States or Protocol States and to what extent  such States have availed themselves of the provisi ns of the</p>
              <p>Convention or Protocol, as the case may be, and any such notification  shall be conclusive evidence of the matters certified therein.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-11">
          <num>11.</num>
          <heading>Power to treat certain ships to be registered in Convention</heading>
          <paragraph id="section-11.paragraph-0">
            <content>
              <p>States.- If the Central Government is satisfied that the requirements  of the Convention have been satisfied in relation to any ship, it may,</p>
              <p>by notification in the Official Gazette, direct th t such ship shall,</p>
              <p>for the purposes of this Act, be deemed to be registered in such</p>
              <p>Convention State as may be specified in the notification.</p>
            </content>
          </paragraph>
        </section>
        <section id="section-12">
          <num>12.</num>
          <heading>Previous sanction necessary for prosecution.- No prosecution for  an offence under this Act shall be instituted except with the previous  sanction of the Central Government.</heading>
        </section>
        <section id="section-13">
          <num>13.</num>
          <heading>Presumptions as to offences under section 3.- In a prosecution for  an offence under sub- section</heading>
          <subsection id="section-13.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <blockList id="section-13.1.list1">
                <listIntroduction>of section 3, if it is proved-</listIntroduction>
                <item id="section-13.1.list1.a">
                  <num>(a)</num>
                  <p>that the arms, ammunition or explosives were recovered from the  possession of the accused and there is reason to believe that such  arms, ammunition or explosives of similar nature were used in the  commission of such offence;</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.1.list1.b">
                  <num>(b)</num>
                  <p>that there is evidence of use of force, threat of force or any  other form of intimidation caused to the crew or passengers in  connection with the commission of such offence; or</p>
                </item>
                <item id="section-13.1.list1.c">
                  <num>(c)</num>
                  <p>that there is evidence of an intended threat of using bomb, fire,</p>
                </item>
              </blockList>
              <p>arms, ammunition, or explosives or committing any form of violence  against the crew, passengers or cargo of a ship or fixed platform  located on the Continental Shelf of India,</p>
              <p>the Designated Court shall presume, unless the contrary is proved,</p>
              <p>that the accused had committed such offence.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
        <section id="section-14">
          <num>14.</num>
          <heading>Protection of action taken in good faith.-</heading>
          <subsection id="section-14.1">
            <num>(1)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No suit,</p>
              <p>prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any person for  anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in  pursuance of the provisions of this Act.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
          <subsection id="section-14.2">
            <num>(2)</num>
            <content>
              <p>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central</p>
              <p>Government for any damage caused or likely to be caused for anything  which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of the  provisions of this Act.</p>
              <p>SUBHASH C. JAIN,</p>
              <p>Secy. to the Govt. of India.</p>
            </content>
          </subsection>
        </section>
      </chapter>
    </body>
  </act>
</akomaNtoso>
